<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#touringtopics">Touring
                     Topics</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
               <date when="1928"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Wolfe1928">The Lost Woman of San Nicolas</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="31"/>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="48"/>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="50"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#gwo">Wolfe, Gordon</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">
                  <emph><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Lost Woman of San
                           Nicolas</persName></rs></emph>
               </title></head>
            <byline><emph>By</emph>
               <persName type="author" key="#gwo">Gordon Wolfe</persName>
            </byline>
            <p>THE afternoon breeze had fallen off to a whisper and the sea was like glass as we
               landed in the little cove. We busied ourselves about the camp fire and made
               everything snug for the night. The sun sank back of the island hills and supper was
               finished by the time full darkness had come. Afterward, we sat in the ruddy circle of
               the firelight, each thinking his own thoughts. There was almost no sound by then, for
               the wind had died entirely away, only the faintest lapp-lapping of tiny waves on the
               beach telling us how close we were to <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the
                  Pacific</placeName>.</p>
            <p>That morning we had left <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, <persName type="seaman" key="#tom">Tomás</persName> and I,
               for a cruise of a day or two among the <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >closer islands in the channel</placeName></rs>. <persName type="seaman"
                  key="#tom">Tomás</persName> is an old Mexican boatman and knows all <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs> well. More than that,
               he is something of a philosopher, having seen much of the world and talked to many
               people. He has a small but seaworthy launch, and for years has plied his trade up and
               down <rs><orgName type="island" key="#re_socalcoast">that rocky coast</orgName></rs>,
               whenever he can charter. That evening we had run into such a calm that he had
               concluded it was safe to anchor close-in in the cove in the lee of <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, and spend the night ashore,
               where we might have the comfort and companionship of an open fire.</p>
            <p>"<persName type="seaman" key="#tom">Tomás</persName>," I broke the long silence, "I
               wouldn't mind being shipwrecked on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these
                     islands</placeName></rs> for a month or so, if I were sure of being rescued
               then. A fellow could have a fine time of it for a while. There are fish in the tide
               pools and many kinds of shellfish on the rocks, plenty of firewood on the mountain
               side and good water in the canyons. Why, it'd be great."</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="seaman" key="#tom">The old Mexican</persName></rs> looked up, his
               weather-seamed face a powerful etching against the blackness beyond the firelight. He
               nodded. "Sí, you are right. It would be far from bad on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs> that have trees and water and are
               sheltered from the winds. But there are others not so favored, such as parts of
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, the next island west
               but one, and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>. But
               worst of all is <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolás</placeName>."</p>
            <p>"Why is it the worst?"</p>
            <p>"Sometime, when you are not so hurried, I shall take you there and you shall see for
               yourself. That <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolás</placeName> is many
               miles further out than <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the other
                     islands</placeName></rs>, so that there is no protection from the winds that
               blow from the ends of the earth. It is barren, for if there were trees, the wind
               would soon uproot them. There is perhaps short brush and cactus hiding in the depths
               of the arroyos where the wind cannot get at them so well, and scant patches of grass
               here and there. That is all.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">"<rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">That
                        island</placeName></rs> is no more than a mountain peak sticking a little
                  way above the waves. It is perhaps eight miles long, of lava rock, and there is
                  much sand. Where that sand comes from, I do not know. Though the wind forever
                  blows it into the sea, there is always much left. <emph><rs><persName
                           type="author" key="#gwo">Señor</persName></rs></emph>, I have been
                  anchored back of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that
                     island</placeName></rs> when the wind came up with a puff and howled through
                  the rigging, and I have seen that sand hanging in the air to the lee of the hills,
                  so thick that it was like a cloak that hangs from a woman's shoulders. Then down
                  it comes, tons and tons of it, like fine rain, and it stings so that you cannot
                  face it and sizzles into the sea on every side. And the surf booms high on the
                  black reefs.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5"><span type="trope" n="6">"But <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">that island</placeName></rs> is dying. The winds have carved
                     into its heart and the waves gnaw forever at its feet and some day the two of
                     them will eat it quite away. It is doomed. And the winds that never cease are
                     always uncovering the grave-things of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the ancient people</orgName></rs> that lived
                     there in the dim time of long ago. Here a skull, there a stone knife or mortar
                     or ornament. Uncovered today and tomorrow buried deep under the shifting sands,
                     while that devil-wind has gone over the next dune and begins digging all over
                     again.</span></span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">"Then perhaps that wind will bring with it the fog, and its
                  cold fingers coil close to the slopes and shut off the rest of the world. That fog
                  is so thick that you can see no further than your own length and you are lost. The
                  sand no longer dances, but crawls, with a low moaning sound, the voice of those
                  murdered ones whose bones dot the dunes. Their ghosts still haunt the lonely
                  arroyos and you can almost feel them as they creep by in the mist. It is
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">a dying land and a land of the
                        dead</placeName></rs>."</span></p>
            <p>"You don't paint a pretty picture. If it's like you say, I wouldn't want to be cast
               away there."</p>
            <p>"Yes, it is bad. Everytime I go there, I say I shall never return, but there is
               something about it, the sadness and the loneliness, that pulls me back. It is bad,
               but <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolás</placeName> had <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one castaway</persName></rs> who lived alone
               there, not a month, but <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">years and years, more than a
                     score</date></rs>. Have you heard of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the lost woman of San Nicolás</placeName></rs>?"</p>
            <p>I had not and I told him so.</p>
            <p>"It is a sad story, <emph><rs><persName type="author" key="#gwo"
                     >señor</persName></rs></emph>, and pitiful. <span type="trope" n="7">You know,
                  when the <name type="nationality" key="#spanish">Spaniards</name> first sailed up
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">this
                     coast</placeName></rs>, all <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these
                        islands</placeName></rs> were thick with <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                        >people</orgName></rs>. There are piles of abalone shells that must have
                  taken many people many centuries to gather. I have taken <emph>profesores</emph>
                  and others interested in such things out to these heaps and we have dug up many
                  skeletons and stone tools and weapons from the black dirt.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="6">"Then the <name type="nationality" key="#spanish"
                     >Spaniards</name> came and took many of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">these
                        island people</orgName></rs> to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                     mainland</placeName>, so that their souls might be the better watched over by
                        <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the good
                     padres</orgName></rs> at <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions"
                        >the missions</orgName></rs>. Many sickened and died for their homes and
                  others married into the larger tribes of the coast and forgot the tongue of their
                  fathers.</span><span type="trope" n="11"> Then came the seal and sea-otter
                  hunters, <name type="nationality" key="#americans">Americans</name> and
                        <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                        >Russians and Indians of the warring tribes far to the
                  north</persName></rs>. These were far more cruel than the <name type="nationality"
                     key="#spanish">Spaniards</name>. They shot the island men just for sport and
                  carried away the women.</span> So in time it came about that all <rs><orgName
                     type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                     people</orgName></rs> were gone from every island save <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolás</placeName>, far out from <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_socalcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> and seldom visited.</p>
            <p>"The <orgName type="government" key="#gov_mexico">Mexican government</orgName> of
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_local">California</placeName> thought it best to
               bring to shore what remained of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the San Nicolános</orgName>. <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">A small schooner</name></rs> was chartered and sent out
               for them. They were at last rounded up in the badlands and taken down to <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs>. Then <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a young woman</persName></rs> cried out that
               she had left <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                  baby</persName></rs> behind her in all the confusion, and must go back for him.
               But <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">the captain</persName></rs> and the
                  <name type="nationality" key="#mexicans">Mexicans</name> could not understand her,
               since she spoke a different language than the Indians of the mainland. Also, the wind
               had started to blow with a fury and he feared to lie-to any longer, lest <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> be capsized. So he
               ordered the anchor to be lifted. <span type="trope" n="9"><rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The poor woman</persName></rs> saw that, and
                  ran and leaped into the sea before they could prevent her, and the last they saw,
                  as <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs> heeled back
                  before that wind, she was swimming straight toward the landing on the sand spit
                  where the wild currents meet and struggle.</span></p>
            <p>"<rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The schooner</name></rs> put about and
               after a stormy passage, made <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> and landed <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">its
                  passengers</persName>. Perhaps <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">that
                     captain</persName></rs> meant to go back after <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> in a few days;
               perhaps he thought she had drowned in the surf. No one knows now. Anyway, before he
               did go back, he headed for a trip to the north and <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">his vessel</name></rs> was never heard from again. So
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> became
               lost and forgotten.</p>
            <p>"Months came and went and turned into years and the only ones who ever visited
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that lonely island</placeName></rs>
               were the hunters. They saw only the seals and otters that they killed, so they
               thought <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolás</placeName> deserted.</p>
            <p>"Then one day, <rs><date when="1853">twenty years later</date></rs>, <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#tje; #nativeamericans">a party</persName></rs> went inland
               further than usual and found traces where some one had lived not long before. <span
                  type="trope" n="9">Their story finally reached the ear of <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the padre at the mission
                        in Santa Barbara</persName></rs> and then he remembered hearing of
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> who
                  had leaped from <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs>
                  there, a generation before.</span> So he persuaded <rs><persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">a sea captain</persName></rs> who lived nearby,
               to take him out and they searched, but found nothing. Then they went back again and
               found traces that brought them back for a third time. This time they took
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">a
                     good many others</persName></rs> to help them search.</p>
            <p>"They stretched out in a line, close enough to cover every foot of the ground and
               went forward. They searched the sand dunes, with no luck, and then came to the rough
               lava hills. Here they must be careful, on account of the danger and also on account
               of the many caves and holes dug out by the wind, in which she might be hiding. After
               much time they came to the highest of the hills and when they had toiled part way up,
               one of <rs><persName type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     Indians</persName></rs> came upon her suddenly. <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The poor creature</persName></rs> had built a
               low fence to break the wind and inside it she had made a hut of whalebones found on
               the beach. She was sitting there at the door of the hut with a half wild dog at her
               side. When she saw that <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the man</persName></rs> was the same color
               as herself she bowed as though she knew him.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14">"She appeared to have forgotten most of the words of her
                  own language.</span> Perhaps you and I would forget, too, with never a soul to
               talk with for <rs><date from="1833" to="1853">twenty long years</date></rs>.
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">The
                     Indians</persName></rs> could no more understand her than <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the
                     whites</persName></rs>, since she spoke a different tongue. <span type="trope"
                  n="10"><rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva; #jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats"
                        >The party</persName></rs> stayed there till bad weather drove them away,
                  seeking to learn of her life there by signs and guesses. As near as they could
                  understand, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                     baby</persName></rs> had died or been killed long before. A dog or two had been
                  left behind; they were her only company. There was water in one of the rugged
                  arroyos and many abalones and mussels along the shores. Sometimes at night she
                  would sneak up and kill the young seals with stones. She caught the sea birds and
                  made dresses of their skins. Several times she had seen seal hunters, but knowing
                  their cruelty she had hidden away till they had gone. Thus had she
               lived.</span></p>
            <p>"They took her aboard <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the vessel</name></rs>
               and returned to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. She
               marveled at the size of the houses and when she saw horses and cattle, fell down to
               her knees in fright. Because of her tragic history, she was quite a curiosity. <span
                  type="trope" n="3">She seemed childish&#8212;perhaps her brain had turned a little
                  from the loneliness. But she appeared to enjoy herself and went every night with
                  the Mexicans to their dances and fiestas. Especially, she liked to see them
                  dance.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="6"><rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The padre</persName></rs> tried to find
                     <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">her people</persName>, who had been
                  taken away so long before. They had been sent to <rs><orgName type="mission"
                        key="#mi_sp">a mission in the south</orgName></rs> and when he got word, it
                  was only that they were dead, having pined away for <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">their native island</placeName></rs>.</span>
               <rs><date from="1833" to="1853" cert="high">Twenty years</date></rs>, with no one to
               talk to; then, people all around her once more, but unable to understand or be
               understood&#8212;that was her life. But the new food she had to eat did not agree
               with her and within the second month she sickened and died, carrying her story to the
               grave with her.</p>
            <p>"And so <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolás</placeName> was left
               lonelier than ever, with only the seals and the gulls to face the sand laden winds
               and the roaring surf."</p>
            <p><persName type="seaman" key="#tom">Tomás</persName> stopped speaking and
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#tom; #gwo">the two of us</persName></rs> sat
               looking into the bed of coals, saying nothing. <span type="trope" n="6">But in my
                  mind's eye I was looking back through <rs><date from="1835" to="1928">the years of
                        half a century and more</date></rs>, seeing clearly that '<rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">lost woman</persName></rs>' keeping her
                  lonely vigil on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">windswept, dying island
                     of San Nicolás</placeName>.</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
