<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#cmagazine">Western
                     Democrat</orgName></title>
               <publisher/><editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="5"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="33"/>
               <date when="1857-02-17"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_char">Charlotte</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="city" key="#st_nc">North Carolina</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#WesternDemocrat1857">A California Cruise [Crusoe].
                     Narrative of a Woman Who Lived Eighteen Years Alone Upon the Island of San
                     Nicholas</title>
                  <biblScope type="page" n="1"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#cru">Russell, C. J. W.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">A
                           CALIFORNIA CRUSOE</persName></rs>.</hi></title>
               <title type="sub"><emph>Narrative of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a
                           Woman</persName></rs> who lived <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen
                           years</date></rs> alone upon the <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                           >Island of San Nicholas</placeName></rs>.</emph></title></head>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#cru">Captain C. J. W. Russell</persName>, who will be
               recollected by the readers of the papers as the writer of many valuable articles in
               their columns on the subject of "California Fisheries," has contributed to <title
                  type="article" key="#Russell1856_HCF">Hutching's Magazine</title> an interesting
               narrative of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs>
               who lived <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> alone upon the
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Island of San
                  Nicholas</placeName></rs>, one of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Santa
                  Barbara group</placeName>, off the <placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast"
                  >lower coast</placeName>, and situated about 43 deg. 15 min. north latitude. While
               stationed in that quarter, making tidal observations for the <orgName
                  type="government" key="#gov_usa">United States Government</orgName>, <persName
                  type="author" key="#cru">Captain Russell</persName> received from one <persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nedevir</persName>, an old California
               resident, <title type="article" key="#Russell1856_HCF">the following remarkable
                  history</title>:</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="11"><rs><date when="1835">Twenty years</date></rs> ago, the
                  whole of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        Indian tribes</orgName></rs> inhabiting <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">the Santa Barbara group of islands</placeName></rs> were
                  engaged in a fierce and exterminating war with each other, and to such an extent
                  was this deadly hostility waged that already the population had very much
                  diminished, and would, in all probability, before many years, become entirely
                  extinct.</span> To prevent this, and at the same time to ameliorate the condition
               of <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                     Indians</orgName></rs>, <persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the
                  good Fathers</persName> of the <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_santabarbaramission">Mission of Santa Barbara</orgName> conceived the
               idea of moving them to <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the main
                     land</placeName></rs>, where they might be watched over, improved and
               preserved, under their immediate superintendence. For this purpose they visited
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>, in
               company with a few <rs><orgName type="nativeamericans" key="#natam_missionindians"
                     >partially civilized Indians</orgName></rs>, and explained to them the
               advantages of removing to <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission"
                     >the Mission</orgName></rs>. They listened attentively to the proposal, and
               finally consented to go on promises of protection from their natural enemies being
               given by <persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the
               Fathers</persName>.</p>
            <p>Accordingly <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a small vessel</name></rs> was
               sent to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the different
                  islands</placeName></rs>, and <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the various
                     tribes</orgName></rs> were taken, one by one, to the <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_santabarbaramission">Mission of Santa Barbara</placeName>. But while
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the last
                     of the Indians</orgName></rs> were embarking, at the <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">island of San Nicholas</placeName>, and all were supposed to be on
               board, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">a child</persName></rs> was
               missing, and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">its
               mother</persName></rs>, in great distress, was seeking it everywhere, without
               success. Each portion of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                  vessel</name></rs> was diligently searched; all the adjacent rocks were examined,
               but no child could be found. Almost frantic, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the mother</persName></rs> requested <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#chu; #isp">the captain</persName></rs> to wait while she went into the
               interior to search for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                     child</persName></rs>, to which he reluctantly consented.</p>
            <p>As night closed down in darkness, heavy masses of clouds rolled up from the horizon,
               and gave evidence of a coming storm. All were anxious for the return of <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> and <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>, before it broke
               upon them, but still they came not. The wind began to blow harder and stronger; the
               storm was rapidly increasing; and as <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the groups
                     of Indians</orgName></rs> on board strained their eyes, trying to discover in
               the darkness, some object that resembled <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the returning woman</persName></rs> and <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>, yet saw them
               not, there were many sad hearts and anxious countenances that night, on their
               account. <span type="trope" n="12">The storm at last came on in all its fury, tossing
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">their little vessel</name></rs>
                  up and down like a feather, and compelled them at last, though reluctantly, to put
                  to sea for safety, before any tidings of <rs><persName key="#lw; #lwchild">the
                        absent ones</persName></rs> could be received. Although <rs><orgName
                        type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        cargo of living freight</orgName></rs> reached <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, before <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs> could return for <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, it was wrecked
                  and entirely lost; and as no other could be obtained at that time, <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the poor woman</persName></rs> had to remain
                  upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, where
                  she lived, <emph>alone</emph>, for <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen
                        years</date></rs>, no doubt forgotten or given up as long since
               dead.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">After the discovery of gold, it was rumored that <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName> was inhabited, and this, no
                  doubt, had its foundation in the fact that several hunters of the sea otter had
                  seen the print of human footsteps, and they endeavored to discover the whereabouts
                  of the individuals, but could not. Yet, as all the foot prints were alike, they
                  concluded that there could be <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">only
                        one person</persName></rs> living upon it. Many attempts were made to find
                  out who, and where <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this strange
                        being</persName></rs> was, but without avail, until one of California's
                  oldest pioneers, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr.
                  Nediver</persName>&#8212;the gentleman who related the story, and who arrived in
                  this country some twenty-five years ago, and still resides in <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>&#8212;went over to look for
                  her. He, having spent many years as a hunter and trapper in <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_rockies">the Rocky Mountains</placeName>, was expert as
                  an Indian in following a trail, and consequently found but little difficulty in
                  discovering the track, which he followed until he saw a singular object among the
                  rocks upon the sea-shore, near the mouth of a ravine, upon its knees, skinning a
                  seal. <span type="trope" n="1">Upon approaching, he found it to be <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs>, clad in a
                     singular dress of feathers. When she saw him she jumped up, and, with excessive
                     joy, ran toward him, and seemed almost beside herself with wild delight at the
                     sight, once more of a human being.</span></span> In her hand she held a rude
               knife blade that she had made from a piece of old iron, probably obtained from the
               fragments of a wreck, and which she evidently valued beyond anything else in her
               possession. <span type="trope" n="10">She was unable to make herself understood,
                  except by signs in making which she showed a great amount of intelligence, and
                  signified her willingness to accompany him to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                     >Santa Barbara</placeName>.</span><span type="trope" n="6"> Here <persName
                     type="missionfather" key="#jru">Father Gonzales</persName>, of <rs><orgName
                        type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">the Mission</orgName></rs> took
                  the greatest pains to discover some of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        Indians</orgName></rs> who had been taken from <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">those Islands</placeName></rs>
                  <rs><date when="1835">eighteen years before</date></rs>, but not one of them could
                  be found, and what became of them is a mystery unto this day.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="10">Not one of the Indians, within a circumference of many
                  miles, could be found who could understand her, so she could communicate only by
                  signs.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="10">It appears from her narrative, that, after leaving
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs> in search
                  of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>,
                  she wandered about for several hours, and when she found it, the wild dogs, which
                  infest <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, even
                  to the present day, had killed and nearly devoured it.</span> We can better
               imagine the feelings of a mother, at such a time, than describe them. When she
               returned to the spot where she had left <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada"
                     >the vessel</name></rs>, to tell her sorrows for the loss of <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>, that too, was
               gone, and was bearing away her kindred and friends from her sight. Could she have
               realized, then, that for <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen long
                  years</date></rs> she must live <emph>alone</emph> in the world, without one kind
               word of comfort, one cheering look from a friendly eye, or one smile of recognition,
               it would have been too much for even her wild but womanly nature to bear, and with
               her, as with us, it is well that we know not the future. From day to day she lived in
               hope, beguiling the weary hours in providing for her wants. With snares, made of her
               hair, she caught birds, and with the skins, properly prepared, she made her clothing.
               Her needles were neatly made of bone and cactu[s ]thorns; her thread was of sinews
               from the seal. In these, and many other articles found in her possession, she
               exhibited much of the native ingenuity she possessed.</p>
            <p>Whether she still remembered her own language or not, will forever remain a mystery.
                  <span type="trope" n="3">She was very gentle and kind, especially to children, and
                  nothing seemed to please her more than to be near them; and <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the poor woman</persName></rs> would often
                  shed tears while attempting to describe, by signs, <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her own little one</persName></rs>,
                  which had been killed and eaten by the wild dogs.</span> The sympathy felt for her
               welfare caused the people to supply her bountifully with everything she needed, and
               very imprudently allowed her to eat almost anything she chose, and the result was
               that in about six months after her escape from her lonely exile she sickened and
               died, having, undoubtedly, been killed with kindness.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
