<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#latimesmag">Los Angeles
                     Times Magazine</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue"/>
               <date when="1931-05-31"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Drake1931">The Little Known Islands That Lie Off Our
                     Coast</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="13" n="19"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#wdr">Drake, Waldo</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head><title type="main">The <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Little Known
                           Islands</placeName></rs> That Lie Off <rs><placeName type="region"
                           key="#re_socal">Our Coast</placeName></rs></title></head>
               <byline><emph>By <persName type="author" key="#wdr">Waldo
                  Drake</persName></emph></byline>
            </div>
            <div n="2">
               <p><rs><date when="1542-11-23">NEARLY 400 years ago</date></rs>
                  <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Juan Rodriguez Cabrillo</persName> found these
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Isles of Summer</placeName></rs>,
                  anchored in the azure sweep of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel"
                        >the warm channel</placeName></rs> that flanks <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_calcoast">California's coast</placeName></rs> south from
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Concepcion</placeName></rs>.
                  From <placeName type="island" key="#i_lc">Los Coronados</placeName> north to the
                  wind-swept <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> there are
                  eleven islands; their shores bathed by the warm waters of the Japanese current, or
                  Kuro Shiwo, and their sombre peaks and verdant valleys tempered by the fresh
                  Westerly and the California sun.</p>
               <p>From these and other weather factors they gain a climate that is hard to equal,
                  having the life of the Mediterranean's <placeName type="region" key="#re_rivera"
                     >Cote d'Azur</placeName> without its chill winds and the tropic beauty of
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ma">Madeira</placeName> without its heat.
                  Actually, they are the tops of mountains rising out of the sea, transformed from
                  barren peaks by a combination of meteorological conditions into gardens of rare
                  beauty and charm. For every man who loves the outdoors the <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> have their
                  fascination.</p>
               <p>Their blue and crystal-clear waters are the home of that bucking bronco of the
                  sea, the leaping tuna, and all of his swaggering cousins, the albacore, the
                  yellowtail, the bonito. Anglers come from all over the world to try their skill
                  against these grand fighters, as well as the marlin and broadbill swordfish, the
                  white sea bass, the blanquillo and a host of smaller game fishes.</p>
               <p>They are the yachtsman's paradise, for it is hard to think of another place on
                  earth where a sailor could find such perfect cruising grounds, with summer weather
                  and fair winds the year around and scores of beautiful little harbors where the
                  yacht on leisurely cruise may anchor in safety. As for the thrill of cruising
                  races, ask any Southland yachtsman who has fought his way down the west shore of
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> during a night
                  of contrary currents and constantly shifting breezes, finally to round <placeName
                     key="#pyramidhead">Pyramid Head</placeName> and then go boiling home to
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> under press of the
                  westerly.</p>
               <p>They have equal thrill for the hunter who has clambered rough canyons and over the
                  needle crags of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> in
                  search of wild goats, or for his brother who in the dead of night has crawled for
                  two miles on his belly to stalk the elusive white geese feeding on the tableland
                  on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>. Those lucky
                     <orgName key="#nimrods">Nimrods</orgName> who have hunted wild boars on
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> and <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName> have enjoyed real danger and
                  excitement and the man who likes upland game bird shooting can find his fill of
                  doves and quail in the verdant slopes and wooded canyons of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>.</p>
               <p>The eleven <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> are
                  divided into three distinct groups. Northernmost are the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_northernchi">Santa Barbara group</placeName>, lying about twenty miles
                  offshore and ranging in an east-west line from <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_ph">Point Hueneme</placeName> to <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_pc">Point Concepcion</placeName></rs>. They include <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr"
                     >Santa Rosa</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
                     Miguel</placeName>. To the southward and off <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_pv">Point Vicente</placeName> is the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_southernchi">Santa Catalina group</placeName>, including <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >San Nicolas</placeName>. Some ten miles south of <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_pl">Point Loma</placeName>, off <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd"
                     >San Diego</placeName>, are the three black <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_lc">Los Coronados</placeName>, called <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_lilasdesiertas">Las Islas Desiertas</placeName> by <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName> needs no
                  introduction. <rs><date when="1930">Last year</date></rs> more than 700,000
                  persons visited the <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Magic
                        Isle</placeName></rs> via steamers of the Wrigley fleet alone, in addition
                  to the thousands who traveled to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_av"
                     >Avalon</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_isthmus1">the
                     isthmus</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_catalinaharbor">Catalina
                     Harbor</placeName> and the island's myriad beauty spots aboard yachts.
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName> is needed,
                  though, as a starting point for the early history of the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, for on <date when="1542-10-07"
                     >October 7, 1542</date>, <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>
                  came ashore to visit an Indian village, variously located between <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_av">Avalon</placeName> and <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_isthmus1">the isthmus</placeName>. He named the Island San Salvador
                  for <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_salvador">his flagship</name></rs> and
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> was called La
                  Victoria, after <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_lavictoria">Cabrillo's other
                        vessel</name></rs>. But when <persName type="seaman" key="#svi"
                     >Vizcaino</persName> visited the <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast"
                     >California coast</placeName> in <date when="1602">1602</date> he gave
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> their
                  present names, as well as changing the names of practically all of the other
                  islands, bays and important headlands <persName type="seaman" key="#jca"
                     >Cabrillo</persName> had discovered <rs><date when="1542">sixty years
                        before</date></rs>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
               <head><title type="section">In Cabrillo's Time</title></head>
               <p>In Cabrillo's time all of the eight upper <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName></rs> except <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> were peopled with
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">Indian
                        tribes</orgName></rs> living in varying states of barbaric civilization.
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Pimugna</placeName></rs> was
                  the native name for <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                     Catalina</placeName>. Authorities agree that the <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_pimugnans">Pimugnans</orgName> and the
                  natives of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, called
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">Kinkapar</placeName></rs>, spoke a
                  dialect called Netela, but among <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_islanders">all of the other islanders</orgName></rs> there were
                  such wide differences in language that those living on <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">neighboring islands</placeName></rs> in sight of
                  each other could not understand one another.</p>
               <p><persName type="seaman" key="#svi">Vizcaino</persName> and <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#tto">Torquemada</persName> both declared <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_islanders">the islanders</orgName> to
                  be physically and mentally superior to the Indians of the mainland and expressed
                  admiration of their ability in building canoes and the dexterity with which they
                  handled these craft, as well as their use of steatite for making mortars. These
                  mortars, made at the steatite quarries at <placeName type="region" key="#empland"
                     >Empire Landing</placeName>, the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_pimugnans">Pimugnans</orgName> are believed to have taken across
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">channel</placeName></rs> to
                     <placeName type="region" key="#spbay">San Pedro Bay</placeName> and sold to the
                  mainland natives as the real beginning of the port's sea-borne trade.</p>
               <p>Excerpts from the diary of the Costanso expedition, which came up the <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_calcoast">California coast</placeName> in <date
                     when="1769">1769</date>, <rs><date when="1542">227 years after</date></rs>
                  <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, indicates that
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        Indians</orgName></rs> were still thriving on the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>:</p>
               <p>"<span type="trope" n="3">They are of good figure and aspect, men and women; very
                     much given to painting and staining with red ochre their faces and bodies. They
                     use great headdresses of feathers, and some banderillas which they bind up amid
                     their hair, with various trinkets and beads of coral of various colors. . . .
                     The men work handsome trays of wood, with firm inlays or coral or of bone; and
                     some vases of much capacity, closing at the mouth, which appear to be made with
                     a lathe&#8212;and with this machine they would not come out better-hollowed nor
                     of more perfect form.</span></p>
               <p>"<span type="trope" n="3">In their houses, the married couples have their separate
                     beds on platforms elevated from the ground. Their mattresses are some simple
                     petates or mats of rushes, and their pillows are of the same petates rolled up
                     at the head. All of these beds are hung about with like mats, which serve for
                     decency and protect from the cold.</span></p>
               <p>"<span type="trope" n="3">The dexterity and skill of <rs><orgName type="group"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">these
                           Indians</orgName></rs> is surpassing in the construction of their
                     launches made of pine planking. They are from twenty-two to twenty-seven and
                     one-half feet in length, including their rake, and of four feet beam . . . They
                     handle the boats With equal cleverness, and three or four men go out to the
                     open sea to fish in them, as they have capacity to carry eight or ten. They use
                     long oars with two blades, and row with unspeakable lightness and
                     velocity.</span></p>
               <p>"<span type="trope" n="3">They know all the arts of fishing, and fish abound along
                     their coasts, as has been said of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San
                        Diego</placeName></span>."</p>
               <p>Life on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> was
                  for these <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                        >savages</orgName></rs> a paradise. The waters abounded then, as now, in
                  marine life of every form, fish, seals, whales, sharks, crayfish, abalones,
                  mussels. Vast heaps of these shells and skeletons still found at town sites attest
                  to the fact that <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">these
                        Indians</orgName></rs> were expert fishermen.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="6">The complete disappearance of <rs><orgName type="group"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                           natives</orgName></rs> within the last century is one of the mysteries of
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs>.</span>
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> is known to have had
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">native
                        inhabitants</orgName></rs>
                  <date notAfter="1830">until 1830</date> and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">the Lost Woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs> was not taken off
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that dreary, wind-swept
                        desert</placeName></rs> until <date when="1851">1851</date>. <persName
                     type="author" key="#cho">Charles Frederick Holder</persName>, the great
                  sportsman who spent <rs><date notBefore="1885" notAfter="1915">some thirty
                        years</date></rs> exploring and studying the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, presents the most logical
                  solution:</p>
               <p>"<span type="trope" n="6">One cannot look upon the human remains, the skulls and
                     skeletons, without wondering where <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the natives</orgName></rs> went, or what
                     accomplished their extinction, as within a century and a half <rs><orgName
                           type="group"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                           inhabitants</orgName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                           >all these populous islands</placeName></rs> have disappeared.</span></p>
               <p>"<span type="trope" n="11"><span type="trope" n="13">According to some, they were
                        killed off by the Russians, Americans, or <rs><orgName type="group"
                              key="#natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">Alaskans</orgName></rs> who came
                        down <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">the
                           coast</placeName></rs> yearly after sea otters, with which <rs><placeName
                              type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">this coast</placeName></rs>
                        abounded in <rs><date notBefore="1800-01-01" notAfter="1850">the early part
                              of the nineteenth century</date></rs>. These people, according to
                        tradition, paid no attention to <rs><orgName type="group"
                              key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                              >the inhabitants</orgName></rs>, shot them down, and robbed them on a
                        freebooter plan for mere amusement.</span></span></p>
               <p>"To me a more plausible explanation of the disappearance of <rs><orgName
                        type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        natives</orgName></rs> is that the <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">Mission Fathers</persName></rs> induced them to
                  give up their island life and settle about <rs><orgName type="mission"
                        key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the missions</orgName></rs>, to be within easy
                  reach of their teachings; and while many were killed in war, swept away by disease
                  or by the invaders, doubtless <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        majority</orgName></rs> went to the various missions, where they soon lost
                  their identity."</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3">
               <head><title type="section">A Fragment of a Volcano</title></head>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente Island</placeName>, lying some
                  twenty miles southwest of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                     >Catalina</placeName>, is the weird fragment of some huge ancient volcano and
                  its eighteen miles of lava flows, cactus-filled canyons, coast line caves and vast
                  sand dunes present a remarkable spectacle of desolation, as compared to the grassy
                  grazing plains of the middle island. Its windward coast is largely low and flat,
                  with several bays and anchorages, but the eastern shore&#8212;apparently the inner
                  rim of a giant volcano&#8212;presents nothing but towering cliffs of lava, in such
                  grewsome, desolate expanse that one recalls the illustrations of Dante's
                  Inferno.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">The island</placeName> is owned by the
                     <orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">United States government</orgName>
                  and has long been inhabited by herders on the sheep ranch operated by <persName
                     key="#ebl">E. G. Blair</persName>, and several coves shelter shacks of
                  fishermen. Its highest peak rises to only 1960 feet, yet a great portion of it is
                  so mountainous that it affords ideal country for the thousands of wild goats still
                  hunted there about its needle-like lava crags and abysmal canyons.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> offers a fair
                  example of the unusual bird life of all the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >Channel Islands</placeName>. Its crags are the home of the American bald eagle
                  and on the broad plains of the middle island are found valley quail, the mourning
                  [morning] dove, humming birds, the savanna sparrow, rock wren, the house finch,
                  lark, 'pewee, the California shrike and most of the coast's warblers. Ravens
                  abound on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> and about
                  its sea-torn cliffs live the American osprey, the white-throated swift and the
                  belted kingfisher. Sea birds making the various islands their winter home include
                  the royal tern, the black-footed albatross, pelicans,cormorants, grebes, loons and
                  auklets and the many species of shore waders. At certain seasons ducks and geese
                  are found about the more verdant islands of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr"
                     >Santa Rosa</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                     Cruz</placeName>.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, the other two islands of the
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_southernchi">Santa Catalina group</placeName>,
                  are both <orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">United States government
                     reservations</orgName>. Santa Barbara's twin peaks rise out of <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">the channel</placeName></rs> forty-seven
                  miles southwest of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>,
                  while bleak <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> is some
                  thirty farther offshore on almost the same bearing. A light has been estabilshed
                  on little <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, but it
                  is uninhabited, save for large rookeries of cormorants, guillemots, pelicans,
                  auklets and the upland birds of the other islands. Almost surrounded by huge kelp
                  beds, Santa Barbara Island waters are fine fishing grounds but they are little
                  frequented by amateur anglers because of the island's isolated position.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, inhabited
                  only by the lonely herders tending the sheep kept there by Messrs. <persName
                     key="#eva">Edward Vail</persName> and <persName key="#rbr">R. L.
                     Brooks</persName>, is the most desolate, wind-swept waste of the entire
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel group</placeName></rs>,
                  but in its story there lies the strange tale of the "<rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Lost Woman of San
                  Nicolas</persName></rs>."</p>
               <p>In <date when="1830">1830</date>
                  <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a schooner</name></rs> was sent to
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName> by the
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">Mission
                        Fathers</persName></rs> to take off the <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">last remnants of the
                        dying tribe of Indians</orgName></rs> that had once thrived on <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. It was the <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better Than Nothing</name></rs>, from
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>, and <persName
                     type="investor" key="#isp">Capt. Sparks</persName> and <rs><persName
                        type="group"
                        key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                        >his crew</persName></rs> had taken aboard the last of <persName
                     type="group" key="#bhagroup">the natives</persName>&#8212;numbering about a
                  dozen&#8212;when <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one
                        woman</persName></rs> begged to be put ashore, explaining that she had left
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>
                  behind. She went ashore, ran up the beach, found <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her baby</persName></rs> and hurried
                  back to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the schooner</name></rs>, only
                  to find that the <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better Than
                        Nothing</name></rs> was under way and heading offshore. Some versions of the
                  tale indicate that the weather was so boisterous that <persName type="investor"
                     key="#isp">Capt. Sparks</persName> was forced to put to sea. Others say that he
                  deliberately left her.</p>
               <p>At any rate, <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the schooner</name></rs>
                  never returned and the woman's isolation became a matter of years. Finally,
                        <rs><date when="1850">after twenty years</date></rs>, <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#gni; #tje">some otter hunter</persName></rs> located her
                  rude hut on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>,
                  and reported it to <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats"
                        >the padres of the Mission Santa Barbara</persName></rs>. <persName
                     type="missionfather" key="#jru">Padre Gonzales</persName> dispatched <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Capt. Nidever</persName> to <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> in search of her. On
                  two trips he combed <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>
                  from end to end without success and on the third trip he took along a
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">number of
                        Indians</persName></rs> and <rs><persName type="group" key="#cdi; #col"
                        >several Santa Barbara residents</persName></rs>, including one
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charles
                  Brown</persName></rs>.</p>
               <p>On this trip <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs>
                  found her hut, made of whalebones and a brush roof, and later that day he and
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        Indians</persName></rs> sighted her, watching them from the opposite side of
                  a hill. By the time they reached the spot, however, she had disappeared. From
                  Brown's narrative:</p>
               <p>"<title type="manuscript" key="#Terry1882">When we got across to <rs><persName
                           type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>, I
                     said, 'There's nothing here, let's go back.' There was a basket and some
                     feathers. She catched shags and had a coat made without sleeves, nicely covered
                     with sealskin. I said to <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>, 'You go to the
                     hill and scatter the feathers and things in the basket, and if she is still
                     alive she will find them.' The same day we found them all gathered up and put
                     in the basket.</title>"</p>
               <p><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> resumed the
                  search the next morning and soon caught sight of her toiling up the hill toward
                  the whalebone hut, carrying something heavy in her arms. He describes her
                  capture:</p>
               <p>"<title type="manuscript" key="#Terry1882">She had a brush fence, about two feet
                     high, to break the wind, and right in front of me she sat facing me. The sun
                     was coming in her face. She was skinning a seal before I came up to her.
                     Thinking she might run I stepped round her, and she bowed as if she knew me
                     before, and when <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                           Indians</persName></rs> came up they all kneeled.</title>"</p>
               <p><rs><date when="1853-07">After a month</date></rs> on <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                     >Capt. Nidever</persName> and <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                        >Brown</persName></rs> took <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                        >the Lost Woman</persName></rs> to the <placeName type="mission"
                     key="#mi_sb">Mission of Santa Barbara</placeName>, where she was christened
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Juana Maria</persName></rs>.
                  But <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">
                        the crew</persName></rs> of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever"
                        >Nidever's schooner</name></rs> had already named her "<rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Better Than Nothing</persName></rs>" and by
                  that name she was known. She was estimated to have been about forty-five years old
                  when found. All efforts to find <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_missionindians">Mission Indians</orgName> who understood her
                  dialect were fruitless and <rs><date when="1853-10-19">after six weeks</date></rs>
                  at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> she became ill
                  and died&#8212;taking with her the enigma of the disappearance of the <rs><orgName
                        type="group" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Channel
                  Islanders</orgName></rs>.</p>
               <p>San Nicolas' eight miles of lava flows, shifting sand dunes, its 900-foot
                  fog-shrouded peak, its deep cut canyons, its bleak cliffs and the crashing seas
                  breaking over its rocky shores make it just about one of the most desolate places
                  on earth. Yet it was one of the most populous of all <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> when <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> and <persName type="seaman" key="#svi"
                     >Vizcaino</persName> visited <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast"
                        >the coast</placeName></rs> and it is still a great treasure ground for
                  archeologists and souvenir hunters. It is the site of one of the largest
                  aboriginal kitchen middens in the world and here may still be found skulls, pipes,
                  beads, ollas, flint spear heads and other traces of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the ancient island
                        people</orgName></rs>. <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName> is literally being blown into the sea and while the
                  northwester is howling with great force across its desolate expanse one can stand
                  on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this bleak desert</placeName></rs> and
                  see <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, where at
                  that same moment an ideal summer climate obtains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4">
               <head><title type="section"><placeName type="island" key="#i_northernchi">The Santa
                        Barbara Islands</placeName></title></head>
               <p>Sailing up channel, the first of the <placeName type="region" key="#i_northernchi"
                     >Santa Barbara islands</placeName> encountered is <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>, "the everchanging," in reality three islands
                  of grotesque shape. <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName> is an
                  island in the last stages of its existence, succumbing to the ravages of wind and
                  sea, and its shores are therefore formed of myriad caves and arches, where the sea
                  rushes in and out in its never-ceasing effort. The largest of Anacapa's three
                  islets is a peak rising 980 feet above the sea, <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_an">the whole Anacapa group</placeName></rs>, in fact, having the
                  appearance of a mountain on edge rising out of the sea.</p>
               <p>Although less than a hundred miles separate the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_northernchi">Santa Barbara islands</placeName> from the <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_southernchi">Santa Catalina group</placeName> a striking
                  change in climate is noted. The westerly wind blows with more gusto down the
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">Santa Barbara Channel</placeName>
                  and its waters seem to be the camp ground of the grim fogs which often envelop the
                  Anacapa Passage. <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>
                  and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName> islands, next in
                  order up channel, on the other hand enjoy a salubrious climate, which is like that
                  of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, tempered by a
                  fresher, cooler west wind. <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_scruz; #i_sr">These
                        two islands</placeName></rs>, both approaching <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName> in size and topographical make-up, are
                  surpassed by none of the <rs><placeName type="region" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        group</placeName></rs> in wild, verdant beauty. Santa Cruz's shores are
                  lined with scores of little coves and bays, there being yachtsmen and fishermen
                  who will tell you that <placeName type="region" key="#re_coche">Cochies
                     Prietos</placeName>&#8212;that perfect little gem of a harbor midway up the
                  south shore&#8212;is the prettiest spot on earth. <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> is world-famous for its great
                  multi-colored shore line caves. Several like the <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_paintedcave">Painted Cave</placeName>, have sea entrances and open up
                  into cavern-canopied lakes under the mountains, while <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_valdezcave">Cueva Valdez</placeName></rs>, near the east end, has
                  both shore and sea entrances. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">The
                        island</placeName></rs> is owned by the heirs of <rs><persName key="#jcaire"
                        >Justinian Caire</persName></rs>, a Frenchman who <rs><date notBefore="1880"
                        notAfter="1885">a half-century ago</date></rs> established on its interior
                  valley a beautiful rancho that is still a faithful reproduction of the vineyard
                  country of <placeName type="region" key="#re_sfrance">Southern France</placeName>.
                  Sheep are also raised on the <placeName key="#cairerancho">Caire
                     rancho</placeName>, while the island's tree-filled valleys and grassy slopes
                  abound with California valley quail and doves.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa Island</placeName>, just across
                  the lively <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">Santa Cruz
                        Channel</placeName></rs> from <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                     Cruz</placeName>, approaches <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">that
                        island</placeName></rs> in size and natural beauty and contains one of the
                  finest cattle ranches in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                     >California</placeName>, maintained jointly by the <orgName key="#vailco">Vail
                     Company</orgName> and the <persName key="#jjvickers">J. V. Vickers</persName>
                  estate, owners of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. It is the wild boar hunters' favorite territory and is
                  a winter rendezvous for huge flocks of white geese, which feed on the upland
                  grazing grounds. Like the other <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                     Islands</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa
                     Rosa</placeName> is mountainous and cut by deep canyons. Its highest peak,
                     <placeName key="#mnegro">Monte Negro</placeName>, rises to a height of 1565
                  feet. <persName key="#ccar">Don Carlos</persName> and <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#jcarillo">Jose Carrillo</persName>, members of the
                  pioneer California family, gained title to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr"
                     >Santa Rosa</placeName> by a grant from the <persName key="#kingsp">King of
                     Spain</persName> in <date when="1834">1834</date>, from whose hands it later
                  passes to the <rs><persName type="group" key="#tmor; #amo; #hmor">More
                        brothers</persName></rs>, of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>, before its purchase by the <persName key="#eva"
                     >Vail</persName> and <persName key="#jjvickers">Vickers</persName>
                  interests.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5">
               <head><title type="section">Cabrillo's Grave</title></head>
               <p>Three miles from <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>,
                  separated by <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">a
                        channel</placeName></rs> of turbulent waters and dengerous currents, lies
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, western sentinel
                  of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the entire channel
                     group</placeName></rs>. Seven and one-half miles long, <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sm">this desolate, wind-swept island</placeName></rs>
                  is first seen as twin peaks rising out of the sea. It is government-owned.
                  Treeless and swept continually by shifting dunes and storms of sand driven by the
                  strong northwester, its shores are for the most part bold and rocky. <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler's Harbor</placeName>, under the lee
                  of <placeName key="#hpt">Harris Point</placeName> on the north shore, is the only
                  harbor of value and even it is filled with kelp and shoals.</p>
               <p>Somewhere along <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler's bleak
                        expanse</placeName></rs>, the remains of <persName type="seaman" key="#jca"
                     >Juan Rodriquez Cabrillo</persName> are believed to lie, for it was there he
                  died on <date when="1543-01-03">January 3, 1543</date>, after suffering intensely
                  for two months from the arm he had broken while at <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> in <rs><date when="1542-10"
                     >October</date></rs>. Dying in those lonely, stormy waters far from home,
                  Cabrillo's valor and courage stayed with him to the last, for <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#bfe">Bartolome Ferrelo</persName>, his pilot, says in
                  describing his passage:</p>
               <p>"He charged them much, at the time of his death, that they would not give up the
                  discovery, as far as possible, of all that coast."</p>
               <p>No monument marks his grave, but beneath the shifting sands of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> lies the real discoverer of
                     <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. He and <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#bfe">Ferrelo</persName> did more than all others to
                  increase Spain's kingdom in the <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific"
                     >Pacific</placeName>, yet the gallant efforts of these <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#jca; #bfe">two bold sailors</persName></rs> are
                  commemorated by not a single prominent landmark along the coast that they were
                  first to find.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
