<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#newbedfordmercury"
                     >New-Bedford Mercury</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">40,</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
               <date when="1847-01-15"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_bedford">Boston</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ma">Massachusetts</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#NewBedfordMercury1847">A Female Crusoe</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="4"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName>
                  </author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">A Female
                        Crusoe</persName></rs>.</title></head>
            <byline>&#8212;A correspondent of the <title type="article" key="#TheBostonAtlas1847"
                  >the Boston Atlas</title> has furnished the following narrative:&#8212;</byline>
            <p>Off the coast of <placeName type="region" key="#re_upcal">Alta
               California</placeName>, about two degrees distant, bearing nearly west from
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_pointsp">Point San Pedro</placeName>, which is
               in the latitude of 33 43 N. and longitude 118 14 W., will be found a small island,
               called by the Spaniards <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Saint
                     Nicholas</placeName></rs>. <span type="trope" n="15"><span type="trope" n="3"
                           ><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">This island</placeName></rs>
                     was formerly inhabited by <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an inoffensive, indolent race of
                           Indians</orgName></rs>, who subsisted almost entirely upon fish, which
                     they caught from the rocks and muscles, which they found in the sands of the
                     beach. They were <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a listless, quiet race of
                        beings</orgName></rs>, who seldom had communication with others of the human
                     family, and who had but few wants, and fewer cares.</span></span></p>
            <p>About the year <date when="1818">eighteen hundred and eighteen</date> or <date
                  when="1820">twenty</date>, <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">the
                     Russians</persName></rs>, form <rs><placeName type="state" key="#re_russam"
                     >their settlements at the North</placeName></rs>, landed on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">this Island</placeName></rs> a party of <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">Kodiac Indians</orgName>, for the
               purpose of hunting the sea otter, which, at that period, abounded in those waters.
               This party remained on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> for more than two years, and were the means of sowing
               the seeds of disease and contention amongst its <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">unsuspecting and
                     unsophisticated inhabitants</orgName></rs>.</p>
            <p>Some ten or twelve years after the departure of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_kodiak">the Kodiacs</orgName>, <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this
                  tribe</orgName></rs> had become diminished to about twenty or thirty individuals,
               when <rs><persName key="#ppi">the Governor</persName></rs> of the <orgName
                  type="government" key="#gov_dptcalifornia"> department of California</orgName>
               sent over <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a small vessel</name></rs> and
               removed them to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the main</placeName>.</p>
            <p>In the last boat, which was embarking with the last of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this
                  people</orgName></rs>, (some six or eight perhaps in number) to convey them to
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs>, which was to
               carry them from <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the home of their
                     nativity</placeName></rs> forever, was <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lwhusband">one of the tribe</persName></rs>, small in stature, not far
               advanced in years, and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">his dusky
                     mate</persName></rs>, then in the bloom of life.<span type="trope" n="9"> The
                  order had been given to shove from the shore; the oars had dipped in the wave,
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs> was rising
                  on the foaming surf when, with the impulse of the moment as it were, <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this young and blooming bride of the red
                        man</persName></rs>, the imprints of whose footstep had been the last left
                  on the sands of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her island
                        home</placeName></rs>, waved an adieu to <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lwhusband">her chosen mate</persName></rs>, plunged into the abyss,
                  "strove through the surge," and, in another moment, stood alone on the shores of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her native
                  land</placeName></rs>.</span> She turned to give the last lingering look to
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwhusband">her departing
                     help-mate</persName></rs>; and then, gathering around her form the flowing
               mantle, wet by the ocean wave, in an instant disappeared forever from the sight of
               her astonished and sorrowing companions.</p>
            <p><rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The vessel</name></rs> weighed anchor,
               spread her canvass [sic]; and, in forty-eight hours, <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#bhagroup">this remnant of the inhabitants of San Nicholas</persName></rs>
               were landed on <placeName type="region" key="#re_pointsp">Point San
               Pedro</placeName>, houseless and forlorn.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1"><span type="trope" n="8">From that period to the
                     present&#8212;if she be not dead, or has not left within the past eighteen
                     months&#8212;has resided alone, on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                        >Isle of San Nicholas</placeName>, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                           key="#lw">this female Crusoe</persName></rs>, the monarch of all she
                     surveys.</span>
                  <span type="trope" n="3">She preferred to part even with <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lwhusband">her chosen mate</persName></rs>,
                     and sever every human tie that could be binding, rather than leave
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the home of her
                           birth</placeName></rs>&#8212;that lonely little Isle, that had been to
                     her a world, which she cared not to exchange for the abode of civilized man,
                     with all its promised luxuries.</span></span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="8"><span type="trope" n="1">Since <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">our Crusoe</persName></rs> became the
                     sole monarch of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        Isle</placeName></rs>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                        Nicholas</placeName> has been visited perhaps ten or twelve different times,
                     by different individuals; but there she has continued to be found, with none to
                     dispute her right&#8212;alone, solitary and forsaken.</span></span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1">Her dress, or covering, is composed of the skins of small
                  birds, which she kills with stones, and sews them together with a needle of bone
                  and the light sinews of the hair seal, sometimes found dead amongst the rocks. Her
                  only food is a shell fish, of the muscle species, with now and then a still
                  smaller fish, which the surf sometimes throws on to the beach. She never remains
                  long in one spot; but is constantly wandering around the shores of <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, sleeping, which she
                  seldom does in small caves and crevices in the rock.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14">During the few last years it has been very difficult to
                  obtain any communication with her. At the approach of the white man she flees, as
                  from an evil spirit; and the only way to detain her is by running her down, as you
                  would the wild goat of the mountain, or the young fawn of the plains.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14">Those who have seen her at the latest period, report that
                  she appears to have lost all knowledge of language; that she makes only a wild
                  noise, altogether inhuman; and, when taken and detained against her will, becomes
                  frightened and restless; that the moment she is liberated, she darts off, and
                  endeavors to secrete [secret] herself in the wild grass, or amongst the rocks
                  which hang over the never ceasing surf.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14">Every endeavor has been made, and every inducement offered,
                  by different individuals, to prevail upon her to leave <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, but in vain. The only
                  home she appears to desire, is <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her own
                        little isle</placeName></rs>. Her last hope, if she has any, is, to finish
                  her journey alone. She has no wish now, to hear again the sweet music of speech.
                  Its sounds are no longer music in her ear&#8212;and, as for civilized man, his
                  tameness is shocking even to her dormant senses.</span></p>
            <p>To all appearance, she is strong, healthy, and content to be alone. What can
               reconcile her to her lot, who can conjecture? Humanity may hope that contentment may
               continue to be hers, to the last hour; for she is destined to lie down and die alone,
               on the cold shore of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her isolated
                     home</placeName></rs>, with no one to administer to her last wants, and none to
               cover her cold body, when the spirit shall have left the clay.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="8">But the story of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lwhusband">our Crusoe's chosen mate</persName></rs>, the companion of
                  her early life, has yet to be told.</span> He saw her for the last time, as we
               have stated, when she stood alone on the shores of <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">her own Isle</placeName></rs>; when the boat with himself and his
               companions was dashing through the wild surf, that broke in uninterrupted succession
               upon the rocks which encircled <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the resting
                     place of his fathers</placeName></rs>, and which he was then leaving forever.
               With the <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">remnant of the family from San
                     Nicholas</persName></rs>, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwhusband"
                     >our hero</persName></rs> was landed at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San
                  Pedro</placeName>, and there left, with the others who had accompanied him, to
               find a home in that land of strangers.</p>
            <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>, it may be known, is a
               bleak, barren, bluff point, running out into the blue waters of the Pacific, on which
               no verdure is to be seen, and but one solitary abode of man, rising amidst the
               desolation which surrounds it. The <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Pueblo de los
                  Angelos</placeName> is situated ten leagues distant with one farm house between
               the one on the point and those of <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">the
                     town</placeName></rs>. The <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sg">mission of
                  San Gabriel</placeName> lies yet farther on, some three or four leagues; where, at
               that time, might be found, perhaps three or four hundred converted Indians.</p>
            <p>But <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwhusband">our hero</persName></rs>, as
               he may be called, never left the beach on which he was first landed. Alone and
               friendless, there he remained, an isolated being, till life ceased to animate his
               frame. True it is, that several times he was induced, and once or twice forced, to
               venture as far as <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">the Pueblo</placeName> and even
               the <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sg">mission of San Gabriel</placeName>; but he
               always, as soon as at liberty, returned and resumed his old station on the beach, or
               fixed himself on the rocks which hung around <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_pointsp">the Point</placeName></rs>. And there he might always be
               seen, a solitary outcast, as it were, and more constantly when the sun was going
               down, with his eyes gazing on that celestial orb as it sank into the western horizon,
               a direction which he well knew pointed to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the lost but never forgotten home of his nativity</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>With difficulty he sustained the wants of nature by fishing about the rocks,
               gathering muscles, and sometimes receiving a scanty pittance of corn from the house
               on <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_pointsp">the Point</placeName></rs>, or a
               few pence from a passing stranger.</p>
            <p>He studiously avoided, as far as possible, all intercourse with his fellow men, and
               sought to live and die in solitude; and so did he continue to live a life which
               manifestly appeared a burthen to him, till one morning, as the sun rose, not two
               years past, his body was found upon the beach a stiffened corpse stretched out, and
               bleaching, as it were, in the white foam on the surf, which was thrown about his
               lifeless remains as the mighty wave broke on the shore.</p>
            <p>It is presumed his death was accidental&#8212;that whilst searching for shell fish,
               in the night, [amongst the cliffs, he must have fallen from an eminence,] and thus
               [terminated his solitary existence.]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
