<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#wwisc">Weekly
                     Wisconsin</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">26</biblScope>
               <date when="1853-11-16"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_milw">Milwaukee</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_wi">Wisconsin</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#WeeklyWisconsin1853">A Female Robinson Crusoe</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="1"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">A FEMALE ROBINSON
                        CRUSOE</persName></rs>.</title></head>
            <p>&#8212;The <title type="article" key="#Goliah1853_DPT">San Francisco
                  Transcript</title>, of <date when="1853-09-15">Sept. 15th</date>, states that
               several leagues off <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, in
               the Pacific, is <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">a small cluster of
                     Islands</placeName></rs>, once inhabited by <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                     >Indians</orgName></rs>[.] <span type="trope" n="3">One of
                     these&#8212;<placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName>&#8212;sixty miles from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                     >Santa Barbara</placeName>, was visited in <date when="1825">1825</date>, by
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_ilmena">a Russian ship</name></rs>, and in a
                  dispute <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                        >the sailors</persName></rs> killed all the men but two, and carried off all
                  the women.</span> Some ten years afterward, the number of inhabitants had
               increased to seventeen, when they were all brought away by <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                     >some Americans</persName></rs> who visited <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>[.] <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">One squaw</persName></rs> missed <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs> when on board, and returned to find
               it. Meanwhile a gale sprang up, and <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                     vessel</name></rs> left.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of the present month, an American, <persName type="frontiersman"
                  key="#gni">George Niedever</persName>, who is now and has long been a resident of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, was engaged in
               otter hunting off the coast, and touched at <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName>. While travelling along the beach, to his great astonishment,
               he suddenly came upon <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this
                     woman</persName></rs>. <span type="trope" n="1">She was engaged in cleaning or
                  curing bird skins, which she sewed together to serve as a covering, and in a
                  garment made of which she was dressed. She did not manifest much surprise at
                  seeing <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr Niedever</persName>, but
                  readily assented to his proposition to leave <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and accompany him to <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">his schooner</name></rs>. She immediately set
                  about making preparations for her departure.</span></p>
            <p>She is now living with <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #sni; #ini; #gnijr; #jacobni; #mrni; #mrfni">the family of Mr.
                     Niedever</persName></rs>, in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, where she has all her wants administered to[.] <span
                  type="trope" n="3">She is about sixty years old, and is as simple as a child, and
                  quite free from deception and guile.</span>
               <rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#jru">One of the reverend
                     clergymen</persName></rs> of the <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_santabarbaramission">mission to Santa Barbara</orgName>, accompanied by
                     <rs><persName type="author" key="#gol">the writer</persName></rs>, went to see
               her as soon as he heard of her arrival. He brought with him <rs><persName
                     type="nativeameican" key="#natamwoman1">one of the Mission
                  Indians</persName></rs>, who could speak the language of one or two tribes of the
               California Indians. She was greatly delighted to see this Indian, but neither of them
               could understand a word of what the other said[.] She had a distinct articulation for
               almost every object she saw, but no one understands her except when she uses signs
               and gestures. She is very contented, and takes great delight in showing to her
               visitors as well as she can, how she dug the roots, caught the fish, manufactured her
               garments, and provided generally for her sustenance.</p>
            <p>Among the articles which she brought along with her from <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, were several needles, with which she
               sewed the bird's skins together. These needles are beautifully made, of fish bones,
               and show a superior degree of ingenuity. The thread which she used was the thin
               fibres of the sinews of a whale. She had also several fishing hooks, made of old
               nails that she probably found in some boards which she picked up on the shore. These
               nails were well bent and sharpened, and attached to lines made of fibres of whale
               sinews, beautifully twisted together. She had also among her moveables a soft clayey
               substance like brick, but whether she used this for dressing the bird's skins, or for
               simply giving a red color to her garments, no one could well make out.&#8212;She had
               a knife also about an inch long, which seems to have been a piece of an iron hoop. It
               is set in a wooden handle. She brought with her some seal meat, but how she could eat
               this seem incomprehensible. Ten or twenty yards is about as near as the olfactory
               organs would permit any of our party to go to it. She had a quantity of roots which
               are generally known here by the Indian name of <emph>cacometes</emph>[.] In taste
               they are like the kernel of an unripe nut.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
