<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#democratandchronicle"
                     >Democrat and Chronicle</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">62</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">364</biblScope>
               <date when="1894-12-30"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_roc">Rochester</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ny">New York</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#DemocratAndChronicle1894">Romance Of the Sea. Relics
                     of a Lost Tribe of Indians Were Found</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="10"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">ROMANCE OF THE SEA.</hi></title>
               <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">Relics of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a Lost Tribe of Indians</orgName></rs> Were
                     Found.</hi></title></head>
            <byline>Exchange.</byline>
            <p>The <name type="ship" key="#sh_alex">schooner Alexander</name>, <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#scott">Captain Scott</persName>, has lately returned to
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> from an otter
               hunting trip along <placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">the Southern
                  coast</placeName>
               <rs><date when="1894-12-01">last Saturday</date></rs>. <span type="trope" n="5"><span
                     type="trope" n="6">The last point at which <persName type="seaman" key="#scott"
                        >Captain Scott</persName> touched was <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                        >San Nicholas Island</placeName>, and he brought from there many curious
                     relics of an ancient race of Indians.</span></span></p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas Island</placeName> is the most
               southwesterly of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the little group off Santa
                     Barbara</placeName></rs>, and it is many years since vessels have touched
               there. <persName type="seaman" key="#scott">Captain Scott</persName> describes the
               place as one of the most barren spots on the earth, and yet up to half a century ago
               it was covered with vegetation and contained soil so rich that the rarest exotics
               flourished there. Now it is a sandy waste, the only sign of habitation being a flimsy
               looking hut of rough boards. <span type="trope" n="7">Twenty or thirty sheep in a
                  half-starved condition were the only signs of life visible and on the hilltops
                  bleaching in the sun were found the bones of hundreds of the ancient rulers of the
                  island.</span></p>
            <p>"We put in under the lee of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>," said <persName type="seaman" key="#scott">Captain
                  Scott</persName> to <rs><persName key="#reporter6">a reporter</persName></rs>, "to
               get a safe harbor until the weather was propitious for otter-hunting. While there I
               determined to go ashore and see what kind of a place it was. We landed on the beach
               and the aspect was dreary enough. As far as the eye could reach over hill and lowland
               there was nothing to be seen but sand and rocks, and a little way off there were
               twenty or thirty sheep. They looked more like wool-covered skeletons than anything
               else. One of the men ran after some of the animals and the latter hobbled about fifty
               yards and then dropped dead.</p>
            <p>"<rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The island</placeName></rs> is about ten
               miles long and five miles wide, and not a bit of soil is to be seen. There had been
               soil there once, but the sheep had dug up the grass by the roots and the wind blew
               the sand up all over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs>.<span type="trope" n="7"><span type="trope" n="5">We went
                     to the top of a little hill and there saw a most curious sight. Evidently this
                     had been the graveyard of the former inhabitants, but no cross or monument
                     marked the spot of burial.</span></span></p>
            <p>"<span type="trope" n="7"><span type="trope" n="5">The wind had swept up the sand and
                     left bare the bones of the dead. All around us were grinning skulls and
                     whitened skeletons and the whistling wind, as it soughed through the little
                     hills and valleys, lent a weird aspect to the scene. We gazed on the remains of
                     what had been mighty specimens of manhood, for the size of the bones showed
                     that the proportions of the dead men must have been immense. I am over six feet
                     in height, and a number of thigh bones I measured extended far below my
                     knee.</span></span></p>
            <p>"<span type="trope" n="7"><span type="trope" n="5">I picked up this club," said
                           <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#scott">the captain</persName></rs>,
                     exhibiting a heavy bar of sandstone. "It is evidently a war club, which was
                     used hundreds of years ago, and you can tell by its heft that it required a
                     pretty strong man to wield it. Here is a mortar and pestle which I also picked
                     up. There were a number of them scattered about <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. They were probably the property
                     of the medicine men of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the tribe</orgName></rs>.</span></span></p>
            <p>"<span type="trope" n="7"><span type="trope" n="5">I have heard that the name of
                           <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                           tribe</orgName></rs> never could be learned and that but little is known
                     about <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                           Indians</orgName></rs>. The people living in and about <placeName
                        type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> in years gone by could
                     not understand their language, and so never were able to find out much about
                     them.</span></span><rs><date when="1864">Thirty years ago</date></rs>
               <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> went to
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> in <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a schooner</name></rs> and took off what was
               left of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     tribe</orgName></rs>. There were only fifteen there, one of the number being
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs>. If
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     men</orgName></rs> had been warriors in times gone by, their martial spirit was
               then diminished, for they offered no resistance. When all hands were aboard and the
               anchor was about to be weighed <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                     woman</persName></rs> signified that she wanted to go ashore, and made
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">the captain</persName></rs>
               understand that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                     papoose</persName></rs> had been left behind. She was rowed ashore, and as soon
               as her feet touched the beach she sped away like a deer. She was a woman fully six
               feet in height, comely and well formed, and built in proportion. After an unavailing
               search for several hours the men returned to <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs>.</p>
            <p>"<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The woman</persName></rs> remained on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> for
                     <rs><date from="1864" to="1874">ten years</date></rs> after that, although
               several hunting parties went after her at different times from <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. She lived in <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_lwcave">a cave</placeName>, subsisting on the mussels, and abalones which
               she gathered from the rocks. Finally she was caught, <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">her
                  pursuers</persName></rs> having got on her trail and followed her to
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_lwcave">her cavern home</placeName></rs>.
                  <span type="trope" n="3">She was taken to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                     >Santa Barbara</placeName>, but civilization was too much for her and she died
                  in a few months. She refused to sleep in a bed, preferring the floor and she used
                  to play about the place like a child.</span>"</p>
            <p>The war-club which <persName type="seaman" key="#scott">Captain Scott</persName>
               brought up with him is twenty-four inches in length, nine inches in diameter at one
               end and five inches at the handle. The mortar is thirteen inches in diameter, and the
               pestle is about half the size of the club. The mortar has the appearance of having
               been hollowed out by the continual pounding of the pestle. Among the other relics of
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     tribe</orgName></rs>, <persName type="seaman" key="#scott">Scott</persName> has
               a flint arrow-head about two inches in length and sharp as a needle at the point. He
               also has two flint balls with holes through them. He thinks that they are part of a
               three-ball catchall similar to that used by the Patagonians. The instrument of the
               latter consists of three balls, to which are attached strings. The latter meet and
               are fastened to a long leash or rope, and when thrown at a horse[,] a bird or a man,
               if they strike the object the strings wind around and around holding the victim as
               tightly as a fish to the meshes of a net.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
