<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="publication" key="#report">Reports of the University of California
                  Archaeological Survey, No. 50</title>
               <biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="date"><date when="1960-05-16"/></biblScope>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_berk">Berkeley</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Heizer1960">A San Nicolas Island Twined Basketry Water
                     Bottle</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#rhe">Hezier, Robert
                     Fleiming</persName></author>
                  <date when="1960-05-16"/>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">76.</hi></title>
               <title type="main"><hi rend="bold">A <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">SAN NICOLAS
                        ISLAND</placeName> TWINED BASKET RY WATER BOTTLE</hi></title></head>
            <byline><persName type="author" key="#rhe">Robert F. Heizer</persName></byline>
            <div>
               <head><title type="section">ABSTRACT</title></head>
               <p>Concerning the few possessions taken by <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">the last surviving native of San Nicolas Island</persName></rs> to
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> in <date
                     when="1853">1853</date>, published records are scarce or non-existent. The
                  basketry analysis presented here is based upon a photograph, reproduced herewith,
                  of a San Nicolas Island twined specimen which finally came to the <orgName
                     type="museum" key="#mu_calacademyofscience">California Academy of
                     Sciences</orgName> in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                     Francisco</placeName>, but which was destroyed in the fire following the 1906
                  earthquake.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="6">In <date when="1836">1836</date> the <rs><persName
                           type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">Franciscan
                           missionaries</persName></rs> effected the removal of <persName
                        type="group" key="#bhagroup">the last survivors of the Nicoleño
                        tribe</persName><hi rend="superscript">1</hi><note type="end" place="bottom"
                        >1. The <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                           >Nicoleño group</orgName> is classified by <persName type="author"
                           key="#tkr">Kroeber</persName> (<title type="monograph" key="#Kroeber1925"
                           >1925</title>:633-34) as Shoshonean. This classification rests upon
                        analysis of four words recorded from <rs><persName type="nativeAmerican"
                              key="#lw">the old woman</persName></rs>. The words (after <persName
                           type="author" key="#gei">Eisen</persName>, <title type="monograph"
                           key="#Eisen1904">1904</title>:15) are: <hi rend="underline">tocah</hi>,
                        hide; <hi rend="underline">nache</hi>, man; <hi rend="underline"
                           >toygwah</hi>, sky; <hi rend="underline">puoochay</hi>, body.</note> to
                        <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>.</span> In
                  the confusion of the transfer <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a
                        woman</persName></rs> was left on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                        >the island</placeName></rs> who remained there alone until <date
                     when="1853">1853</date> when <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George
                     Nidever</persName> brought her to <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">Santa
                     Barbara mission</placeName> where, after four months, she died. The several
                  published and manuscript accounts of her life alone for <date from="1835"
                     to="1853">eighteen years</date> on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas Island</placeName> are being prepared by me for
                  <!--<title type="report"
                     key="#HeizerElsasser1961">-->seperate
                  publication<!--</title>-->.</p>
               <p>The few personal possessions which she brought with her to <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> in <date when="1853">1853</date> are
                  said to have been sent to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>
                  except for one piece described as a "<title type="monograph" key="#Eisen1904"
                     >water bottle made of rushes and covered with asphaltum</title>." This water
                  bottle was reported in <date when="1904">1904</date> by <persName type="author"
                     key="#gei">Eisen</persName> as in the possession of the <orgName type="museum"
                     key="#mu_calacademyofscience">California Academy of Sciences</orgName> in
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, and the
                  illustrations of that same basketry piece shown here (Fig. 1) are reproduced from
                  photographic prints found in the <persName key="#jcmerriam">C. Hart
                     Merriam</persName> files at the <orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucb"
                     >University of California</orgName>. The photographs were secured by Merriam's
                  efforts, and are of particular value because the basket was destroyed, along with
                  the building and other collections of <rs><orgName type="museum"
                        key="#mu_calacademyofscience">the Academy</orgName></rs>, in the fire
                  following the 1906 earthquake.</p>
               <p>Dimensions of the bottle are not recorded, but its height may be estimated at
                  about 10 inches (ca. 25 cm.) and its diameter at about 6 inches (ca. 16 cm.). The
                  base of the bottle has a surface coating of asphaltum and there are small spots
                  randomly distrubuted on the outer surface of the basket which apparently are daubs
                  of asphaltum applied over leaks. Since <rs><persName type="nativeAmerican"
                        key="#lw">the old Nicoleño woman</persName></rs> is known to have followed
                  the customary Chumash-Gabrielino trick of coating the interior of baskets with
                  asphaltum by means of lumps of asphalt and hot stones which melted the asphalt and
                  distrubed it over the inner walls, it seems unlikely that the basket was, as
                     <persName type="author" key="#gei">Eisen</persName> (<title type="monograph"
                     key="#Eisen1904">1904</title>:15) states, "asphaltum covered."</p>
               <p>The basket is made by the twined technique and the accompanying diagram (Fig. 2a)
                  of technique has been kindly provided by <persName type="author" key="#mab">Dr. M.
                     A. Baumhoff</persName>. In the diagram the dotted lines represent weft elements
                  which have disappeared through rotting away. The disintegrated wefts may have been
                  of buckskin, fur strips, feathers or hair. Two main areas, the body just above the
                  center, and the neck, once held the decorative bands which have now disappeared.
                  The ordinary warp appears to be of bundles of fibers rather than a single vegetal
                  element, and this type of warp according to <persName key="#ldaw">Mr. L.
                     Dawson</persName>, who has made a particular study of Southern California
                  basketry, is also the ordinary Chumash technique. The alternately spaced wefts,
                  now disappeared, probably were decorative elements. The alternating pitch of
                  single pairs of weft elements to form a chevron has not been noted by <persName
                     key="#ldaw">Mr. Dawson</persName> as a Chumash basketry trait, but he has
                  observed this in two baskets attributed to Salinan manufacture, and this feature
                  has been also noted by <persName key="#ldaw">Dawson</persName> on some of the
                  basketry fragments from <placeName type="region" key="#re_imc">Isabella Meadows
                     Cave</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="#co_monterey">Monterey
                     County</placeName> (Meighan, <date when="1955">1955</date>).</p>
               <p>Beyond this not much can be said. Any basket from the <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_socalcoast">Southern California coastal area</placeName> is of
                  interest because we know so little about the textile art of such groups as the
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">Chumash</orgName> and
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                     >Gabrieliño</orgName>. The uniqueness of the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> specimen lies partly in the circumstances
                  surrounding its history and preservation of this bare record in the form of a
                  photograph now over half a century old. That such water bottles were commonly used
                  by the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_shoshone">Shoshonean
                     tribes</orgName> of <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern
                     California</placeName> seems probable since the mainland desert groups are
                  otherwise reported to have used such forms, and there is a <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">Chumash</orgName> record for a
                  large asphalt-sealed water bottle of basketry (<persName type="author" key="#rhe"
                     >Heizer</persName>, <date when="1955">1955</date>, p. [102]) as well as one for
                  the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_costan">Costanoans</orgName>
                     (<hi rend="underline">ibid</hi>., p. 163). That there remain as yet
                  undiscovered baskets dating from the <date from="1700" to="1799">eighteenth
                     century</date> is a practical certainty, and in the course of time museum
                  collections in <placeName type="country" key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</placeName> and
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_europe">Europe</placeName> will probably
                  yield such treasures to the seeker. <persName key="#font">Father Font</persName>
                  on the Anza expedition in <date when="1776">1776</date> says that he saw no
                  baskets being made on the <placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">Santa
                     Barbara Channel</placeName> coast and quotes some religious colleagues who told
                  him that baskets were made on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz
                     Island</placeName> and traded from there to the mainland people. Anza collected
                  a number of baskets from the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_chumash">Chumash</orgName> on the way north with the intention of
                  taking them back to <placeName type="country" key="#re_newsp">Mexico</placeName>,
                  and it is these pieces which may ultimately turn up in <placeName type="country"
                     key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</placeName> if a search is made for them. <persName
                     key="#font">Font</persName> remarked on the return trip a few months later that
                  no baskets were to be seen in the Channel villages because the expedition had
                  already collected them--presumably the supply was not yet replenished. While
                  speaking of unusual baskets, reference should be made to the two remarkable early
                  ninteenth century specimens, one of which is now in the <orgName type="museum"
                     key="#mu_lowie">University of California Robert H. Lowie Museum of
                     Anthropology</orgName> and described by <persName key="#znuttall">Zelia
                     Nuttall</persName> (<date when="1924">1924</date>) and to the unusal seedbeater
                  (?) from a cave in the <placeName type="region" key="#re_manzana">Manzana
                     region</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="#co_sb">Santa Barbara
                     County</placeName>, described by <persName key="#irw">Irwin</persName> (<date
                     when="1946">1946</date>) and illustrated by <persName type="author" key="#rhe"
                     >Heizer</persName> (<date when="1951">1951</date>, Fig. 3E).</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
