PERIL ON SAN NICOLAS.

A Tidal Wave and Heavy Earthquakes.

The Old Harbor Filled With Sand.

Electrical Storms Killed the Crawfish and Paralyzed the Kanakas.

Special Dispatch to the CHRONICLE.

SAN DIEGO, July 6.&#8212;The steam schooner Jennie Griffin arrived this morning from San Nicolas island and Captain Mullett and the crew tell of strange and wonderful meteorological disturbances on the island. The schooner is enganged in the crawfish business for the Pacific Coast Fishing and Packing Company of this city, and a couple of weeks ago left a gang of eight men on San Nicolas island to prosecute this work.

The Jennie Griffin arrived there last Sunday to load the catch for this port, but recieved news instead which astounded the whole party and caused Captain Mullett to take the gang from the shore and leave the island as quickly as he could.

The men reported that the island had been visited by a tremendous gale of wind which raised the sea until it resembled a tidal wave, completely filling with sand the only harbor of the island, which is marked "coral harbor" on the Government charts. Captain Mullett was dum[b]founded to find a stretch of sand where two weeks ago he rode at anchor in the small but safe harbor. The big crawfish car, holding about five tons of fish, which was moored in the bay, was half covered with sand and the fish were lost.

The men told the people on board that the action of the water had been the most peculiar they had ever known and something seemed to foretell disaster. All the sea birds and living things acted strangely. On June 26th at 11 A. M. a heavy earthquake was experienced on the island, the oscillation being from east to west, the shock lasting several seconds.

On June 30th at 4 A. M. another was felt, continuing for some seconds. The weather was very foggy and the heat oppressive and stifling. A peculiar light covered the sea in spite of the fog which seemed to center about the island.

On June 30th a large ocean steamer was seen sailing within a few yards of the breakers. Captain Mullett thinks her compasses were affected by the strange electrical disturbances. The Jennie Griffin was in the neighborhood, and her two compasses would not work together while near the island. During the last few days the foreman on the island was unable to compel his men to work, and nothing was done beyond getting water and wood.

Several of the fishermen were kanakas [sic], who were scared almost to death, and prophesied that the island would be swallowed up. All the crawfish caught in the pots died from some inexplicable cause. The uncanny aspect of nature&#8212;the gale, fog, heat and earthquakes&#8212;was too much for the men, and they went wild with joy when the Jennie Griffin came abreast of the island and they were taken off in the small boats.

San Nicholas is the most westerly of the group known as the Santa Barabara islands, and is about 150 miles distant from San Diego. Twenty-five years ago it was covered in grass, which afforded pasture for thousands of sheep, and its owner lived there in a fine residence. A strange transformation has been going on since then. It is now a windy, barren, sandy waste, where but a few hundred sheep, without a shepherd, pass a miserable existence. It is but eight miles long and four wide, but wherever one digs can be found human bones and skulls.

The case of an Indian woman, who was left on the island for more than thirty years, excited much interest several years ago. She was abandoned by her people and in solitude forgot her own language. She was found in a cave subsisting on fish which she caught with hooks made out of abalone shells. She was taken off the island by another hunter, but her return to civilization was disastrous, as she soon succumbed to consumption.

Captain Mullett, who has visited the island many times during the past twenty years, says he was glad to get away from it with his men. He has visited it for the last time.