PERIL ON __place__SAN NICOLAS.

A Tidal Wave and Heavy Earthquakes.

__place__The Old Harbor Filled With Sand.

Electrical Storms Killed the Crawfish and Paralyzed the __org__Kanakas.

Special Dispatch to the CHRONICLE.

__place__SAN DIEGO, July 6.&#8212;__ship__The steam schooner Jennie Griffin arrived this morning from __place__San Nicolas island and __pers__Captain Mullett and __group__the crew tell of strange and wonderful meteorological disturbances on __place__the island. __ship__The schooner is enganged in the crawfish business for the __org__Pacific Coast Fishing and Packing Company of __place__this city, and __date__a couple of weeks ago left __group__a gang of eight men on __place__San Nicolas island to prosecute this work.

The __ship__Jennie Griffin arrived there __date__last Sunday to load the catch for __place__this port, but recieved news instead which astounded __group__the whole party and caused __person__Captain Mullett to take __group__the gang from __place__the shore and leave __place__the island as quickly as he could.

__group__The men reported that __place__the island had been visited by a tremendous gale of wind which raised the sea until it resembled a tidal wave, completely filling with sand __place__the only harbor of __place__the island, which is marked __place__”coral harbor" on the __org__ Government charts. __pers__Captain Mullett was dum[b]founded to find a stretch of sand where two weeks ago he rode at anchor in __place__the small but safe harbor. The big crawfish car, holding about five tons of fish, which was moored in __place__the bay, was half covered with sand and the fish were lost.

__group__The men told _group__the people on board that the action of the water had been the most peculiar they had ever known and something seemed to foretell disaster. All the sea birds and living things acted strangely. On __date__June 26th at 11 A. M. a heavy earthquake was experienced on __place__the island, the oscillation being from east to west, the shock lasting several seconds.

On __date__June 30th at 4 A. M. another was felt, continuing for some seconds. The weather was very foggy and the heat oppressive and stifling. A peculiar light covered the sea in spite of the fog which seemed to center about __place__the island.

On __date__June 30th __ship__a large ocean steamer was seen sailing within a few yards of the breakers. __pers__Captain Mullett thinks her compasses were affected by the strange electrical disturbances. The __ship__Jennie Griffin was in the neighborhood, and her two compasses would not work together while near __place__the island. During the last few days __pers__the foreman on __place__the island was unable to compel __group__his men to work, and nothing was done beyond getting water and wood.

Several of __group__the fishermen were __org__kanakas [sic], who were scared almost to death, and prophesied that __place__the island would be swallowed up. All the crawfish caught in the pots died from some inexplicable cause. The uncanny aspect of nature&#8212;the gale, fog, heat and earthquakes&#8212;was too much for __group__the men, and they went wild with joy when the __ship__Jennie Griffin came abreast of __place__the island and they were taken off in the small boats.

__place__San Nicholas is the most westerly of the group known as the __place__Santa Barabara islands, and is about 150 miles distant from __place__San Diego. __date__Twenty-five years ago it was covered in grass, which afforded pasture for thousands of sheep, and __pers__its owner lived there in __place__a fine residence. A strange transformation has been going on since then. It is now a windy, barren, sandy waste, where but a few hundred sheep, without a shepherd, pass a miserable existence. It is but eight miles long and four wide, but wherever one digs can be found human bones and skulls.

The case of __pers__an Indian woman, who was left on __place__the island for more than __date__thirty years, excited much interest several years ago. She was abandoned by __org__her people and in solitude forgot her own language. She was found in __place__a cave subsisting on fish which she caught with hooks made out of abalone shells. She was taken off __place__the island by __pers__another hunter, but her return to civilization was disastrous, as she soon succumbed to consumption.

__pers__Captain Mullett, who has visited __place__the island many times during __date__the past twenty years, says he was glad to get away from it with __group__his men. He has visited it for the last time.