<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="monograph"><orgName type="publication" key="#calfabind">California's
                     Gabrielino Indians, vol. 8</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <date when="1962"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="chapter" key="#Johnston1962">Islands Spanish Exploration by
                     Sea</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="113"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#bjo">Johnston, Bernice
                     Eastman</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold"><rs><placeName type="island"
                              key="#i_chi">The Islands</placeName></rs></hi></hi></title>
               <title type="sub">Spanish Exploration by Sea</title></head>
            <p>Visible from <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> lay
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> to which
               the Spanish were to affix the melodious names of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> and <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, and beyond was small <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">The Gabrielinos</orgName>
               had a descriptive phrase for them. "<emph>Wexaj momte asunga wow</emph>," they said:
               "Mountain ranges that are in the sea."</p>
            <p>The language spoken on all <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these
                     islands</placeName></rs> and perhaps on tiny <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara Island</placeName> as well, was Shoshonean. The dialect
               of the most dominant of the group, <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>, was Gabrielino, and it is probable that this was also true
               of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>. The speech of the
               inhabitants of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>
               off the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ven">Ventura</placeName>-<placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> coast was Chumash, but the
               material culture of the entire group at the time of the advent of the Spanish, is
               classified under the term "Canaliño."</p>
            <p>True to form, the mainland <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">Gabrielinos</orgName> found something uncanny, even
               sinister, in the isolation granted their tribesmen by the rough waters of the
               channel. Although brisk trading went on between them, and <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> had learned from the religious genius of
               the men of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>
               many of the elements of their vigorous <emph>Chungichnish</emph> cult, it was
               whispered that while the shamans of <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName> might kill their enemies with poison, those of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> were fierce wizards who
               used wolves to carry out their lethal designs.</p>
            <p>The <orgName type="island" key="#natam_Luisenos">Luiseño Indians</orgName> had a
               similar respect for the men of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>. One of the informants of <persName type="author" key="#hro"
                  >Helen H. [sic] Roberts</persName> told her that <rs><orgName type="island"
                     key="#natam_Luisenos">these islanders</orgName></rs> "knew better" than the
               folk of <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, that they
               could "prophesy truly." It was believed that they lived two or three hundred years
               and were so strong they could bend trees. These trees were like gods, it was said.
               They were frequently named in songs by a clan from <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> which had migrated to <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, whereupon all that they
               "called for would come true."</p>
            <p>The Spanish, when the turn of history brought them to <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> in <date when="1542-10">October,
                  1542</date>, saw nothing at all to fear in these fishermen and artisans in
               basketry and stone. As Juan Rodriguez Cabrillo's ships came to anchor <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                  natives</orgName></rs> took up their bows, while their women and children fled to
               hide in the chaparral, but the exploreres managed to convey by signs convincing proof
               of their peaceful intent. Soon the Spaniards went ashore, amid what seems to have
               been a feeling of friendliness and mutual trust.</p>
            <p>An even more cordial reception was accorded the Vizcaino party in <date when="1602"
                  >1602</date>, which was beckoned to shore by signal fires. <rs><persName
                     type="author" key="#carp">The author of the general diary of that expedition
                     wrote</persName></rs>: "We anchored, and the admiral, <persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#hal">Ensign Alarcon</persName>, <persName
                  key="#antdelaasc">Father Fray Antonio</persName>, and <persName key="#peguero"
                  >Captain Peguero</persName>, with some soldiers, went ashore. Many Indians were on
               the beach, and the women treated us to roasted sardines and a small fruit like sweet
               potatoes."</p>
            <p>Thus, almost casually, are reported the earliest meetings of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">these
                     Indians</orgName></rs>, so long established on their peaceful shores, with the
               restless Europeans who were welcomed with shouts and "great rejoicings." Many
               elements of drama are present in these events, and not the least of them lies in the
               extraordinary courage of the explorers in their small, poor ships, with simple
               navigation equipment and inadequate stores of food and water. A description of the
               symptoms of scurvy, as penned by <persName type="seaman" key="#tto">Father Juan de
                  Torquemada</persName> from the records of the Vizcaino expedition removes from
               these oft-told events any tinge of mere romantic adventure.</p>
            <p>Although <persName type="seaman" key="#svi">Vizcaino</persName> went on to explore
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mobay">Monterey Bay</placeName> he saw little
               more of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">the coast</placeName></rs>
               than had <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, 60 years earlier, or
                  <persName key="#cermeno">Cermeno</persName> during the intervening years. He
               visualized the use of this bay as a port of call for the treasure ship, the <name
                  type="ship" key="#sh_mangal">Manilla Galleon</name>, which annually reached a
               point almost, if not quite, as far north as <placeName type="region" key="#re_cmen"
                  >Cape Mendocino</placeName> before turning to sail before the northwest wind to a
               haven in <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja">Mexico</placeName>, sometimes
               running a gauntlet of freebooters on the way. Critics point out that these ships
               stood out to sea a hundred or more miles at the most northerly point, and that
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName> would have made a much
               better port and one far closer to sources of supply and defense.</p>
            <p>However Vizcaino's motives and accomplishments may be evaluated, he was an intrepid
               explorer, and he and his chroniclers left a mass of reports that became the sources
               for historians, from <persName type="seaman" key="#tto">Father Torquemada</persName>
               and <persName key="#venegas">Venegas</persName> down to those of today. The original
               narratives and "representations" were intended to influence <persName key="#kingp"
                  >His Majesty, Philip III of Spain</persName>, to order a second expedition. During
               a long delay, while this was under consideration, <persName type="seaman" key="#svi"
                  >Vizcaino</persName> died. All his ambitious plans for the settling of <placeName
                  type="country" key="#co_mexico">California</placeName> and the conversion to
               Christianity of the thousands of Indian inhabitants, for whose souls, "going to
               destruction," he apparently felt a genuine concern, went into the dusty archives of
                  <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName> and <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_baja">Mexico</placeName>.</p>
            <p>The importance, to our study, of these expeditions lies in these diaries and
               narrations. <persName key="#venegas">Venegas</persName> quoted from them in his
               descriptions of the women of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName> as handsome, with lovely eyes and features, and of the
               children as fair, affable and usually smiling. <rs><persName type="author"
                     key="#carp">The writer of the Vizcaino diary</persName></rs> reported that the
               faces of the women showed them to be modest. All seemed to agree, however, that the
               men added a talent for thievery to their general cleverness and first-rate
               intelligence.</p>
            <p>Soon after their landing, probably in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_av"
                  >Avalon</placeName> bay, the ships moved to an anchorage in the Port of <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, on the seaward side of the
               isthmus. Here, <rs><persName type="author" key="#carp">the diarist</persName></rs>
               wrote, "<rs><persName type="seaman" key="#svi">The general</persName></rs> went
               inland to see the opposite coast. He found on the way a level prairie, very well
               cleared, where <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                     >the Indians</orgName></rs> were assembled to worship an idol which was there.
               It resembled a demon, having two horns, no head, a dog at its feet, and many children
               painted all around it. <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">The Indians</orgName></rs> told <rs><persName
                     type="seaman" key="#svi">the General</persName></rs> not to go near it but he
               approached it and saw the whole thing, and made a cross, and placed the name of Jesus
               on the head of the demon, telling <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the Indians</orgName></rs> that that was good, and
               of heaven, but that the idol was the devil. At this <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                  Indians</orgName></rs> marvelled, and they will readily renounce it and receive
               our Holy Faith, for apparently they have good intellects and are friendly and
               desirous of our friendship."</p>
            <p>Other records called this clearing a "patio" and described the "temple" as a large
               circle, surrounded by feathers from birds which the Indians had sacrificed. At one
               side of the figure painted "like a demon" was an image of the sun, at the other one
               of the moon. While the party was visiting the spot two ravens flew from the enclosure
               to some rocks. The soldiers killed them with their arquebuses, which threw
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                     Indians</orgName></rs> into the wildest lamentation. The devil, explained
                     <rs><persName type="author" key="#carp">the writer</persName></rs>, talked to
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                     natives</orgName></rs> through the ravens.</p>
            <p>The skill of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                     >the islanders</orgName></rs> as fishermen was described by such adjectives as
               graceful, easy and pleasant. Sea lions and large fish were caught with bone harpoons
               which were fastened to the ends of thin willow rods tied with long cords. So
               impressed were the Spanish by the plank boats that they credited them as being large
               enough to carry 20 men, adding that they were often managed by only two, with a boy
               along "to bail out the water which flows in."</p>
            <p>We read: "<rs><persName type="seaman" key="#svi">The general</persName></rs> gave
               them beads and they gave him prickly pairs and a grain like the <emph>gofio</emph> of
               the <placeName type="island" key="#i_canary">Canary Islands</placeName>, in some
               wicker baskets very well made, and water in vessels resembling flasks which were like
               rattan inside and very thickly varnished outside. They had acorns and some very heavy
               skins, apparently of bears, with heavy fur, which they used for blankets."
                     <rs><persName type="author" key="#carp">The diarist</persName></rs> noted the
               trading prowess of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the Indians</orgName></rs> who produced, in
               exchange for old clothes, "skins, nets, thread, and very well-twisted ropes, these in
               great quantities and resembling linen."</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="3">Through these records we can clearly visualize <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">these
                        Indians</orgName></rs> in their prehistoric state as members of a stable,
                  primitive society, clean in body, healthy, skillful artisans, boatmen and
                  fishermen of grace and skill, and also deeply religious in their own
                  tradition.</span> Where in these earliest portraits of the island <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">Gabrielinos</orgName> do
               we find the mythical "<orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_DiggerIndians"
                  >digger Indians</orgName>," the lazy degenerates, the filthy and loutish folk
               which the later tradition set up as typical of the natives of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">this
                  tribe</orgName></rs>?</p>
            <p>One of the authors whose first-hand reports of the expedition of <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#svi">Sebastian Vizcaino</persName> afforded material for the
               later historians was <persName key="#antdelaasc">Fray Antonio de la
                  Ascension</persName>. In <date when="1620">1620</date> one of his reports was
               forwarded to the <persName key="#riv">Viceroy of Mexico</persName>. This was
               accompanied by a "Memorial" by one <persName key="#arell">Francisco de
                  Arellano</persName> which read as follows: </p>
            <p>"A Brief Report in which is given the Information of the Discovery which was made in
               New Spain, in the South Sea, from the Port of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_aca"
                  >Acapulco</placeName> to a Point beyond <placeName type="region" key="#re_cmen"
                  >Cape Mendocino</placeName>; containing an Account of the Riches, the Temperate
               Climate, and the Advantages of the Realm of <placeName type="group"
                  key="#re_upcal; #re_baja">the Californias</placeName>, and setting forth how
                     <rs><persName key="#kingp">his Majesty</persName></rs> will be able at little
               cost to pacify it and incorporate it into His Royal Crown and cause the Holy Gospel
               to be preached in it. By <persName key="#antdelaasc">Father Fray Antonio de la
                  Ascension</persName>, a Religious of the Discalced Order of Carmelites, who took
               part in it and as Cosmographer made a map of it."</p>
            <p>It is possible that <persName key="#antdelaasc">Fray Ascension</persName> pictured
               himself in the role which the Franciscan <persName type="missionfather" key="#jse"
                  >Father Serra</persName> was to play in reality many years later, for he left not
               only a glowing description of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_upcal">the
                     country</placeName></rs> but detailed suggestions for organizing the
               occupation. The guard, he recommended, should contain no less than 200 "good and
               honorable men," who must be expert and experienced seamen and soldiers as well. Two
               captains would be needed, "good Christians and God-fearing men." These were to "hold
               themselves in strict obedience and subjection to the religious who are of their
               company." Without the priests' order, consel and advice war might not be made "or the
               heathen Indians be otherwise molested."</p>
            <p>Another of the stipulations of <persName key="#antdelaasc">Fray Ascension</persName>
               was that no woman should embark on the expedition, "in order to avoid offenses to God
               and dissensions between one another." Throughout his report he stresses that only
               love and affection must be shown the Indians. Their possessions must be respected, so
               that they will learn to obey the Spaniards "without opposition or repugnance" and
               find good reason to be grateful and to give willing assistance. He does, however,
               advise a watch tower and a continuous sentinel. These provisions make interesting
               reading when compared to the actual plans for the founding of <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the Franciscan Missions</orgName>, and to the events
               which took place in actuality.</p>
            <p>For a century and a half after this "Memorial" was sent to the <persName key="#riv"
                  >Viceroy</persName> the Indians could dance in their <emph>tobet</emph> feathers
               undisturbed. But when, at last, <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain"
                  >Spain</placeName> took over this land the teeming population began at once to
               diminish. Diseases for which the native constitution had set up no resistance took a
               fearful toll. However, when the end came for <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">these
                     peaceful islanders</orgName></rs>
               <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName> and her successor,
                  <placeName type="group" key="#re_upcal; #re_baja">Mexico</placeName>, were only
               indirectly involved. The rich furs, which the diarist of the Vizcaino party thought
               might be bear robes but which were in reality the skins of sea otters, drew hunters
               of every adventurous race of man able to reach <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs> in the sailing ships of the
               time.</p>
            <p><rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">The
                     islanders</orgName></rs> were no match for the fierce <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">Aleuts</orgName> who came as
               hunters in the crews of Russian ships, or for <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_hawaiian">Kanakas</orgName> brought in by American sailing vessels.
               Ruthless and violent warfare very nearly exterminated both the sea otter and
                     <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                     Indians</orgName></rs>. The time came when the hunting was no longer
               profitable, but before that the settlements in the coves and inlets had dwindled to
               the point where it became the better part of mercy to remove the survivors to
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>. Refugees from
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> were assigned to
                  <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sl">Mission San Luis Rey</placeName>, which may
               possibly account for a report that the ancient dialect of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scl">that island</placeName></rs> had been Luiseño.
               Although <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sg">San Gabriel</placeName> is said to have
               been the destination of those from <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>, it is on a list compiled from the Baptismal Register of
                  <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_sfern">San Fernando</orgName> that we find the
               name "<emph>Pipimas</emph>," and in parentheses following, "Islas."</p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> suffered most cruelly.
               It has been said that <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_kodiak"
                  >Kodiaks</persName></rs>, left on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> to hunt, massacred <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the men</orgName></rs>
               and appropriated their families. Some <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">20
                     survivors</persName></rs> were rounded up and taken to <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> in <date when="1835">1835</date>. <span
                  type="trope" n="9">Amid the confusion of the evacuation, however, <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one woman</persName></rs>, discovering that
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>
                  had been left behind, leaped from <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                        rescue boat</name></rs> and swam back to shore.</span> Because of the high
               gales and heavy surf <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs>
               had to leave without her. <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">Its
                     captain</persName></rs> intended to return later for <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, but after delivering
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">his Indian charges</persName></rs>
               safely to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> his craft
               was lost in a subsequent storm.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="8">For years this "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">female Robinson Crusoe</persName></rs>" was forgotten&#8212;until
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_upcal">California</placeName></rs>
                  passed into American hands and occasional fishermen reported seeing someone
                  wandering over the island plateau.</span> In <date when="1850">1850</date> a
               search of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> failed
               to reveal a single human being but <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#tje; #nativeamericans">the party</persName></rs> returned to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> with the news of a resurgence
               among the sea otters and the black seals. New hunts, by local crews, were organized
               and on the third of these, in <date when="1853">1853</date>, traces of human
               occupancy were discovered which led to the finding of the "<rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">lost woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs>." She
               was dressed in a tunic of satiny green cormorant feathers and her first act was to
               prepare a meal for <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">her
                  guests</persName></rs> from her small store of roasted roots.</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">This intrepid woman</persName></rs>
               lived but a few months after her rescue. No trace of a single member of <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#bhagroup">the party which had preceded her</persName></rs>
               to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>
               <date from="1835" to="1853">18 years</date> earlier could be found, and no Indian who
               was brought to see her, not even a few <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">natives of Santa Catalina</orgName></rs>, could
               understand her dialect, although it seemed to be from Shoshonean stock. It has been
               reported that her dress and other belongings were sent to the <orgName type="museum"
                  key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">Vatican</orgName>.</p>
            <p>This story of the "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Lost Woman of San
                     Nicolas</persName></rs>," although not fictional, has become a legend and is
               told in many versions. The outline given above is based on an article printed in
                     <emph><title type="article" key="#Hardacre1880_SM">Scribner's
                  Magazine</title></emph> in <date when="1880">1880</date>. <persName type="author"
                  key="#eha">Emma Hardacre</persName>, the author, came to <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> in <date when="1876">1876</date> and knew
               several of <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the people who took part
                     in the rescue</persName></rs>. She made every effort to produce a factual
               report.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#eha">Mrs. Hardacre</persName> also met and talked to
                  <persName type="author" key="#lce">M. Leon de Cessac</persName>, whom she
               described as "a gentleman engaged in collecting archeological specimens for the
                  <orgName type="government" key="#gov_french">French Government</orgName>." The
               activities of <rs><persName type="author" key="#lce">this French
                  scientist</persName></rs> account for the amazing knowledge some Europeans have of
               our local Channel Island culture. <persName type="author" key="#lce">M. de
                  Cessac</persName> also discovered in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, and managed to secure for <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_france">France</placeName>, a second original manuscript of Father
               Boscana's "<emph>Chinigchinich</emph>."</p>
            <p>This may be the one which was translated by <persName type="author" key="#jha">John
                  Peabody Harrington</persName>, which differs in some details from the manuscript
               translated by the early pioneer resident, <persName type="author" key="#arob">Alfred
                  Robinson</persName>.</p>
            <p>The island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, which for
               years boasted a population of <rs><persName key="#fju">one Basque
                     sheepherder</persName></rs>, with his dogs, sheep, and the howling wind for
               company, now belongs to the <orgName type="military" key="#mi_navy">U.S.
                  Navy</orgName> and is occupied by several hundred naval and civilian personnel
               engaged in the work of the naval air missile testing program. The wind, the ravens,
               the sea elephants and sea lions are still there, as are evidences of the Indian past.
               Generations of collectors, some genuinely scientific in spirit, others who can only
               be called "pot-hunters," have removed literally tons of archeological material from
               the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, even from this
               most distant and lonely of the group, but no one can quite obliterate the
               accumulations of centuries of the numerous and skillful fishermen and artisans who
               lived there.</p>
            <p>Few individuals, other than the naval and civilian personnel stationed on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> and <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, are enabled to view these outlying islands.
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, on the
               contrary, is visited by a great number of tourists each year, and of these many join
               the guided bus tours into the interior. Circumscribed as these necessarily are, they
               do traverse mountain ridges, canyons and inlets, and afford lovely vistas of the sea.
               These comparatively isolated regions stimulate the imagination of one bent on
               reconstructing the aboriginal scene.</p>
            <p>Throughout these tours distressing evidences of erosion cannot be ignored. These can
               be explained, not only by the cycle of drought which afflicts the Southwest, but by
               the industrious grazing and rooting of the descendants of tame animals left on the
               island by white voyagers. The now wild goats and boars have multiplied enormously,
               and to their efforts have been added those of a small herd of bison, veterans of a
               movie production left behind when the rest of the cast returned to <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>.</p>
            <p>If today <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina
                  Island</placeName> were to be restored to the ownership of <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the Gabrielinos</orgName>
               of old it is doubtful that they could live at their ancient high standard. Certainly,
               the busy pigs and piglets of the wild boar population must have enormously reduced
               one great resource, the roots which flourished so well that the Spanish reported them
               as part of the native export trade with <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName>. Their loss undoubtedly contributes to the great areas of
               loose, dusty soil, waiting to be washed or blown away at the first rain or gale.</p>
            <p>Of these roots, those that Vizcaino's men compared to the sweet potato may have been
               of the wild cucumber, or Big Root, which was common on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName>. The Spanish called these "jicamas" or
               "xicamas." <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">The
                     Indians</orgName></rs> exported the smaller ones, but some of them grew to be
               quite enormous. The men of the Cermeno expedition in <date when="1595">1595</date>
               ate cakes prepared from these on <placeName type="island" key="#i_smar">San Martin
                  Island</placeName>, off <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja">Lower
                  California</placeName>, and were made quite ill as they seemed to have purgative
               qualities dangerous to the unaccustomed. Another favorite food found on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina; #i_smar">both the
                     islands</placeName></rs> and <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName> was the roots, or rather corms, of the Brodiaea, that lovely
               spring flower of heavenly blue which still survives, though sparsely. The Spanish
               named these nut-flavored morsels "cacomites," from the Aztec
               "<emph>cacomitl</emph>."</p>
            <p>The traveling public gains a very faint idea of the once flourishing Indian life on
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>. On one
               tour, as the bus skirts the heights above <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_littleharbor">Little Harbor</placeName>, "the Indian burial ground" is
               pointed out far below, and as the escarpment is rounded the trenches of an
               archeological dig made by the <orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University
                  of California, Los Angeles</orgName>, in <date when="1953">1953</date> are viewed.
               These two glimpses, interesting as they are, afford but a meagre notion of the
               discoveries which have been made in regard to <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                  Indians</orgName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the
                     island</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>Luckily for those who would like a more comprehensive picture of <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> as it used to be, one
               can turn to the writings of <persName type="author" key="#cho">Charles Frederick
                  Holder</persName>, zoologist and sportsman, founder of the famous <orgName
                  key="#tuna">Tuna Club</orgName>. One of Holder's first impressions on his arrival
               there in <date when="1886">1886</date> concerned the rollicking antics and the
               ingrained impudence of the many ravens which were constantly stealing little chickens
               and turkeys from the ranch of "<persName key="#chixjoe">Chicken John</persName>," in
               a canyon back of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_av">Avalon</placeName>. The
               privileged status of these birds during the centuries of Indian tenancy was soon made
               evident to the newcomer as he entered wholeheartedly into historical research,
               consulting the records of the Vizcaino party and the work of <persName
                  type="missionfather" key="#boscana">Father Boscana</persName> in order to
               establish a background for the fine descriptive passages he was to write.</p>
            <p>Among the many unforgettable scenes <persName type="author" key="#cho"
                  >Holder</persName> recorded where the dunes of lonely <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. They "cover and uncover the dead," he wrote.
               "They fill the canyons, form strange shapes which float in the air before they are
               carried away." He described a "mesa of pebbles which leap into the air and blow
               about" and "great natural stair-cases leading from mesa to beach." <rs><persName
                     key="#fju">The Basque sheepherder</persName></rs> was firm in the belief that
               the spirits were angry and made the wind blow because of the "grave-robbing" which
               had been carried on so extensively.</p>
            <p>"At the west end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs> lay a great kitchen-midden about ten feet high and
               extending over a mile," <persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> wrote.
               It was "made up of shells of various kinds, mostly abalones, thrown here for ages. In
               this area are graves of countless natives who were buried in the long ago. As each
               man was buried with all his possession there is an object in grave-robbing. Scores of
               parties have explored here, and doubtless the region has hardly been touched on."</p>
            <p>In addition to the familiar objects of stone found in typical Gabrielino sites,
                  <persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> mentioned seeing objects of
               wood, but did not describe them in detail. These would be of more than ordinary
               interest to the modern student, as time and the custom of cremating the dead of the
               inland villages has left somewhat of a gap in our knowledge of the material culture
               in so far as the use of wood is concerned. <persName type="author" key="#cho"
                  >Holder</persName> told of one "collector" who found implements stored in
               "coffins" of wood. He himself saw fishing lines made of "bull kelp" still attached to
               the equipment, although the Spanish reported cord and rope "as fine as linen." He
               also saw, in a collection, a long stone club, "doubtless a token of office" as it was
               "an extraordinary weapon."</p>
            <p>A custom of the <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">island
                     Indians</orgName></rs> was to preserve their small treasures in an abalone
               shells cemented together with asphalt. One of these was presented to the <orgName
                  type="museum" key="#mu_southwest">Southwest Museum</orgName> by <persName
                  key="#whbur">W. H. Burnham</persName>, who purchased it from a collector, and
               countless visitors have found it of great interest. Displayed near it is an X-ray
               photograph of the contents, as this prehistoric jewel case has never been opened
               since it was sealed by the original owner.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="13">Continuing with his description of <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>
                  <persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> wrote, "I found one spot
                  years ago which must have been a battlefield similar to the one I found at
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>. Skeletons were
                  piled up, skulls crushed, and bones broken; while mortars too heavy to carry off
                  were strewn about&#8212;a perfect golgotha." <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >San Nicolas</placeName>, he recalled, had been ravaged by the <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">Russians from
                        Alaska</orgName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#lce">De Cessac</persName>, during his excavations on
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, in the period of
                  <date from="1877" to="1879">1877 to 1879</date>, also found many examples of the
               work of <rs><orgName type="group" key="#natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">Northwest
                     Indians</orgName></rs>, ample proof of the visits of the hunters of the sea
               otter. <rs><persName type="author" key="#lce">This French scientist</persName></rs>
               held the opinion that the culture of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName> was related to that of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl"
                  >San Clemente</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>, rather than to <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_northernchi">the islands off the coast of Santa Barbara
                     County</placeName></rs>. He was particularly eloquent in regard to the
               exquisite stone work, beautifully turned mortars and pestles, and small carvings of
               the creatures of sea, land and air. <persName type="author" key="#lce">De
                  Cessac</persName> was fascinated, as many have been since his time, with the odd
               hook-shaped stone carvings which resemble conventionalized pelicans; or, as <persName
                  type="author" key="#rhe">Heizer</persName> expresses it, "the scheme or embryo of
               the statue of a cetacean." These may have been fetiches. One can see the possibility
               of such a use in the small carvings of boats, some of them inlaid with decorations of
               shell, to bring home safely men who braved the sea in plank canoes.</p>
            <p>Holder's account of a trip made in <date when="1907">1907</date> across <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> is a classic. Of one episode
               he wrote, "We climbed the steep hill at Howland's and were shortly on the remarkable
               sand-dunes; where the first view of the ancient town sites became apparent. The long
               billowy white sand, a menace to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, filling the cañons, was dotted here and there with
               human bones and broken skulls." On <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                     island</placeName></rs>
               <persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> saw an entire mesa "covered with
               midden and broken implements." At the base of a "lava" flow a midden lay in front of
               a cave. He described "lava" cliffs cut by cañons, "gaping, uncanny caves" and
               gleaming heaps of abalones, most of these long ago exported to be resold here and
               elsewhere in the shape of pearl buttons and trinkets.</p>
            <p>Of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>
               <persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> wrote, as late as <date
                  when="1909">1909</date>, "When a trench is dug in any part of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_av">Avalon</placeName> today, especially along the north
               beach, shells, implements, and ancient human bones are often found, and the black
               earth crops out, telling the story of one of the most interesting ancient
               archeological treasure-houses in <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa"
                  >America</placeName>." He describes the work and "collections" of various men who
               excavated in the many village sites which existed at <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_isthmus1">the Isthmus</placeName>, at "every cañon having a beach along
               the north coast." Specific locations were mentioned at <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_catalinaharbor">Catalina Harbor</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_littleharbor">Little Harbor</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_johnland">Johnson's Landing</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_empland">Empire Landing</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_whiteland">White's Landing</placeName> and many another inlet. Signs of
               occupation were also found at far less accessible places, as in caves at considerable
               altitudes.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> found "the old quarry at
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_empland">Empire landing</placeName>, with its
               myriads of chips and flints, just as though the workers had been driven off and
               forced to drop their possessions and run." Here in the chaparral were outcroppings of
               steatite and the clear evidences of a prehistoric stone works. It seemed that the
               plan of the vanished artisans had been to "chip out a mortar with their rude
               implements until it resembled a ball the size of a man's head or larger, connected by
               a small stem. This sphere was knocked or broken off, and then hollowed
               out&#8212;doubtless by women&#8212;by a tedious process with stone implements . . ."
               The explorer saw "half-made mortars, others a third made, still fastened to the rock,
               almost perfect ones in the bush hard by, while the steatite ledge was covered in
               places with the scars of mortars which had been successfully removed." </p>
            <p>Among the early excavators on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                  Islands</placeName> were <persName type="author" key="#sbo">Stephen
                  Bowers</persName>, for the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">American
                  Museum of Natural History</orgName> and <persName type="author" key="#psc">Paul
                  Schumacher</persName>, who was commissioned by the <orgName type="government"
                  key="#gov_usa">United States Government</orgName> and sent huge collections to the
                  <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName> and
               to the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_peabody">Peabody Museum</orgName> in the <date
                  notBefore="1870" notAfter="1879">1870s</date>. In <date when="1877">1887</date>
               <persName type="author" key="#cho">Dr. Holder</persName> and <persName key="#wchan"
                  >Dr. William Channing</persName> of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_boston"
                  >Boston</placeName> "trenched down through four or five layers of graves at
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_isthmus1">the Isthmus</placeName>." The upper
               layers contained European objects but nothing made of metal was found in the lower
               strata.</p>
            <p>Excavations have been made by contemporary scientists, who are aided by the methods
               developed by modern archeology but severely handicapped by the wholesale destruction
               of most of the sites by "pot-hunters" of the past. Notable among the more recent
               archeologists who have worked on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                  Islands</placeName> are <persName type="author" key="#bbr">Bruce Bryan</persName>,
                  <persName key="#mrog">Malcolm Rogers</persName>, <persName type="author"
                  key="#awo">Arthur Woodward</persName> and <persName key="#porr">Phil
                  Orr</persName>. An article in the <date when="1953-10">October, 1953</date>, issue
               of <emph><rs>American Antiquity</rs></emph> by <persName type="author" key="#cme"
                  >Clement W. Meighan</persName> and <persName type="author" key="#heb">Hal
                  Eberhart</persName> reports a reconnaissance of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> made by these two writers and
               summarizes the work of those mentioned above.</p>
            <p>At various times between <date from="1958" to="1960">1958 and 1960</date>
               <persName key="#croz">Charles Rozaire</persName> and <persName type="author"
                  key="#bbr">Bruce Bryan</persName> of the <orgName type="museum"
                  key="#mu_southwest">Southwest Museum</orgName> have worked on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, and the results have
               been published in short papers in <emph><orgName type="publication" key="#masterkey"
                     >The Masterkey</orgName></emph>, published by the museum. A richly stratified
               site was excavated on the southeast shore of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the island</placeName></rs> which yielded numerous examples of material woven
               from sea grass (grass skirts, mats, etc.). Several new and unknown types of selvage
               were included among these fragments, some of which were found at a depth of about
               nine feet. Two or three metates, considered by some to have been lacking in San
               Nicolas culture, were also found by the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_southwest"
                  >Southwest Museum</orgName>.</p>
            <p>In <date when="1959">1959</date>, on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     same island</placeName></rs>, archeologists of the <orgName type="institution"
                  key="#in_ucla">University of California, Los Angeles</orgName>, found a group of
               very interesting burials with which many tarred baskets were closely associated.
                     <rs><orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucla">This university</orgName></rs>
               is at present doing work at various sites on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas Island</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                  Clemente</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>
               Islands.</p>
            <p>An answer to the question of whether or not <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn; #i_scl; #i_an">these islands</placeName></rs> were occupied before
               the coming of the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                  >Gabrielinos</orgName> seems to be given in the affirmative in the recent
               excavation by <persName type="author" key="#cme">Meighan</persName>, the one which
               may be viewed by tourists on the crest of the heights above <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_littleharbor">Little Harbor</placeName> on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>. Here there was evidence of an
               occupancy going back at least 4,000 years, which well antedates the probable arrival
               of the Indians of Shoshonean stock. The settlement below, in <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_littleharbor">Little Harbor</placeName> itself, had been so thoroughly
               gutted by pot-hunters that not much could be learned about it, although it was
               certainly Gabrielino and occupied in historic times as the U.C.L.A. party found trade
               beads at the site.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#cme">Meighan</persName> believed the material he found
               on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> to go back less than
               a thousand years, but <persName key="#porr">Orr</persName> saw parallels there with
               discoveries he had made on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa
                  Rosa</placeName> of a "Dune Dweller" culture of great antiquity. Carbon-14 tests
               have placed materials from Dune Dweller burials on the latter, more northern, island
               at about 7,000 years ago. More recently, in still older strata on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, <persName key="#porr"
                  >Orr</persName> has found charred bones of an extinct Ice Age "dwarf" elephant
               that had apparently been cooked and eaten by man. These have been dated by Carbon-14
               as being about 29,000 years old.</p>
            <p>No such sensational finds have been made in the southern group, although one cannot
               predict what knowledge could come from comprehensive work, backed with sufficient
               funds and carried on by such reputable men and institutions as have done the recent
               surveys and excavations.</p>
            <p>It is impossible to apply with any degree of certainty any of the traditional
               Gabrielino place names to the villages which once existed on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, although the island itself is
               listed by <persName type="author" key="#hre">Reid</persName> as
                  <emph>Pineug-na</emph>, by <persName type="author" key="#akroe">Kroeber</persName>
               as <emph>Pimu</emph> and <emph>Pipimar</emph>, and by <persName type="author"
                  key="#jha">J. P. Harringto</persName>n as <emph>Pimu'na</emph>, with "n" indicated
               as nasal, a form we have been transcribing as "ngna." <emph>Limu</emph>, as found in
               a record of an early Spanish explorer, was probably an incorrect recording of
                  <emph>Pimu</emph>. The Baptismal Register, as noted above, listed
                  <emph>Pipimas</emph> and the few survivors of the island were known as
                  <emph>Pipimares</emph>.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder</persName> did not use a single native name
               in his descriptions of the village sites on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, but in a work of fiction for
               juveniles, "The Adventures of Torqua," he made use of "literary license" in applying
               names from Reid's list&#8212;and one less fortunately chosen from Chumash
               sources&#8212;to the localities which his young Indian and Spanish heroes visited.
               Unfortunately an early pamphlet on the subject of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> appears to have copied two of these
               as factual, and thus set off a chain of repetition of these place names which seem to
               have no other claim to authenticity.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#hre">Reid</persName> assigned the name
                  <emph>Kinkipar</emph> to <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente
                  Island</placeName>, but <persName key="#jswanton">Swanton</persName> calls this
               the name of "a village on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                  Clemente</placeName>." As this duplicates that of a village in the <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> area, the meaning of which could
               perhaps be "Houses by the Sea," the application of the name to a village rather than
               to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> itself is
               confirmed by the small item of evidence.</p>
            <p>An insoluble puzzle may lie in the name on Reid's list, <emph>Harasg-na</emph>, the
               only one which he gave without assigning a location. This was mentioned by J. P.
               Harrington's informants as being "a place near <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp"
                  >San Pedro</placeName>," but also, as <emph>Xarasngna</emph>, quite clearly
               described as <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente Island</placeName>.
                  <persName key="#gudde">Gudde</persName> also mentions <emph>Kimki harasa</emph> as
               the Luiseño name for <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
               Clemente</placeName>.</p>
            <p>So far this information appears to harmonize, but one cannot ignore the fact that
                  <emph>Ghalas-at</emph>, the Chumash title for <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                  >San Nicolas</placeName>, as <persName type="author" key="#akroe"
                  >Kroeber</persName> points out, is probably the Chumash form of the Gabrielino
                  <emph>Harasg-na</emph>, as recorded by <persName type="author" key="#hre"
                  >Reid</persName>. The similarity is made more apparent when it is remembered that
               the northern tribe had no sound "r" and that "l" would be the normal substitute. </p>
            <p>J. P. Harrington's notes give the origin of this name in the term of
                  <emph>ijoxarin</emph>, meaning "stony," probably in the sense of "eroded," as his
               informants went on to explain this in the phrase, "We are living in the island of the
               uncovered earth." This is certainly an apt description of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, although <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> need not be excluded as a contender for the
               title.</p>
            <p>An Indian of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>
               would have been known as a <emph>Pimuvit</emph>, these old <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">Gabrielinos</orgName>
               agreed, but when at last there existed but a few individuals who traced their
               ancestry to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the
                  island</placeName></rs> they were known to the folk of the <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_la">Pueblo of Los Angeles</placeName>, near which they existed in a tiny
               settlement, not as <emph>Pimuvitam</emph> but as the <emph>Pipimares</emph>. <span
                  type="trope" n="6">They no longer seemed, to their almost equally diminished
                  tribesmen of <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, the
                  fierce wizards who had once fared across the rough channel waters from the
                  mysterious stronghold of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">their
                        island home</placeName></rs>. They were mild, quiet and aloof, and quite
                  soon they disappeared entirely from the dusty streets of <rs><placeName
                        type="city" key="#ci_la">the Pueblo</placeName></rs>, as they had some years
                  earlier from their beloved "mountains which are in sea."</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
