<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#horn">Horn Book
                     Magazine</orgName></title>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">67</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
               <date when="1991"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#bo">Boston</placeName><placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_ma">Massachusetts</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Lovelace1961">Scott O'Dell: A Biographical
                     Note</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="316" to="319"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#mlo">Maud Hart Lovelace</persName></author>
                  <note type="supplied">Sara can put note here</note>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><persName type="author" key="#sod">SCOTT
                        O'DELL</persName></hi></title> <title type="sub">A BIOGRAPHICAL
               NOTE</title></head>
            <byline><emph>By</emph>
               <persName type="author" key="#mlo">MAUD HART LOVELACE</persName></byline>
            <p><hi rend="bold">S</hi>COTT O'DELL's earliest recollections are of a house standing on
               stilts beside the <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">Pacific
                  Ocean</placeName>. The tide came up beneath it. This was on what is now <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_ti">Terminal Island</placeName>, near <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, where he was born. <rs><persName key="#bsc"
                     >His father</persName></rs> was a railroader, and the family moved frequently,
               keeping to the same general area. Never during Scott's boyhood was he far from the
               wash of the sea. This is one of several factors which explain the ring of authority
               in <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>.</p>
            <p>From his home in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>, where he
               lived from ages six to nine, he could almost see <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                  >San Nicolas</placeName>, <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island on
                     which <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an Indian
                        girl</persName></rs> had once lived alone for <rs><date from="1835"
                           to="1853" cert="high">eighteen years</date></rs></placeName></rs>.
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> then was a roaring port,
               overrun by seamen from tramp steamers and even a few sailing vessels. <rs><orgName
                     key="#odellelemsc">The school</orgName></rs> took its temper from
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">the town</placeName></rs>, with fights
               in the school yard every day. Scott's schoolmates were the sons of Portuguese and
               Italian fishermen, and at first did not take kindly to the <rs><persName
                     type="author" key="#sod">blue-eyed, Scotch-Irish, too-literate
                     O'Dell</persName></rs>. He was the butt of jokes and the target of bullies, and
               school was a frightening ordeal. Fortunately, he could hold his own in the pigmy
               battles, and no doubt he already had some of the effortless charm which is so much a
               part of him now. At last he was allowed to join the crowd on a Saturday expedition to
               the beach.</p>
            <p>Racing to their favorite cove, the boys stripped, climbed a steep bank, and leaped
               joyfully into the surf. <persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott</persName> did not
               mention not knowing how to swim. He would have preferred drowning to confessing such
               damning ignorance. He leaped, along with the rest, and somehow dogpaddled to
               shore.</p>
            <p>After that, such excursions filled every Saturday . . . in summer, almost every day.
               The boys swam. They dug cockles and steamed them in a washtub borrowed from an
               amiable mother. Someone always brought along a long loaf of chewy Italian bread. They
               gathered abalones and searched submerged rocks for little devilfish and came to know
               the world of beach and sea.</p>
            <p>By the time he entered <orgName type="institution" key="#in_longbeach">Long Beach
                  Polytechnic High School</orgName>, Scott's present easy gregariousness was
               established. He excelled in water polo and the 440-yard dash. With little effort he
               achieved fine grades, and in <!--when was this exactly, for sure?-->his sophomore
               year found time to make a collection of synopses of forty plays . . . not for a
               school project, but for fun.</p>
            <p>He started college at California's <orgName type="institution" key="#in_occidental"
                  >Occidental</orgName> when the emphasis was chiefly on military training and
               getting into World War One. But the war ended, and he had the inspired idea that
               attending a different college every year would be a fine way to see the world. So he
               moved on to the <orgName type="institution" key="#in_uofwis">University of
                  Wisconsin</orgName>. He ended there with only a B average.</p>
            <p>"I was chagrined. I wanted top grades but wasn't used to working for them."</p>
            <p>At <orgName type="institution" key="#in_stanford">Stanford</orgName>, he revolted
               against the curriculum, which seemed to reserve the most fascinating subjects for
               seniors and graduate students. He became a special student, and took twelve hours of
               philosophy, including the beginning course and the one most advanced, also courses in
                  <persName type="author" key="#wsh">Shakespeare</persName> and Russian Literature.
               Then, gorged with learning, he went to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_hollywood"
                  >Hollywood</placeName> and taught a mail-order course in photoplay writing,
               producing a textbook on the subject.</p>
            <p>This was the glamorous <placeName type="city" key="#ci_hollywood"
                  >Hollywood</placeName> of <persName key="#gga">Greta Garbo</persName> and
                  <persName key="#rva">Rudolph Valentino</persName>, and soon <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">Scott</persName> was working in <orgName key="#paramount"
                  >Paramount</orgName>'s technical department preparing sets. He changed to <orgName
                  key="#mecto">Mecto-Goldwyn-Mayer</orgName> and was sent to <persName type="city"
                  key="#ci_rom">Rome</persName> for the filming of <emph>Ben Hur</emph>. In off
               hours, he studied at the <orgName type="institution" key="#urome">University of
                  Rome</orgName>, and this ended his unorthodox college career.</p>
            <p>When the last wheel in Ben Hur's chariot race had turned, he went to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_flo">Florence</placeName> and wrote
               <!--It would be cool to know which one-->a novel.</p>
            <p>"<emph>Pinfeathers</emph>. It was an appropriate title," he says. For after he
               returned to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nyc">New York</placeName>, an agent
               advised him to write it off to experience, all 100,000 words of it.</p>
            <p>Back in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_hollywood">Hollywood</placeName>, he kept on
               writing, worked on magazines and newspapers, and ranched with <rs><persName
                     key="#bsc">his father</persName></rs>, who had bought an orange grove near
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_cla">Claremont</placeName>. Here <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">Scott</persName> discovered the old Spanish families of
               the <placeName type="region" key="#re_pva">Pomona Valley</placeName>, visiting their
               ranchos and listening to evocative tales of the past. This led to his fine historical
               novel, <emph>Hill of the Hawk</emph>. He wrote
               <!--It would be cool to know which one-->three novels in all and <emph>Country of the
                  Sun</emph>, an informal history of the nine <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName> counties.</p>
            <p>It was in the period of the early novels that he owned <rs><name key="#ericveb">Eric
                     von Ebrochtal</name></rs>, the nobly handsome German shepherd, brother of <name
                  key="#sthe">Strongheart</name>, who shared his life for
               <!--when? would be cool to know?-->seven years.</p>
            <p>"I took him with me everywhere. I stayed only in hotels that would accept him. He
               never saw a kennel."</p>
            <p>During Eric's final illness, <rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">his
                     master</persName></rs> nursed him with loving sorrow, played a fan upon him
               through long hot summer nights. When <persName type="author" key="#sod"
                  >Scott</persName> tells of his death, it sounds like the death of <rs><name
                     type="fictional" key="#ron">Karana's dog</name></rs>, <name type="fictional"
                  key="#ron">Rontu</name>.</p>
            <p>"Slowly, he walked to where I was standing and fell at my feet. I put my hand on his
               chest. I could feel his heart beating, very slowly . . . and then no more."</p>
            <p>There are French Poodles around <placeName key="#stoneapple">Stoneapple
                  Farm</placeName> in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ju">Julian</placeName>,
                  <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, where <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">Scott</persName> lives now. He is married to his gay,
               exciting <persName key="#jod">Dorsa</persName>, daughter of <persName key="#wra"
                  >Mr.</persName> and <persName key="#mwra">Mrs. William H. Rattenbury</persName> of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nb">New Britain</placeName>, <placeName
                  type="state" key="#st_ct">Connecticut</placeName>, and <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_cla">Claremont</placeName>. She gives, he says, valuable editorial advice
               and even types his manuscripts. The poodles romp about the book-lined living room,
               snooze beside the huge fireplace, sniff appreciatively in the roomy old-fashioned
               kitchen, and keep quiet in their master's study.</p>
            <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_ju">Julian</placeName> is not far from two Indian
               reservations, and <persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott</persName> is
               knowledgeable about the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Cupenos"
                  >Cupeños</orgName> and the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_Luisenos">Luiseños</orgName> but he learned more about the Indian
               temperament, he says, from the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_Tarascan">Tarascan Indians</orgName> whom he and <persName key="#jod"
                  >Dorsa</persName> came to know during a summer near <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_pat">Lake Pátzcuaro</placeName> in <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</placeName>.</p>
            <p>They lived in the guest cottage on an estate cared for by <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#pfl">the Indian father of nine
                  children</persName></rs>. <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car"
                  >Carolina</persName>, the sixteen-year-old eldest, was <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#car">the O'Dells' cook</persName></rs>. The others
               hung around all day and in late afternoon came inside to chatter over chocolate and
                  <emph>buñuelos</emph> with the friendly, relaxed, soft-voiced <emph><rs><persName
                        type="author" key="#sod">señor</persName></rs></emph> and the blonde smiling
                        <emph><rs><persName key="#jod">señora</persName></rs></emph>. This family
               sponsored <rs><persName type="group" key="#jod; #sod">the Americans</persName></rs>
               at secret <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan"
                  >Tarascan</orgName>
               <emph>fiestas</emph>, helped them obtain a native canoe.</p>
            <p>"We used to take <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car">Carolina</persName> to
               the Friday market," <persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott</persName> says.
               "Anything we bought as a gift for her she would take home carefully to share with her
               brothers and sisters."</p>
            <p>It is not hard, when he talks of <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car"
                  >Carolina</persName>, to see <name type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name>
               caring for <rs><name type="fictional" key="#ram">her little brother</name></rs>.</p>
            <p>Scott O'Dell's life brought him naturally a knowledge of Indians, dogs, and the
               ocean; and he was born with an inability to keep away from writing. So he gave us the
               moving legend of <name type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
