<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#paccoastarch">Pacific Coast
                     Archaeological Society Quarterly</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="28"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="4"/>
               <date when="1992-09-01"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#costamesa">Costa Mesa</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ca">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#SchwartzMartz1992">Overview of the Archaeology of San
                     Nicolas Island, Southern California</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="73"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#ssc">Schwartz, Steven J.
                     Schwartz</persName></author>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#patmartz">Martz,
                     Patricia</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">AN OVERVIEW OF THE ARCHAEOLOGY OF <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">SAN NICOLAS ISLAND</placeName>, <placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_socal">SOUTHERN
               CALIFORNIA</placeName></hi></title></head>
            <byline><persName type="author" key="#ssc">Steven J. Schwartz</persName> and <persName
                  type="author" key="#patmartz">Patricia Martz</persName></byline>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">ABSTRACT</title></head>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, the outermost
                  of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_southernchi">southern Channel
                     Islands</placeName>, has been investigated for over 100 years, but little of it
                  has been adequately analyzed and published. The available reports, which are
                  mostly unpublished, show that <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs> was occupied as early as 6,000 years ago. Midden
                  samples reveal a wide variety of shellfish, fish, and sea mammal bone indicating a
                  marine subsistence focus. Burials and a variety of artifacts, such as pestles,
                  bowl fragments, bone implements, basketry impressions, cobble tools, shell beads,
                  and fishhooks, reflect a broad range of cultural activities and suggest permanent
                  settlement. These data form the basis for planning further work in terms of
                  contemporary research goals to better understand the island's prehistory and human
                  adaptations to this restricted environment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">INTRODUCTION AND BACKGROUND</title></head>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> is located
                  approximately 120 km southwest of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                     Angeles</placeName> and 102 km from the nearest point of land at <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_pmugu">Point Mugu, California</placeName> (Fig. 1). It
                  is 14 km long and 5 km wide. At the time of European contact, <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> was occupied by
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                        >Indians</orgName></rs> who probably spoke one of the Cupan languages in the
                  Takic family, which is part of the Uto-Aztecan linguistic stock. <span
                     type="trope" n="6">This assumption is based on a few words that were recorded
                     as spoken by <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the last
                           survivor</persName></rs>, a woman who was left behind on <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> when <rs><persName
                           type="group" key="#bhagroup">the remaining small
                        population</persName></rs> was removed to <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> in <date when="1835">1835</date>
                     (Bean and Smith <date when="1978">1978</date>; Eisen <date when="1905"
                        >1905</date>; Meighan and Eberhart <date when="1953"
                  >1953</date>).</span></p>
               <p>There was archaeological interest in <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas Island</placeName> as early as the <date from="1870" to="1879"
                     >1870s</date>. Investigators such as <persName type="author" key="#psc">Paul
                     Schumacher</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#lce">Léon de
                     Cessac</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#sbo">Stephen
                  Bowers</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#bbr">Bruce Bryan</persName>,
                     <persName key="#mrog">Malcolm Rogers</persName>, <persName type="author"
                     key="#awo">Arthur Woodward</persName> (<date>n.d.</date>), and <persName
                     key="#porr">Phil Orr</persName> (<date when="1945">1945</date> and <date
                     when="1946">1946</date>) have all worked on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. Numerous surveys and excavations
                  have been conducted, though for the most part these investigations have gone
                  unreported. As <persName type="author" key="#cme">Meighan</persName> and <persName
                     type="author" key="#heb">Eberhart</persName> (<date when="1953"
                  >1953</date>:113) remarked,</p>
               <p>None of these collections have been published except for brief notes on
                  exceptional pieces. Although many of the collections were made by untrained
                  individuals in the days before scientific records were kept, it is nonetheless
                  regrettable that despite some 15,000 specimens from <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> preserved in American museums so little is
                  known of the island's archaeology.</p>
               <p>Meighan and Eberhart's paper "Archaeological Resources of San Nicolas Island,
                  California" (<date when="1953">1953</date>) marked a major shift in archaeological
                  studies on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>. As
                  the title implies, the shift was toward looking at archaeological sites as
                  "resources" which could be used to answer specific research questions. The
                  majority of subsequent work has been question-oriented and the level of
                  documentation has increased dramatically.</p>
               <p><persName key="#reinman">Fred Reinman</persName> began work at <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> during the <date
                     notBefore="1956" notAfter="1959">late 1950s</date>. His investigations include
                  the excavation of six burial sites (Reinman and Townsend <date when="1960"
                     >1960</date>), a survey of the upper plateau of <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> (Reinman <date when="1962"
                     >1962</date>), and a series of test excavations to clarify cultural sequences
                  at SNI-11 and SNI-16 (Lauter <date>n.d.</date>a and <date>n.d.</date>b; <persName
                     key="#reinman">Reinman</persName>
                  <date>n.d.</date>a and <date>n.d.</date>b; <persName key="#reinman"
                     >Reinman</persName> and <persName key="#lauter">Lauter</persName>
                  <date>n.d.</date>a). In addition, an intensive, systematic survey of the entire
                  island was conducted by <persName key="#reinman">Reinman</persName> in <date
                     from="1983" to="1984">1983-1984</date> as a resource management project. The
                  purpose of this survey was to locate all of the visible archaeological resources,
                  provide information regarding integrity and eligibility for the <orgName
                     key="#nationalregister">National Register of Historic Places</orgName>, and
                  provide recommendations for further research and management (Reinman and Lauter
                     <date>n.d.</date>b).</p>
               <p>In spite of all of the attention that the island's archaeological resources have
                  received, only ten of the 500 known sites have been excavated and reported on
                  specifically. Of the ten, one is located on the central plateau, two are on the
                  southern shore, and seven are on the northwest shore (Fig. 2).</p>
               <p>Although ten sites have been excavated, five of these investigations were limited
                  to removal of exposed burials; the midden areas were not tested (Reinman and
                  Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>). Sites SNI-38 and SNI-51 were tested by
                     <persName key="#croz">Rozaire</persName> (<date when="1959">1959</date>) for
                  the express purpose of locating woven materials for an analysis of the weaving
                  technique; some midden analysis was performed incidentally. Three sites, SNI-11,
                  SNI-16, and SNI-79, have been examined primarily for midden constituents (Reinman
                     <date when="1964">1964</date>). Of these, the most fully reported to date is
                  SNI-11, which was the subject of two Master's theses (Clevenger <date>n.d.</date>;
                     <persName key="#bleitz">Bleitz-Sanburg</persName>
                  <date>n.d.</date>a), part of a dissertation (Salls <date>n.d.</date>b), and a site
                  report (Reinman <date>n.d.</date>a). SNI-16 was the basis for one Master's thesis
                  (Lauter <date>n.d.</date>a) emphasizing chronology.</p>
               <p>This lack of reporting has resulted in a very limited knowledge of the island's
                  archaeology. Future research should increase understanding of the cultural
                  processes. To this end, a preliminary research design has been developed, and
                  archaeological investigations are currently being conducted by <orgName
                     key="#csula">California State University, Los Angeles (CSULA)</orgName>, under
                  the direction of <persName type="author" key="#patmartz">Patricia Martz</persName>
                  . [sic] Excavations were also conducted by <orgName key="#csuf">California State
                     University, Fullerton</orgName>, and <persName key="#chaffey">Chaffey
                     College</persName> in <date when="1991">1991</date>, and these data will be
                  analyzed at <orgName key="#csula">CSULA</orgName> and integrated into a
                  comprehensive research design. This review of the past archaeological work on
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> reflects
                  the current interest in developing new research into the prehistory of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and
                  provides the background for these studies.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-11, Thousand Springs Site</title></head>
                  <p>The Thousand Springs site is the only extensively excavated site on
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> that
                     has been adequately reported. The site is located on the island's northwest
                     coast near one of the main water sources, near a rocky intertidal zone. SNI-11
                     is a large dune site measuring some 450 by 200 m. The site is subdivided into
                     four mounds designated A, B, C, and D. At least three strata are observable in
                     Mound B. The site was tested on two occasions &#8212; first by the <orgName
                        key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA Archaeological Survey</orgName> in <date when="1959"
                        >1959</date> (Reinman and Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>) and then
                     by <orgName key="#csula">CSULA</orgName> in <date from="1977" to="1979"
                        >1977-79</date> (Reinman <date>n.d.</date>a). The site is still considered
                     to have excellent research potential.</p>
                  <p>A series of column samples were taken in <date when="1959">1959</date> by the
                        <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA Archaeological Survey</orgName>. The depth
                     of the midden varied in the units, ranging from 38 to 56 cm below the present
                     surface. Three samples from three locations along the western edge of Mound A
                     were examined for midden constituents. Analysis revealed that four main
                     shellfish species were present in the midden: abalone, tegula, mussel, and sea
                     urchin. The exploitation of these species changed through time. The procurement
                     of mussels remained relatively constant, while abalone usage increased and
                     tegula usage decreased. The usage of sea urchin increased and then decreased
                     through time and seemed to fluctuate more than the others (Reinman <date
                        when="1964">1964</date>).</p>
                  <p>In <date from="1977" to="1979">1977-79</date>
                     <orgName key="#csula">CSULA</orgName> excavated fifteen 1.5- by 1.5-m test
                     units. The material was screened through 1/4-inch mesh. A number of radiocarbon
                     dates have been processed from this site making it the best-dated site on
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                     (Table 1).</p>
                  <p>Based on a preliminary analysis prior to the submission of the radiocarbon
                     samples, <persName key="#reinman">Reinman</persName> suggested that the
                     artifacts indicate a good stratigraphic context with Late Period fish hooks in
                     the upper Stratum I, and bone fish gorges, leaf-shaped projectile points, and
                     bifaces in the lower strata (<date>n.d.</date>a). However, a review of the
                     radiocarbon dates reveals some stratigraphic inconsistencies and indicates the
                     need for a re-evaluation of the sampling and processing procedures, as well as
                     a better understanding of the post-depositional processes of a sand dune midden
                     site. For example, Mound B, Stratum I, has a 2469-2046 B.C. (4419-3996 B.P.)
                     date and an A.D. 1280-1387 (670-536 B.P.) date at 10-20 cm. A date of 4894-4846
                     B.C. (6844-6796 B.P.) overlies that of 2869-2701 B.C. (4819-4651 B.P.) in
                     Stratum III. Mound A contains only Stratum I, and the base of the mound, dated
                     at 399-123 B.C. (2349-2073 B.P.), is overlain by a date of 3036-2896 B.C.
                     (4986-4846 B.P).[sic] at the 30-40 cm level. The site is complex, with four
                     mounds (A,B,C,D); three strata (I, II, III) are represented in Mounds B and C.
                     The strata are separated by light-colored sand with few cultural materials. All
                     three strata had surface expressions on sloping sides and eroded tops of the
                     mounds.</p>
                  <p>All of the dates are from charcoal samples, which leaves us with at least three
                     possible explanations: (1) some of the charcoal may have been contaminated with
                     asphaltum which would produce an older date: (2) the charcoal samples were not
                     in their original stratigraphic context; and (3) the stratigraphy of the site
                     is not as undisturbed as it appears. Additional radiocarbon samples, obsidian
                     sourcing, and soils and geomorphological studies are needed to resolve these
                     issues.</p>
                  <p><persName key="#bleitz">Bleitz</persName> (<date when="1991">1991</date>)
                     provides an analysis of a basketry impression found in a lump of asphaltum
                     recovered from Stratum III, Mound B, at a depth of 90 cm. The impression is
                     from a basket which was made by the coiling technique. The coiling was
                     clockwise. This find may push the introduction of coiled basketry into
                        <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> back earlier
                     than 2000 B.C.</p>
                  <p><persName key="#salls">Salls</persName> (<date>n.d.</date>b) analyzed the fish
                     remains from SNI-11 as part of his dissertation research. Two test units were
                     analyzed, one from Mound A which contained materials assigned to Stratum I, and
                     one from Mound B which represented Strata II and III.</p>
                  <p>The intensity of fishing at this site resembles that of modem commercial
                     fisheries. A total of 43,404 specimens were recovered, the equivalent of 5,293
                     per cubic meter. The total minimum number of individuals was 2,193. The fish
                     specimens per cubic meter are more than five times as many compared to what may
                     be the densest site on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente
                        Island</placeName>, Eel Point (SCI-43C), even though that sample was
                     screened with 1/8-inch mesh compared to the 1/4-inch mesh used at SNI-11.</p>
                  <p>The exceptionally wide diversity of fishes recovered from SNI-11 (some 70
                     species) indicates a non-selective fishery. There does not appear to be a
                     preferred species such as was documented for <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_scl">San Clemente Island</placeName> where sheephead was the most
                     common species at every site examined (Salls <date>n.d.</date>b). The fish
                     sample from SNI-11 indicates a watercraft-oriented strategy where hook-and-line
                     fishing was extremely important &#8212; many were rock and kelp fishes. Dip
                     nets, drift or gill nets, and beach seines were also probably used, as
                     indicated by the presence of small schooling fish such as sardines and
                     silversides.</p>
                  <p>The analysis disclosed that 78% of the bones were from the head, while only 22%
                     were other body parts. One possible explanation for this anomaly is that
                     preparation and cooking methods may have exposed the vertebrae to differential
                     preservation rates. Many large bowls, mortars, and pestles have been recovered
                     from <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. It
                     has been proposed that the grinding implements were used for processing fish.
                     An alternate interpretation is that the fish were prepared for off-site or
                     off-island consumption, in which case the heads were removed for transport to
                     reduce bulk.</p>
                  <p>Eighteen otoliths from SNI-11 were examined for seasonality data (Huddleston
                        <date>n.d.</date>; Salls <date>n.d.</date>b). Seasonality readings were
                     obtainable on all specimens. Seventeen of the otoliths, representing 94% of the
                     sample, were captured in the winter season, from approximately early October to
                     mid-May. Only a single specimen was from a fish caught in the summer. The 17
                     otoliths with rings indicating winter capture were subdivided into fall and
                     late winter/early spring periods. Eleven (65%) were fall (early October to the
                     end of December). The remaining six fish were caught during the late
                     winter/early spring (early March to mid-May).</p>
                  <p>Analysis of the mammal and bird bone (Bleitz-Sanburg <date>n.d.</date>a)
                     indicates an emphasis on the hunting of fur-bearing marine mammals. There is a
                     gradual decrease over time in the acquisition of large pinnipeds, such as
                     elephant seals and sea lions. Although the quantities do not indicate that they
                     were a primary focus, there was a marked increase in the procurement of
                     dolphins and porpoises.</p>
                  <p>The complex of birds identified at SNI-11 suggests a pattern of exploitation
                     centered offshore and around the kelp beds, which was incidental to a more
                     generalized fishing procurement strategy. The range of bird species appears to
                     diminish in the Late Period.</p>
                  <p>A wide variety of mammals is characteristic for the Late Period. The
                     distribution of mammalian fauna reflects an insular shore-based collecting and
                     hunting pattern, which was dominated during the late occupation by an
                     intensified exploitation of offshore fauna foraging in and around the kelp
                     beds.</p>
                  <p>Lithic analysis was undertaken on 7,000 debitage flakes recovered from Mound B
                     (Clevenger <date>n.d.</date>). Based on this analysis, it is proposed that the
                     lithic manufacturing strategy represents an attempt by the inhabitants of
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> to
                     make use of locally-available lithic materials and limit dependence on
                     off-island resources. <persName key="#clevenger">Clevenger</persName>
                     determined that they were using relatively small, coarse-textured
                     metasedimentary and metavolcanic cobbles, available in conglomorate bed
                     exposures on the island, as a source of raw material rather than imported
                     lithic material of better quality. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The
                           island</placeName></rs> is formed of sedimentary rock, and the materials
                     favored by flintknappers, such as cherts and volcanics, are not available.
                        <persName key="#clevenger">Clevenger</persName> describes the tool
                     production method as a "split cobble reduction strategy" using a bipolar
                     flaking technique. The tools made in this manner, while rather crude in
                     appearance, were evidently adequate for the processing of fish and
                     shellfish.</p>
                  <p>Obsidian hydration measurements were made on two small flakes from this site
                     (Table 2). Interpretation of the measurements is problematical because the
                     obsidian was not sourced and the samples were not recovered from the same or
                     equivalent depositional contexts as the radiocarbon samples. If, based on
                     information from <placeName type="regionn" key="#re_mld">the
                        mainland</placeName> (e.g., <placeName key="#orangeco">Orange
                        County</placeName>), we were to make the assumption that the obsidian is
                     from <placeName key="#coso">Coso</placeName>, there is a considerable range of
                     age estimates for hydration rates proposed for Coso obsidian. For example, the
                     range for five microns is from 712-3125 years B.P. (Hall <date when="1988"
                        >1988</date>:37). Interpretation may be possible in the future through the
                     dating of carbon, which may be available in curated column samples recovered
                     from the same depositional contexts as the obsidian. Lacking this information
                     it is not possible to say more than that the hydration rims of 5.4 and 7.7 are
                     consistent with the stratigraphy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-14</title></head>
                  <p>SNI-14 is located on the northwest coast of <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. It is a sparse shell midden,
                     approximately 165 by 105 m in extent and 10-50 cm deep, capping a large sand
                     dune. The site is situated near a rocky shoreline area. SNI-14 was
                     test-excavated by the <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA Archaeological
                        Survey</orgName> in <date when="1959">1959</date> to recover an exposed
                     burial (Reinman and Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>The burial was a primary inhumation of an infant. It was tightly flexed and
                     lying on its right side. The orientation was undetermined. No pathologies were
                     noted. Metric data are available in <persName key="#rootenberg"
                        >Rootenberg</persName> (<date when="1960">1960</date>). Accompanying the
                     burial were 11 spire-lopped olivella beads and a bone implement made from a
                     mammal long bone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-15</title></head>
                  <p>SNI-15 is situated above a rock intertidal shore on the northwest coast of
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. It
                     consists of patches of midden on two large dunes connected by a low saddle. The
                     occupation debris is 10-20 cm deep and extends over an area 260 by 140 m.
                     SNI-15 was test-excavated by the <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA
                        Archaeological Survey</orgName> in <date when="1959">1959</date> to recover
                     an exposed burial (Reinman and Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>A single burial was found weathering out of the sand at the base of the dune.
                     It was a primary inhumation of a young adult female in a tightly flexed
                     position, lying on the right side. The skull exhibited some degree of occipital
                     protrusion or "bunning." Metric data are available in <persName
                        key="#rootenberg">Rootenberg</persName> (<date when="1960">1960</date>).
                     Associated with the burial were 568 tubular bird-bone beads in the chest and
                     neck regions, perhaps indicating a necklace. Several of the bone beads were
                     incised. A steatite bead and a bone awl were also with the burial.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-16</title></head>
                  <p>SNI-16 is located on the northwest coast of <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. It is a typical dune site,
                     consisting of patches of shell midden capping a large dune approximately 2,580
                     m in length and some 25 m high. Observable midden covers an area of about 428
                     by 123 m. SNI-16 has been tested on three different occasions (Reinman and
                     Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>; Reinman <date when="1964">1964</date>;
                     Lauter <date>n.d.</date>b).</p>
                  <p>A burial area was excavated by the <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA
                        Archaeological Survey</orgName> in <date when="1958">1958</date> (Reinman
                     and Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>). The burial area was located on the
                     landward end of the dune. It was approximately 15-20 m below the midden remains
                     on the top of the dune and followed what would seem to be the preferred burial
                     pattern in that it was off the main midden in a fairly level area.</p>
                  <p>Forty-three 5- by 5-foot squares were excavated to depths ranging from 24 to 36
                     inches. Much of the excavation area had been previously disturbed by relic
                     hunters. The most productive area was located in the most heavily disturbed
                     portion of the site. In this area, in addition to Burials 2 and 3, a large
                     number of abalone and mussel shell pendants of many types, stone and bone
                     pendants, and large numbers of scattered human and animal bones were found.
                     Scattered among the bones, pendants, and burials were many small basketry
                     fragments containing red ochre, as well as a number of beads of steatite and
                     shell. On the surface were scattered a number of skull and long-bone fragments.
                     In addition to these, a number must have been destroyed by the extensive
                     erosion that has taken place on this end of <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.</p>
                  <p>In all, three burials were recovered that could be considered undisturbed.
                     Burial 1 was a young female buried face down, tightly flexed. The burial
                     exhibited exostosis of the auditory meatus and occipital protrusion or
                     "bunning," congenitally-missing mandibular third molars, and an abscessed tooth
                     (Rootenberg <date when="1960">1960</date>). No artifacts were recovered with
                     this burial. Burial 2 was a male in a tightly-flexed sitting position with the
                     skull partially protruding through its covering of asphaltum-coated matting or
                     basketry. The hands were covering the face. Several steatite and bone beads and
                     pendants accompanied this burial. Burial 3 was an infant either wrapped in
                     asphaltum-coated matting or placed in a basket. It was unaccompanied by
                     artifacts. Metric data for these burials are available in <persName
                        key="#rootenberg">Rootenberg</persName> (<date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>A total of 394 artifacts was recovered from this excavation. Of this number 147
                     were shell pendants. Most were unassociated with the recovered burials but were
                     found in the other excavation units. A number of them can be attributed to
                     burials previously destroyed by erosion, but many were also found in various
                     units either out of the disturbed area or below the level of disturbance. In
                     several of the units human mandibles, skull fragments, and long bones were
                     found in situations of partial articulation as well as in complete disorder.
                     Some of these bone assemblages might possibly represent the practice of
                     reburial. Excavation to a depth of 36 inches to sterile sand failed to reveal
                     any deeper burials.</p>
                  <p>Additional work was performed at the site in <date when="1962">1962</date>
                     (Reinman <date when="1964">1964</date>) to explore the midden area. The site
                     was divided into four separate mounds (designated from the seaward end to
                     inland as Mounds A, B, C, and D). Midden remains are found on each of the four
                     mounds and each was tested during the excavation. Eleven 5- by 5-foot pits were
                     excavated (one in Mound A, four in Mounds B and C, and two in Mound D). The
                     maximum midden depth of 36 inches was found on Mound A and the shallowest on
                     Mound B, where the midden ended between 0 and 6 inches from the surface. In
                     addition to the excavation of the units, column samples were taken from each
                     mound to provide data on the midden constituents. Two radiocarbon samples were
                     processed (Table 1).</p>
                  <p>The total number of artifacts recovered in the excavations, including those
                     gathered from the surface, was 138; 98 were stone, 25 bone, and 14 shell. In
                     addition, a single basketry impression was found on Mound B. A total of 19
                     cubic yards of midden was excavated, with the greatest amount taken from Mound
                     C.</p>
                  <p>The most recent excavations at SNI-16 were directed toward establishing a
                     chronology specific to the island (Lauter <date>n.d.</date>a,
                     <date>n.d.</date>b). The excavations centered on known midden areas and
                     artifacts noted on the surface. Eight 1.5- by 1.5-m units were excavated.</p>
                  <p>The midden consisted of several strata that were identifiable by their color.
                     Abalone shells and shell lenses occurred frequently in all test pits. Mussel,
                     tegula, land snail, and sea urchin were abundant in every pit and at most
                     levels. Tegula, sea urchin, and land snails were found primarily in pockets or
                     lenses and may represent a single processing event. These pockets are
                     distributed throughout the site and occasionally may be seen eroding out of the
                     surface or sides of the dune in small piles. Chiton, limpet, norissia,
                     olivella, and astrea were found in all pits as were fish, bird, and sea mammal
                     bone. Artifacts total 708; 347 are utilitarian objects and 361 are
                     ornamental.</p>
                  <p>Obsidian hydration measurements were made on three flakes found in the
                     excavations and two from previous excavations (Table 2). Three have been
                     sourced to <placeName key="#coso">Coso</placeName> and one to <placeName
                        key="#casadiablo">Casa Diablo</placeName> (Janet Scalise, personal
                     communication, <date when="1993">1993</date>). As mentioned previously,
                     accurate interpretation of the measurements would require sourcing of the
                     obsidian and the dating of carbon from the same depositional contexts as the
                     obsidian.</p>
                  <p>One burial was recovered in the <date when="1979">1979</date> excavations. The
                     burial was a primary inhumation, positioned on its left side, loosely flexed,
                     and oriented toward the north. It has been identified as a probable female
                     about 35-40 years of age with no evident pathologies (Salls
                     <date>n.d.</date>a). Associated objects included a side-notched projectile
                     point fragment, a sea mammal tooth pendant, a sea mammal effigy, a clam shell
                     ring, a worked clam shell object, and three steatite pendants, two of which had
                     biconical perforations. The remains were in very poor condition due to natural
                     decomposition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-18</title></head>
                  <p>SNI-18 is located near the northwest tip of <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> with major rocky intertidal zones
                     both to the east and west sides of the site. These adjacent areas currently are
                     a major rookery for western gulls, Brandt's comorants, and California sea
                     lions. It is a very high dune site, about 700 by 175 m, consisting of shell
                     midden scattered over the top and sides. It is probably the largest remaining
                     site on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.
                     Excavations were undertaken by the <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA
                        Archaeological Survey</orgName> in <date when="1959">1959</date> centering
                     on an exposed burial area (Reinman and Townsend <date when="1960"
                     >1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>Burial 1 was observed weathering out of the sand on top of the dune. Burials 2
                     and 3 were discovered about 100 feet east, also eroding out of the midden.
                     Burials 2 and 3 had been disturbed. The skeletons were not articulated, and the
                     bones ranged in depth from the surface to 35 inches. It is possible that they
                     are reburials that were disturbed when the graves were dug for Burials 4 and 5,
                     which were immediately below. The only artifact associated with Burial 4 was a
                     large ball of yellow ochre in the pelvic region. Burial 5 was slightly below
                     this burial and somewhat to the west; it was evidently the cause for the
                     disturbance of the previous burials. It was an adult male, tightly flexed,
                     lying on the left side, with several artifacts in association. Included were a
                     hafted point, four complete abalone fishhooks, a stone pipe, and a possible
                     "treasure box" consisting of four interlocking abalone shells that contained an
                     incised steatite pebble. The "treasure box" was situated directly over this
                     burial but at only 8 inches from the surface, while the skeleton was at a depth
                     of 36 inches.</p>
                  <p>Burial 2 exhibits exostosis of the auditory meatus. Burial 4 exhibits occipital
                     protrusion or "bunning." Burial 4 also has an osteoma at the juncture of the
                     left parietal, frontal, and sphenoid sutures (possibly caused by an old
                     injury), and on the rear of the left parietal along the left lambdoid suture.
                     Burials 2, 4, and 5 had abscessed teeth. Metric data are available in <persName
                        key="#rootenberg">Rootenberg</persName> (<date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>In excavating the burials, two hearths were uncovered. The first was 4 feet in
                     diameter and 17 inches thick, extending from 17 to 34 inches from the surface.
                     Within the pit at the 34-inch level was a series of stones in a triangular
                     arrangement; within this area was the greatest concentration of ash, shell
                     fragments, pieces of asphaltum, a large quantity of sea urchin spines, and a
                     few scattered artifacts. The latter included a stone pestle, a bone awl, pieces
                     of rock with asphaltum, and scattered burnt animal bone (sea lion, bird, and
                     fish bones as well as badly charred pieces of whale vertebra). The second
                     hearth was a double fire pit, 91 inches in length, 58 inches wide, and in the
                     form of two overlapping circles. It too contained ash, shell fragments, sea
                     urchin spines in great quantity, pieces of asphaltum, and a large number of
                     artifacts. Included were a stone pestle, two cores, a chopper, a bone wedge
                     with asphaltum, a stone net sinker, two bone awls, a bone spatulate object, and
                     a broken stone slab covered with asphaltum.</p>
                  <p>No further burials were recovered, and only a few artifacts were recovered from
                     the other pits, including a bone gorge, the broken tip of an awl or flaker, and
                     some fishhook fragments and blanks. A total of 128 artifacts were recovered
                     from the excavations. One shell sample from the burial area was submitted for
                     radiocarbon analysis (Table 1).</p>
                  <p>Two dog burials were also found, both completely articulated. They were not
                     accompanied by artifacts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-38, Daytona Beach Site</title></head>
                  <p>The Daytona Beach site is located on the southeast coast of <rs><placeName
                           type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> adjacent to a large
                     sandy beach. There is a rocky intertidal area just to the east. The site was
                     heavily impacted when the current barge landing was constructed. The remaining
                     site area covers some 160 by 140 m. The site contains a wide variety of
                     cultural materials.</p>
                  <p><persName key="#croz">Rozaire</persName> undertook excavation of SNI-38
                     primarily to learn more about weaving skills of <rs><orgName
                           type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                           islanders</orgName></rs> (Rozaire <date when="1959">1959</date>, <date
                        when="1967">1967</date>). Six 5- by 5-foot squares were excavated. Midden
                     depth was a maximum of four feet. Two possible occupations are represented by
                     differing colors of soil, the lower layer being decidedly more brown than
                     black. The side-wall profile of one unit revealed a sterile overburden of three
                     feet. The excavated portion of the site has since been destroyed to make room
                     for the current barge landing, although some deposit still remains to the east.
                     Woven sea-grass specimens, cordage, and limited evidence of basketry
                     impressions were found.</p>
                  <p>Over three dozen examples of woven sea grass were recovered. All examples have
                     plain, two-element S-twining. The warps and wefts were essentially small
                     bundles of untwisted sea grass. About 20 examples of twisted cordage made from
                     sea grass were also recovered. Structurally, most were S-strand with two
                     Z-yarns. These findings were consistent with Rozaire's (<date when="1957"
                        >1957</date>) earlier proposal that twining techniques are culturally
                     distinctive and that S-twining is associated with Uto-Aztecan peoples.</p>
                  <p>A feature consisting of 130 tarred pebbles was recovered near the only burial
                     recovered during the excavations. The feature measured 33 by 25 inches and was
                     at a depth of 15 inches. A second concentration of 19 tarred pebbles was
                     recovered at a depth of 26 inches in another pit.</p>
                  <p>The excavations yielded 75 stone artifacts, 23 bone artifacts, 61 fishhooks, 19
                     fishhook blanks, 10 shell beads, 4 specimens of woven sea-grass, and 7 of
                     cordage. Numerous shellfish species, crustaceans, sea mammals, fish, and bird
                     remains were also recovered.</p>
                  <p>One burial was recovered. It is possible that it was in a flexed position. It
                     appeared to have been placed in a small depression with a considerable amount
                     of charcoal. From the condition of the skeleton, it is assumed that the burning
                     in the pit occurred prior to interment. Scattered within the pit were fragments
                     of woven sea-grass and some small concentrations of unwoven sea-grass.</p>
                  <p>A second burial was later recovered at or near SNI-38 in <date when="1960"
                        >1960</date> (Rozaire <date when="1970">1970</date>). The burial was exposed
                     in a cut bank about 914 m from the shoreline. No midden soil was associated
                     with the burial though scattered shell was observed on the surface nearby. The
                     skeleton was contained within an oval grave pit which measured about 58 by 94
                     cm and was situated a maximum of 84 cm below the surface. The burial was
                     tightly flexed, in a ventral position, and face down with the head pointing to
                     the south. The individual was a male in his early twenties. The two hemispheres
                     of the frontal bone had not united, thus producing a metopic suture from bregma
                     to nasion. The only associated cultural materials were a few bits of woven sea
                     grass and fragments of cordage which may, together, constitute the remnants of
                     a cape or shroud.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-40</title></head>
                  <p>SNI-40 is located near the west coast of the island overlooking a rocky
                     intertidal area which is currently used heavily by sea lions. The site area
                     measures some 300 by 100 m. Depth of the observed midden is in excess of one
                     meter. A number of exposed burials were recovered by the <orgName
                        key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA Archaeological Survey</orgName> in <date when="1959"
                        >1959</date> (Reinman and Townsend <date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>The dune itself is about 805 m in length, running from northwest to southeast.
                     It is about 61 m wide and perhaps 23 m high. The burial area was on the inland
                     slope of the dune in a level space 3 to 6 m below the top of the southwest
                     side. The burials were all found in sterile sand with the midden seemingly
                     skirting the edge of the area and continuing on beyond for about 15 m, but only
                     on the eastern side.</p>
                  <p>A 30-foot trench was laid out in a north-south direction over an area disturbed
                     by previous looting. This was later extended into a larger grid encompassing
                     some 88 five-foot squares, of which 57 were excavated, and from which 20
                     burials and 136 cubic yards of earth were removed. With the burials were found
                     75 artifacts, exclusive of 5,384 shell beads of varying types. Twenty-five of
                     the artifacts were abalone shell dishes. A sample of olivella beads was
                     submitted for radiocarbon analysis (Table 1).</p>
                  <p>Since the burial area was in sterile sand, no stratigraphy was noted, with the
                     exception of three features. All three consisted of a burned layer of sand,
                     charcoal, and large quantities of land-snail shells.</p>
                  <p>Burials 1 and 12 evidenced exostosis of the auditory meatus. Burial 15
                     exhibited several wormian bones along the lambdoid and possibly the sagittal
                     sutures. Burials 4 and 9 exhibit occipital protrusion or "bunning." Burials 1,
                     3, and 4 have congenitally missing mandibular third molars. Burials 4 and 16
                     have dental abscesses. Burial 6 was missing four teeth, possibly due to an
                     accident. Several teeth were missing from Burial 9 indicating periodontal
                     involvement. Metric data are available in <persName key="#rootenberg"
                        >Rootenberg</persName> (<date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-51, <placeName type="region"
                           key="#re_dutchharbor">Dutch Harbor</placeName></title></head>
                  <p>The Dutch Harbor site is located at the west end of <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_dutchharbor">Dutch Harbor</placeName>, near the center of the
                     southern shore of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                           island</placeName></rs>. The site covers an area of about 325 by 100
                     meters. <placeName type="region" key="#re_dutchharbor">Dutch Harbor</placeName>
                     is the largest sandy beach on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                           island</placeName></rs>. The site is located near the western end of the
                     beach, and there is also a rocky intertidal area nearby. The site was tested in
                        <date when="1958">1958</date> (Rozaire <date when="1959">1959</date>, <date
                        when="1967">1967</date>), with the primary intent of recovering woven
                     material, and in <date when="1960">1960</date> to obtain datable materials in
                     stratigraphic context (Rozaire <date when="1970">1970</date>).</p>
                  <p>Fourteen pieces of woven sea grass were recovered and all but two have some
                     remains of selvage. The basic weave is plain two-element S-twining, with
                     braided three- and four-element S-twining found in the top selvage of four
                     specimens. Over 20 pieces of twisted sea grass cordage were uncovered. All were
                     S-strand, with two Z-yarns, except for one piece of S-strand with two S-yarns.
                     These findings were consistent with Rozaire's (<date when="1957">1957</date>)
                     earlier proposal.</p>
                  <p>The original excavation consisted of eight 5-foot squares. The squares were
                     excavated to a depth of only 36 inches due to limited time. A bulldozer cut
                     revealed that the midden extended to a maximum depth of nine feet below the
                     surface.</p>
                  <p>Twenty stone artifacts, three bone artifacts, and 10 fishhooks were recovered
                     along with 16 specimens of woven sea-grass. Numerous shellfish species, sea
                     mammal, fish, and bird remains were also recovered.</p>
                  <p>The 1960 excavation consisted of four 5-foot squares. Two were excavated to
                     sterile soil and two were terminated at depths of 30 and 54 inches due to time
                     constraints. A portion of a cut bank was excavated to obtain some woven sea
                     grass eroding from the cut. The woven sea-grass was encountered at a depth of
                     about 6 feet in association with sea-grass cordage, a bone tool fragment, two
                     scrapers, and charcoal.</p>
                  <p>The four excavated units revealed a clear stratigraphic profile which had
                     numerous lenses. The profile probably reflects the slow build-up of the midden
                     in an active dune area. Numerous artifacts were recovered from the surface as
                     well as from below the surface. In general, artifact yield greatly decreased
                     below 48 inches.</p>
                  <p>Two burials were also recovered at this time: one inhumation and one cremation.
                     The cremation was found eroding out of the side of a cut bank 14 inches below
                     the surface and several hundred yards above the road. The fragmented and
                     charred bones were contained in a saucer-shaped depression, 35 by 24 inches,
                     which had been excavated seven inches into the compacted yellowish sand. The
                     soil in the bottom of the pit was slightly reddish and was covered by a thin
                     layer (less than 1/2 inch thick) of chunks of charcoal. Charcoal and dark earth
                     filled the rest of the pit; it was in this matrix above the thin charcoal layer
                     that most of the fragmented human bone occurred. Though the bones were
                     carefully exposed, there was no apparent pattern to give a clue to original
                     position. It would appear that the remains constitute a secondary burial
                     following cremation. In the course of burning, the bones had been poked around
                     to assure that they were completely charred by the fire. Over 1,300 shell and
                     bone beads were scattered throughout the pit. These appear to have been thrown
                     loosely into the cremation fire during burning rather than as a necklace.
                     Interestingly, over half of the beads were not charred. The cremation pit also
                     contained a few small chunks of red and yellow ochre and five pieces of small
                     rock, shell, and animal bone fragments. Approximately 100 tarred pebbles were
                     scattered about in small clusters of three or four above the cremation. The
                     cremation was associated with the remnant of a shallow, compacted, dark-colored
                     midden 10 to 14 inches thick (Rozaire <date when="1967">1967</date>, <date
                        when="1970">1970</date>).</p>
                  <p>The inhumation was discovered about 25 feet north of the cremation, weathering
                     out of a small gully about two feet deep. The bones were disarticulated, broken
                     in some instances, and mixed and scattered over an area of about 41 inches
                     square, indicating a secondary burial. The skull was upright facing west. Some
                     small scraps of woven sea grass and fragments of cordage were associated with
                     the bones (Rozaire <date when="1970">1970</date>).</p>
                  <p>Charcoal from the cremation and shell samples from an unknown location within
                     the excavated areas were submitted for radiocarbon analysis. The radiocarbon
                     determinations appear to be stratigraphically consistent (Table 1).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-56, Redeye Site</title></head>
                  <p>SNI-56 is located on the northwest coast of <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> in an area known locally as
                     Redeye. It is adjacent to a small sandy beach with rocky intertidal areas to
                     the east and west. A number of water sources are nearby. The site extends over
                     a 300 by 175 m area of grassy hummocks and patches of midden. It displays an
                     extremely wide array of cultural materials. Three burials were excavated by the
                        <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA Archaeological Survey</orgName>, one in
                        <date when="1952">1952</date> and two in <date when="1959">1959</date>. A
                     small surface collection was also made by <persName key="#reinman"
                        >Reinman</persName> and <persName key="#sjtownsend">Townsend</persName>
                        (<date when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>Burial 1, with the exception of the skull, was not salvaged. The skull was
                     resting on a spool-shaped object made from a whale vertebra (Meighan and
                     Eberhart <date when="1953">1953</date>). The 1959 excavation centered on two
                     exposed burials and consisted of eight 6- by 6-foot units. Burials 2 and 3 were
                     found weathering out of the sand in an area down from the main dune area in the
                     same location from which Burial 1 was recovered in <date when="1952"
                        >1952</date>. Other artifacts found with the burials at this site include
                     the following: Burial 2 had five unmodified abalone shells, and Burial 3 was
                     accompanied by a few spire-lopped olivella beads, a perforated stone ring, four
                     unmodified abalone shells, and three fish gorges of bird and mammal bone.</p>
                  <p>Burial 2 was a young adult female. This was a primary inhumation in a tightly
                     flexed position lying on the left side and oriented toward the west. A
                     cylindrical growth was observed extending downward between the right mastoid
                     and the right occipital condyle. The growth has an articular facet on the
                     anterior portion and may have articulated with the transverse process of the
                     atlas. If so, it would have limited vertical head movement and horizontal
                     movement to the left. The skull exhibits occipital protrusion or "bunning." The
                     dentition exhibits congenitally-missing third molars (Rootenberg <date
                        when="1960">1960</date>).</p>
                  <p>Burial 3 was the primary inhumation of a young adult male. It was in a tightly
                     flexed supine position oriented toward the north. The skull exhibits occipital
                     protrusion or "bunning." Metric data for both burials are available in
                        <persName key="#rootenberg">Rootenberg</persName>
                     <date when="1960">(1960</date>).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNI-79, Powerhouse Site</title></head>
                  <p>The Powerhouse site is located on the central plateau at about the center of
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.
                        <placeName key="#celerycreek">Celery Creek</placeName>, one of the major
                     drainages on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>, is located just to the west. The site was tested by
                     the <orgName key="#uclaarchsur">UCLA Archaeological Survey</orgName> (Reinman
                        <date when="1964">1964</date>).</p>
                  <p>SNI-79 is a rather large site, covering a slightly raised knoll some 370 m long
                     and 115 m wide. Crude core tools of various kinds as well as bowl fragments,
                     pestles, and other implements were found scattered over the surface of the
                     midden. The midden consists of a lightly compacted sandy soil overlying a
                     lighter-colored sandy layer and is only slightly darker than the surrounding
                     soil. Small shrubs and grasses cover the surface, making a survey of the site
                     difficult.</p>
                  <p>Five 5- by 5-foot test pits were excavated to a depth of 24 inches. Three of
                     the pits (1, 3, and 5) were screened through 1/8-inch mesh, with all of the
                     material from Pit 3 saved for laboratory analysis (Reinman <date when="1964"
                        >1964</date>).</p>
                  <p>A total of 143 artifacts was recovered, including the surface collection. Nine
                     cubic yards of midden were excavated. This gives an average of 14.5 artifacts
                     per cubic yard (excluding the 12 from the surface collection). The catalog from
                     this site reveals a relatively high percentage of stone artifacts compared to
                     the other sites excavated. The amount of shell in the midden was also
                     considerably less than at other sites, with only 80.3 grams of shell per cubic
                     foot of midden.</p>
                  <p>Both fishhooks and hook blanks were recovered from all levels of the midden. In
                     addition, a few stone tools (drill, reamer, file) which were apparently used in
                     the manufacture of fishhooks were also found. There were also a number of
                     pestles and bowl fragments on the surface and in the excavations. Two small
                     fragments of bone were clearly tools, either a wedge or pry fragment and a
                     broken pointed object, probably an awl or flaker. Two other bone fragments, one
                     covered with asphaltum and the other a small, incised fragment, constitute the
                     remaining bone artifacts. Of the 26 shell objects, 22 are either fishhooks or
                     fishhook blanks. The remaining four artifacts include a perforated norissia
                     shell and three fragments of abalone covered with asphaltum.</p>
                  <p>Radiocarbon samples have not been submitted from SNI-79; however, one fishhook
                     has been identified as a Late Period type (Strudwick <date>n.d.</date>) which
                     may indicate that the site was occupied during this period. Five major food
                     shells were identified: abalone, mussel, tegula, sea urchin, and limpet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">SNl-351</title></head>
                  <p>In <date when="1991">1991</date> and <date when="1992">1992</date> the <orgName
                        key="#csula">California State University, Los Angeles</orgName>
                     archaeological field school conducted test excavations at SNI-351, a shell
                     midden and lithic site situated on the central plateau. This site was selected
                     to provide information that can be compared with the shoreline sites, SNI-11
                     and -16.</p>
                  <p>SNI-351 has been affected by both wind and water erosion. Portions of the site
                     are dissected by ravines, and there are large areas that have been deflated and
                     resemble a desert pavement of lithics, pebbles, and caliche.</p>
                  <p>The main cultural deposit consists of a stabilized sand dune containing a shell
                     midden. The dune midden deposit forms an L-shaped mound above a large ravine at
                     the south-central portion of the site. The mound covers an area approximately
                     10.5 by 4 m in a generally east-west direction and 7.5 by 4 m north-south.</p>
                  <p>Additional midden deposits are found below the mound in sandy/silty soil to the
                     east and north. These deposits do not extend more than 10 to 15 m beyond the
                     central dune.</p>
                  <p>Another smaller shell midden sand dune is situated within the northwestern
                     portion of the site. The depths of the midden deposits range from 50 to 110
                     cm.</p>
                  <p>A number of small, discrete shell deposits with little or no depth were
                     recorded within the terrace extending toward the east. A series of shovel test
                     pits extending from the midden area to the east were excavated and screened.
                     These contained only surface material and helped to define the extent of the
                     main midden area.</p>
                  <p>A total of 23 1.5- by 1.5-m units were excavated. The material was screened
                     through 1/8-inch mesh. The residues left in the screen were bagged and sorted
                     in the lab. This resulted in the retrieval of otoliths and small fish bones,
                     beads, and flaked stone.</p>
                  <p>Preliminary analysis indicates that the bulk of the midden constituents
                     consists of marine shell. The main shellfish types are abalone, mussel, tegula,
                     and owl limpet. The majority of the bones are fish, followed by sea mammal.
                     Morning glory seeds are plentiful and some are burned. Artifacts include small
                     amounts of asphaltum, including plugs; olivella beads and bead detritus; flaked
                     stone cobbles, including bifaces; a few flakes and shatter of exotic materials
                     such as obsidian, Monterey chert, and quartz; and a few bone tools. Although a
                     few whole pestles, bowl fragments, a metate, and a mano were recovered from the
                     surface, groundstone artifacts were rare within the subsurface deposit.
                     Features consisted mainly of deposits of burned shell and bone, soil stains,
                     and hearths.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">SUMMARY</title></head>
               <p>Some summary figures will help to put the current state of knowledge into some
                  perspective. Five sites have been excavated for the recovery of exposed burials.
                  Only five sites have been tested in terms of defining midden constituents.</p>
               <p>SNI-11 is the best documented of the tested sites. However, there are still some
                  areas of additional analysis that would prove fruitful. Additional radiocarbon
                  samples should be processed and sourcing of the obsidian samples should be
                  performed to correct inconsistences and clarify the stratigraphic sequences.
                  Geomorphological studies may provide useful data regarding the post-depositional
                  processes of a sand dune midden deposit. Additional analysis of the reptilian,
                  crustacean, and botanical remains should be conducted. A synthesis report should
                  be prepared and published.</p>
               <p>SNI-16 has been adequately sampled, though reporting of this site is incomplete. A
                  detailed analysis of the faunal remains compared against the SNI-11 sample would
                  be very instructive in defining shoreline activities and subsistence strategy. An
                  attempt should be made to obtain radiocarbon dates from the same depositional
                  contexts as the obsidian. A synthesis report should be prepared and published.</p>
               <p>Additional sampling of SNI-79 would be very fruitful. Until recently, this was the
                  only site on the plateau that had been tested. Additional sampling and analysis
                  would provide information for comparisons with shoreline sites and with SNI-351, a
                  recently excavated plateau site that appears to have more shell.</p>
               <p>The analyses of the materials recovered from SNI-351 have not been completed. The
                  data from these studies can be used to determine the type of site, length, season,
                  and time of occupation, and to compare SNI-351 with the shoreline sites. The
                  results of these analyses may provide clues to why this location on the central
                  plateau was selected for occupation. The nearest water source may have been
                     <placeName key="#celerycreek">Celery Creek</placeName>. This creek and its
                  tributaries are dry today, but it is obvious that water played an important role
                  in the formation of the numerous ravines that dissect the plateau. Shellfish
                  processing and consumption appear to be the main activities conducted at the site,
                  but since the site is not situated at a convenient distance from the ocean, it is
                  probable that the shellfish were used to sustain the population while they were
                  concentrating on some other activity. Some propositions to be evaluated are that
                  the site was situated near an important plant resource or near a cobble
                  conglomerate bed exposure. Other factors that may have played a part in the
                  selection of this location are the elevation and view of <rs><placeName
                        type="group"
                        key="#i_an; #i_scl; #i_sm; #i_sn; #i_sb; #i_scatalina; #i_scruz; #i_sr">the
                        other islands</placeName></rs> and the practical consideration that the site
                  would be free of kelp flies and other coastal pests that plague people while
                  processing shellfish at the shoreline during certain seasons.</p>
               <p>Environmental reconstruction is needed using geology, geomorphology, paleoclimate,
                  soils, flora, and fauna analysis. Sourcing the origins of the artifacts and the
                  flora and fauna remains, and determining the means and the energy expenditure
                  required to get them, is another important line of inquiry.</p>
               <p>Additional testing of SNI-38 and SNI-51 should be conducted to provide an adequate
                  sample. This, coupled with additional research on existing collections, would
                  provide solid comparative data to examine differences between the northwest
                  shoreline, plateau, and south shore.</p>
               <p>The other sites have only been tested in terms of burial recovery and thus do not
                  provide any midden materials that could address archaeological research questions
                  such as cultural change, diet, ecological adaptation, and environment. In
                  addition, a number of other sites on the island have been excavated but not
                  reported. These include investigations by <persName key="#mrog">Malcolm
                     Rogers</persName> and <persName key="#gcarter">George Carter</persName> in
                     <date when="1930">1930</date>, <persName type="author" key="#awo">Arthur
                     Woodward</persName> in <date from="1939" to="1941">1939-1941</date>, and
                     <persName key="#porr">Phil Orr</persName> in <date when="1941">1941</date>. The
                  collections and notes from some of the unreported investigations are still in
                  existence, and a more complete analysis of these museum collections would add
                  substantially to our understanding of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas Island</placeName> prehistory. A synopsis of Malcolm Rogers's work from
                  the <date from="1930" to="1939">1930s</date> will serve as an indication of this
                  untapped potential.</p>
               <p>Under the auspices of the <orgName key="#sdmusofman">San Diego Museum of
                     Man</orgName>, <persName key="#mrog">Malcolm Rogers</persName>, accompanied by
                     <persName key="#gcarter">George Carter</persName>, spent one month on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> in
                     <date when="1930">1930</date> surveying and collecting. The team collected 45
                  cases of specimens (including 33 burials) which were taken to <orgName
                     key="#sdmusofman">the San Diego museum</orgName> where the collection was
                  cataloged. Only a preliminary manuscript describing the fieldwork was completed
                  (Rogers <date>n.d.</date>), though his field notes are on file at the <orgName
                     type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName> in
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_dc">Washington</placeName>.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Chronology</title></head>
                  <p><persName key="#lauter">Lauter</persName> (<date>n.d.</date>a,
                        <date>n.d.</date>b) describes the island's chronology in terms of three
                     cultural phases (Early, Intermediate, Late). At that time (<date when="1982"
                        >1982</date>) there were no dated sites that could be designated as Early
                     Phase, pre-3000 B.C. The Early Phase includes the Paleo-Indian Tradition, ca.
                     13,000 to 11,000 B.C., and the subsequent culture complexes in <placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_socal">southern California</placeName> known as the
                     San Dieguito Tradition, the Hunting Period, the Encinitas Tradition, the
                     Millingstone Horizon, and the Early Period (Warren <date when="1968"
                        >1968</date>, Wallace <date when="1978">1978</date>, C. King <date
                        when="1981">1981</date>). This was the time of adaptation to the
                     environmental changes of the Holocene, followed by regional developments
                     emphasizing use of plant foods and the first use of marine resources (Moratto
                        <date when="1984">1984</date>). The earliest sites on the island are dated
                     to the Early Phase. These include SNI-11, Mound B, Stratum III; SNI-21; and
                     SNI-339.</p>
                  <p>The Intermediate Phase, ca. 3000 to 1000 B.C., includes SNI-40, SNI-16, and
                     Strata II and III of SNI-11. This phase corresponds to Warren's Encinitas
                     Tradition (<date when="1968">1968</date>), Wallace's Period III: Diversified
                     Subsistence (<date when="1978">1978</date>), and King's Middle Period (<date
                        when="1981">1981</date>). It is characterized by the introduction of the
                     mortar and pestle used in the processing of acorns and other hard seeds. The
                     atlatl is used for hunting, and marine resources are exploited along the
                     coast.</p>
                  <p>Late Phase sites, ca. 1000 B.C. to historic contact, include SNI-51, SNI-18,
                     and Stratum I of SNI-11. Late Phase sites can be related to Warren's Shoshonean
                     Tradition <date when="1968">(1968</date>), Wallace's Late Prehistoric Horizon
                        (<date when="1955">1955</date>), and King's Late Period (<date when="1981"
                        >1981</date>). Late Period populations are characterized by a diversified
                     subsistence, increased population density, reliance on maritime resources,
                     social complexity, trade, and large permanent communities. The introduction of
                     the bow and arrow, pottery, a monetary system, and artistic elaboration also
                     mark this period (King <date when="1981">1981</date>, Wallace <date when="1955"
                        >1955</date>, Warren <date when="1968">1968</date>).</p>
                  <p>In <date when="1988">1988</date>, a number of additional radiocarbon dates were
                     processed from SNI-11 (Breschini et al. <date when="1992">1992</date>). These
                     dates introduce an element of confusion regarding the chronology and
                     stratigraphy of the site (Table 1). One date from the 140-150 cm level of
                     Stratum III is 5033-4729 B.C., which falls within the Early Phase. This
                     suggests an earlier occupation of the site than previously estimated. However,
                     consideration must be given to the fact that this date is problematic because
                     it overlies Stratum III, 170-190 cm, which has a later date of 2919-2505
                     B.C.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">FUTURE DIRECTIONS</title></head>
               <p>Islands are a natural laboratory for the study of cultural and biological systems
                  and human adaptation. The ocean provides a barrier to many forms of terrestrial
                  life, the physical boundaries are clearly delineated, and <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> provides specific
                  circumscribed environmental constraints and opportunities. The <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> have abundant resources
                  that were important to human populations. They are discrete geographic units with
                  significant variation in the nature of resources and provide an ideal context to
                  test hypotheses about cultural-environmental interactions.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> provides a
                  particularly favorable environment for archaeological research. As one of the
                  smallest of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>
                  and the farthest from <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                     mainland</placeName>, it is a discrete geographical unit with sufficient
                  resource and environmental variation to test hypotheses about human adaptive
                  systems. For example, it is likely that the entire settlement system is
                  represented in the archaeological deposits, and because <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> is small, it may be
                  possible to identify all of the components and to examine change through time.
                  Although there has been some damage due to erosion, construction, and collecting,
                  archaeological preservation is generally good. An important plus is that because
                  of the absence of burrowing animals, stratigraphic contexts are largely
                  undisturbed.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> was remote
                  (there is no evidence of a land bridge), small, wind-swept, semi-arid, sparsely
                  vegetated, and the only terrestrial animals are the island fox, a mouse, and a
                  lizard. Assuming that these conditions are approximately similar to those of the
                  past few thousand years, the island population clearly faced some environmental
                  challenges. The materials recovered from the archaeological excavations can be
                  analyzed to reconstruct the prehistoric environment and to address questions
                  regarding prehistoric human adaptation.</p>
               <p>The major research domains that have been identified for <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> prehistory are as follows:</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Paleoenvironmental influences</title></head>
                  <p>Recent paleoenvironmental research has produced a wealth of information
                     regarding environmental change during the Holocene (Anderson <date>n.d.</date>;
                     Schimmelmann <date>n.d.</date>; Stine <date>n.d.</date>; Wigand
                        <date>n.d.</date>). Paleoenvironmental reconstructions can be used to
                     identify the environmental factors that may have influenced hunter-gatherer
                     adaptations on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>. This information can be used to address questions
                     regarding environment and cultural behavior. For example, two models have been
                     proposed regarding subsistence change on the <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>. The environmental model attributes
                     subsistence change to environmental factors such as sea temperature (Glassow
                        <date>n.d.</date>a, <date>n.d.</date>b; Glassow, Wilcoxon, and Erlandson
                        <date when="1988">1988</date>; Walker and Snethkamp <date>n.d.</date>). The
                     alternative model proposes that prehistoric exploitation strategies and the
                     pressure of human predation on limited island resources provides the best
                     explanation for diachronic changes in settlement and subsistence patterns
                     (Bleitz-Sanburg <date>n.d.</date>a, <date>n.d.</date>b; Bleitz-Sanburg and
                     Salls <date>n.d.</date>; Raab <date>n.d.</date>; Raab and Yatsko <date
                        when="1990">1990</date>; Reinman <date when="1964">1964</date>; Salls
                        <date>n.d.</date>b).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Settlement systems</title></head>
                  <p>We do not know the size of the prehistoric population on <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> or whether it was
                     occupied on a continuous basis. Unlike mainland territories where the
                     boundaries are ill-defined and many parts of the settlement pattern have been
                     lost, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>
                     provides a relatively finite and manageable sample universe for the analysis of
                     settlement patterns and population size. If it is assumed that the location of
                     sites in a particular area reflects a pattern of adaptive behavior, the
                     reconstruction of the settlement pattern can be used to examine a broad range
                     of cultural and environmental factors that may have influenced hunter-gatherer
                     adaptations on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>.</p>
                  <p>This line of inquiry is important. Although the locations of all of the sites
                     that are visible on the surface have been mapped, additional investigations are
                     needed to identify site function and to reconstruct the configuration of the
                     settlement pattern. There is some information regarding material culture and
                     faunal remains from a few of the coastal sites. but there is a lack of
                     information about site function and how the aboriginal population used various
                     areas of the island, especially the upper central plateau.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Subsistence strategies</title></head>
                  <p>There is a preponderance of data indicating a marine subsistence focus;
                     however, very little is known regarding the subsistence patterns on <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>. The emphasis has
                     been on the investigation of coastal sites; little is known about subsistence
                     on the central plateau, and even less is known about aboriginal utilization or
                     availability of plant foods. For example, it is not known whether the large
                     number of mortars and pestles found on the island were used for the preparation
                     of plant materials or pounding fish and shellfish. (See also the discussion of
                     paleoenvironmental influences.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Island cultural chronology</title></head>
                  <p>Culture sequences have been formulated for southern California prehistory
                     (Wallace <date when="1978">1978</date>; Warren <date when="1968">1968</date>;
                     King <date when="1981">1981</date>; Chartkoff and Chartkoff <date when="1984"
                        >1984</date>; Moratto <date when="1984">1984</date>). These can be used as a
                     source of information to test hypotheses regarding the prehistory of <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>.</p>
                  <p><persName key="#raab">Raab</persName> and <persName key="#yatsko"
                        >Yatsko</persName>
                     <date when="1990">(1990</date>) suggest that these reconstructions may not
                     accurately reflect cultural development on the <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, particularly the earliest cultural
                     periods. For example, radiocarbon dates and recent information regarding
                     aboriginal fisheries on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        Islands</placeName> suggest that aboriginal occupation began as early as
                     8,500 B.C. on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel
                        Island</placeName>, 7,700 B.C.on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                        Clemente Island</placeName>, and 6,200 B.C. on <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> (Raab and Yatsko <date
                        when="1990">1990</date>; <persName key="#salls">Salls</persName>
                     <date>n.d.</date>a). <persName key="#raab">Raab</persName> and <persName
                        key="#yatsko">Yatsko</persName> propose that these data reveal some of the
                     earliest fully maritime cultural adaptations in the Western Hemisphere and that
                     maritime adaptations were an important aspect of coastal Paleo-Indian
                     adaptation (<date when="1990">1990</date>).</p>
                  <p>According to <persName key="#erlandson">Erlandson</persName> (<date when="1958"
                        >1985</date>), sea-level rise during the Holocene may have obliterated most
                     of the evidence of early maritime adaptations along <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_paccoast">the mainland coast</placeName> and encouraged a return to
                     more terrestrial resources exploitation as the estuaries were drowned or filled
                     with silt. Recent modelling by <persName key="#pierson">Pierson</persName>,
                        <persName key="#shiller">Shiller</persName>, and <persName key="#slater"
                        >Slater</persName> (<date>n.d.</date>) indicates that at 6550 B.C.
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> may have
                     had 25% more land mass than at present, and at 9050 B.C. the land mass may have
                     been over three times the current size.</p>
                  <p>Based on a survey and collection of artifacts on <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> in <date when="1930">1930</date>,
                        <persName key="#mrog">Malcolm Rogers</persName> proposed that three cultural
                     periods are represented on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                           island</placeName></rs>. The early sites appeared to contain small
                     quantities of marine shell and to lack bone or artifacts. As land snail shells
                     were plentiful, he suggested that the earliest culture exploited them. Later
                     the sites contain pink abalone, and house floors were observed between the
                     piles of shell (<date>n.d.</date>).</p>
                  <p>The Canaliño period is the second cultural sequence described by <persName
                        key="#mrog">Rogers</persName>. This period is characterized by many house
                     pits of a size that would accommodate a family. Dogs were introduced to
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> at
                     this time. The first shell fishhooks appear, and midden constituents include
                     black abalone, mussel shells, and a high percentage of fish bone. Later during
                     this period, community houses measuring 30 to 40 feet in diameter appear. Six
                     of these were described (Rogers <date>n.d.</date>).</p>
                  <p>The third period in Rogers's cultural sequence is the Shoshonean. This period
                     is characterized by the presence of cremations, metates, obsidian projectile
                     points, and perhaps the sweat house. Cremations were found in eight village
                     sites near the west end directly over Canaliño-period deposits. <persName
                        key="#mrog">Rogers</persName> suggests that the Shoshonean occupation does
                     not date to any antiquity.</p>
                  <p>The culture sequences that have been proposed for <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socal">southern California</placeName> and <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> can be tested using carefully
                     collected, calibrated, and interpreted radiocarbon samples. The anomalous dates
                     that have been recovered both from <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                        Nicolas Island</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                        Clemente Island</placeName> indicate that there are a number of problems to
                     be solved. Since marine shell is more abundant than charcoal, it will be very
                     important to solve the problems that interfere with the accurate dating of this
                     material, such as contamination, upwelling, and the fact that different species
                     vary in their habitat and ingestion of organisms in equilibrium with older
                     seawater. Contamination of charcoal samples, perhaps with asphaltum, and the
                     interpretation of radiocarbon dates in light of the complex stratigraphy of
                     shell mounds also need to be addressed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Social organization</title></head>
                  <p>Archaeological, ethnographic, and historic data indicate that at the time of
                     European contact <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                        Chumash</orgName> and possibly <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the Gabrielino</orgName> were organized at the
                     chiefdom level of social complexity (C. King <date when="1981">1981</date>; L.
                     King <date when="1982">1982</date>; Martz <date when="1984">1984</date>). A
                     general trend toward greater complexity is proposed for the Pacific Coast
                     groups beginning around 2000 B.C. (Chartkoff and Chartkoff <date when="1984"
                        >1984</date>). This social complexity included a system of social
                     differentiation with hereditary political leaders at the top of the status
                     ladder, followed by religious practitioners and craft specialists. This elite
                     group controlled the procurement and distribution of surplus resources and had
                     differential access to wealth. The rise of complexity is attributed to the high
                     productivity of the Pacific Coast resource base as well as the social
                     institutions that managed them.</p>
                  <p>It will be particularly interesting to address the question of whether a trend
                     toward greater social complexity was present on <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, and to examine the basis for
                     social organization, the level of complexity, and the development of this
                     society through time.</p>
                  <p>Island-specific craft specialization industries have been identified on
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> and
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> islands
                     (Arnold <date when="1987">1987</date>, <date when="1991">1991</date>; Rosen
                        <date when="1980">1980</date>). Because islands are relatively isolated and
                     limited in resource variety, it is proposed that craft specialization and the
                     development of a specialized manufacturing industry would be necessary to
                     ensure adequate supplies of resources that are not available on <rs><placeName
                           type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. This would be a
                     significant adaptive device and, as <persName key="#arnold">Arnold</persName>
                     <date when="1987">(1987</date>) suggests, an impetus for the development and
                     maintenance of social complexity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Regional interaction and trade</title></head>
                  <p>Although ethnographic sources and historic accounts provide numerous
                     descriptions of trade between the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        Islands</placeName> and <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                        mainland,</placeName> there is no information regarding the part that was
                     played by <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                           >the inhabitants of San Nicolas Island</orgName></rs>. Trade is very
                     important to our understanding of San Nicolas prehistory because it involves
                     the exchange of ideas as well as economic goods and can provide information
                     regarding craft specialization and social complexity. In addition to artifact
                     manufacturing areas indicating craft specialization and the production of
                     surplus for trade, the presence of exotic plant and animal remains, raw
                     materials, and finished artifacts would indicate trade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Cultural affiliation</title></head>
                  <p><span type="trope" n="4">There is no mention of <rs><orgName
                              type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians of
                              San Nicolas Island</orgName></rs> in the diaries of the European
                        explorers, and virtually all of the current ethnographic information
                        regarding <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                              key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">these people</orgName></rs> is based on
                        the artifacts of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the "Lone
                              Woman of San Nicolas Island"</persName></rs> at the time of her
                        discovery.</span> According to <persName type="author" key="#akroe"
                        >Kroeber</persName>, who analyzed four words spoken by <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the "Lone Woman,"</persName></rs>
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> was
                     occupied by Shoshonean speakers at the time of European contact (Eisen <date
                        when="1905">1905</date>). Based on archaeological and linguistic evidence,
                     people speaking this language are thought to represent an intrusive desert
                     culture group who displaced the Hokan speakers who were the original
                     inhabitants of the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>,
                        <placeName key="#orangeco">Orange County</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="#inlandemp">Inland Empire</placeName>, and <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_southernchi">southern Channel Islands</placeName> region. The
                     direction, nature, extent, and time of this intrusion is subject to debate with
                     some placing the intrusion at about A.D. 750 and others arguing for an earlier
                     occupation at about 1000 B.C.</p>
                  <p>Some possibilities regarding cultural affiliation of the populations occupying
                     the <placeName type="island" key="#i_southernchi">southern Channel
                        Islands</placeName> are based on studies of human osteology on <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente Island</placeName> (Titus
                        <date>n.d.</date>). <persName key="#titus">Titus</persName> suggests that
                     two distinct genetic populations occupied <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. The earliest population is
                     attributed to the widely distributed Hokan-speaking peoples and the more recent
                     genetic population to the relatively recent Shoshonean speakers and ancestors
                     of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                        Gabrielino people</orgName> of the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                        Angeles</placeName> Basin and <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sana">Santa
                        Ana</placeName> River watershed. The correlation between a genetic
                     population and a linguistic grouping must be viewed with caution. However, it
                     would be important to determine whether distinct genetic populations can be
                     identified for <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas
                        Island</placeName> and to reconstruct the sequence of occupation.</p>
                  <p>In addition, further analysis of preserved woven sea-grass and basketry
                     impressions may reveal weaving techniques that can be attributed to a
                     particular cultural affiliation (Rozaire <date when="1959">1959</date>, <date
                        when="1967">1967</date>, <date when="1970">1970</date>, <date>n.d.</date>).
                     Variations in fishhook types may also provide important clues (Strudwick
                        <date>n.d.</date>). If found in good stratigraphic contexts, this
                     information can be compared with data regarding changes in
                     settlement-subsistence strategies through time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Technology</title></head>
                  <p>Very little is known about the technology of <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>. Ethnographic information is not
                     available, and the material culture must be reconstructed from archaeological
                     data. According to early investigators, the sites contain an abundance of
                     mortars and pestles, projectile points are rare, and metates are absent.
                     Steatite effigies, shell beads and fishhooks, bone tools, and woven sea grass
                     are also reported (Benson <date>n.d.</date>; Bryan <date when="1927"
                        >1927</date>; Meighan and Eberhart <date when="1953">1953</date>; Schumacher
                        <date>n.d.</date>). De Cessac's observations in <date when="1878"
                        >1878</date> are particularly interesting. He noted that many of the
                     artifacts are different from those he had encountered on the coast of
                        <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and the
                     islands of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>,
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>, and <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>. <persName type="author"
                        key="#lce">De Cessac</persName> was particularly impressed by the
                     workmanship, originality, and beauty of the bird and fish effigies, the "stone
                     vases," and the mortars and pestles. In addition to finished pieces, he
                     evidently observed and collected items representing entire sequences of
                     manufacture (<persName type="author" key="#rhe">Heizer</persName>
                     <date when="1951"> 1951</date>).</p>
                  <p>The flaked cobble stone-tool industry identified by <persName key="#clevenger"
                        >Clevenger</persName> (<date>n.d.</date>) provides an interesting contrast
                     to the groundstone craftsmanship described by <persName type="author"
                        key="#lce">de Cessac</persName>. <persName key="#clevenger"
                        >Clevenger</persName> proposed that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the inhabitants of SNI-11</orgName></rs> were
                     using locally-available cobbles as a source of raw material rather than
                     imported lithic materials of better quality. Additional studies are needed to
                     determine whether this lithic-procurement and manufacturing system is an
                     island-wide adaptive system and represents an attempt to limit dependence on
                     off-island resources, or whether it was confined to coastal fish- and
                     shellfish-processing sites as the least expensive tool source. Further studies
                     regarding lithic procurement and manufacture, stone tool use, and tool kits
                     should provide additional insights regarding stone tool traditions and craft
                     specialization.</p>
                  <p>The numerous fishhooks, fishhook blanks, fish gorges, cordage, drills, net
                     gages, weights, and other related items recovered and observed on
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                     provide the opportunity to trace the development of fishing technology through
                     time. The discovery of shaped and utilized shell fragments at SNI-38 opens
                     another line of inquiry regarding the use of shell, perhaps as a substitute for
                     wood (Dana Bleitz-Sanburg and Jane Rosenthal, personal communication, <date
                        when="1993">1993</date>). Shell bead and detritus features have been
                     observed on the surface of various sites along the coast, and bead making may
                     have been an important island industry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head><title type="subsection">Site formation and post-depositional
                        processes</title></head>
                  <p>The formation of the archaeological sites on <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> can be attributed to a variety of
                     natural and cultural processes. In addition, natural and cultural
                     post-depositional processes such as wind and water erosion, sedimentation,
                     sand-dune formation, sheep ranching, and military activities have modified the
                     sites and obscured the archaeological record. The patterns produced by these
                     processes are often mistaken for cultural patterning; therefore a comprehensive
                     understanding of their effects is critical for interpretations of site
                     chronology, stratigraphy, spatial organization, and function (Erlandson and
                     Rockwell <date when="1987">1987</date>).</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title></head>
               <p>This research has been supported by the <placeName type="region" key="#re_pmugu"
                     >Naval Air Weapons Station, Point Mugu</placeName>, and <orgName key="#csula"
                     >California State University, Los Angeles</orgName>. <persName
                     key="#amschwartz">Audrey McNulty Schwartz</persName> provided editorial
                  assistance and <persName key="#bleitz">Dana Bleitz</persName> prepared the base
                  map for site locations. Their efforts are greatly appreciated. Special thanks are
                  owed <persName key="#kdixon">Keith Dixon</persName>, <persName key="#bpadon">Beth
                     Padon</persName>, and <persName key="#jrosenthal">Jane Rosenthal</persName> for
                  their invaluable editing assistance. Thanks are also due to the unknown reviewer
                  and to <persName key="#raab">Mark Raab</persName> and <persName key="#salls">Roy
                     Salls</persName> for their very insightful and helpful critiques.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">REFERENCES CITED</title></head>
               <div>
                  <p><persName><persName type="author" key="#rsanderson">Anderson, R.
                           Scott</persName></persName></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>High Elevation Vegetation Dynamics and Paleoclimates: The
                           Late-Quaternary Record from California's Sierra Nevada</emph>. Paper
                        presented at the 27th Annual Meeting of the <orgName key="#soccaarch"
                           >Society for California Archaeology</orgName>, <date from="1993-04-07"
                           to="1993-04-11">April 7-11, 1993</date>, <placeName key="#asilomar"
                           >Asilomar</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><persName><persName key="#arnold">Arnold, Jeanne E.</persName></persName></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1987">1987</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Craft Specialization in the Prehistoric Channel Islands, California.
                              <emph><orgName key="#ucpubanth">University of California Publications
                              in Anthropology</orgName></emph> 18. <orgName type="publisher"
                           key="#ucalpress">University of California Press</orgName>, <placeName
                           type="city" key="#ci_berk">Berkeley</placeName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1991">1991</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Transformation of a Regional Economy: Sociopolitical Evolution and the
                        Production of Valuables in Southern California. <emph><orgName
                              type="publication" key="#aman">Antiquity</orgName></emph> 65
                        :953-962.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#lbe">Bean, Lowell J.</persName>, and
                           <persName type="author" key="#csmith">Charles R.
                     Smith</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1978">1978</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Gabrielino. In, <emph><orgName key="#handnoramind">Handbook of North
                              American Indians, Vol. 8: California</orgName></emph>, ed. by
                           <persName type="author" key="#rhe">Robert F. Heizer</persName>. pp.
                        538-549. <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian
                           Institution</orgName>, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_dc">Washington,
                           D.C.</placeName></bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#asbenson">Benson, Arlene
                        S.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>The Noontide Sun: The Field Notes and Unpublished Manuscripts of the Rev.
                        Stephen Bowers. Master's thesis, <orgName key="#csula">California State
                           University, Los Angeles</orgName>. [<date when="1982"
                     >1982</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#bleitz">Bleitz-Sanburg, Dana E.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>a</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>The Changing Exploitation of Mammalian and Avian Food Resources at
                           SNl-11, San Nicolas Island, California</emph>. Master's thesis, <orgName
                           key="#csula">California State University, Los Angeles</orgName>. [<date
                           when="1987">1987</date>]</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>b</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>The Wavy Turban</emph> (Astraea undosa) <emph>on Santa Catalina
                           Island: An Ecological Analysis and Zooarchaeological Assessment</emph>.
                        Paper presented at the 24th Annual Meeting of the <orgName key="#soccaarch"
                           >Society for California Archaeology</orgName>, <date from="1990-04-04"
                           to="1990-04-07">April 4-7, 1990</date>, <placeName key="#fostercity"
                           >Foster City</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#bleitz">Bleitz-Sanburg, Dana E.</persName>, and <persName
                           key="#salls">Roy A. Salls</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Fishheads, Spearheads, and Sheepheads: Prehistoric Maritime
                           Exploitation and the Effect on the Stable State of Marine Fauna/
                           Resources</emph>. Paper presented at the Southern California Data-Sharing
                        Meeting of the <orgName key="#soccaarch">Society for California
                           Archaeology</orgName>, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                           Angeles</placeName>, <date when="1987">1987</date>. Manuscript on file,
                        Institute of Archaeology, <orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucla"
                           >University of California, Los Angeles</orgName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#gbreschini">Breschini, Gary</persName>,
                           <persName type="author" key="#thaversat">Trudy Haversat</persName>, and
                           <persName key="#erlandson">Jon Erlandson</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1992">1992</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>California Radiocarbon Dates</emph>, 7th edition. <orgName
                           key="#coyotepress">Coyote Press</orgName>, <placeName type="city"
                           key="#ci_sal">Salinas</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#bbr">Bryan, Bruce</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1927">1927</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Collecting Indian Relics on a Desert Island. <emph><orgName
                              key="#museumgraphic">Museum Graphic</orgName></emph> 1(4):145-150.
                           <orgName type="musuem" key="#mu_museumofnaturalhistory">Los Angeles
                           County Museum of Natural History</orgName>, <placeName type="city"
                           key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><persName type="author" key="#jlchartkoff">Chartkoff, Joseph L.</persName>, and
                        <persName type="author" key="">Kerry Kona Chartkoff</persName></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1984">1984</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>The Archaeology of California</emph>. <orgName type="publisher"
                           key="#stanpress">Stanford University Press</orgName>, <placeName
                           key="#stanford">Stanford</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#clevenger">Clevenger, Joyce M.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>The Split Cobble Reduction Technology on San Nicolas Island, California.
                        Master's thesis, <orgName key="#csulb">California State University, Long
                           Beach</orgName>. [<date when="1982">1982</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#gei">Eisen, Gustav</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1905">1905</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>An Account of the Indians of the Santa Barbara Islands in California.
                           <emph>Sitzungsberichte der Konig/ichen Bohmischen Gesellschaft der
                           Wissenschaften, Mathematisch-Naturwissenschaftliche Classe, Jahrgang
                           1904</emph>. Prag.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#erlandson">Erlandson, Jon M.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1985">1985</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Early Holocene Settlement and Subsistence in Relation to Coastal
                        Paleogeography: Evidence from CA-SBA-1807. <emph><orgName type="publication"
                              key="#jcgb">Journal of California and Great Basin
                              Anthropology</orgName></emph> 7:103-109.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#erlandson">Erlandson, Jon M.</persName>, and <persName
                           type="author" key="#tkrockwell">Thomas K. Rockwell</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1987">1987</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Radiocarbon Reversals and Stratigraphic Discontinuities: The Effects of
                        Natural Formation Processes on Coastal California Archaeological Sites. In,
                           <emph>Natural Formation Processes and the Archaeological Record</emph>,
                        ed. by <persName type="author" key="#dtnash">D.T. Nash</persName> and
                           <persName type="author" key="#mdoetraglia">M.D. Petraglia</persName>, pp.
                        51-73. BAR International Series 352, <placeName key="#oxford"
                           >Oxford</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#maglassow">Glassow, Michael
                        A.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>a</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>An Archaeological Overview of the Northern Channel Islands</emph>.
                        Report prepared for the <orgName key="#warchcen">Western Archaeological
                           Center, National Park Service</orgName>, <placeName key="#tucson"
                           >Tucson</placeName>. [<date when="1977">1977</date>]</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>b</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>The Red Abalone Midden layers of the Northern Channel Islands: A
                           Preliminary Report on Their Chronology and Implications for Environmental
                           Change</emph>. Paper presented at the 18th Annual Meeting of the <orgName
                           key="#soccaarch">Society for California Archaeology</orgName>, <date
                           from="1984-03-29" to="1984-03-31">March 29-31, 1984</date>, <placeName
                           type="city" key="#ci_sal">Salinas</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#maglassow">Glassow, Michael</persName>,
                           <persName type="autor" key="#lwilcoxon">Larry Wilcoxon</persName>, and
                           <persName key="#erlandson">Jon Erlandson</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1988">1988</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Cultural and Environmental Change During the Early Period of Santa
                        Barbara Prehistory. In, <emph>The Archaeology of Prehistoric
                           Coastlines</emph>, ed. by <persName type="author" key="#gbailey">Geoff
                           Bailey</persName> and <persName type="author" key="#jparkington">John
                           Parkington</persName>, pp. 64-77. <orgName key="#camupress">Cambridge
                           University Press</orgName>, <placeName key="#cambridge"
                           >Cambridge</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="city" key="#mchall">Hall, M.C</persName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1988">1988</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>For the Record: Notes and Comments on "Obsidian Exchange in Prehistoric
                        Orange County." <emph><orgName key="#paccoastarch">Pacific Coast
                              Archaeological Society Quarterly</orgName></emph> 24
                     (4):34-48.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#rhuddleston">Huddleston,
                        Richard</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Otoliths from SNI-11, San Nicolas Island, California. Manuscript on file,
                           <orgName key="#sciresearchsys">Scientific Research Systems</orgName>,
                           <placeName key="#elmonte">El Monte, California</placeName>. [<date
                           when="1977">1977</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#cking">King, Chester</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1981">1981</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>The Evolution of Chumash Society: A Comparative Study of Artifacts
                           Used in Social System Maintenance in the Santa Barbara Channel Region
                           Before A.D. 1804</emph>. Ph.D. dissertation, <orgName key="#ucdavis"
                           >University of California at Davis</orgName>. University Microfilms,
                           <placeName key="#annarbor">Ann Arbor</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#lking">King, Linda</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1982">1982</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Medea Creek Cemetery: late Inland Chumash Patterns of Social
                           Organization, Exchange and Warfare</emph>. Ph.D. dissertation, <orgName
                           type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University of California at Los
                           Angeles</orgName>. University Microfilms, <placeName key="#annarbor">Ann
                           Arbor</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#lauter">Lauter, Gloria A.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>a</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Defining an Intermediate Period in San Nicolas Island, California,
                           Chronology: Test Excavations at SNI-16</emph>. Master's thesis, <orgName
                           key="#csunorth">California State University, Northridge</orgName>. [<date
                           when="1982">1982</date>]</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>b</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Establishing a Cultural Sequence for San Nicolas Island: Test
                           Excavations at SNl-16</emph>. In, Mugu Lagoon/San Nicolas Island
                        Ecological Research Symposium. Manuscript on file, <placeName type="region"
                           key="#re_pmugu">Naval Air Weapons Station</placeName>, <placeName
                           type="region" key="#re_pmugu">Point Mugu</placeName>. [<date when="1983"
                           >1983</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#patmartz">Martz,
                     Patricia</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1984">1984</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Social Dimensions of Chumash Mortuary Populations in the Santa
                           Monica Mountains Region</emph>. Ph.D. dissertation, <orgName
                           key="#ucriver">University of California at Riverside</orgName>.
                        University Microfilms, <placeName key="#annarbor">Ann
                        Arbor</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#cme">Meighan, Clement W.</persName>, and
                           <persName type="author" key="#heb">Hal Eberhart</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1953">1953</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Archaeological Resources of San Nicolas Island, California.
                              <emph><orgName type="publication" key="#aman">American
                              Antiquity</orgName></emph> 19(2):109-125.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#mjmoratto">Moratto, Michael
                        J.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1984">1984</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph><orgName type="publication" key="#caarchaeology">California
                              Archaeology</orgName></emph>. <orgName key="#academicpress">Academic
                           Press</orgName>, <placeName key="#orlando"
                     >Orlando</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#porr">Orr, Phil C.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1945">1945</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Return to San Nicolas. <emph><orgName key="#museumleaflet">Museum
                              Leaflet</orgName></emph> 20(7):75-79. <orgName type="museum"
                           key="#mu_sbmuseum">Santa Barbara Museum of Natural History</orgName>,
                           <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1945">1946</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Anthropology. In, <emph>Annual Report for the Year 1945</emph>, pp.
                        11-12. <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_sbmuseum">Santa Barbara Museum of
                           Natural History</orgName>, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                           Barbara</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#gwpearson">Pearson, Gordon W.</persName>,
                           <persName type="author" key="#jrpilcher">J.R. Pilcher</persName>,
                           <persName type="author" key="#mgbaille">M.G. Baille</persName>, <persName
                           key="#dmcorbett">D.M. Corbett</persName>, and <persName key="#fqua">F.
                           Qua</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1986">1986</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>High-Precision 14C Measurement of Irish Oaks to Show the Natural 14C
                        Variations from AD 1840-5210 BC. <emph><orgName key="#radiocarbo"
                              >Radiocarbon</orgName></emph> 28:911-934.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#gwpearson">Pearson, Gordon W.</persName>,
                        and <persName type="author" key="#mstuiver">Minze
                     Stuiver</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1986">1986</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>High-Precision Calibration of the Radiocarbon Time Scale, AD 500-2500 BC.
                              <emph><orgName key="#radiocarbo">Radiocarbon</orgName></emph>
                        28:839-862.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#pierson">Pierson, Larry J.</persName>, <persName
                           key="#shiller">Gerald I. Shiller</persName>, and <persName key="#slater"
                           >Richard Slater</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Archaeological Resource Study: Morro Bay to Mexican Border, Final
                           Report</emph>. Report on file, Minerals Management Service, <orgName
                           type="government" key="#gov_deptinterior">U.S. Department of the
                           Interior</orgName>, <placeName key="#camarillo">Camarillo</placeName>.
                        [1987]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#raab">Raab, L. Mark</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Eaten Out of House and Home: Residential Mobility of Maritime
                           Hunter- Gatherers on Prehistoric San Clemente Island, California</emph>.
                        Manuscript on file, Center for Public Archaeology, California State
                        University, Northridge. [1989]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#raab">Raab, Mark L.</persName>, and <persName
                           key="#yatsko">>Andrew Yatsko</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1990">1990</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Prehistoric Human Ecology of Quinquina, a Research Design for
                        Archaeological Studies on San Clemente Island, Southern California.
                              <emph><orgName type="publication" key="#paccoastarch">Pacific Coast
                              Archaeological Society Quarterly</orgName></emph>
                        26(2/3):10-37.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#reinman">Reinman, Fred M.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1962">1962</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>New Sites on San Nicolas Island, California. <emph><orgName
                              key="#archsruvannrep">Archaeological Survey Annual
                           Report</orgName></emph> 4:1 l-21. <orgName type="institution"
                           key="#in_ucla">University of California, Los
                     Angeles</orgName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>1964</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Maritime Adaptation on San Nicolas Island, California: A Preliminary and
                        Speculative Evaluation. <emph><orgName key="#archsruvannrep">Archaeological
                              Survey Annual Report</orgName></emph> 6:51-75, <orgName
                           type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University of California, Los
                           Angeles</orgName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>a</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Test Excavations at the Thousand Springs Site: Sni-11, San Nicolas
                           Island, California</emph>. Manuscript on file, <placeName type="region"
                           key="#re_pmugu">Naval Air Weapons Station, Point Mugu</placeName>. [<date
                           when="1982">1982</date>]</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>b</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>New Data From San Nicolas Island, California</emph>. Manuscript on
                        file, <placeName type="region" key="#re_pmugu">Naval Air Weapons Station,
                           Point Mugu</placeName>. [<date when="1985">1985</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#reinman">Reinman, Fred M.</persName>, and <persName
                           key="#lauter">Gloria A. Lauter</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>a</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Fishhooks, Gorges. and Shell Beads: Time Markers on San Nicolas
                           Island, California</emph>. Paper presented at the <orgName
                           key="#socamerarch">Society for American Archaeology</orgName> Annual
                        Meeting, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>, <date
                           when="1981">1981</date>. Manuscript on file, <placeName type="region"
                           key="#re_pmugu">Naval Air Weapons Station, Point
                     Mugu</placeName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>b</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>San Nicolas Island Cultural Resource Survey Report, Vols. 1-3. Manuscript
                        on file, <placeName type="region" key="#re_pmugu">Naval Air Weapons Station,
                           Point Mugu</placeName>. [<date when="1984">1984</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#reinman">Reinman, Fred M.</persName>, and <persName
                           key="#sjtownsend">Sam-Joe Townsend</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1960">1960</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Appendix 2: A Petroglyph Cave on San Nicolas Island. In, Six Burial Sites
                        on San Nicolas Island. <emph><orgName key="#archsruvannrep">Archaeological
                              Survey Annual Report</orgName></emph> 2:101-106. <orgName
                           type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University of California, Los
                           Angeles</orgName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#mrog">Rogers, Malcolm J.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Report of Archaeological Investigations on San Nicolas Island in
                           1930</emph>. Bureau of American Ethnology manuscript no. 2124(2). On
                        file, National Anthropological Archives, <orgName type="museum"
                           key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName>, <placeName
                           type="city" key="#ci_dc">Washington, D.C.</placeName> [<date when="1930"
                           >1930</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#rootenberg">Rootenberg, Sheldon</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1960">1960</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Appendix 4: Cranial and Post-Cranial Measurements and Observations for
                        San Nicolas Island Skeletal Remains. In, Six Burial Sites on San Nicolas
                        Island. <emph><orgName key="#archsruvannrep">Archaeological Survey Annual
                              Report</orgName></emph> 2: 115-130. <orgName type="institution"
                           key="#in_ucla">University of California, Los
                     Angeles</orgName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#mdrosen">Rosen, Martin
                     D.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1980">1980</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Archaeological Investigations at Two Prehistoric Santa Catalina Island
                        Sites: Rosski (SCaI-45) and Miner's Camp (SCal-118). <emph><orgName
                              type="publication" key="#paccoastarch">Pacific Coast Archaeological
                              Society Quarterly</orgName></emph> 16 ( l/2):26-60.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#croz">Rozaire, Charles E.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1959">1959</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Archeological Investigations at Two Sites on San Nicolas Island,
                        California. <emph><orgName type="publication" key="#masterkey"
                              >Masterkey</orgName></emph> 33(4):129-152. <orgName type="museum"
                           key="#mu_southwest">Southwest Museum</orgName>, <placeName type="city"
                           key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1967">1967</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>The Southwest Museum's Field Work on San Nicolas Island. In.
                        Archaeological Explorations on San Nicolas Island, by <persName
                           type="author" key="#bbr">Bruce Bryan</persName>, pp. 139-149.
                           <emph>Southwest Museum Papers</emph> 22. <orgName type="museum"
                           key="#mu_southwest">Southwest Museum</orgName>, <placeName type="city"
                           key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1970">1970</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Archaeological Considerations Regarding the Southern California Islands.
                           <emph>Proceedings of the Symposium on the Biology of the California
                           Islands</emph>, <persName key="#rnphilbrick">Ralph N.
                           Philbrick</persName>, ed., pp. 327-336. <orgName key="#sbbotgar">Santa
                           Barbara Botanical Gardens, Inc.</orgName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Twined Weaving and Western North American Prehistory</emph>. Ph.D.
                        dissertation, <orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University of
                           California, Los Angeles</orgName>. [<date when="19575"
                        >1957</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#salls">Salls, Roy A.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>a</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Skeletal Analysis of Burial - Pit 1.5S/24E. Sni-16 San Nicolas
                           Island, California</emph>. Manuscript on file, <placeName type="region"
                           key="#re_pmugu">Naval Air Weapons Station, Point Mugu</placeName>. [<date
                           when="1981">1981</date>]</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date>b</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Prehistoric Fisheries of the California Bight</emph>. Ph.d.
                        dissertation, <orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University of
                           California, Los Angeles</orgName>. [<date when="1988"
                     >1988</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#aschimmelmann">Schimmelmann,
                           Arndt</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>High Resolution Paleoclimatic Information from Varved Marine
                           Sediments of the Southern California Borderland</emph>. Paper presented
                        at the 27th Annual Meeting of the <orgName key="#soccaarch">Society for
                           California Archaeology</orgName>, <date from="1993-04-07" to="1993-04-11"
                           >April 7-11, 1993</date>, <placeName key="#asilomar"
                        >Asilomar</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#psc">Schumacher, Paul</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Continuation of Contents of Boxes Forwarded to Empire Warehouse in
                           San Francisco</emph>. Manuscript on file, Smithsonian Institution
                        Archive, Record Unit 305, accession no. 4199. [<date when="1875"
                        >1875</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#sstine">Stine, Scott</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Extreme Drought During Medieval Time, and Its Possible Influence on
                           Human Populations of California</emph>. Paper presented at the 27th
                        Annual Meeting of the <orgName key="#soccaarch">Society for California
                           Archaeology</orgName>, <date from="1993-04-07" to="1993-04-11">April
                           7-11, 1993</date>, <placeName key="#asilomar"
                        >Asilomar</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#ihstrudwick">Strudwick, Ivan
                        H.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Temporal and Areal Considerations Regarding the Prehistoric
                           Circular Fishhook of Coastal California</emph>. Master's thesis, <orgName
                           key="#csulb">California State University, Long Beach</orgName>. [<date
                           when="1986">1986</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#mstuiver">Stuiver, Minze</persName>, and
                           <persName type="author" key="#gwpearson">Gordon W.
                        Pearson</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1986">1986</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>High-Precision Calibration of Radiocarbon Time Scale, AD 1950-500 BC.
                              <emph><orgName key="#radiocarbo">Radiocarbon</orgName></emph>
                        28:805-838.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#mstuiver">Stuiver, Minze</persName>,
                           <persName type="author" key="#gwpearson">Gordon W. Pearson</persName>,
                        and <persName key="#tbraziunas">Tom Braziunas</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1986">1986</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Radiocarbon Age Calibration of Marine Samples Back to 9000 Cal Yr BP
                              <emph><orgName key="#radiocarbo">Radiocarbon</orgName></emph> 28
                        :980-1021.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#mstuiver">Stuiver, Minze</persName>, and
                           <persName type="author" key="#pjreimer">P.J. Reimer</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1986">1986</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>A Computer Program for Radiocarbon Age Calibration. <emph><orgName
                              key="#radiocarbo">Radiocarbon</orgName></emph> 28:
                     1022-1030.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName key="#titus">Titus, Michele D.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Evidence for Prehistoric Occupation of Sites on San Clemente Island
                           by Hokan and Uta-Aztecan Indians</emph>. M.A. thesis, <orgName
                           type="institution" key="#in_ucla">University of California, Los
                           Angeles</orgName>. [<date when="1987">1987</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#plwalker">Walker, Phillip L.</persName>,
                        and <persName type="author" key="#pesnethkamp">Pandora E.
                           Snethkamp</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Final Report, Archaeological Investigations on San Miguel Island--1982,
                        Prehistoric Adaptations to the Marine Environment. Office of Public
                        Archaeology, Social Process Research Institute, <orgName key="#ucsb"
                           >University of California, Santa Barbara</orgName>. [<date when="1984"
                           >1984</date>]</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#wjwallace">Wallace, William
                        J.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1955">1955</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>A Suggested Chronology for Southern California Coastal Archaeology.
                              <emph><orgName key="#swjouranth">Southwestern Journal of
                              Anthropology</orgName></emph> 11 (3):214-230.</bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1978">1978</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Post-Pleistocene Archeology, 9000 to 2000 B.C. In. <emph>Handbook of
                           North American Indians, Vol. 8: California</emph>, ed. by <persName
                           type="author" key="#rhe">Robert F. Heizer</persName>, pp. 25-36. <orgName
                           type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName>,
                           <placeName type="city" key="#ci_dc">Washington,
                     D.C.</placeName></bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#cnwarren">Warren, Claude
                        N.</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date when="1968">1968</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Cultural Tradition and Ecological Adaptation on the Southern California
                        Coast. In, Archaic Prehistory in the Western United States, ed. by <persName
                           key="#cirwinwill">C. Irwin-Williams</persName>. <emph><orgName
                              key="#enwucont">Eastern New Mexico University Contributions in
                              Anthropology</orgName></emph> 1(3):1-14. <placeName key="#portales"
                           >Portales</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#pwigand">Wigand,
                     Peter</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><emph>Dynamics of Great Basin Plant Communities During the La.st 12,000
                           Years as a Proxy for the Holocene Climate of California</emph>. Paper
                        presented at the 27th Annual Meeting of the <orgName key="#soccaarch"
                           >Society for California Archaeology</orgName>, <date from="1993-04-07"
                           to="1993-04-11">April 7-11, 1993</date>, <placeName key="#asilomar"
                           >Asilomar</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p><bibl><persName type="author" key="#awo">Woodward, Arthur</persName></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl><date>n.d.</date></bibl></p>
                  <p><bibl>Archaeology. In, <emph>Progress Report of the Los Angeles Museum-Channel
                           Islands Biological Survey: Fourth Expedition; San Nicolas, San Miguel,
                           Santa Rosa and Santa Cruz Islands. July 21 to August 19, 1939</emph>, by
                           <persName type="author" key="#dme">Don Meadows</persName>, pp. 35- 36.
                        Manuscript on file, <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_museumofnaturalhistory"
                           >Los Angeles County Museum of Natural History</orgName>, <placeName
                           type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>.</bibl></p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
