<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="monograph" key="#piedpipers">The Pied Pipers</title>
               <editor>Fisher, Emma</editor>
               <editor>Wintle, Justin</editor>
               <biblScope unit="pages" from="1" to="320"/>
               <date when="1975"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#nyc">New York</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#ny">NY</placeName></pubPlace>
               <publisher><orgName type="publisher" key="#paddington">Paddington Press
                     Ltd.</orgName></publisher>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="chapter" key="#Wintle1975">Scott O'Dell</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="181"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#jwi">Wintle, Justin</persName></author>
                  <date when="1975"/>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head><title type="chapter"><hi rend="bold"><emph>12</emph></hi></title> <title
                  type="main"><persName type="author" key="#sod"><hi rend="bold"><emph>Scott
                           O'Dell</emph></hi></persName></title></head>
            <byline>Interviewed by <persName type="author" key="#jwi">Justin
               Wintle</persName></byline>
            <p>Another author who turns to the past for subjects is <persName type="author"
                  key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName>; but unlike <persName type="author" key="#jai"
                  >Joan Aiken</persName> he deals in history realistically, as a way of exploring
               social equations that are still present in his own society on the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_paccoast">West Coast of the United States</placeName>. Many
               of his themes are well established in the annals of American literature. <emph>The
                  King's Fifth</emph> is a full-blooded tale about a corrupting and divisive lust
               for gold among a band of early Spanish settlers. <emph>Sing Down The Moon</emph>
               tells of the suffering of an Indian tribe pushed forever westward by the European
               conquest. <span type="trope" n="8"><emph>Island Of The [sic] Blue Dolphins</emph>,
                  winner of the <date when="1961">1961</date> Newberry [sic] Award and later made
                  into a film of the same title, is about <rs><persName type="group" key="#lw; #kar"
                        >an Indian girl</persName></rs> left alone on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">an island</placeName></rs> off <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_paccoast">the coast of California</placeName>, an American equivalent
                  of <emph>Robinson Crusoe</emph>.</span></p>
            <p>O'Dell's preoccupations are probably best explained by his long and eventful life.
               Officially, he was born in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                  Angeles</placeName> just after the turn of the century; unofficially in <date
                  when="1899">1899</date>. <persName key="#bsc">His father</persName> was a railroad
               man, and the family moved around what was then the frontier land of <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName>. After leaving high
               school <persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> attended the <orgName
                  type="institution" key="#in_uofwis">University of Wisconsin</orgName>, where,
               already determined to become a writer, he quickly became disillusioned with his
               academic courses. He abandoned the idea of graduation and concentrated simply on
               those subjects that appealed to him&#8212;psychology, philosophy, English and
               history. This, he claims, has given him "a sense of comradeship with the students of
               today."</p>
            <p>Having left <placeName type="state" key="#st_wi">Wisconsin</placeName>, <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> went into films, and, among other
               productions, worked as a second cameraman on the original version of <emph>Ben
                  Hur</emph>. He spent <!--it would be cool to know which-->a year with the <orgName
                  type="military" key="#mi_airforce">Air Force</orgName> in <placeName type="state"
                  key="#st_tx">Texas</placeName> during World War Two, and subsequently became the
               book editor of <rs><orgName type="publication" key="#ladailynews">a Los Angeles
                     newspaper</orgName></rs>. He wrote a number of books for adults during
                     <rs><date notBefore="1950" notAfter="1959">the fifties</date></rs>, and in
                     <rs><date notBefore="1960" notAfter="1969">the sixties</date></rs> his books
               for children. In <date when="1972">1972</date> he was awarded the Hans Christian
               Andersen Author's Medal.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> lives near <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>, within striking distance of the
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_mexicanborder">Mexican
                  border</placeName></rs>, with <rs><persName key="#ehall">his second
                     wife</persName></rs>, who edits the popular journal <emph><orgName
                     type="publication" key="#psychtoday">Psychology Today</orgName></emph>.</p>
            <div type="interview">
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Your recent children's books have been written for what is referred to as
                     the Young Adult market. Why is that?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>For one thing we've found that here in <rs><placeName type="country" key="#co_usa"
                        >the States</placeName></rs> children read more advanced books than parents
                  and educators thought they could or would. Furthermore, there's a dearth of books
                  for young adults, because they're not nearly as profitable for publisher or
                  author. But there's an important need, so the last two books I've done have been
                  in this field. One has just come out, called <emph>Child of Fire</emph>. The
                  background is the <placeName type="region" key="#re_mexicanborder">Mexican
                     border</placeName>, just south of here. The story concerns five Chicano gangs
                  and presents a problem that the ancestors of these boys met 400 years ago. Young
                  Spaniards of the <date from="1500" to="1599">sixteenth-century</date>, yearning
                  for adventure, came to <placeName type="region" key="#re_americas">the
                     Americas</placeName> in search of gold. Their descendants, living in
                        <rs><placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">modern America</placeName></rs>,
                  have the same desire for adventure, but no place to find it except in the world of
                  drugs and pointless warfare. The Chicano, for all his proud heritage, is a
                  prisoner of the <emph>barrio</emph>, a second-class citizen. <emph>Child of
                     Fire</emph> deals with his problem, both realistically and symbolically and, I
                  hope, with some understanding.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Many of your books (one is tempted to say all your books) are concerned with
                     traditional American themes, particularly themes of the frontier&#8212;conquest
                     of new lands, what it's like to be midway between having laws made for you and
                     making them for yourself, the conflict of interests between the old tribes and
                     the new settlers, and the sense of opportunity given to youth. Is this because
                     of the life you've led?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I've been asked that question before, and I've never given what I thought was an
                  adequate answer. I've led a very full life, gone to many schools, done a lot of
                  things, lived abroad extensively, been in a couple of wars. A mixed up sort of
                  life, perhaps. I think the fact that I've written about the past has to do with
                  this. It's not necessarily an escape (though I think there's part of that in it),
                  or an attempt to look back at calmer times; rather I have the feeling that the
                  present is the past and the past is the present. The fundamental human is about
                  the same as he was a couple of thousand years ago. The basic changes have not been
                  vast. Human needs for love, affection, understanding, a chance to succeed at
                  something, are about the same. Although I may write about a <rs><name
                        type="fictional" key="#bmo">Navajo girl</name></rs> (<emph>Sing Down The
                     Moon</emph>), I feel that she is a contemporary. I just wanted to pay a tribute
                  to the human spirit, and the fact that this spirit happened to be in an Indian
                  girl is really incidental. I'm not interested in <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_navajo">the Navajos</orgName>
                  particularly&#8212;they're not my favorite tribe even. They were
                  marauders&#8212;they rode in and took the crops of other Indians, after the
                  harvest sometimes. But there was this thing that happened at the <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_canyonchelly">Canyon de Chelly</placeName>. <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#cca">Carson</persName> and <rs><orgName
                        type="government" key="#gov_usa">the government</orgName></rs> rounded up
                  the Indians and drove them to <placeName key="#fortsumner">Fort
                  Sumner</placeName>. The important thing was the story. If the story is a good
                  story children will read it for the suspense, and you can use suspense to do
                  things. In <emph>Sing Down The Moon</emph> I wanted to call children's attention
                  to the fact that there are such things as endurance, as loyalty to your family,
                  loyalty to the place where you live. Nowadays people are dispersed, can live
                  anywhere they want to. That's the trouble here in <placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_cal">California</placeName>&#8212;we're just a bunch of uprooted
                  people. You don't know your neighbor and he never speaks to you. But this
                        <rs><name type="fictional" key="#bmo">Navajo girl</name></rs>&#8212;she did
                  want to go back to where her family had lived and have a child and live in a cave
                  on the side of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_canyonchelly">the
                        Canyon</placeName></rs>. Even though she knows <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_navajo">her people</orgName></rs>
                  were driven out, she still goes back and starts over again. I hope there's a
                  lesson in this, an inspiration for children. It's very strong in me, this
                  didactic, inspirational thing. I had a lot of circuit writers and educators in my
                  family, going back for 150, 200 years. While I'm not formally religious, I think
                  this messianic thing has rubbed off on me. I want to teach and say something to
                  people. Adults have pretty well established their lives, but you can say something
                  to children. If you can get their attention and their affection, then there is
                  something that can really be done with children. You can tell a story and add
                  something that might be of interest and importance in their lives. It is
                  messianic. As I said I've had a particularly full life, which I've lived and don't
                  want to talk about; and for the most part, with the possible exception of
                     <emph>The Child Of Fire</emph> (which has some of my life in it) I have written
                  about times before l was born. Perhaps leaving the present and going back
                  furnishes sustenance of an emotional kind. But things haven't changed very much,
                  so it doesn't matter what period you write about.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Your books are full of respect for that human quality of endurance you
                     referred to; but I can't see that there would be as much opportunity for
                     children or young people to demonstrate such a quality here in <placeName
                        type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> as there was perhaps when
                     you were young, when <rs><placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">the
                           State</placeName></rs> was still opening up.</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>That's part of it. There are things like the <orgName key="#sla">SLA</orgName>
                     (<orgName key="#sla">Symbionese Liberation Army</orgName>), but all they want
                  to do is shoot off their guns. Like <rs><orgName key="#sla">these
                     kids</orgName></rs> who held up a bank for a million dollars just to prove they
                  could get it. There's a need. They had nothing to do. They didn't have a job and
                  they didn't have transportation. You can't walk in <placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, so it's bad if you don't have
                  transportation. But here are things to do. Not necessarily here, but if they went
                  to <placeName type="region" key="#re_africacon">Africa</placeName> they could do a
                  lot. There are millions of kids starving over there. There are challenges all over
                  the world, but nobody's bothered to point them out to the young. Their horizons
                  are so narrow that they don't know anybody ever existed. They don't know that
                     <persName key="#gca">Caesar</persName> existed, or <persName key="#alex"
                     >Alexander the Great</persName>, or <persName key="#aei">Einstein</persName>,
                  or anybody else. They're alone. They haven't got transportation. Maybe their old
                  man's out of a job. They've gone hungry a couple of times, and they're all mixed
                  up. There's <persName key="#phe">this Hearst girl</persName> backing the <orgName
                     key="#sla">SLA</orgName>. It's so stupid, even the liberals are
                  antagonized.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Even so, she'll probably go down as a folk-hero among some
                  people.</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>Oh sure, particularly if they don't analyze the escapade. For instance, that four
                  million dollars' worth of food. It's just people cramming their stomachs for a
                  couple of meals; instead they could have set up a center where really poor people
                  could benefit&#8212;people who are poor materially and mentally and physically. A
                  center like that, if properly funded, might have taken care of 500 people a day
                  with a modest meal for a long time. Instead of this they bought a lot of groceries
                  and threw them around. They were only interested in making a display and showing
                  their guns. I've written against the gun. <emph>The Island Of The Blue
                     Dolphins</emph> was a direct protest against the gun, and the killing of
                  animals and the killing of people.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>That's <rs>another book</rs> that has <rs><name type="fictional" key="#kar"
                           >an Indian girl</name></rs> as its heroine. Why is it that you write so
                     sympathetically about the Indians?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I think it is accidental, in the sense that I've lived in <rs><placeName
                        type="state" key="#st_cal">a country of Indians</placeName></rs>. The story
                  of <rs><name type="fictional" key="#kar">an Indian girl</name></rs> who lives
                        <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> on <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">an island</placeName></rs> alone is a dramatic
                  idea, so I used it as a vehicle for what I wanted to say. If she had been a girl
                  from <placeName type="state" key="#st_ia">Iowa</placeName> or <name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_mayflower">the Mayflower</name> I still would have done it, because of
                  the situation. The same with the <name type="fictional" key="#bmo">Navajo
                     girl</name> in <emph>Sing Down The Moon</emph>, a ready-made situation about
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_navajo">a people who
                        were persecuted, uprooted and driven from their homes</orgName></rs>. Again,
                     <emph>The Black Pearl</emph> is based on a legend current down there below
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>. <persName
                     type="author" key="#jstein">Steinbeck</persName> also used it. Our stories are
                  quite alike up to the time when <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_fictionalpearl">the
                        pearl</name></rs> is sold: then they diverge. I think of all this as just an
                  accident, that I was born out here. If I'd been born in <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_mwest">the Middle West</placeName> and stayed in <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mwest">the Middle West</placeName>, I would come into
                  contact with different legends, probably about early French voyages and so forth.
                  In <emph>Child of Fire</emph> it's a <rs><name type="fictional" key="#mca">young
                        Spaniard</name></rs>. They are people I've grown up with, people I do know.
                  I have Indian friends, just as I have Spanish and Mexican friends. There's quite a
                  difference between the Spanish and the Mexicans, who are really Indians, or who
                  have Indian blood in them. There are also a lot of different tribes in <placeName
                     type="country" key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</placeName>. For instance I lived a
                  summer in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_pat">Patzcuaro</placeName>, where the
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan">Tarascan
                     Indians</orgName> live, about 9,000 feet above the sea. They were never
                  conquered by any Indian tribe, not even by the <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aztec">Aztecs</orgName>. They lived in
                  a beautiful little city called <placeName type="city" key="#ci_tz"
                     >Zinzunzan</placeName>, "<rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_tz">the place of
                        the hummingbirds</placeName></rs>." Then <persName key="#nbu"
                     >Guzman</persName>, a Spaniard looking for gold, came with his five men. He
                  talked with <persName key="#tng">the King</persName>, and told him "We come for
                  gold." <persName key="#tng">The King</persName> had never seen gold. Instead he
                  gave <persName key="#nbu">Guzman</persName> beautiful garments made of hummingbird
                  feathers which he promptly threw away. <persName key="#nbu">Guzman</persName> was
                  sure <persName key="#tng">the King</persName> was lying, so he tied him to the
                  tail of a horse, dragged him round the square and threw him on a bonfire.
                  Immediately all the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan"
                     >Tarascans</orgName>, who had never been conquered before, disappeared into the
                  high mountains, and they're still there today. That's a long story. But there was
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car">a girl</persName></rs> in
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_pat">Patzcuaro</placeName>, one of eleven
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan">Tarascan</orgName>
                  children, and we took her on as our cook. I modeled <rs><name type="fictional"
                        key="#kar">my Indian girl</name></rs> on her. This illustrates the
                  mechanism. If I had been in the <placeName type="region" key="#re_mwest">Middle
                     West</placeName> it would have been somebody else.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Your books are all told in the first person, through the eyes of the
                     protagonist. Is that because many of them are based on stories you've heard
                     word of mouth?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I think it's the easiest way to write, though some of my adult books have been
                  written in the third person. Though I don't think you'd find any evidence of it in
                  my present writing, I have been influenced by <persName type="author" key="#jcon"
                     >Conrad</persName>. I was a great admirer of his for many years. What he did
                  was more complex than I am able to handle. Sometimes he would have three
                  narrators&#8212;the author, <name type="fictional" key="#marlow">Marlow</name> and
                     <name type="fictional" key="#jim">Lord Jim</name>, for example&#8212;each
                  telling different parts of the same story as they saw it. I think writing in the
                  first person is easier because you don't have to work so hard for suspension of
                  disbelief. When you read that "I did it" there's a tendency to believe what you're
                  being told. You get an almost automatic identification which I think is so
                  important in a story. In <emph>Child of Fire</emph> I have a device which goes
                  back to the <name type="fictional" key="#marlow">Marlow</name> situation in
                  Conrad. I use <rs><name type="fictional" key="#del">a parole officer</name></rs>,
                  in charge of fifty children, who tells the story of <rs><name type="fictional"
                        key="#mca">one particular boy</name></rs>. It has drawbacks of course,
                  because you can only report what you have seen. I have a situation in which the
                  boy leaves <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName> and goes on a
                  tuna clipper to <placeName type="country" key="#co_ec">Ecuador</placeName>, where
                  there's a mutiny and where he's thrown in prison. ln the end he escapes and gets
                  back to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>. Well, he has to
                  tell this story; there's no other way of getting it. It's not as dramatic as it
                  would have been if the <rs><name type="fictional" key="#del">parole
                     officer</name></rs> had gone with him, and so had been able to tell the story
                  himself, like an omnipotent observer. But that was obviously impossible. So there
                  are penalties.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>I understand you are now working on a novel about <persName key="#wty"
                        >William Tyndale</persName>, the first Englishman to do a creditable version
                     of the Bible. Although this is obviously set in the past, it doesn't seem to
                     have much else to do with your other children's books. Are you doing this as an
                     extension of your own messianic tendencies?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I'm terribly interested in his story. He wanted every ploughboy to read the Bible
                  as it came from the original Greek and Hebrew, not as it came from the Vulgate,
                  and not as the priest read it in the pulpit. This is what <persName key="#wty"
                     >Tyndale</persName> wanted to do, and this is what <persName key="#wty"
                     >Tyndale</persName> did&#8212;and he did it so beautifully that when the King
                  James version came along they used 70 to 75 per cent of Tyndale in it. Today we
                  speak Tyndale. It's extraordinary if you compare the passages he translated from
                  the Greek with the same passages in the Latin. If you are really concerned with
                  something it gets into the fabric of the story and is transmitted to the reader.
                  That was <persName type="author" key="#dhlaw">D. H. Lawrence</persName>'s feeling,
                  and it's certainly one I share. I have only done things that I've been really
                  enthusiastic about, stories that have stirred me. With <persName key="#wty"
                     >Tyndale</persName>, and with this messianic quirk of mine, I feel that I am
                  performing a mission; it may be a little grandiloquent to call it that, yet that
                  is my feeling. Children speak the language, but they don't know where the hell it
                  came from. They don't know whom to credit for it, and they certainly don't know
                  Tyndale's story, how the man lived in attics and burrows and was pursued by spies
                  all over <placeName type="country" key="#co_ger">Germany</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="country" key="#co_hol">Holland</placeName> and <placeName type="country"
                     key="#co_bel">Belgium</placeName>, attempting to seize him and take him back to
                     <placeName type="country" key="#co_eng">England</placeName>. His Bible was
                  smuggled into <placeName type="country" key="#co_eng">England</placeName>. It had
                  to be, because it was against the law to own it or read it. He very calmly gave up
                  his life for this purpose. He was a hero. Today children don't feel there are
                  important things to do. They take it out on sports&#8212;the football players and
                  the baseball players are heroes, so that at any given time we've got 5,000 heroes.
                  But this is a very empty thing; it's heroism delegated. Nobody enjoys sports more
                  than I do, but I don't enjoy them for that reason. I don't think they should be
                  used as a substitute for the meaningful things in life that never occur to
                  children brought up by fathers who are crazy about sports in houses where there
                  aren't any books. And our divorce statistics and our crime statistics are
                  frightening. In this county alone, <placeName type="county" key="#co_sdcounty">San
                     Diego</placeName>, there are 23,000 parolees. In other words, sometime this
                  afternoon you have been in contact with two or three parolees in <rs><placeName
                        type="county" key="#co_sdcounty">this area</placeName></rs>. You can't miss
                  them. And what do you do with them? I'm on a board of directors for one of these
                  crash programs. We run a tranquillity house where we have twenty or so very young
                  girls and boys who have drug problems. They live in this house and police
                  themselves under certain restrictions and rules. What we're trying to do is put
                  them back in the mainstream. We've been most successful when they've gotten jobs
                  or something to do, and don't have to sit round the house all day, which is
                  lethal.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>But one can see why they get like that in an overdeveloped urban
                     society.</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>Young people are terribly restricted on the basis of what we consider important.
                     <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">The country</placeName> is poisoned by
                  money, so that anybody who doesn't get rich and make a lot of it is considered a
                  failure. There's none of the old idea, still around in some places of the world,
                  that you do your work because you enjoy doing it. Well, the unions have taken over
                  now. If you're a checker at a Safeway store, you get five dollars ninety-five
                  cents an hour, and benefits, so you don't have to worry about a lot of things, the
                  quality of your work for one thing. It's very easy of course to sit here having
                  something quite different to do and talk in general terms. I think it's partly the
                  way schools are run today. Think of the past, when children weren't children but a
                  real part of the family. If the father was a stonemason then the son was a
                  stonemason; and if the mother worked at a loom making tapestries, then the
                  daughter learned to make tapestries. The family was monolithic, as <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan">the Tarascans</orgName> are
                  in <persName type="country" key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</persName> today. The family
                  was very strong, and the children learned trades and were proud of them. By the
                  age of ten or so they were adults. I think children should be given adult
                  responsibilities as soon as possible. Of course, child labor has been abused, as
                  it was in the Industrial Revolution. What we're doing though is extending
                  childhood to infinity, protecting our children from what, for Christ's sake?
                  They're much smarter than we are, much smarter than their parents, certainly in
                  worldly ways. We need to change the fabric of the family so there are books in the
                  home and mothers and fathers reading to their children, instead of this generation
                  gap, children wanting to get out of the house as fast as they can because of
                  restrictions. How this is to be done I don't know. It probably isn't possible.
                  There's some element that is missing. In the Orient the father is honored, and the
                  grandfather and the grandmother are honored. There is honor. But here in
                     <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">America</placeName>, when you get to be
                  over forty you might as well be dead.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p>In <emph>The King's Fifth </emph> it certainly suprised me that <rs><name
                        type="fictional" key="#esa">a boy of fifteen</name></rs> was entrusted with
                  the post of cartographer on a large exploring vessel.</p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>It's an example of what I'm talking about. For instance, our captains and your
                  captains who sailed to the Far East usually retired at the age of thirty.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>There is real evidence that a skill like that could be acquired by the time
                     you were fifteen in the Spanish Empire?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>They learned these skills when they were very young. <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#flu">Coronado</persName> was <emph>only</emph> twenty-nine when he led
                  his great expedition. In this story I've just published, <emph>Child of
                     Fire</emph>, <rs><name type="fictional" key="#mca">the boy</name></rs> was
                  inspired by <persName type="seaman" key="#flu">Coronado</persName>. But are there
                  any Coronados around today! There aren't, but there are still things to do. We
                  shouldn't try to make adults out of children too quickly; but we can still give
                  them a sense of responsibility. We can give girls the knowledge that marriage
                  won't solve all their problems, either when they're at junior high, or preferably
                  before. They must realize that, though it's a wonderful idea, there will be more
                  problems, more responsibilities after than before they're married. They have to
                  learn that in marriage you're in trouble if you expect to find in your mate all
                  the men in the world or all the women in the world. I don't think children are
                  prepared for marriage at all. I think the statistics prove it, particularly here
                  in <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">America</placeName>. <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> is the worst of
                  all&#8212;something like one divorce in every two and one-half marriages. But if
                  you tried to teach sex in the schools, the parents wouldn't stand for it. So the
                  kids educate themselves, without good examples or good sexual relationships. They
                  just bat their heads around until hopefully they find something workable. I'm all
                  for divorce as an escape from horrors, but I still think it's a frightening
                  indication.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Have you had any children yourself?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>No. <rs><persName key="#ehall">My wife</persName></rs> (we're both previously
                  divorced) has <rs><persName type="group" key="#daughter1; #son1">two
                        children</persName></rs>&#8212;<rs><persName key="#daughter1">a girl who's
                        twenty-four and married twice</persName></rs>, and <rs><persName key="#son1"
                        >a boy still at school</persName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>One can see how this society is bad for marriage. But on the other hand one
                     might say that marriage is bad for this society. To you, obviously, marriage is
                     important.</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I think it's terribly important. It's an anchor. I don't think you can have much
                  without it, except chaos. There are so many things involved. Children first of
                  all. You can say that children would be better off herded, as <persName
                     type="author" key="#gsh">Shaw</persName> suggested, and taken away from their
                  parents. It's an interesting theory, but it doesn't work. The human psyche is a
                  very fragile thing. Children demand, must have, love. Most children don't have it,
                  and that's one of our troubles. Children need to feel they have a place, that
                  they're not some object, and that they have a designated and honorable role in a
                  family where everybody contributes. American children don't contribute. They do
                  what they want to do, or what they can get away with. And that's what they're
                  brought up to do. It's difficult to argue with them, so parents don't argue with
                  them. They are afraid to attack the problem because if they talk too much then the
                  children will leave the house. The family is certainly fragmented. I would like to
                  have it all go back to the farm, where children grew up knowing how to use a hoe
                  and milk a cow. To live out in the country and raise a lot of the things that you
                  use&#8212;that to me is the ideal life. It may be impossible, but it's still
                  ideal. The last thing that ninety-nine out of a hundred people want to do is get
                  up at four in the morning and milk a cow. But it's a wonderful life because once
                  again the family can become monolithic, one depending upon the other. In the past
                  there have been disadvantages to this&#8212;little schooling and a lot of
                  isolation. But now with television it's quite different. This is what I'd like to
                  see. How you get it in an overpopulated industrial society I don't know. Anyway
                  people don't want it. They want what they've got now&#8212;a lot of sports and
                  TV.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>You're obviously a man of faith. Perhaps the most powerful moment in all
                     your books occurs at the end of </emph>The Black Pearl, <emph>when despite the
                     fact that <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_fictionalpearl">the pearl</name></rs>
                     has wrought such misfortune to the community, <rs><persName type="fictional"
                           key="#rsa">the boy</persName></rs> still takes it back to the church
                     where it is enshrined. Where did that come from?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I think it's just a logical working out of the plot. At present <emph>The Black
                     Pearl</emph> is being made into a motion picture. I've read the script[,] not
                  that I have any say in it. What the producer does is to have <rs><persName
                        type="fictional" key="#rsa">the boy</persName></rs> sell <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_fictionalpearl">the pearl</name></rs> and buy food and
                  clothing for the town. It's the <orgName key="#sla">SLA</orgName> idea again.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>And exactly what you avoided.</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>Yes. I said to him, Well, it's dramatic, but I don't like it because, and I'm not
                  a Catholic, you're criticizing <orgName type="church" key="#ch_catholic">the
                     Catholic Church</orgName>. In essence <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_fictionalpearl">this pearl</name></rs> could buy twenty or
                  twenty-five thousand dollars' worth of groceries, but in my version <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_fictionalpearl">the pearl</name></rs> exists and
                  everybody can come and look at it and feel that it belongs to them. That's the
                  theory in <orgName type="church" key="#ch_catholic">the Catholic Church</orgName>,
                  that the Cathedral and the <persName key="#mary">Virgin</persName> are yours. I've
                  seen Indians who have come hundreds of miles to <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_mc">Mexico City</placeName> to see the <rs><persName key="#mary"
                        >Guadalupe Virgin</persName></rs>. These Indians come with a vision of the
                     <persName key="#mary">Virgin</persName> in their eyes and nothing else. They'd
                  walk over you and never notice. Adoration, excitement! So the way I closed
                     <emph>The Black Pearl</emph> seemed the logical way.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>How much research goes into your books?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>Certainly a lot for <emph>The King's Fifth</emph>. That was an overly ambitious
                  book when I first started it. All the cities were allegorical cities. I woke up
                  one morning and found that I was competing with <persName type="author" key="#dal"
                     >Dante</persName>. So I quit that and started over.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Are your books intended as a way through the barriers between children and
                     their parents, the problem we have discussed?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>Yes&#8212;I think the written word is one of the few great resources we have. I
                  don't think our television, with its violence and overdisplay of firearms and
                  bosoms and everything, is helpful at all. I have a dedication to the idea of
                  trying to reach this young group that hasn't been abandoned yet, to reach them
                  with a few simple comments about life. I get a lot of letters from children,
                  particularly on <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>. They like the idea of
                  fighting for survival; they are challenged by it and they would like to try it
                  themselves.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Do you have any opinions about the commune movement which has been going on
                     for <rs><date notAfter="1964" to="1974">ten years or s</date></rs>o now? It
                     seems a variation on the idea of the return to the farm and a closer family
                     existence.</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>In the beginning I was critical about it because I didn't understand what they
                  were trying to do. Then it became associated with marijuana, which, incidentally,
                  I don't think is as bad as cigarettes. It has been degraded by the word "hippy"
                  and by long hair. People don't realize of course that for thousands of years young
                  men wore their hair long. What disappoints me about this youth revolution though,
                  is that very little has come out of it artistically. The best is from the <orgName
                     key="#beatles">Beatles</orgName>&#8212;they've made a contribution. But in
                  poetry and prose and art there has been very little. They attend Woodstock by the
                  thousands, but that's not productive. The same group with the same excitement 500
                  years ago would have built cathedrals beautiful to look at.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Perhaps it's a lack of independence among the gatherers at Woodstock that
                     you find hard to take?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I do think independence is a very important thing if you can combine it with the
                  family. <rs><persName key="#bsc">My father</persName></rs> was an autocrat who
                  couldn't care less about his children. I never had a good relationship with him,
                  so I can't speak too much from experience about the family. But I still think we
                  should try to restore it.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Would that help to solve the other problems in <placeName type="country"
                        key="#co_usa">America</placeName>&#8212;the racial problem, for
                     instance?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>It would help. I don't think you can solve the Black problem by any one approach.
                  It's a tremendous task and all acts of good will help.</p>
               <p>Q</p>
               <p><emph>Do you still have stories you want to write?</emph></p>
               <p>A</p>
               <p>I have a lot more&#8212;three or four at the moment. But it's difficult to get to
                  them because when I quit smoking <rs><date when="1970">four years ago</date></rs>
                  I found that I could no longer write at the typewriter. Now I write with a pen. It
                  takes longer to get myself together, using a pen, and I work more slowly.</p>
               <dateline>
                  <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, <date when="1974"
                     >1974</date></dateline>
               <note type="contributers_note"><emph>Among the many books <persName type="author"
                        key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> has written are:</emph> Island of the
                  Blue Dolphins (<date when="1960">1960</date>, Newberry [sic] Award Winner); The
                  King's Fifth (<date when="1966">1966</date>, a Newberry [sic] Honor Book); The
                  Black Pearl (<date when="1967">1967</date>, also a Newberry [sic] Honor Book); The
                  Dark Canoe (<date when="1968">1968</date>); Journey to Jericho (<date when="1969"
                     >1969</date>); Sing Down the Moon (<date when="1970">1970</date>); The Treasure
                  of Top-el-Bampo (<date when="1972">1972</date>) <emph>and</emph> The Cruise of the
                  Arctic Star (<date when="1973">1973</date>).</note>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
