<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#sbmag">Santa Barbara
                            Magazine</orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                    <date when="1988-07-01"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>,
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="article" key="#Howorth1988-Magic">San Nicolas Island: The
                            Elusive Source of the Chumash Magic Stones</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="42"/>
                        <author><persName type="author" key="#howorth">Howorth, Peter
                            C.</persName></author>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main"><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas
                            Island</placeName>: The Elusive Source of the Chumash Magic
                        Stones</title></head>
                <byline>By <persName type="author" key="#howorth">Peter C.
                    Howorth</persName></byline>
                <p><emph><rs><persName key="#chusor">A Chumash sorcerer</persName></rs> slowly
                        arranges twenty elongated stones in a circle around a disc-shaped stone.
                        Suddenly he clashes all the stones together and sprinkles water over them.
                        Smoke rises. Now the rains will come.</emph></p>
                <p><emph>In the area that will someday bear the name <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_ven">Ventura</placeName>, <rs><persName key="#chusor">a
                                shaman</persName></rs> squeezes an oddly shaped stone in his fist.
                        When he opens his fingers, the stone is moist, proof of its rainmaking
                        power.</emph></p>
                <p><emph>At <placeName type="city" key="#ci_tej">Tejón</placeName>, <rs><persName
                                key="#chusor">an Indian</persName></rs> opens a deerskin pouch and
                        removes a stone from where it lies nestled among goose down and chia seeds.
                        He takes out the feathers and the seeds, makes a pile of them, then lights
                        them on fire. Having burned his animal offering to the stone, <rs><persName
                                key="#chusor">the Indian</persName></rs> places fresh down and seeds
                        in the pouch, feeding the stone, caring for it. He speaks to the stone.
                        "Guard the house because you are very powerful; care for the house when the
                        wind makes it shake."</emph></p>
                <p><emph>The magic stones are unusual, alien. They are lens-shaped, metallic; they
                        even seem to rust. Some have faint concentric stratifications. They are
                        surprisingly heavy, yet comfortable to hold.</emph></p>
                <p><emph>Where did these magic stones come from? Were they shaped by hand or formed
                        by nature? Why did native tribes throughout much of the <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName> coast have
                        them, call them by similar names and use them in similar ways? These
                        questions and more have baffled researchers since the <rs><date
                                notBefore="1800-01-01" notAfter="1820-01-01">early
                        1800s</date></rs>, when <persName type="missionfather" key="#boscana">Father
                            Gerónimo Boscana</persName> from <placeName type="mission"
                            key="#mi_stjohn">Mission San Juan Capistrano</placeName> first
                        documented the stones' existence.</emph></p>
                <p><emph>Through a dramatic sequence of events, researcher <persName type="author"
                            key="#howorth">Peter C. Howorth</persName> has uncovered a major source
                        of the magic stones. By discovering the location, he has brought fresh
                        insight to one of the great archaeological puzzles on the <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_paccoast">West Coast</placeName>.</emph></p>
                <p><emph>The search for the origin of the stones began at <rs><date notBefore="1899"
                                notAfter="1901">the turn of this century</date></rs>. . .
                    .</emph></p>
                <p>In the <rs><date notBefore="1900-01-01" notAfter="1920-01-01">early
                        1900s</date></rs>, anthropologist <persName type="author" key="#jha">John
                        Peabody Harrington</persName>, who had studied the local <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">Chumash Indians</orgName>
                    and their culture for decades, noticed that their magic stones were like nothing
                    he had seen on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>,
                    yet many mainland natives had them. He decided to find out why. He asked
                            <rs><persName key="#indian12">an Indian</persName></rs> about the origin
                    of the stones. <rs><persName key="#indian12">The man</persName></rs> replied
                    vaguely that the stones could be found on an island or at the beach. <persName
                        type="author" key="#jha">Harrington</persName> purchased some of these
                    stones from <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                            Indians</orgName></rs>. He continued his research, but the mystery
                    remained unsolved.</p>
                <p>In <date when="1981">1981</date>, the late <persName type="author" key="#thu"
                        >Travis Hudson</persName>, curator of anthropology at the <orgName
                        type="museum" key="#mu_sbmuseum">Museum of Natural History</orgName>,
                    discovered an obscure reference to the magic stones' origin in one of
                    Harrington's voluminous multilingual manuscripts. The stones supposedly came
                    from distant <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara
                        Island</placeName>, nearly 70 miles offshore from the city of <placeName
                        type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</p>
                <p><persName type="author" key="#thu">Hudson</persName>, knowing my longstanding
                    interest in anthropology, mentioned the mystery of the magic stones' origin to
                    me and his discovery of the clue which suggested that they came from <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara Island</placeName>. Acting on
                    Hudson's evidence, he and I organized an expedition to try to locate the source
                    of the magic stones on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">the
                            island</placeName></rs>. Anthropologist <persName type="author"
                        key="#tbl">Thomas Blackburn</persName>, one of Hudson's collaborators,
                    joined us.</p>
                <p>We combed <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">the island</placeName></rs>
                    carefully but were disappointed. We could find neither the stones nor the
                    geologic structure that would form their matrix. I speculated that the reference
                    that guided us to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">this
                            island</placeName></rs> actually referred to the <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> in general rather
                    than to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara Island</placeName> in
                    particular. Before the turn of the century, when <persName type="author"
                        key="#jha">Harrington</persName> made his provocative notation, mainland
                    residents called the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        Islands</placeName> the Santa Barbara Islands. An error in transcription
                    could easily have steered us in the wrong direction. In any event, we would
                    never find the solution to the puzzle on lonely <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara Island</placeName>. We would have to look for the
                    stones on the remaining seven islands and <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld"
                        >the mainland coast</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Over the ensuing years the puzzle continued to tease me. I tucked the information
                    away in the back of my mind and wondered if anyone would ever discover where
                    Indian sorcerers gathered their magic stones.</p>
                <p>In late <date when="1987">1987</date>, a search for historic shipwrecks takes me
                    to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, the most
                    remote of our eight <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        Islands</placeName>. The <orgName type="military" key="#mi_navy">United
                        States Navy</orgName> has managed <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                        Nicolas</placeName> since <date when="1947">1947</date>, using it as a
                    testing site for military weaponry. Part of the Navy's mission is to preserve
                    the cultural and historic resources on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                            >the island</placeName></rs>; hence my shipwreck search.</p>
                <p>The <orgName type="military" key="#mi_navy">Navy</orgName> assigns <persName
                        type="author" key="#klope">Matt Klope</persName>, a civilian employed by the
                    military as a wildlife biologist, to facilitate my research on <rs><placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. <persName
                        type="author" key="#klope">Klope</persName> also serves as an escort; the
                        <orgName type="military" key="#mi_navy">Navy</orgName> has declared
                            <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                    strictly off-limits to the general public, allowing occasional access to special
                    groups such as professional researchers.</p>
                <p>We are up before dawn, rattling across <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                            >the island</placeName></rs> in a military truck. A broad sandy cove
                    opens in front of us like a catcher's mitt. We begin searching amid the flotsam
                    and jetsam and soon discover bits of wreckage. Nothing large, nothing historic.
                    I urge <persName type="author" key="#klope">Klope</persName> on; we hope to walk
                    around <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                    during our stay.</p>
                <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> is a wild, hostile
                    place, yet it seems to welcome those who revel in natural surroundings. Like a
                    half-submerged egg, its smooth flanks flow into the sea just as the sea flows
                    around it. Confronted by sharp winds and eerie rock formations, I begin to think
                    about the mysterious tribe of Indians called <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>
                    who lived here long ago.</p>
                <p>Who were <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                            >these resourceful people</orgName></rs>? Anthropologists believe they
                    were part of the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">Gabrielino tribe</orgName>, who lived south of
                        <placeName type="city" key="#ci_malibu">Malibu</placeName>. Beyond that,
                    researchers know little about them: only a few of their words and virtually
                    nothing of their culture.</p>
                <p>The sculptured sandstone, hewn by the surf, forms a haunting seascape. Empty
                    abalone shells glitter on the bluffs overlooking the shore; <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>
                    once harvested abalones along this lonely coast. The nearby intertidal zone
                    still teems with the marine life that provided sustenance for <rs><orgName
                            type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the island's
                            hardy inhabitants</orgName></rs>.</p>
                <p>Farther on, <persName type="author" key="#klope">Klope</persName> points out a
                    spot where the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                        >Nicoleños</orgName> chipped a groove under a bluff which seeped fresh
                    water. The groove culminates in a ledge where <rs><orgName
                            type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                            Indians</orgName></rs> could have left a tar-lined basket to collect the
                    dripping water.</p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="6">We continue our search, walking in the shadow of
                                <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                                >these forgotten people</orgName></rs>, exploring the tide pools
                        they once visited. The sandstone seems to retain something of their
                        presence; the rock pools evoke a thousand moods. If only the rocks could
                        speak; if only we could set back the clock a few hundred years.</span></p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="5"/>The otherworldliness of the place strikes me. Something
                    seems unusual here. I notice a dark form imbedded in the sandstone. An oddly
                    shaped rock stares up at me.</p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="5">A magic stone.</span></p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="5">I chip it out of the rocks, handling it
                        carefully.</span></p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="5">The little stone is lens-shaped and stratified. It
                        glares at me like a bloodshot eye, oozing rusty tears onto the sandstone. It
                        seems alive, powerful, yet I feel no sense of foreboding. Instead, I feel
                        strangely at peace. Perhaps I was meant to find it. Maybe the rocks have
                        whispered their secret to me after all.</span></p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="5">Have I discovered the very spot where Nicoleño sorcerers
                        gathered their magic stones? I silently vow to find the answer.</span></p>
                <p><persName type="author" key="#klope">Matt</persName> and I continue walking,
                    thoughtful now. We see evidence of the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName> everywhere.</p>
                <p>I remember that <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George
                        Nidever</persName>, a sea otter hunter, wrote that all but one of <persName
                        type="group" key="#bhagroup">the remaining Nicoleños</persName> were brought
                    to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> in <date
                        when="1835">1835</date>. At the last moment, just before <rs><name
                            type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> was to sail,
                            <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one woman</persName></rs>
                    left the group to search <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                            island</placeName></rs> for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                            key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>, whom she never found. A strong
                    wind forced <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> to
                    sail without <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        woman</persName></rs>. <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Lone
                        Woman</persName>, as she came to be called, was marooned on <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> for <date
                        from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date> before <persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName> finally discovered her and
                    brought her to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>.
                    By that time, <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">her fellow tribe
                        members</persName> had completely disappeared. <rs><persName
                            type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Lone Woman</persName></rs> died a
                    few weeks after her arrival on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                        mainland</placeName> and was buried behind <rs><placeName
                            key="#sbmissioncemetary">the Old Mission</placeName></rs>.</p>
                <p>I shiver a little as the sun arcs lower over the sea. We have reached the west
                    end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> at
                    last, and the weirdly shaped sandstone formations radiate a golden glow. I
                    wonder if this place held any special significance for the <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>.
                    Something about <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                        island</placeName></rs> affects me profoundly.</p>
                <p>Back on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, the
                    stone burns a hole in my pocket. I telephone <persName type="author" key="#jti"
                        >Jan Timbrook</persName>, associate curator of anthropology at the <orgName
                        type="museum" key="#mu_sbmuseum">Santa Barbara Museum of Natural
                        History</orgName> and long-time associate of <persName type="author"
                        key="#thu">Travis Hudson</persName>. She wants to see the stone.</p>
                <p>Feeling unsure about my find, I explain that much time has passed since I have
                    seen a pedigreed magic stone from the museum's collection and that what I have
                    is probably a worthless rock. I remind <persName type="author" key="#jti"
                        >Timbrook</persName> that I'm no geologist, so we should have a geologist
                    examine the rock.</p>
                <p><persName type="author" key="#jti">Timbrook</persName> compares the stone I found
                    on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> with the magic
                    stones in the museum's collection. It's hard to tell them apart. She also
                    unearths a geologist's hypothesis about where <rs><orgName
                            type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                        Indians</orgName></rs> may have found the magic stones. We are astounded;
                    the description is a blueprint for the San Nicolas site.</p>
                <p>I confer with <persName type="author" key="#conti">Kathy Conti</persName>, a
                    staff associate at <rs><orgName type="museum" key="#mu_sbmuseum">the
                            museum</orgName></rs>, and describe my find. She asks if I have read
                        <persName type="author" key="#henshaw">Henshaw</persName>, a linguist who
                    studied Native American languages in the latter part of the nineteenth century.
                    She tells me that in <date when="1885">1885</date>
                    <persName type="author" key="#henshaw">Henshaw</persName> wrote a paper on the
                    Indian vocabularies of this region. The paper, relates <persName type="author"
                        key="#conti">Conti</persName>, contains a tantalizing footnote.</p>
                <p>The footnote is a bombshell. After noting the word <emph>Ha-la-ca't</emph>, the
                    Chumash word for <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas
                        Island</placeName>, <persName type="author" key="#henshaw"
                        >Henshaw</persName> added the cryptic phrase "magicians' stones from
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this island</placeName>." I feel a
                    strange thrill at reading the note <persName type="author" key="#henshaw"
                        >Henshaw</persName> penned <rs><date when="1885">more than a century
                            ago</date></rs>. Another piece of the puzzle falls into place.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, <persName key="#geologist">a geologist</persName> who has worked at
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> offers
                    us another clue. <persName key="#geologist">The geologist</persName> explains
                    that when organic matter becomes trapped in sand with just the right chemical
                    composition, the decaying organic matter attracts iron. Gradually, the layers of
                    sand build, and the iron concentration flattens as the sand hardens into stone.
                    This type of sandstone occurs only on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                        Nicolas Island</placeName>, on the three largest northern <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_northernchi">Channel Islands</placeName> and along a
                    few parts of <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>.
                    But the iron concretions do not always occur in this type of sandstone.
                    Certainly I can't remember finding any iron outcrops on <rs><placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_northernchi">those three other
                        islands</placeName></rs>, nor along <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld"
                        >the mainland coast</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Joining the list of specialists who have become involved in the project is
                        <persName type="author" key="#tbl">Thomas Blackburn</persName>, the
                    anthropologist who accompanied me on the 1981 search for the magic stones on
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara Island</placeName>.
                        <persName type="author" key="#tbl">Blackburn</persName> is enthusiastic and
                    encouraging about my find. Willing to visit <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                        >San Nicolas</placeName> with us to look at the site, he will give us a
                    professional opinion on our findings.</p>
                <p>With the permission of the <orgName type="military" key="#mi_navy"
                    >Navy</orgName>, we assemble another expedition to <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>. The new team consists of
                            <rs><persName type="author" key="#howorth">myself</persName></rs>,
                        <persName type="author" key="#jti">Jan Timbrook</persName>, <persName
                        type="author" key="#tbl">Thomas Blackburn</persName>, <persName
                        type="author" key="#conti">Kathy Conti</persName> and <persName
                        type="author" key="#gal">Glenn Allen</persName>, a professional photographer
                    who will help document our finds. Together we examine the magic stone site and
                    collect new specimens. Considering the evidence we have already unearthed in our
                    studies on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>,
                        <persName type="author" key="#tbl">Blackburn</persName> voices his opinion
                    that this spot was very likely a major source for the sorcerers' magic
                    stones.</p>
                <p>Reviewing the process that led us to solve the mystery of the magic stones
                    prompts us to assess the implications of our team's find. Even though we now
                    know that the magic stones almost certainly came from <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, we are still no closer to
                    understanding the enigmatic <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>. Were they just another
                    lonely tribe, isolated from other groups by the savage sea? The <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>
                    would have been able to paddle over to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                            >the other islands</placeName></rs> or to <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> only during exceptionally calm
                    weather. Certainly they had a precious commodity to trade: stones believed to
                    possess supernatural powers and found nowhere else in this region. The
                    difficulty of transporting such stones from this windswept shore would only
                    enhance their value. <span type="trope" n="5">Or were the <orgName
                            type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                            >Nicoleños</orgName> a cult of shamans who performed sacred rituals on
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that wild, remote
                                island</placeName></rs>?</span></p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="5">We may never know the answers to these questions. Almost
                        all of the evidence has been swept away by the winds of <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, making each find
                        precious, each clue vital to the research. We can only piece together the
                        fragments of history left to us, search for more evidence and hope,
                        eventually, to unlock another mystery of the past.</span></p>
                <p><emph><rs><persName type="author" key="#howorth">The author</persName></rs>
                        and</emph>
                    <orgName type="publication" key="#sbmag">Santa Barbara Magazine</orgName>
                    <emph>deeply appreciate the cooperation of the <orgName type="military"
                            key="#mi_navy">United States Navy</orgName> and <persName type="author"
                            key="#klope">Matt Klope</persName> in helping to make this story
                        possible.</emph></p>
                <p><emph>Naturalist, writer and photographer <persName type="author" key="#howorth"
                            >Peter C. Howorth</persName> specializes in stories relating to the
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        Islands</placeName>.</emph></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
