<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#camag">The Californian
                     Illustrated Magazine</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
               <date when="1892-05"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Holder1892">A Four-in-Hand in Southern
                     California</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="326" to="335"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#cho">Holder, Charles
                     Frederick.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">A FOUR-IN-HAND IN <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal"
                     >SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</placeName>.</title></head>
            <byline>BY <persName type="author" key="#cho">CHARLES FREDERICK
               HOLDER</persName>.</byline>
            <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">LOS ANGELES</placeName>, <rs><placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_la">the Queen City of the South</placeName></rs>, is the
               metropolis of <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern
                  California</placeName>, which, speaking generally, may be said to include that
               tract of country from <placeName type="county" key="#co_sb">Santa Barbara
                  County</placeName> to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mexicanborder">the Mexican
                  line</placeName>, though a broader division would include a much larger area.
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName> was the starting
               point, the center of radiation for many of our coaching and riding trips to
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and beyond, and
               through <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName> to
               the adobes of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_tj">Tia Juana</placeName>. To see
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName>
               effectively the trip should be made by coach, carriage or on horseback. The finest of
               roads extend all over the country, inviting one to the old ranches, cañons, ruins and
               Missions that cannot be seen from car windows.</p>
            <p>It was a mere conceit, perhaps, but remembering that in the olden time pilgrims and
               travelers in this fair country found a Mission at the end of nearly every day's
               journey from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> to
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName> and beyond, we
               determined to emulate the ancient custom and go over the old roads; not on horseback,
               as did the old Californian, but in a four-in-hand, making as nearly as possible a
               Mission every night, seeking the hospitatlity of its secularized walls in reverential
               fashion, as did the traveler of the last century, yet receiving it for obvious
               reasons perchance at the neighboring ruin.</p>
            <p>The plan had not only an essence of romance and novelty to commend it but was within
               the possibilities, the ecclesiastical chain being as follows, beginning at <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>:</p>
            <p><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">Santa Barbara Mission</placeName>, founded in
                  <date when="1786">1786</date>, by coach to the <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_venturamission">Mission of San Buenaventura</placeName> (<date
                  when="1782">1782</date>), thirty miles. From <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_venturamission">Ventura</placeName> to <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_sfern">Mission of San Fernando Ryz [Rey] de Espana</placeName> (<date
                  when="1797">1797</date>), sixty-four miles. From <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_sfern">San Fernando</orgName> to the <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_sgabriel">Mission of San Gabriel Archangel</placeName> (<date when="1771"
                  >1771</date>), via <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>,
               thirty-five miles. From <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sgabriel">San
                  Gabriel</placeName> to <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_stjohn">San Juan
                  Capistrano</placeName> (<date when="1776">1776</date>), thirty miles. From
                     <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_stjohn">San Juan</placeName></rs> to the
               trio of Missions of <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_pala">Pala</placeName>,
                  <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_rc">Rincon</placeName>, and <placeName
                  type="mission" key="#mi_pb">Panba</placeName>, about sixty miles. <placeName
                  type="mission" key="#mi_pala">Pala</placeName> to <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_sl">San Luis Rey de Francia</placeName> (<date when="1798">1798</date>)
               thirty miles. <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sl">San Luis Rey</placeName> to the
                  <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sd">Mission of San Diego de Acala</placeName>
                  (<date when="1769">1769</date>), fifty miles, these figures being approximate and
               in the main correct. Not only could these Missions be reached in a single day's
               journey, but good hotels, often the best, were available. This, with the guarantee of
               perfect roads, good weather, and choice scenery made the trip one of more than
               pleasant anticipation.</p>
            <p>The four-in-hand was not running on time; there were no relays to be met; hence the
               attempt to make a new Mission every night was not directly adhered to, though the
               ecclesiastical route was followed literally as outlined, with many an interesting
               side-trip to cañon, seashore and mountain range.</p>
            <p>Under such inspiration a jolly party bowled toward the <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_sb">Santa Barbara Mission</placeName> one morning, and reined up under
               its ancient walls. The "outfit" was a modernized California coach, the plethoric boot
               packed with hampers of good things; rifles for the black-tailed deer and shotguns for
               the valley quail, while four or five grey and stag hounds following were suggestive
               of coursing, with the hare and coyote as objectives.</p>
            <p>According to a calendar, which <rs><persName key="#woman14">the young lady on the box
                     seat</persName></rs> carried, it was that thoroughly uncomfortable period
               midway the Christmas holidays and the first of March, when, in the East, thaws and
               violent freezes follow each other like avenging Nemeses; yet here nature seemed
               conspiring to impugn the testimony of the records. It was winter as the seasons go,
               but to all intents and purposes midsummer in <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal"
                  >Southern California</placeName>. The breeze was coming in from the Pacific,
               sweeping up the mesa of the old town, bowling over acres of golden poppies, robbing
               the fields of wild forget-me-not of their odor and carrying it over the Mission wall,
               to mingle with the incense of the church. <rs><persName key="#man23">The
                     driver</persName></rs> called it a winter day; yet as he flecked his leaders
               and the horn gave an answering note to the meadow lark on the Mission wall, there was
               not one in the party who really believed that the Ides of March were near at
               hand.</p>
            <p>From the highlands about <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                     Mission</placeName></rs> the first view of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                  >Santa Barbara</placeName> is obtained. The Pacific is before us, stretching away
               to illimitable distance, the crescent-shaped beach facing the south, from which
               reaches back the intervening town with its broad streets lined with palm, pepper,
               magnolia and a wealth of semi-tropical plants and trees. To the north extends the
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_syvalley">Santa Ynez Valley</placeName>, the
               blue ocean on one side, the mountains to the other, while to the south and east deep
               groves of orange, lemon and lime tell of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_montecito"
                  >El Montecito</placeName> and <placeName type="city" key="#ci_car"
                  >Carpinteria</placeName>.</p>
            <p>It was at <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the Mission</placeName></rs>
               that the complete supremacy of man was demonstrated, as, after interviewing
                     <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the courteous
                     Fathers</orgName></rs>, the gentlemen of the party were invited into the
                  <placeName key="#sbgarden">Mission garden</placeName>, while the ladies rested in
               the outer hall, consumed with curiousity. No woman had ever entered <rs><placeName
                     key="#sbgarden">the garden</placeName></rs>, so it was said; and the <persName
                  key="#gardener">old gardener</persName>, gowned and cowled, laughingly told of the
               pretexts adopted by fair visitors, who evidently believed that the grim walls
               concealed some deep mystery.</p>
            <p>The <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">Mission of Santa Barbara</placeName> is
               the only one that has never been out of Franciscan control, and is one of the finest
               in the State, standing as it did a century ago when its bells rang the Angelus, their
               echoes calling the faithful up the deep cañons of <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_santaynezmts">the Santa Ynez.</placeName></rs></p>
            <p>The <persName type="missionfather" key="#father_1">father</persName> told us of the
               ancient splendors of <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                     church</placeName></rs>, of its inception by <persName type="missionfather"
                  key="#jse">Junipero Serra</persName>, its erection in <date when="1786"
                  >1786</date> by <persName type="missionfather" key="#anpa">Father Antonio
                  Paterna</persName>, and detailed its completion in <date when="1794">1794</date>.
               In <date notBefore="1810" notAfter="1812">1810-1812</date>, he said, it was nearly
               destroyed by earthquakes, but was ultimately rebuilt. We entered the old dormitories,
               the workshops once filled with native artisans; stood on the red-tiled roof, and
               looked down upon the broad arched corridors where <rs><orgName type="missionfathers"
                     key="#misfats">the Fathers</orgName></rs> walk and read; strolled among the
               ancient graves of the founders, and tarried in the chapel with its quaint decorations
               while <persName type="missionfather" key="#father_1">the Father</persName> whispered
               the history of the treasures upon the walls. He told us of the struggles of
                     <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the Fathers</orgName></rs>,
               the act of <persName key="#mexgov">the Mexican Governor</persName> in <date
                  when="1827">1827</date> in freeing the Indians, resulting in the destruction of
               the revenues of <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                  Mission</placeName></rs>; of the desecration that accompanied the demand for
               secularization, and various efforts at confiscation. In <date when="1833">1833</date>
               <orgName type="government" key="#gov_sb">the Government</orgName> succeeded, and
                  <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the Missions</orgName> were
               converted into secular curacies. Later <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the Missions</orgName> fell into the hands of
               commissioners, and in <date when="1834">1834</date> the public literally seized the
               Mission lands. We listened to the story of the successive phases of the struggle, of
               the times under <persName key="#jva">Don Juan Alvarado</persName>, who, it was
               claimed, plundered <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the
                  Missions</orgName>, of the attempt in <date when="1840">1840</date> to restore
                  <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the Missions</orgName> to
               power, and of the act of <persName key="#greg">Pope Gregory XVI</persName>, in
                     <rs><date when="1840">the same year</date></rs>, making <placeName type="state"
                  key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, a bishopric, and many other moves, resulting
               to-day in <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the Missions</orgName>
               being, instead of centers of ecclesiastical power, simple parish churches.</p>
            <p><rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">The Mission</placeName></rs> as a whole is
               a delight to the artistic eye. The cell-like rooms, the ancient and worn stone
               pavements, the crude doors with huge iron trappings, the high windows, enormous
               walls, the odor of ancient sanctity, all tend to complete a historical picture of the
               greatest interest. Without, the commanding front with its two towers of stone and
               adobe pierced with arched doors, the lofty façade with its finely cut columns, the
               time-worn statues of the saints above, make the pile at once striking and impressive.
               No little architectural and artistic skill was shown by the builders. Especially does
               the stone fountain in front, with its round basin and quaint carvings, attract the
               eye. Near here was an adobe bath-house, in the façade of which a lion's head was
               carved, from which once poured the clear water of <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_santaynezmts">the Santa Ynez</placeName></rs>. In fact, it is evident
               that the builders of <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                     Mission</placeName></rs> were men of artistic feeling; and the old building
               reflects credit upon their memory.</p>
            <p>But we have tarried too long. A number of dark-eyed penitents are waiting for
                  <persName type="missionfather" key="#father_1">the Father</persName> by the
               confessional, and after handing an ancient nail or spike of <rs><placeName
                     type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the old Mission</placeName></rs> as a memento to
                     <rs><persName key="#woman15">one lady</persName></rs>, a photograph of
                     <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the church</placeName></rs> and some
               flowers from <rs><placeName key="#sbgarden">the garden</placeName></rs> to others,
                  <persName type="missionfather" key="#father_1">the Father</persName> disappears to
               banish the past in the sins of the present generation.</p>
            <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> reminds one of some of
               the Mediterranean resorts, and has been compared to <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_nice">Nice</placeName>; but the comparison is hardly just. The American
               resort has the advantage in climate, is always delightful, winter or summer, but has
               none of the artificial decorations of European places. Its winter mean is 54.29; that
               of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nice">Nice</placeName> 47.88; its summer mean
               67.71; that of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nice">Nice</placeName> 72; its
               difference between winter and summer 13 to 24 of <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_nice">Nice</placeName>. Again, <persName key="#barb">the Santa
                  Barbaran</persName>, or Barbarian of the saints, as <rs><persName key="#woman14"
                     >the young lady on the box-seat</persName></rs> calls our host, tells us that
               the hot, burning winds of <placeName type="region" key="#re_southeurope">Southern
                  Europe</placeName> are never known here,&#8212;that this is the only paradise, the
               real land of <emph>dolce far niente</emph>, the home of the gods.</p>
            <p><rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">The quiet old town</placeName></rs> with its
               fine hotels, long asphalt-paved streets, its miles of gardens, shops for the sale of
               curiousities, its <placeName key="#ci_china">Chinatown</placeName>, where the odor of
               opium and firecrackers mingles with the perfume of flowers, its long wharf, yachts
               and vessels, all offer inducements to tarry. Spanish-town still remains inviolate,
               and we stop at the old <placeName key="#guerrahouse">De la Guerra
               mansion</placeName>, where <persName type="author" key="#rda">Richard H.
                  Dana</persName> witnessed the marriage festival in <date when="1836">1836</date>.
               The family is still in possession, and <rs><placeName key="#guerrahouse">the
                     house,</placeName></rs> with its open court, adobe walls and tiled roof, still
               resembles the description in "Two Years Before the Mast." We buy a
                  <emph>reboso</emph>, an Indian basket, from <persName key="#mexwoman">an old
                  Mexican woman</persName>, some of the stamped-leather articles for which the place
               is famous, half a dozen fiery tamales from another <persName key="#oldwoman">old
                  woman</persName>, for luck, <persName key="#driver">the driver</persName> puts it,
               and are away up the fine, hard road to <rs><placeName key="#patera">La
                     Patera</placeName></rs>, where the Indians buried their stone mortars and
               household gods in the long ago.</p>
            <p>Near here we drive through the fine ranches of <placeName key="#holranch"
                  >Hollister</placeName>, <placeName key="#cooranch">Cooper</placeName> and
                  <placeName key="#storanch">Stowe</placeName>, <rs><placeName key="#holranch">the
                     former</placeName></rs> known as "<rs><placeName key="#holranch">Glen
                     Annie</placeName></rs>." "<rs><placeName key="#cooranch"
                  >Ellwood</placeName></rs>," the <rs><placeName key="#cooranch">Cooper
                     homestead</placeName></rs>, is famous for its olive orchard,&#8212;the largest
               in <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName>, also in
                  <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">America</placeName>, with works the
               perfection of neatness, over which the courteous host takes us. The home is embowered
               with flowers from every clime,&#8212;a garden the year round. From here we pass for
               several miles up the picturesque little cañon by the side of a stream and beneath
               trees that were young in the days of <orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats"
                  >the Franciscan padres</orgName>, and finally at the head of the ravine halt for a
               consideration of the well-filled hampers which the coach is made to disgorge; for
               this is a feature of coaching in <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern
                  California</placeName>,&#8212;the mid-day meal is carried, and a picnic is enjoyed
               in some nook or corner that may meet the eye.</p>
            <p>From <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">this region</placeName></rs>
               endless trips can be made to glens and eyries which, in their beauty, compare
               favorably with those of European resorts: the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_gaviotapass">Gaviota Pass</placeName>, the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_syvalley">Valley of the Santa Ynez</placeName>, <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_santaynezmts">the mountains rising to the
                     east</placeName></rs>, while to the west the ocean is seen, here and
               there,&#8212;a reminder of the extremes that <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                  >Santa Barbara</placeName> affords. Here the lover of the picturesque may spend
               weeks without exhausting its beauty. But we are off again, rolling down to the beach
               with its long line of shining sands, calling to mind our own <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_ne">New England</placeName> shore. But here, <persName key="#sb1">the
                  Santa Barbaran</persName> tells us, the water on this February day has a
               temperature of 61 degrees, about that of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_newport"
                  >Newport</placeName> in June. Tourists are enjoying the surf; the beach is gay
               with riders, while the castellated rocks on the north are dotted with strollers from
               the hotels. Over beyond the blue stretch of water that formed the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">Santa Barbara Channel</placeName> rose the
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, the
                  smallest&#8212;<placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
               Nicolas</placeName>&#8212;having a peculiar interest. In <date when="1836"
                  >1836</date>, we are told, the last <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup"
                  >Indians</persName> were taken away; but as they were leaving <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a squaw</persName></rs> ran back to get
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>,
               and for some reason was left and abandoned. In <date when="1856">1856</date>, twenty
               years later, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nidever</persName> of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> landed there on an
               otter hunt. To his surprise he found huts of whale-bone, and near one <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an old woman</persName></rs>, dressed in a garb
               of skins and feathers. She presented a weird appearance; her language was
               unintelligible. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName> took her
               to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, where every attempt
               was made to find some one who could talk to her, but without success. What became of
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs> no
               one knew. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The "lost
                  woman"</persName></rs> died three months after her rescue, and was buried by
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the Mission
                     Fathers</persName></rs>,&#8212;unknown,&#8212;a mystery of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericans" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a lost
               people</orgName></rs>.</p>
            <p>We could have reached the famous <placeName type="region" key="#re_ojvalley">Ojai
                  Valley</placeName>, thirty-seven miles southeast from <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, through the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_caspass">Casitas Pass</placeName>, but preferred to go by the <placeName
                  type="mission" key="#mi_venturamission">Mission of San Buenaventura</placeName>,
               thirty miles away. This took us through the delightful suburbs of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_montecito">El Montecito</placeName>, with its hot sulphur
               springs far up the cañon, thirteen hundred feet above the sea, where the Indians
               resorted years ago, by nooks and corners of <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_santaynezmts">the Santa Ynez</placeName></rs>, the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_smpass">San Marcos Pass</placeName> and the <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_paintedcave">Painted Cave and
               Rocks</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>The stage road winds along the edge of the shore, now desecrated by the rails of the
                     <rs><orgName type="company" key="#spacrrco">Southern Pacific</orgName></rs>,
               gleaming sandy crescents succeedings one another in endless variety. Through the
               orange groves of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_montecito">Montecito</placeName> we
               enter <placeName type="city" key="#ci_car">Carpinteria</placeName> and its slopes.
               Here a peculiar patch of black ground being plowed by <rs><persName key="#man22">a
                     Mexican</persName></rs> catches the eye of a scientific coacher, who pronounces
               it the site of an ancient Indian village. <rs><persName key="#man22">The
                     Mexican</persName></rs> stops work as the coach slows up, leans upon his plow,
               and while rolling a cigarette sententiously answers the questions thrown at him
               singly and in pairs. After much solicitation he finally enters the adobe near at hand
               and returns with some of the results of his plowing,&#8212;ancient relics turned up
               in former barley seasons: a stone mortar, some abalone shells, the holes stopped with
               asphaltum, the dishes of theIndians, bits of soapstone with perforations, arrowheads
               of flint, and, horror of horrors! a flute that some ancient disciple of the muse has
               manufactured from the arm-bone of possibly a kinsman. It is rudely made, and
               ornamented with bits of pearl from the abalone. Beads of shell and a flint knife
               complete the treasures of this collection.</p>
            <p>"Who were these people?" asks <rs><persName key="#man24">some one on the top of the
                     coach</persName></rs>.</p>
            <p>"No sabe, señor," puffs <persName key="#man22">the Mexican</persName>.</p>
            <p>He might have said that his house was resting on a veritable
                  <emph>kitchen-midden</emph>, a townsite, graveyard, and what not of the early met
               when he sailed up the <placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">Santa Barbara
                  Channel</placeName>
               <date when="1542">nearly three hundred and fifty years ago</date>. He could have said
               that <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#jca">the adventurer</persName></rs> found this
               land the site of many villages, where lived thousands of happy natives. He might have
               told us that his ancestors were of the party, and that they buried <rs><persName
                     type="seaman" key="#jca">the great captain</persName></rs>, <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> over yonder, where he still sleeps. But he said
               nothing, and looked in stolid amazement at the volubility and learning of the
               American whip of the strange vehicle.</p>
            <p>Our road follows the beach through <placeName type="city" key="#ci_car"
                  >Carpinteria</placeName>, past sand-dunes where rich grasses grow, where the faint
               track of sea-birds is seen and the roar of the surf breaks gently on the ear. Beyond
               is the ocean, smooth as glass, with beds of kelp floating lightly,&#8212;the resting
               place of the gull and otter; over beyond the sail of a Chinese junk, the smoke of an
               American steamer. On we pass, the ocean to the right, the green slopes of
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_santaynezmts">the Santa
                  Ynez</placeName></rs> on the other side, through little cañons that reach down to
               the shore, playing a veritable game of hide-and-seek with the gleaming ocean. Now the
               adobe of some Mexican ranges into view, with its barren, well-worn dooryard; its
               ramada and garlands of chilies, red and glaring, its hairless dogs, and dark-eyed
               children who have never seen a red and yellow coach and stare hard and long, silent
               at the melody of the horn.</p>
            <p>Down we plunge into the little arroyo, splashing across the clear brook that, with
               its sparkling sands and dashing trout, comes gurgling down under the arches of elder
               and willow; up the bank with a rush, winding through a grove of live-oaks where the
               tap tap of the woodpecker echoes and the gray squirrel flashes his fox-like tail; out
               into the fields again, the road lined with yellow violets, with crazy-quilts of
               color,&#8212;bluebells, cream cups, daisies, poppies, bluettes and other wild-flowers
               galore, reaching far up to the manzanita and wild myrtle of the upper slopes. From
               the hillside comes the melody of the valley quail, then the roar of its wings. The
               nest of the wood-rat hangs on a limb. The air is filled with insect life dancing
               lightly in the sunbeams.</p>
            <p>And so on we go, over the same road that <persName type="missionfather" key="#jse"
                  >Father Junipero Serra</persName> and <persName key="#fdn">Governor Felipe de
                  Neve</persName> with their guard of sixty soldiers passed when marching to found
               the <placeName key="#presidio">Presidio of Santa Barbara</placeName>
               <rs><date when="1783">one hundred and nine years ago</date></rs>, and with a final
               burst we ride bravely into the old town of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ven"
                  >Ventura</placeName>, cross <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_venriver">the
                     shallow river</placeName></rs> that creeps lazily out from the grove of alders
               and willows, round the big hill that divides the town, and passing the shadows of the
               old <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_ventura">Mission of San
                  Buenaventura</placeName> seek the more material comforts of the inn of the
               roses.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
