A FEMALE CRUSOE. 

AN INDIAN WOMAN EIGHTEEN YEARS ON SAN NICOLAS ISLAND&#8212;HOW SHE LIVED, WAS RESCUED AND DIED.

The San Francisco <emph>Call</emph> of the 7th inst. contains a very interesting account of an Indian woman, who was abandoned on San Nicolas Island, on the coast of Southern California, and spent eighteen years alone there before she was rescued. The main facts are as follows:&#8212;

According to the information I have obtained from the three persons consulted through the interpreter, the history of the Indian woman, the feminine "Crusoe," is as follows:&#8212;She was absent, gathering wood, when the others were taken away, but returned tho the camp or quarters, and finding them deserted, she followed in time to ge taken aboard the schooner, but not finding her children there, one a babe at the breast, and the other about three years old, she plunged into the water and swam ashore in search of them. Unable to find her children, she returned to the beach just in time to see the schooner leaving. She called to those on board, but the only reply she got, and which she remembered to the day of her death, was "<emph>manyana</emph>," pronounced mah-nyah-nah, the Spanish word for "to-morrow," evidently meaning that the schooner would return for her to-morrow or the following day. She threw herself down on the beach and cried long and bitterly. She did not find her children, and supposed they were either taken off by the schooner or carried away and devoured by the wild dogs on the Island. She became very sick and lay a long time without either water or food, but finally recovered and forgot her grief in wandering about the island. She lived on a plant resembling the cabbage, called by Californians "palosanto," and a root known by the name of "coreomite,” also a yellow root, the name of which was not given, and seal or sea-lion blubber. As she had abalone shellfish hooks, and lines made of the sinews of the seal, it is probable she supplied herself with fish from the ocean.

An approaching storm and night coming on, the water being quite shoal about the island and unsafe for a vessel during a high wind, they were compelled to leave for the safety of the schooner, intending to return at a future time for the deserted woman. The vessel ran before the gale, and reached San Pedro Harbor in safety; but circumstances did not permit a return prior to the loss of the schooner in a storm a few weeks later, and the distance to the island was too great to be safely made in small shore boats.

In 1851 Mr. Nidever visited the island otter hunting, and saw signs of a human inhabitant. He saw a footprint made during the previous rainy season, sunken deeply in the now dry, hard ground, and from the size judged it to be that of a woman; also three small circular enclosures about two hundred yards from the beach and about a mile apart. They were about six feet in diameter, made of brush; the walls five feet high, with a small opening on one side. Near these openings were sticks of driftwood stuck in the ground in the form of a tripod supporting dried seal blubber. These inclosures [sic] appeared to be simply wind breaks, affording no protection from the rain. The investigation was pursued no further, as an approaching storm compelled him to leave the Island. 

Mr. Nidever having seen many otter on his first trip to the island made a second during the winter of 1852, and being requested by the Mission Fathers of Santa Barbara had determined to make a careful hunt for the supposed lone inhabitant of the island. The head of the island being better supplied with fresh water closer to the beach and better facilities for fishing, and the altitude such as to command a view of the greater portion of the island and coast, he supposed if alive she would be found there, and made his arrangements accordingly. He and his party found the same or similar enclosures, above mentioned, and the tripod sticks supporting renewed pieces of blubber. In the neighborhood of the huts or wind breaks were seven or eight wild dogs, about the size of a coyote (a small wolf on the coast), and in color black and white. Mr. Nidever said he had seen the same kind of dogs among the Northwestern Indians. They appeared to be very wild. Within half a mile of the head of the island they discovered a basket in the crotch of a bush or small tree, covered with a seal skin, and containing a dress made of shags' skins (the shag is a species of duck on this coast that can neither walk nor fly), carefully folded up, and several square pieces of skins similar to those of which the dress was made; also a rope made of seal sinews, abalone shell fish hooks, bone needles, &amp;c. As it was late and time for them to return to their boat for the night, Mr. Nidever scattered the contents of the basket on the ground, so that upon his return he could judge of the presence or absence of the owner, by finding them gathered up or remaining as he left them. The following four or more days were busily spent in otter hunting, and before the search for the Indian woman was renewed a southeast gale compelled them to seek a more hospitable harbor at the island of San Miguel.

A third voyage by Mr. Nidever and six others, four of whom were Indians from Santa Barbara Mission, was made to the island in July, 1853, and although otter hunting was the main object of the visit the Indian woman was not forgotten. They landed on the northeast side of the island early in the day, and, having selected their camping site, all but one, the cook, started for the head of the island. Near there were observed fresh footprints leading from the beach to the ridge or higher elevation, but were soon lost in the moss covered ground, which ended their search for that day. The following day they were more successful. One of the party, Mr. Brown, discovered the object of their search at a distance, and, cautiously approaching in an opposite direction from the balance of the party, got quite close to her without being observed. She was in one of her pens, or wind breaks, clothed in a garment made of the skins of the shag, without sleeves, low necked, and, as observed when standing up, extending almost to the ankles. She was sitting cross legged, skinning seal blubber with a rude knife, made of a piece of hoop iron driven into a piece of wood.

There was no covering on her head excepting a thick mass of matted hair of a yellowish brown color. [sic] due to the exposure to the sun and air. The hair was short, looking as though the tree [free] ends had rotted off. She would occasionally raise her hand and shade her eyes and look toward the other men on a sandy plain near the beach, whom she evidently saw. There were two or three of the wild dogs around the enclosure, who began to growl as Mr. Brown approached, but ran off at the bidding of their mistress. The balanace of the party were now signalled in order that she might be captured if she attempted to escape. To the surprise of all she made no attempt to get away, but greeted each one as they approached with a bow and a smile, and chatted all the time in a dialect that none of them understood, although the Indians accompanying Mr. Nidever were acquainted with several Indian dialects. She was talking, apparently to herself, from the time Mr. Brown approached within hearing distance until she was made aware of his presence.

With[i]n the enclosure was a fire smouldering, and a large ash pile outside showed that to have been her abiding place for some time. She was very hospitable, preparing a meal from her limited store of roots before named, and serving the party with a grace and bearing that surprised them all. The expression of her face was pleasing, her features were regular and her complexion much fairer and her form more symmetrical than that of the Indian women on the main land, and she is believed to have belonged to a different and superior race, which opinion is strengthened by the fact of Mons. Leon de Cessac, a Frenchman, now engaged in collecting archæological and other specimens of bygone years on the Pacific coast of North and South America for a Paris museum, finding many things on the island (San Nicolas) similar to those previously collected in Oregon, Washington Territory and further north, and unlike anything found on either the main land or the other islands. Also the skulls and other bones of the human skeleton found there are unlike those found in other sections of Southern California. A notable observation is the absence of any evidence of syphilis, a striking contrast with other human bones found in this latitude. I have had the privilege of examining several skulls exhumed from other islands, showing very plainly the ravages of this disease in those who have passed away probably centuries ago.

Near her enclosure were several stakes, between which was stretched a rope made of seal sinews, supporting seal and sea elephant blubber. And further on were three huts made of whale's ribs, covered with brush, but giving no evidence of having been lately occupied. By signs and other means of communication she was made aware that they wanted her to accompany them, and, without any apparent hesitation, she made ready to follow. She filled a basket&#8212;such as were common among the Indians of this coast for packing on their backs&#8212;with provisions, fishing tackle and other articles, and, taking it on one arm and a firebrand in the other hand, she followed the company.

In her course to where the schooner lay at anchor they found a beautiful spring of water issuing from the bank above the beach, under a shelving rock. The cracks or fissures in this rock were stuck full of bones and there were other evidences of an encampment of the lone inhabitant of the island. These bones were used for nourishment, obtained by sucking; they were dried and resucked many times, showing that occasionally she was put upon short rations, but at the time of her discovery appeared to have an abundance, such as it was. She retained all her teeth, but they were worn low, supposed to be due to her chewing tough and solid articles of food. Her age appeared to be about fifty years.

Further on was another spring near the beach, under the bank. Here she indicated a desire to bathe, and was permitted to do so by the balance of the party retiring out of sight. After her bath she joined the others and went direct to the shore boat, and thence to the schooner. She was prevailed upon to abandon her firebrand and seal blubber before leaving the beach. Going aboard the schooner, she went directly to the stove and warmed herself, indicating that she knew what the stove was for. She ate heartily of the food of the crew, appeared to enjoy it and it agreed with her. Mr. Brown made her a skirt of ticking, with which and a sailor's cotton shirt and a black necktie, her dress was complete. She assisted in making her dress, but could not see to thread her needle. Her sewing was quite rude. She appeared much pleased with her new dress.

The following day she went ashore with the men, who made a seperate shelter for her, which she occupied about a month, the time spent on the island otter hunting. She was quite industrious, carrying wood and water without being asked. She appeared contented and happy, frequently singing and chattering to herself. The men could not understand what she said, nor she they, but Mr. Nidever said it was truly wonderful how she could converse with them by signs. She occupied a portion of her time in making water vessels of grass and asphaltum, a substance plentiful both on the island and shore of the main land. The grass was plaited into a shape resembling a demijohn, but wider at the top, and lined with asphaltum. She would put in several small pieces of the last mentioned substance and then drop on them small stones or pebbles about the size of huled walnuts, heated sufficiently to melt the asphaltum, and, grasping the neck with both hand, the lower end on the ground, give it a rapid rotary motion for several minutes, and then empty the stones on the ground. The vessels had a continuous coating on the inside, and are reported to have been water tight, the lining even resisting the heat of the sun when covered with water. She had both stone and earthen vessels in which to boil water and cook if desired. To procure seal blubber she could kill the seals with a club when on land sunning themselves or snare them wiht her sinewy ropes. She obtained fire by rubbing two dry sticks together. One of them, partly flat, had a groove along its entire length, the other was pointed and fitted into the groove, in which it was rubbed rapidly backward and forward until it burned.

As usual a storm compelled the party to leave the island, and, embarking with their island queen, soon found themselves at sea in a storm. She made signs that she could stop the storm, and, obtaining permission, she knelt on the deck facing the quarter whence the wind came and commenced muttering something supposed to be a prayer. She soon got up, but continued the prayer at intervals during the day, apparently without fear, and when the wind began to abate she turned to her fellow voyagers and with a smile made signs that her prayers had been answered.

When they came in sight of Santa Cruz Island, off this coast, she told them by signs that it was an island, and indicated from there how she had seen from her island ships pass up and down, but never land. Also that she had seen the Nidever party the previous day to her discovery as they passed to the head of the island. She was afraid to make herself known until she knew there was no danger to her person. There were many places of concealment on the island and unless taken unawares she would have been hard to find.

As she was about to land at Santa Barbara an ox team passed, which so delighted her that she talked, laughed, danced and gesticulated, and before that excitement ended a man on horseback approached that gave her even more pleasure than the appearance of the ox team.  At first it was supposed that she thought the man and horse constituted one animal, but if so the mistake was soon corrected, for on land she went up to the horse and carefully examined it. The examination gave her additional pleasure; she would turn to her late companions, and, laughing, request them to look at the horse. She straddled the thumb of the left hand by the two forefingers of the right, and moved them to represent the horse and rider as they passed along the beach.

She was taken to the house of Mr. Nidever, where she became the centre of attraction. The Mission Fathers took a great interest in her, sending to Los Angeles and other places, hoping to find some one who could converse with her, but failed. Even the Pepimaros Indians, who were said to have had an acquaintance with the Indians on the island, could not understand her.

The family of Mr. Nidever became very much attached to her, and although the captain of the brig Fremont offered largely for the privilege of taking her to San Francisco and placing her on exhibition, it was refused; also, an offer of $1,000 from another party for a like purpose was refused.

Many people called on her and she received them kindly, but the afternoon was her favorite time for receiving calls, when she would put on her shag-skin dress and entertain her callers with a song-dance. She cared nothing for money, giving it to the children when given to her. She did not wish to sleep in a bed, and when in bed, did not desire bed covering but was careful not to expose her person. Her manners were not rude, and in many things she was much more refined than many who enjoyed civilized privileges; yet in many things she was very much like a child. She wanted everything she saw that appeared pleasant to the eye or taste, and if fruit was withheld from her she would plead for it in such a child-like manner that it was hard to refuse her.

When found she was in excellent physical condition, strong and active; but the eating of fruit and vegetables brought on a diarrhœa or dysentery in about three weeks after she landed, and that, in connection with an injury to the spine, received by falling from a porch, terminated her life four weeks later, or seven weeks from the time she landed. During her sickness she reluctantly permitted the kind hostess to dress her in flannel underclothes, and took her bed under proper covering, but positively refused to return to her former plain diet, as was proposed by some of those who called to see her. Her dress of shag skins, basket and trinkets were given to Father Gonzalez, of the Mission, who, it is said, sent them to Rome.