<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#aevening">Albany Evening
                     Journal</orgName></title>
               <editor><persName type="author" key="#hey">Henry James Ten Eyck</persName></editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume">49</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">14830</biblScope>
               <date when="1879-02-14"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_al">Albany</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ny">New York</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#AlbanyEveningJournal1879">A Feminine Crusoe. Alone on
                     a Dreary Desert Island for Eighteen Years</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="1"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">A
                           FEMININE CRUSOE</persName></rs>.</hi></title>
               <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">Alone on a <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                           >Dreary Desert Island</placeName></rs> for <rs><date notBefore="1835"
                           notAfter="1853">Eighteen Years</date></rs>.</hi></title></head>
            <byline>From the <rs><title type="article" key="#SanFranciscoChronicle1879">San
                     Francisco Chronicle</title></rs>. </byline>
            <p>The romance of "Robinson Crusoe," woven so ingeniously by the imaginative <persName
                  type="author" key="#dde">De Foe</persName> from the slender thread of fact
               afforded by the narrative of <persName type="seaman" key="#ase">Alexander
                  Selkirk</persName>, who for over four years was sole human inhabitant of the
               lonely island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_jf">Juan Fernandez</placeName>,
               possesses a perennial interest. It appeals to the sympathies of the reader, and by
               the fascination of its style almost persuades him to accept it as veritable history.
                  <span type="trope" n="8">The story which we are about to relate, though true in
                  every particular, possesses a remarkable similarity in many of its incidents to
                  the tale told by <persName type="author" key="#dde">De Foe</persName>, and affords
                  another illustration of the adage that "truth is stranger than fiction."</span> In
               the spring of <date when="1835">1835</date> the schooner <foreign xml:lang="sp"><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es Nada</name></foreign>, built at
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName>, was chartered by
                  <persName type="investor" key="#lbu">Lewis T. Burton</persName> and <persName
                  type="investor" key="#isp">Isaac J. Sparks</persName> for an otter-hunting
               expedition from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> to the
               coast of <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja">Lower California</placeName>.
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The schooner</name></rs> sailed in
               May, but the trip not proving so successful as was anticipated, she returned as far
               north as <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>, where she
               remained at anchor during a portion of the month of August of the same year. It being
               known that the small island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName>, situated about seventy miles southwest of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> and a little further southeast from
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, was inhabited by
                  <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">a number of Indians</persName>, the
                  <foreign xml:lang="sp"><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es
                  Nada</name></foreign> was despatched to remove them to <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_mld">the main land</placeName>. <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup"
                  >Nineteen men, women and children</persName> were taken on board <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the schooner</name></rs>, which was preparing
               to depart, when <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one of the Indian
                     mothers</persName></rs> discovered that two of <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her offspring</persName></rs> had been
               forgotten and left on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs>. <span type="trope" n="9">With true maternal devotion she
                  sprang into the water and swam to the shore in search of <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the missing children</persName></rs>,
                  one of which was three years of age and the other an infant unable to walk.</span>
               Her hurried search was unavailing, and, abandoning all hope of finding <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the babes</persName></rs>, she returned to
               the beach just in time to see <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                     schooner</name></rs> sailing away with all her friends on board. She called
               frantically for some one to take her to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada"
                     >the vessel</name></rs>, but received no reply but one sad word, <foreign
                  xml:lang="sp"><emph>man yana</emph></foreign> (to morrow), which never after
               ceased to ring in her ear and was repeated on her dying bed.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4"><rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The
                        schooner</name></rs> never went back to <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, which was not again visited until
                     <date when="1853">1851</date>, when <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                     >George Nidever</persName>, another hunter, stopped there for a few days. He
                  was not previously aware that the place was inhabited, but on this occasion he
                  became convinced that such was the case. He noticed three small circular
                  inclosures about 200 yards from the beach and about a mile apart. They were about
                  six feet in diameter, and made of brush, the walls five feet high, with a small
                  opening on one side. Near these openings were sticks of drift wood stuck in the
                  ground in the form of a tripod, supporting dried seal blubber. These inclosures
                  appeared to be simply wind breaks, affording no protection from the rain. He also
                  saw a mysterious footprint, and judged it to be that of a woman from its small
                  size and arched centre. An approaching storm obliged <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_nidever">Nidever's vessel</name></rs> to leave <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> without allowing him
                  to pursue his investigations any further.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4"><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr.
                     Nidever</persName> having seen many otter on his first trip to <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, made a second druing
                  the winter of <date when="1852">1852</date>, and being requested by the
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">Mission
                        Fathers of Santa Barbara</persName></rs>, he and <persName type="group"
                     key="#tje; #nativeamericans">a party</persName> determined to make a careful
                  hunt for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the supposed lone
                        inhabitant</persName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>. Within half a mile of the head of <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> they discovered a
                  basket in the crotch of a bush or small tree, covered with a sealskin, and
                  containing a dress made of shag's skins&#8212;a sea fowl common in that
                  section&#8212;carefully folded up, and several square pieces of skins similar to
                  those of which the dress was made, also, a rope made of seal sinews, abalone shell
                  fish-hooks, bone needles, etc. As it was late, and time for them to return to
                  their boat for the night, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr.
                     Nidever</persName> scattered the contents of the basket on the ground, so that
                  upon his return he could judge of the presence or absence of <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the owner</persName></rs> by finding them
                  gathered up or remaining as he left them. The following four or more days were
                  spent in otter hunting, and before the search for <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the Indian woman</persName></rs> was renewed
                  a southeast gale compelled them to seek a more hospital [hospitable] harbor at the
                  island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4"> A third expedition, made to <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> in <date when="1853">1853</date>, by
                     <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName>, <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charles Brown</persName> and <persName
                     type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">four Indians</persName> from
                  the <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">Santa Barbara Mission</placeName>, was
                  more successful. On the day after landing, <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                        key="#cdi">Mr. Brown</persName></rs> discovered the object of their search
                  at a distance, and cautiously approaching in an opposite direction from the
                  remainder of the party, got quite close to her without being observed. She was in
                  one of her pens or wind breaks, clothed in a garment made of the skins of the
                  shag, without sleeves, low-necked, and, as observed when standing up, extending
                  almost to the ankles. She was sitting cross-legged, skinning seal blubber with a
                  rude knife made of a piece of hoop iron driven into a piece of wood. There was no
                  covering on her head excepting a thick mass of matted hair of a yellowish brown
                  color, due to the exposure to the sun and air. The hair was short, looking as
                  though the free ends had rotted off. She would occasionally raise her hand and
                  shade her eyes and look toward <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the other men</persName></rs> on
                  a sandy plain near the beach, whom she evidently saw. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">The balance of the
                        party</persName></rs> were now signaled in order that she might be captured
                  if she attempted to escape. </span>
               <span type="trope" n="3">To the surprise of all she made no attempt to get away, but
                  greeted each one as they approached with a bow and a smile, and chattered all the
                  time in a dialect none of them understood, although <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>
                  accompanying <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName> were
                  acquainted with several Indian dialects.</span> She was talking apparently to
               herself form the time <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Mr.
                     Brown</persName></rs> approached in hearing distance until she was made aware
               of his presence. <span type="trope" n="3">The expression of her face was pleasing,
                  her features were regular, and her complexion much fairer and her form more
                  symmetrical that that of the Indian women on the main land; and she is believed to
                  have belonged to <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a different and superior
                  race</orgName></rs>.</span> By signs and other means of communication she was made
               aware that they wanted her to accompany them, and without any apparent hesitation she
               made ready to follow. In their course to where <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_nidever">the schooner</name></rs> lay at anchor they found a beautiful
               spring of water issuing from the bank above the beach, under a shelving rock. The
               cracks or fissures in the rock were stuck full of bones, and there were other
               evidences of an encampment of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone
                     inhabitant</persName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. These bones were used for nourishment obtained by
               sucking; they were dried and resucked many times, showing that occasionally she was
               put upon short rations, but at the time of her discovery appeared to have an
               abundance, such as it was. She retained all her teeth, but they were worn low,
               supposed to be due to her chewing tough and solid articles of food. Her age appeared
               to be about fifty years. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Mr.
                     Brown</persName></rs> made her a skirt of ticking, with which, and a sailor's
               cotton shirt and a black necktie, her dress was complete.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1">A severe storm arose, and embarking with <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">their Island Queen</persName></rs>,
                     <persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                     >the men</persName> soon found themselves at sea in a storm. She made signs
                  that she could stop the storm, and obtaining permission she knelt on the deck
                  facing the quarter whence the wind came and commenced muttering something supposed
                  to be a prayer. She soon got up, but continured the prayer at intervals during the
                  day, apparently without fear, and when the wind began to abate she turned to her
                  fellow-voyagers, and with a smile, made signs that her prayers had been answered.
               </span> She was taken to the <placeName key="#nideverhouse">house of Mr.
                  Nidever</placeName>, in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, where she became the centre of attraction.</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The Mission
                     Fathers</persName></rs> took a great interest in her, sending to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName> and other places, hoping to find
               some one who could converse with her, but failed. Even the <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_pepimaros">Pepimaros Indians</orgName>,
               who were said to have had an acquaintance with the <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Indians on the
                     island</orgName></rs>, could not understand her. <rs><persName type="seaman"
                     key="#tru">Two offers</persName></rs>, one of $1,000, for the privilege of
               taking her to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, were
               refused by <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName>. When
               found she was in excellent physical condition, strong and active, but the eating of
               fruit and vegetables brought on a sickness, which, in connection with an injury to
               the spine received by falling from a porch, terminated her life four weeks later, or
               seven weeks from the time she landed. Her dress of shag skins, basket and trinkets
               were given to <persName type="missionfather" key="#jru">Father Gonzalez</persName>,
               of <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the Mission</orgName>, who, it is said, sent
               them to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>. Messrs. <persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName> and <rs><persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> are still living, and it
               is on their authority that the foregoing strange narrative is given to the readers of
               the <rs><title type="article" key="#SanFranciscoChronicle1879"
                     ><emph>Chronicle</emph></title></rs>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
