<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#morningcall">The Morning
                     Call</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">74</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">73</biblScope>
               <date when="1893-07-07"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#TheMorningCall1893">A Stricken Isle. Earthquake Shocks
                     San Nicolas. Gales and Tidal Waves. Terrible Experience of Fishermen Off the
                     Coast of Southern California</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="1"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">A STRICKEN
                        ISLE</placeName></rs>.</title>
               <title type="sub">Earthquake Shocks on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName>.</title>
               <title type="sub">GALES AND TIDAL WAVES.</title>
               <title type="sub">Terrible Experience of Fishermen Off <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_socalcoast">the Coast of Southern
               California</placeName>.</title></head>
            <byline>Special to <orgName type="publication" key="#morningcall">THE MORNING
                  CALL</orgName>.</byline>
            <dateline><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">SAN DIEGO</placeName>, <date
                  when="1893-07-06">July 6</date>.&#8212;</dateline>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The steam-schooner <name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">Jennie
                     Griffin</name> arrived this morning from <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >San Nicolas Island</placeName>. <persName type="seaman" key="#jmu">Captain
                     Mullett</persName> and crew tell of strange and wonderful meteorological
                  disturbances on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">The
                        schooner</name></rs> is engaged in the crawfish business for <orgName
                     type="company" key="#paccoastfishing">the Pacific Coast Fishing and Packing
                     Company</orgName> of <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">this
                        city</placeName></rs>, and a couple of weeks ago left a gang of eight men on
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> to prosecute the
                  work.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The <name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">Jennie Griffin</name>
                  arrived there last Sunday to load the catch for this point, but received news
                  instead which astounded the whole party, and caused <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#jmu">Captain Mullett</persName> to take on the gang from shore and leave
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> as
                  quickly as he could.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The men reported that <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName>
                  </rs> had been visited by a tremendous gale of wind which raised the sea in the
                  nature of a tidal wave, completely filling with sand the only harbor of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, which
                  is marked "<placeName type="region" key="#re_coralharbor">Coral
                  harbor</placeName>" on the Government charts. <persName type="seaman" key="#jmu"
                     >Captain Mullett</persName> was dumfounded to find a stretch of sand where two
                  weeks ago he rode at anchor in <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">his
                        schooner</name></rs>. A big crawfish car holding about five tons of fish,
                  which was moored in the bay, was half-covered with sand and the fish were
                  lost.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The foreman on shore kept a logbook, which was seen by
                     <orgName type="publication" key="#morningcall">THE CALL</orgName>
                  correspondent. In it is recorded everything occurring from the date of the arrival
                  of the men until <date when="1893-07-02">July 2</date>. The weather for several
                  days was most remarkable. Everything seemed to foretell disaster. Seabirds and
                  other living things acted strangely. On <date when="1893-06-26">June 26</date> at
                  11 A. M. a heavy earthquake was experienced on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. The oscillation was from east to
                  west, the shocks being of several seconds' duration. <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_hawaiian">The Kanakas</orgName> and one
                  negro [sic] in a separate camp were scared almost to death and became almost
                  crazy, running up and down in terror.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The weather was then very foggy with stifling heat. A
                  peculiar light covered the sea in spite of the fog, adding a weird aspect to the
                  scene. So far as the men could tell the fog centered about <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. Next day a tremendous
                  wind-storm arose, causing great damage. No attempt was made by the men to work.
                  All expected <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                  to sink in the sea at any moment.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">On <date when="1893-06-26" cert="high">June</date>
               </span><supplied reason="damanged"><span type="trope" n="5"
                  >[...]</span></supplied><span type="trope" n="5"> earthquake </span><supplied
                  reason="damanged"><span type="trope" n="5">[...]</span></supplied><span
                  type="trope" n="5"> was heavy </span><supplied reason="damanged"><span
                     type="trope" n="5">[...]</span></supplied>
               <span type="trope" n="5">over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        is</placeName></rs></span><supplied reason="damanged"><span type="trope"
                     n="5">[...]</span></supplied>
               <span type="trope" n="5">men obser</span><supplied reason="damanged"><span
                     type="trope" n="5">[...]</span></supplied><span type="trope" n="5"> a few
                  yard</span><supplied reason="damanged"><span type="trope" n="5"
                  >[...]</span></supplied><span type="trope" n="5"> transparency of </span><supplied
                  reason="damanged"><span type="trope" n="5">[...]</span></supplied>
               <span type="trope" n="5">see for quite a distance, and <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#jmu">Captain Mullett</persName> thinks the steamer's compasses were
                  affected by the strange occurrences and the accompanying electrical disturbance.
                  The <name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">Jennie Griffin</name> was in the
                  neighborhood in the fog and her two compasses would not work together while near
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. The
                  men could not make out the name of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">the
                        steamer</name></rs>, which finally stood away from <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">Still another distinct shock of earthquake was felt at noon
                  on <date when="1893-06-30">June 30</date>, the vibrations being from east to west.
                  This completed the demoralization of the camp, and the logbook says the men became
                  howling savages.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">A remarkable incident connected with the phenomena is that
                  crawfish and other fish died from some unknown cause, probably electricity, as the
                  men remembered afterward seeing lights on the water at night.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">When the <name type="ship" key="#sh_jennie">Jennie
                     Griffin</name> hove in sight the men waded out to meet the small boats,
                  refusing to return to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        land</placeName></rs>. <persName type="seman" key="#jmu">Captain
                     Mullett</persName> refused to believe their story, but was finally compelled to
                  accept the foreman's word. All the men were taken on board <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_jennie">the schooner</name></rs>, which hastily sailed
               away.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5"><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>
                  is the most westerly of the group known as <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >the Santa Barbara Islands</placeName> and is about 150 miles from <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>. <rs><date when="1868"
                        >Twenty-five years ago</date></rs> it was covered with grass, which afforded
                  pasture for thousands of sheep, whose owner lived there in a fine residence. A
                  strange transformation has been going since then.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5"> It is now a windy, barren, sandy waste, where but a few
                  hundred sheep without a shepherd eke out a miserable existence. It is but eight
                  miles long and four wide, but wherever one digs can be found human bones and
                  skulls. In the distant past it must have been rather densely populated, or may
                  have been the site of a burial-ground or a battle-field.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5"><rs><date when="1853">Some fifty years</date></rs> ago
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the last
                     inhabitant</persName></rs> was found in the person of a woman. <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">A Santa Barbara otter-hunter</persName></rs>
                  named Nidever found her and took her to his home, where she died shortly after
                  without being able to make any one understand her language. She was found in a
                  cave, subsisting on fish caught with hooks made of abalone shells. Her discovery
                  caused considerable interest in the scientific world at the time.</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
