<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper" key="#pdcleve">Plain Dealer</title>
               <editor/>
               <publisher/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="63rd year"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="45"/>
               <date when="1904-02-14"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_cl">Cleveland</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#oh">Ohio</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#ClevelandPlainDealer1904">Relics of a Vanished Race.
                     Found on a Lonely Island Off California</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="23"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">RELICS OF <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">A VANISHED RACE</orgName></rs></title>
               <title type="sub">Found on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">a Lonely
                        Island</placeName></rs> Off <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                     >California</placeName>.</title></head>
            <p>Students of anthropology and ethnology are manifesting a lively interest in the
               explorations now being conducted on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                  islands</placeName>, off the coast of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName>, by some twenty-five young men of the <orgName
                  type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian institution</orgName> and <orgName
                  type="institution" key="#stanford">Leland Stanford university</orgName> [sic]. The
               exploration expedition has been at work several weeks, and the news now comes from
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> that the
               field has been found so interesting that the exploration will continue until
                     <rs><date notBefore="1904-03" notAfter="1904-05">early
               spring</date></rs>&#8212;probably longer. <rs><date when="1894">Ten years
                  ago</date></rs> the late <persName key="#hearst">Senator Hearst</persName> of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> offered to sustain
               an expedition of scientists, who should spend a summer season in exploring <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> and <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> islands, and to give the results of their
               finds to the <rs><orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucb">State university at
                     Berk[e]ley</orgName></rs>, in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName>; but there arose such a feeling of jealousy among several
               of the leaders in the proposed expedition that <rs><persName key="#hearst">the
                     senator</persName></rs> withdrew his offer.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                     Islands</placeName> constitute California's only archipelago, with the possible
                  exception of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_far">rocky and scanty Farallone
                     islands</placeName>. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">The
                        former</placeName></rs> have been the objects of romantic legends, curiosity
                  and mystery for a generation or more. Notwithstanding all <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> are within
                  eighty-two miles of the <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">California
                     shore</placeName>, they are solitary and unfrequented, and years roll by
                  without visits to them of more than twenty people annually. Each island has its
                  own particular, strange, uncanny traditions, and each has countless traces of
                  occupation by thousands of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                        >Indians</orgName></rs>.</span><span type="trope" n="6">When <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#jca">Juan Rodriquez Cabrillo</persName>, the Portuguese
                  navigator, sailed up the coast of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                     >California</placeName>, in <date when="1542">1542</date>, he stopped for a day
                  or two at each of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                     islands</placeName>, and his records bear testimony that on the Islands of
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >San Nicolas</placeName> there was "<rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">a
                        vigorous and lusty race of natives</orgName></rs>, who thronged the shores
                  of the little bays and headlands" and gazed in mute wonder at <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_salvador; #sh_lavictoria">the white sailed
                     ships</name></rs> of <rs><persName type="group" key="#jca; #bfe">the
                        navigators</persName></rs>. Today <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                        >the islands</placeName></rs> stand as they did over 350 years ago, but
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        natives</orgName></rs> are only a memory, represented by immense quantities
                  of stone implements, barrels of fine wampum and literal car loads of human
                  bones.</span><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas island</placeName>,
               which lies eighty miles immediately opposite the little city of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_ven">San Buenaventura</placeName> (recently called by the
               more modern and easy name of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ven"
               >Ventura</placeName>), is the most interesting of all the <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_chi">Channel islands</placeName> from many points of view. As far back as
               the memory of any person in <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">southern
                  California</placeName> runs, hundreds of white skeletons have dotted the valleys
               and hillsides. <span type="trope" n="5">Strange utensils of serpentine, sandstone and
                  steatite are found there among the human bones, and <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">its
                        inhabitants</orgName></rs> have a history so curious that it is difficult of
                  comprehension.</span></p>
            <p>Nothing more desolate than the general appearance of <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> can be imagined. As far as the eye can
               trace there are innumerable circular depressions, showing where primitive dwellings
               once stood. Not a vestige remains of the materials used in the construction of these
               rancherias. Hundreds of shell mounds are scattered about, and are found to consist of
               astonishing numbers of mollusks, the bones of every species of fish found in the
               channel, skeletons of seals, sea elephants, whales, sea otter, the island fox and
               various aquatic birds. Without question these animals were used for food by the
               tribes that once thronged these boundaries. There are also numerous canine skeletons,
               several of which indicate a species of bull terrier. Judging from the immense
               quantities of dead mollusks everywhere there must have been a time when
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> supported
               a luxuriant vegetation. Of all this verdure nothing is seen today but a few stunted
               thorn bushes, and now and then a cactus forlornly reaching its grotesque arms out of
               the interminable sweeps of sand.</p>
            <p>An examination of some of the mounds disclosed all sorts of curious utensils, stone
               cooking pots, water ollas, mortars, pestles, drills, bone needles and fishhooks,
               shell beads, charm stones, pipes, cups and a few arrow heads, spear points and swords
               made of bone. <span type="trope" n="3">The absence of many weapons proves the
                  peaceful attributes of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the islanders</orgName></rs>. Small imitations
                  of boats and fishes carved from crystallized talc and serpentine also show a
                  rudimentary knowledge of the art of sculpture.</span> In many places conical piles
               of small black pebbles contrast oddly with white sand. In some instances these
               pebbles were closely packed in abalone shells. No trace is seen of the "brush pens,"
               in which the <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">lone woman of San
                     Nicolas</persName></rs>
               <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">for years</date></rs> found her only shelter from the
               cutting wind and sand. Nature, ever mindful of the individual, long singe merged the
               superhuman efforts of this courageous life into the universal fate of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an entire
                     race</orgName></rs>. Indeed, <span type="trope" n="6">every foot of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this strange
                     island</placeName></rs> is eloquent of the extinction of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an almost unheard of
                        people</orgName></rs>.</span></p>
            <byline>&#8212;<title type="article" key="#TheBrooklynDailyEagle1904">Brooklyn
                  Eagle</title>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
