<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <settlement><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName><placeName
                        type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></settlement>
                  <repository key="#braun">Braun Research Library</repository>
                  <idno type="Bod">MS 770</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <msItem>
                     <author><persName type="author" key="#jte">Terry, James</persName></author>
                     <title key="#Terry1882">Reminiscences of George Nidever and Charles Brown of
                        the Early History of Santa Barbara and the Finding of the Woman (Indian) of
                        San Nicolas Island.</title>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc/>
               </physDesc>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <availability>
                        <p>Courtesy of the Braun Research Library, Autry National Center of the
                           American West, Los Angeles; Manuscript Collection, MS. 770.</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="manuscript">
            <head><title type="main">Reminiscences of <hi rend="underline"><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nidever</persName></hi> and <hi
                     rend="underline"><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charles
                           Brown</persName></rs></hi> of the Early History of <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and the Fin[d]ing of <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the Woman</persName></rs> (<rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                     >Indian</orgName></rs>) on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas
                     Island</placeName>.</title></head>
            <div type="interview1">
               <p>Q. What is your name?</p>
               <p>A. My name is <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nidever</persName>.
                  I was born in the St<del rend="strikethrough">a</del>te of <placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_tn">Tennessee</placeName> in <date when="1802">1802</date>.</p>
               <p>Q. How old were you when you left home?</p>
               <p>A. I was a boy, quite small, not more than 10 years old, when I left <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_tn">Tennessee</placeName> and went to <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ar">Arkansas</placeName> and <placeName type="country"
                     key="#re_upcal">Mexico</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Q. What did you do when you were in <placeName type="state" key="#st_ar"
                     >Arkansas</placeName> and <placeName type="country" key="#re_upcal"
                     >Mexico</placeName>?</p>
               <p>A. <del rend="strikethrough">Folled</del>Followed hunting. Traveled about from the
                  time I was 18 years old and have been traveling ever since. I went to <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_tx">Texas</placeName> and came back to <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ar">Arkansas</placeName>. There was a company coming to
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_rockies">the Rocky Mts.</placeName> in <date
                     when="1830">1830</date>. We traveled in <placeName type="state" key="#st_ar"
                     >Arkansas</placeName>, given by treaty to the <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_cherokee">Cherokee Indians</orgName>. I
                  had to leave.</p>
               <p>Q. What was your father's occupation?</p>
               <p>A. Farmer</p>
               <p>Q. That means hunter in those days?</p>
               <p>A. Yes - small farmer - not like they do now.</p>
               <p>Q. What started you to come to <placeName type="region" key="#re_local"
                     >California</placeName>?</p>
               <p>A. It was a company coming to <placeName type="region" key="#re_rockies">the Rocky
                     Mountains</placeName> for two years to trap beaver. I was a good shot and they
                  wanted me to come out.</p>
               <p>Q. What did you come out here to do?</p>
               <p>A. The company were nearly all killed. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#jwa"
                     >Capt. Walker</persName> was coming across and they did not make much and said
                  they were coming to <placeName type="region" key="#re_local"
                     >California</placeName>. Well I came with them.</p>
               <p>Q. How many where there in the company?</p>
               <p>A. Thirty-six when they came here.</p>
               <p>Q. How many started? Ans. 48.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">A</del>Q. What become [sic] of the rest? Ans. Some
                  stopped.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you meet any Indians on the way? Ans. Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you have any trouble with them?</p>
               <p>A. We were troubled all the while with them till we came to <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_local">California</placeName>. There was some trouble
                  here but not with the Indians, but Indians from the north.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you have any fights with them? Ans. Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you shoot at them? Ans. Yes, we killed 34 in one place.</p>
               <p>Q. What tribe? Ans. <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_piutes"
                     >Piutes</orgName>.</p>
               <p>Q. Did they kill any of your folks? Ans. No, they did not.</p>
               <p>Q. You had guns and they had bows and arrows? Ans. Yes, and spades.</p>
               <p>Q. What year was that when you came here?</p>
               <p>A. <date when="1834">1834</date>. Came into <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo"
                     >Monterey</placeName> first. Struck <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> there at <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sjo">St. Joseph</placeName>. <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName> was the capital. Struck <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> at a place
                  called <placeName type="city" key="#ci_gil">Gilroy</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Q. Packed, did you? Ans. Yes.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">A</del>Q. Did you walk a good deal of the way? Ans. Yes,
                  we had to kill our meat all the way.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you live on meat all the way? Ans. Nothing but meat. Did not take any
                  flour.</p>
               <p>Q. Was there any time when you could not find any game?</p>
               <p>A. There was a time when we could not find much, but always killed something.</p>
               <p>Q. What did you kill - what kind of meat? Ans. Buffalo, elk, deer, bear.</p>
               <p>Q. How long were you coming from <placeName type="state" key="#st_tn"
                     >Tennessee</placeName> here?</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">Z</del>A. I left about 10 years old. It [I] got here in
                     <date when="1834">'34</date> - several years on the way. Sometimes we would be
                  stopped 2 or 3 years in a place trapping; catched (cached?) a good many beaver but
                  lost them by the Ind<del rend="strikethrough">a</del>ians.</p>
               <p>Q. What did they do? Ans. Took the skins. They were worth $4.00 a lb.</p>
               <p>Q. When you got here did you find any Americans?</p>
               <p>A. Some Americans in <date when="1834">1834</date>, about 50 or 60 in <placeName
                     type="country" key="#re_upcal">the country</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Q. How many Indians did you find here? Ans. More than white men.</p>
               <p>Q. Ask him if he remembers anything about <rs><orgName type="mission"
                        key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the old Missions</orgName></rs>. Tell us anything
                  you remember about it.</p>
               <p>A. They had cattle and horses. <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats"
                        >The priests</orgName></rs> had charge of everything; raised corn and wheat;
                  raised enough to live on; had a good many cattle and lived on them.</p>
               <p>Q. What did you do when you came here?</p>
               <p>A. Hunted sea otter 20 or 30 years. It must be learned; we had no rifles like we
                  have now, but one-barrel old fashioned rifle.</p>
               <p>Q. How many Indians did you ever kill?</p>
               <p>A. <del rend="strikethrough">C</del>I could not tell how many. I know I killed
                  four. There were only 36 of us; we had got well used to the Indians. We wanted to
                  get them on us. Finally they followed us and finally they intended to take us. We
                  did not know any names and that was called <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_maryrun">Mary Run</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_saltlake">Salt Lake</placeName>, and there was a trail and the trail
                  went through a bunch of willows. We knew they intended to take us and at about 200
                  yards we turned off, and as soon as we turned off they came out. They l<del
                     rend="strikethrough">k</del>ived in villages. Every village <del
                     rend="strikethrough">g</del>has its captain. They came up. The first party
                  coing [going] up we met them, 15 of us, and about 200 yards away we tied the
                  horses altog<del rend="strikethrough">o</del>ether. There were 15 of us and these
                  15 were choice shots. They came walking right up within 40 or 50 yards of us and
                  they were kind of falling to - every fellow had his hands full of arrows - and we
                  commenced firing all 15 shots at once. There were 34 Indians killed, the rest ran
                  away. You were asking me how many I killed. About two days a fterward [sic] we
                  were out, me and <rs><persName type="frontieresman" key="#jwa">the
                        captain</persName></rs>. There were five. I got off to one side to the left
                  and walked up to a place where we were to meet. They had not come yet. I saw two
                  Indians coming. I thought they were after me, but they had not seen me. They ran
                  along and kept looking back. I thought they had shot a man and so I thought I
                  would kill one. I had <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#mni">a
                        brother</persName></rs> killed by them. Finally they came to a point of the
                  hill. I shot. I killed them both. They just fell and rolled.</p>
               <p>Q. <del rend="strikethrough">A</del> Where about did you hit them?</p>
               <p>A. The first was shot on the left side and killed instantly.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="11">Q. Ask him if he did not see any friendly Indians, any
                     he had confidence in.</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="11">A. No, could not trust any. There was what is called
                        <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_snake">the Snake
                        Indians</orgName>, about the best, but could not trust them.</span></p>
               <p>Q. Ask him if he had anything to do with the <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_apache">the Apache
                     Indians</orgName></rs>.</p>
               <p>A. Yes, coming through <placeName type="state" key="#st_nm">New
                  Mexico</placeName>. Saw some there.</p>
               <p>Q. <del rend="strikethrough">A</del> Were not they friendly?</p>
               <p>A. Not very. They would steal.</p>
               <p>Q. <del rend="strikethrough">Was it there you stll</del> Was it there you settled
                  down first?</p>
               <p>A. Yes. I came to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName> and
                  went up to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>; was at
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sjoa">San Joaquin</placeName> in a boat and
                  come down to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>. The
                  ship <name type="ship" key="#sh_california">California</name> was there and was
                  coming down to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and
                  saw some Americans and told them they ought to come here. When I came here it was
                  in <date when="1835">1835</date> in the city of <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. There were 17 or 18 at firs<del
                     rend="strikethrough">s</del>t the year I came to <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, 85.</p>
               <p>Q. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">This wom[a]n</persName></rs> -
                  how came she to be left on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        Island</placeName></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. <persName type="investor" key="#isp">Sparks</persName> took them all down to
                  the beach, She [sic] had <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">a
                        child</persName></rs> back on the land and wa<del rend="strikethrough"
                     >i</del>nted to go back and finally they let her go and she did not come back
                  and they went away and she was left there. <persName type="investor" key="#isp"
                     >Sparkes</persName> came and said there was <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> left on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. All expected she could not
                  live.</p>
               <p>Q. Who was <persName type="investor" key="#isp">Sparkes</persName> and how came to
                  to [sic] go for <rs><persName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians</persName></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. The Mexicans sent them to bring them off. <name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">The schooner</name> got lost just afterwards. They
                  calculated to go back. All thought that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> wiuld [sic] not live long, so they did
                  not go back. <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The schooner</name></rs>
                  went to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> and got
                  lost.</p>
               <p>Q. Why did you want to bring <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians</orgName></rs> off anyway?</p>
               <p>A. They wanted them at <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission"
                        >the Mission</orgName></rs> anyhow and <rs><orgName type="government"
                        key="#gov_mexico">the Government</orgName></rs> sent to fetch them off.</p>
               <p>Q. Did <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                        Indians</orgName></rs> go to work in <rs><orgName type="mission"
                        key="#mi_santabarbaramission">the Mission</orgName></rs>, <persName
                     type="group" key="#bhagroup">these particular ones</persName>?</p>
               <p>A. They sent them to work different places, those they brought off.</p>
               <p>Q. How did <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                        >the Indians</orgName>
                  </rs> get on there in the first place?</p>
               <p>A. Born and raised there - never been on <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socalcoast">the coast</placeName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you see <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians</orgName></rs> on there before they
                  were taken off?</p>
               <p>A. No, I never saw them.</p>
               <p>Q. How came you to find <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this
                        woman</persName></rs> was left there? Didyou [sic] see her tracks?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, it was three times before I found her. I went over. <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The
                     priests</persName></rs> here wanted me to hunt for her.</p>
               <p>Q. What priest was it?</p>
               <p>A. <persName type="missionfather" key="#jru">Father Gonzales</persName>, after
                     <persName type="missionfather" key="#sanchez">Sanchez</persName>.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">A</del>Q. How long was it before you found her after you
                     w<del rend="strikethrough">n</del>ent to <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. I found her pretty quick. We had been all over <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs> and it was 12 o'clock I suppose. It
                  was very pretty weather. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Capt.
                        Brown</persName></rs> was with me. Me and h<del rend="strikethrough"
                  >o</del>im walked over to the head of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        Island</placeName></rs> and we saw a track where she had been to the water.
                  We did not find her that evening. Fenally [Finally] went and brought over several
                  Indians on board of the crew - t<del rend="strikethrough">s</del>wo or three white
                  men the rest Indians. We took all of them ashore except <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#cook">the cook</persName></rs>. We thought she
                  would try and hide and we s<del rend="strikethrough">a</del>cattered off two or
                  three hundred yards apart. She had a little house made of brush and had a fire;
                  sitting by the fire with a little knife; she was working with it; she had a bone.
                  All came up and looked at her well. She had a heap of roots. That is what she
                  lived on and had little sacks to carry them in. As soon aa [as] we sat down she
                  put a lump of them to roast on the fire. Finally we got ready to go and we made
                  signs f<del rend="strikethrough">l</del>or her to come with us. She picked up her
                  things to take them on board. She did not appear to be seasick at all and was
                     conte<del rend="strikethrough">ted</del>nted. Next day we moved ashore and <del
                     rend="strikethrough">t</del>stayed there a month and killed a good many otter.
                  She appeared to like everything we had to eat. When we got ready to come we made
                  signs we were coming and she was very willing to come. She came here.</p>
               <p>Q. W hat [sic] did she say when she came to the beach and saw them on
                  horseback?</p>
               <p>A. She said it in her own tongue; looked up and down <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socalcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> and thought it was an
                  island. It was a month or five weeks after she landed before she died.</p>
               <p>Q. What did she have on when you found her on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. Had her dress made of bird skins, out of what they <del rend="strikethrough"
                     >xxxx</del> call shag (a species of black duck). We made her clothes right off;
                  made her petticoats right off. Gave her shirts.</p>
               <p>Q. What did she make the petticoats of?</p>
               <p>A. Clothes we had.</p>
               <p>Q. Men's clothes would not make good petticoats.</p>
               <p>A. No, cut them up, y<hi rend="underline">ou</hi>/see [sic].</p>
               <p>Q. Dressed her instyle [sic], did you?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, made her presentable here.</p>
               <p>Q. How did she sew those bird skins together?</p>
               <p>A. Got<del rend="strikethrough">n</del>the [sic] sinews of a seal. It made quite a
                  nice thread and she had needles of bone.</p>
               <p>Q. What did she do with the dress?</p>
               <p>A. The dress <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the
                        priests</persName></rs> have. I think they sent it to <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>. <rs><persName key="#sni">My
                     wife</persName></rs>
                  <del rend="strikethrough">lest</del> let them have them all, her needles and all
                  the things. she [sic] had a demijohn to carry her water, held a gallon or 1 1/2
                  gallons, made out of rushes and stopped with asphaltum. She was ma[k]ing another.
                     Wal<del rend="strikethrough">l</del>ked up and down. She would walk every day.
                  Finally I see she had a fire made and had small round stones heating of them, and
                  she put them in the asphaltum and threw in these hot stones and it would run all
                  over and make them as tight as a demijohn.</p>
               <p>Q. How d<del rend="strikethrough">n</del>id she make fire?</p>
               <p>A. Out of sticks.</p>
               <p>Q. No <del rend="strikethrough">maches</del>matches?</p>
               <p>A. No, she made it with a stick rubbing a stick. I have done it myself.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you bring those things off that she used for water?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, was fetched here. Scattered in different places, different persons getting
                  them. <span type="trope" n="10">She said <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                           key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs> was eaten up by wolves or wild
                     dogs, which were on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                           Island</placeName></rs>.</span></p>
               <p>Q. Ask him if none of the Indians <del rend="strikethrough">w</del>here understood
                  what she said.</p>
               <p>A. No, there was none of the Indians here that understood her good; I tried to
                  find some tribe that could talk to her and finally got some wo<del
                     rend="strikethrough">k</del>man that could talk a little.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">"</del>Q. Where did <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#natamwoman1">that old woman</persName></rs> come from that could talk
                  to her a little?</p>
               <p>A. She was raised on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Q. You say there was <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#natamwoman1">one
                        woman</persName></rs> who could understand her a little?</p>
               <p>A. She was fetched from some of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        islands</placeName></rs>.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">Q. Did she tell <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                           key="#natamwoman1">that woman</persName></rs>
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>
                     was eatent [sic] up by the dogs?</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">A. No.</span></p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough"><span type="trope" n="10">A</span></del><span
                     type="trope" n="10">Q. How did you know?</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">A. From her signs.</span> She thought that the dosg
                  [dogs] had eaten it. There are a great many dogs there, wild dogs; they were
                  poisoned off some years after.</p>
               <p>Q. She used to live with you till she died?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, died right here in this room.</p>
               <p>Q. What seemed to <del rend="strikethrough">t</del>be the matter with her?</p>
               <p>A. Just kind of give up. Could not tell what was the matter. Indians when they are
                  sick naturally give up, don't care if they live or not.</p>
               <p>Q. How old was she?</p>
               <p>A. About 50; that's what <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the priests</persName></rs>
                  thought.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you hunt any after that?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, killed lots of otter there, 7<del rend="strikethrough">p</del>0 in one
                  month.</p>
               <p>Q. Have you got any Indian relics here?</p>
               <p>A. None now except this (shows).</p>
               <p>Q. Where did you get it. A. [sic] It came from the islands, I don't know wh<del
                     rend="strikethrough">`ch</del>ich island.</p>
               <p>Q. Who found it?</p>
               <p>A. I don't know. It is a weapon to fix in a stick. I was in the war with the
                  Mexicans. This is a medal (shows medal). S ol<del rend="strikethrough"
                  >id</del>diers [sic] in the Mexican war had them. I was in <placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_cal">California</placeName> here with <persName key="#jcfre"
                     >Fremont</persName>. The Mexican war commenced in <date when="1846"
                  >1846</date>. I entered in <date when="1848">1848</date>.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">A</del>Q. Where did you come from?</p>
               <p>A. A native of <placeName type="state" key="#st_penn">Pennsylvania</placeName>
                  .</p>
               <p>A. What descent was he?</p>
               <p>A. German.</p>
               <p>Q. Could you tell me something about otter hunting? I expect you have seen some
                  pretty hard times shooting otter.</p>
               <p>A. No.</p>
               <p>Q. How do you hunt them?</p>
               <p>A. From boats . [sic]</p>
               <p>Q. How many boats do you generally take?</p>
               <p>A. One time there were six.</p>
               <p>Q. How many shots do you have to fire to get an otter?</p>
               <p>A. It's a hard animal to kill.</p>
               <p>Q. How many have you killed in your life?</p>
               <p>A. I have killed 13 in one day, places wherethey [sic] were never hunted before.
                  They they [sic] were worth $20 apiece.</p>
               <p>Q. You made a pretty goo[d] day's work.</p>
               <p>A. There were three with me.</p>
               <p>Q. Do they keep under water more than a seal?</p>
               <p>A. About the same as seals.</p>
               <p>Q. Do otter ever come on shore on rocks?</p>
               <p>A. No. I saw a wounded one once on a rock, that's all. An otter never gets wet
                  alive; after they die they get wet.</p>
               <p>Q. Ho<del rend="strikethrough">d</del>w do you know they get wet before you get to
                  them?</p>
               <p>A. When they take them in the boat <del rend="strikethrough">t</del>just as dry as
                  on land right out of the water. I am 82 and would like to go on an exploring
                  expedition. I killed my last otter when I was 70. When I first came here the
                  Americans and English used to come from the northwest and go up there and fetch 12
                  or 13 canoes and come alon<del rend="strikethrough">r</del>g <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> here. That is
                  what killed off the otter and run them off. They used to rob the people here.
                  There were so many of them, could not fight them. <persName type="investor"
                     key="#isp">Sparkes</persName> he got robbed. Took their skins and provisions
                  and everything they could get hold of. Went over to <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>, and <persName type="investor"
                     key="#isp">Sparkes</persName> said, what are we to do even if they come? l said
                  I would fight first and, if too many, run. There were 13 canoes. We had a great
                  fight. There were 4 hunters there and 3 in our canoes and a Portuguese. We agreed
                  not to run. Finally they came. We were off to sea running otter and as soon as
                  they saw us they came as fast as they could; we<del rend="strikethrough">v</del>nt
                  very fast and just as we got ashore there was one boat 70 or 80 yards from us. One
                  boat got ashore nefore [before] the other was outside. This man that got ashore he
                  shot. He lost the powder out of his gun and did not kill the Indian. <persName
                     type="investor" key="#isp">Sparkes</persName> got ashore next. He shot and hit
                  the Indian and <del rend="strikethrough">y</del>he fell and got up again and ran
                  ashore. I had always two or three guns. When I got ashore I shot. The foremost
                  fell and then <persName type="investor" key="#isp">Sparkes</persName> and the
                  other man killed three.</p>
               <p>Q. Where did the Indians get their ammunition?</p>
               <p>A. Brig went - this was an English brig - went <del rend="strikethrough">xxx</del>
                  after the Indians, and Americans too. They got the Indians down to hunt otter. The
                  captain told them to kill us and take all the skins we had.</p>
               <p>Q<del rend="strikethrough">L</del>. What year was that?</p>
               <p>A. That was in <date when="1836">1836</date>. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">This woman</persName></rs> was found 18 years after, in <date
                     when="1853">1853</date>.</p>
               <p>Q. Will you ask him if while she lived she seemed contented and happy?</p>
               <p>A. Yes. She would go around to different houses and dance.</p>
               <p>Q. D id [sic] she dance?</p>
               <p>A. Indian dance.</p>
               <p>Q. Did she go around and visit neighbors?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, all over <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">townd</placeName></rs>
                  [town] and <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the Mission</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Q. All alone? A. [sic] No. Always a party with her, 20 or 30.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">A</del>Q. Were they Indians and Mexicans with her?</p>
               <p>A. Yes.</p>
               <p>Q. She was a curiosity.</p>
               <p>A. Yes. You see the people who passed in the vessels that passed here heard there
                  was <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an Indian woman</persName></rs>
                  who had lived alone on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">an
                        island</placeName></rs>
                  <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">17 years</date></rs> and
                  they would not believe it until they came to see her.</p>
               <p>Q. How was it you did not find her the second time you were there?</p>
               <p>A. Bad weather.</p>
               <p>Q. Did they pay you anything for finding her?</p>
               <p>A. No. <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#tru">They</persName></rs> offered me
                  $1000 for her, to take her around and exhibit.</p>
               <p>Q. I thought you would have taken $1000 for her.</p>
               <p>A. It did not look right to sell a person.</p>
               <p>Q. How did she look? Was she good looking?</p>
               <p>A. Very good looking and weighed about 100 or 130 lbs.</p>
               <p>Q. How do you suppose <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        woman</persName></rs> caught the shags?</p>
               <p>A. At night.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">A</del>Q. How did she get her seal blubber?</p>
               <p>A. They slept on the rocks and she caught them.</p>
               <p>Q. What did she eat?</p>
               <p>A. She would eat seal when she could get them. She had fishhooks made of bone and
                  line made of the sinews of the seak [seal] back. She was skinning a piece of seal
                  when we found her.</p>
               <p>Q. Ask him if he remembers how her dress was made, [sic]</p>
               <p>A. Out of the skins.</p>
               <p>Q. What was it made like?</p>
               <p>A. The skins were sown. I cannot hardly tell. Feathers all laid down.</p>
               <p>Q. Had it arms to it?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, she ahd [had] cover round and looked quite well.</p>
               <p>Q. She seemed to be glad to see yOu [sic] when you fOund [sic] her?</p>
               <p>A. She was glad to see us and was not afraid of us.</p>
               <p>Q. Did you ever see any of the Indian skulls with two rows of teeth?</p>
               <p>A. No, I never saw any. I believe I have heard of it. I never went much with
                  Indians. They wanted to kill me.</p>
               <p>Q. Did they steal your horses?</p>
               <p>A. Yes. We were out after meat once and they got after us. There were six of us
                  and about forty Indians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="interview2">
               <head><title type="section"><hi rend="underline">Charles Brown's
                     Statement</hi></title></head>
               <p>Born in <placeName type="country" key="#co_prussia">Prussia</placeName>. My name
                  is really <hi rend="underline"><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Carl
                        Ditman</persName></hi>. Ever since I left <placeName type="country"
                     key="#co_ger">Germany</placeName> I go by the name of <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charles Brown</persName></rs>. I went in
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_martinet">an English vessel</name></rs> and
                  shipped in a man's place as <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charles
                        Brown</persName></rs>. I was born in <date when="1822">1822</date>.</p>
               <p>Q. You always followed the sea?</p>
               <p>A. For 10 or 12 years. Then I came here and here I stick. I came here in <date
                     when="1844">1844</date> with <persName type="seaman" key="#wilson1">Capt.
                     Wilson</persName> and have been here ever since.</p>
               <p>Q. When did you commence otter hunting?</p>
               <p>A. <rs><date when="1845">The year afterwards</date></rs>. Sent us down to the
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_cerros">Island of Cerros</placeName>, about
                  600 miles from here. I hunted there and built a boat of Monterey pine. The brig
                  left us for she wen<del rend="strikethrough">d</del>t down to <placeName
                     type="country" key="#re_baja">Mexico</placeName> hunting. <rs><persName
                        type="investor" key="#isp">Old man Sparkes</persName></rs> had charge of
                  her. I built a boat and hunted, coming up to <placeName key="#memm"
                     >Memmosa</placeName> (?). Made the most hunt there.</p>
               <p>Q. How did you come to go over to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicholas</placeName>? Did <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the Padre</persName></rs> want you to
                  go and get <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the Indian
                        Woman</persName></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName> settled at
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>. He had a little
                  vessel and he went on to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicholas</placeName> before I went on there and he could not do anything with
                  one boat. He said, I wish you would get a boat and go hunting with me. I said I
                  would build a boat. He said he had seen a sign on [of] <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs> and he was there
                  afterward and could never find the track again. W<del rend="strikethrough"
                  >j</del>hen I went there it was a stormy day and we could not go ashore for three
                  days. We let the anchor go. He thought it was in a bunch of kelp but it was under
                  a rock. When the swells came I said we have got to get out of this. I said we have
                  to wait till slack water, because the flue of your anchor is in the rock. We all
                  hauled and when the swell came on us all had to let go, so he said to leave it
                  this way. So we stayed for three days and got anchored all right. Nothing broke.
                  Then after we weant [went] ashore <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">the
                        Old Man</persName></rs> got the spyglass to see for otter. We got on the
                  head of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>.
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The Old Man</persName></rs> got
                  tired. I went around the head of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        Island</placeName></rs> and found tracks of <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, so I went back
                  and told <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">the old
                     gentleman</persName></rs>
                  <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> was alive.
                  He said how do you know? I said I have found her track. He said it must be some of
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">our
                        Indians</persName></rs>. I said <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">our Indians</persName></rs> have got bigger
                  tracks than <del rend="strikethrough">a</del>that. And he said, well if you think
                  she is alive let us hunt for her and take all the m<del rend="strikethrough"
                     >a</del>en ashore. We went up to the head of <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>. There was a kind of hill in the
                  middle. I put <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">my
                        Indians</persName></rs> 200 yards apart. <span type="trope" n="14">I did not
                     know what kind of a woman she was. I thought she might bite or scratch, and
                     went from one side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                           Island</placeName></rs> to the other and we could not see the
                     hill.</span> She was sitting on the side of the hill eatching [watching] us,
                  and when we got across to <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                        >the Indians</persName></rs> I said there is nothing here and I said go
                  back. There was a basket and some feathers. She ca<del rend="strikethrough"
                     >r</del>tched [sic] the shag and had a coat made like a coat without sleeves -
                  had it nicely covered with sealskin. I said to <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs> you go to the hill
                  and scatter the feathers and things in the basket and if she is alive she will
                  find them. And we found them all gathered up again the same day and put in the
                  basket. I went around another way. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">The Indians</persName></rs> found it all
                  picked up. We took a good many things to the camp before and <del
                     rend="strikethrough">s</del>when I came back I see the tracks again and I said
                  now I am going to have you sure. I am going to track you.</p>
               <p><del rend="strikethrough">We went up to the head of <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>. There was a kind of hill in the
                     middle I put my</del></p>
               <p>In <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName> there is moss
                  growing over just like this carpet. I got half way up and then I see her. She had
                  something to carry and made small stages and she rested. When I went up a little
                  higher I see three huts made out of whalebone. I thought to myself she is in
                  there. I peeped in and there was no signs there. I thought to myself where in the
                  world can she be? I stayed on the highest part and saw <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs> going where I told
                  them. I looked and I looked and saw something like a crow sitting on a whalebone.
                  I said to <del rend="strikethrough">M</del>myself what is that? So when I came to
                  find out it was her I took my gun and stuck my hat on and held <del
                     rend="strikethrough">o</del>it up to make signs to <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>. I did not know if
                  she would bite or scratch. I motioned <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs> to come along.</p>
               <p>She had a brush fence about two feet high to break the wind and right in front she
                  sat facing me, [sic] The sun was coming her in <del rend="strikethrough"
                  >n</del>her face. She was skinning a seal before I came up to her. The dog when he
                  noticed me he began to growl. I thought if she <del rend="strikethrough">knew
                     me</del> should run. I stepped right around her and she bowed as if she knew me
                  before and when <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        Indians</persName></rs> came up they all kneeled down. When she saw there
                  were some of her color she held out some of her food like an onion. She got out
                  some of them and offered them all some and offered me some too; but I did not
                  eat.</p>
               <p><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Old man Nidever</persName></rs> was
                  [s]itting on the point. He would not go any further and we had a good deal of
                  trouble for him to come. At last he came. He made a motion sign and she was kind
                  of scared. So <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Old Man
                        Nidever</persName></rs> said to <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>, in case she would
                  not come could not we take her by force. I said no, she is not afraid. So I took
                  her by the shoulder and said <hi rend="underline">Varmoose</hi> and she understood
                  at once. I took everything she had and she took a big seal head in basket and that
                  was all. We all had something to carry. Then she with a <del rend="strikethrough"
                     >strange kind of steplike</del> ,little [sic] brand of fire and she took that
                  away and wobbled along with a strange kind of steplike, until we came to a place
                  in the beach where there was water. We all had a drink there and we told her to go
                  right along. Then we came to another watering place about 5o [sic] feet down the
                  bank and they all went down there and she went too. She sat down there and we
                  watched to see what she would do. She washed herself all over. He[r] hair was all
                  rotted away and kind of bleached by the sun. We got to <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_nidever">the vessel</name></rs> and she kneeled down. We had a
                  stove on deck and she crawled to the stove. We gave her a piece of biscuit and she
                  ate like a good fellow.</p>
               <p>It came on to blow. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Old Man
                        Nidever</persName></rs> had some bedticking and made her a dree [dress] and
                  gave her a man's shirt. She had nothing but a coat on, made of birdksins, got no
                  sleeves, sewn with the sinews of animals she found on the beach. Anyway we took
                  her on board and we lay there for three days, and while we were laying there I
                  made her a skirt out of bedticking. She was tic[k]led to death. There was a lot
                  ofwild [sic] dogs there.</p>
               <p>Q. We want to know how it was she was left there and how <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the first
                        Indiands</orgName></rs> [sic] came there.</p>
               <p>A. Early times I suppose all <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        islands</placeName></rs> were settled with <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                        >Indians</orgName></rs>.<span type="trope" n="11"><rs><orgName type="group"
                           key="#natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">Northwest Indians</orgName></rs> used
                     to come to hunt and shoot <rs><orgName type="group"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                           Indians</orgName></rs> just for mischief.</span></p>
               <p>Q. How did she come to be left there?</p>
               <p>A. I only know from what I have heard from <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                        key="#gni">Old Man Nidever</persName></rs>; built a vessel called "<rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better than Nothing</name></rs>." They
                     cat<del rend="strikethrough">f</del>ched [sic] <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this
                        family</orgName></rs> there on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicholas</placeName> and took them all away except her, and when she came back
                  to camp she found everybody gone. <span type="trope" n="10">She had <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild" cert="high">two
                        children</persName></rs>. She sh</span><del rend="strikethrough"><span
                        type="trope" n="10">h</span></del><span type="trope" n="10">ook her breast
                     meaning one nursing and one with teeth. She found they were all gone and she
                     commenced to halloo and hunted around and saw the tracks and saw they went to
                     the lower part of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the Is<del
                              rend="strikethrough">n</del>land</placeName></rs>. When she got there
                     she found <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessels</name></rs>
                     going away and she called "Manyanna," but it never came and they took
                           <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild" cert="high">the two
                           children</persName></rs>, all except her.</span> They made signs for her
                  to come back. She put her head on the ground and cried and they never came. She
                  talked some words, "Kanake" - some kind of Indian - mixed it all up. <rs><persName
                        type="missionfather" key="#jru">The priest</persName></rs> here had all the
                  Indians in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sy">Santa In<del rend="strikethrough"
                     >z</del>ez</placeName> to see if they understood her. They could understand
                  some words but not all. <del rend="strikethrough">T</del>She<del
                     rend="strikethrough">y</del> got baptized and they made her a Christian and
                  everything. <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_fremont">A steamer</name></rs> came up
                  from below. <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#fremontcpt">The
                     captain</persName></rs> offered to take her up and show her, but <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Old Man Nidever</persName></rs> would not
                  agree to anything. She died. They gave her green corn and melon and that set her
                  over. Shen [When] she was over at <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        Island</placeName></rs> a month she camped out with them and lived on what
                  they did and she was perfectly well. <span type="trope" n="3">She would go off and
                     get wood and water for herself and come back again and sit in camp and play
                     like a child. There was a little otter (see Note) and she lodged a stick and
                     hung it over for the sun not to shine in her eyes.</span> She made baskets of
                  the grass that grows on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        Island</placeName></rs>. She had leaves for baskets, dozen or so never
                  finished, worked on one and then the other, never finishing them. That is the way
                  she passed her time away. Her teeth. She had solid teeth but they were worn away
                  to the gums eating that tough stuff. When I brought her to the camp I took the
                  skin of the otter and threw the carcass to the water and she saw it. She made
                  signs it was to eat and she held it up. She liked potatoes, rice, fish. <span
                     type="trope" n="3">She did not </span><del rend="strikethrough"><span
                        type="trope" n="3">each</span></del><span type="trope" n="3"> eat much, but
                     often, just like a child.</span> She would take a bone and suck it.</p>
               <p>When we left <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>
                  it was pretty rough and we made her go below in the cabin and <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">old man Nidever</persName></rs> said we
                  better turn back. She would not stay there but made a sign to pray for the wind to
                  go down. She had named all <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        islands</placeName></rs>. I don't recollect the names. She had names for all
                  of them. When we came to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName> beach there was nobody living there except <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">old man Nidever</persName></rs>. Seeing the
                  boys coming along on horses she thought it was awful and when she saw the cattle
                  crawled on the sand beach on her hands and knees.</p>
               <p>Q. Tell me about <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs>
                  that went and fetched the rest of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians</orgName></rs>.</p>
               <p>A. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                        >Party of hunters</persName></rs>, I believe; <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_peoresnada">a little vessel</name></rs>. They landed at <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Q. How did they know <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians</orgName></rs> were there?</p>
               <p>A. Went around <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs>, probably found <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup"
                     >the Indians</persName> there and took them right off.</p>
               <p>Q. How do you suppose they went?</p>
               <p>A. I suppose of their own free will.</p>
               <p>A [Q]. Do you know what became of <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the
                     Indians</persName>?</p>
               <p>A. They all died out.</p>
               <p>Q. Where were they carried to?</p>
               <p>A. <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>. They say the men
                  were strong <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                        >Indians</orgName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Q. How many were there?</p>
               <p>A. I think seven. They were taken off before I came here. <span type="trope"
                     n="14">It was only <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                           woman</persName></rs> I catched [sic] and helped to take off. She was not
                     wild. They all ask me if she was wild.</span> Her hair was kind of rotten,
                  bleached kind of red. <span type="trope" n="10">She had been there <rs><date
                           notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">17 years</date></rs> all a
                     lone [sic] and she made signs she had been sick, living in the dirt for days.
                     She could not move, all alone. She was down sick, could not move, and got
                     well.</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">Q. How did you get the story of <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                  child</persName></rs>?</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">A. The story they told[,] she went back to get
                           <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                        child</persName></rs>. They did not know anything about it. I understand she
                     made signs so plain - she showed two fingers for two children and she shook her
                     breast; one was sucking and the other had teeth. She sucked her
                  fingers.</span></p>
               <p>Q. How did <del rend="strikethrough">you</del>she make you understand that they
                  took off <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                        children</persName></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. They told [her they would] come back tomorrow, "manyanna" - made plain signs -
                  never came back. She could see us the day before when we were on the head of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and
                  showed fingers. She would not come down until we had stumbled right over her.</p>
               <p>Q. Then she did not want to go off.</p>
               <p>A. S he [sic] did not want to come.</p>
               <p>Q. If she had felt a strong desire she would have come.</p>
               <p>A. That is the Indian way.</p>
               <p>Q.Did it occur to her to go to them, to want to see what happened? She might have
                  seen you.</p>
               <p>A. Yes, before.</p>
               <p>Q. Probably seen hunters before.</p>
               <p>A. They all told [that] she had been dead for years. They knew there was
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> left
                  there. Nobody hunted for her and when <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                        >Old Man Nidever</persName></rs> saw the tracks thought she was dead until I
                  found the tracks again, and then we hunted for her.</p>
               <p>Q. What became of the dress?</p>
               <p>A. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName> gave it to
                        <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the priests</orgName></rs>
                  and they sent it to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>. She had
                  bone needles with eyes drilled in and she had a kn<del rend="strikethrough"
                     >o</del>ife made with bone and another with a piece of wood, that she had when
                  I catched [sic] her cleaning the sealskin. She had nails pointed for catching fish
                  with. She had the rope nicely twisted with sinews and had it twisted as true as
                  any ropemake[r] could make, and she had bottles made of grass about the size of a
                  gallon demijohn. We found some dishes of wood with handles.</p>
               <p>Q. What became of all these things?</p>
               <p>A. I gave them to <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName>. If
                  we had taken care of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        woman</persName></rs> and shown her we could have made a hatful [sic] of
                  money. <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#fremontcpt">Captain</persName></rs> of
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_fremont">the steamer</name></rs> gave news
                  that we had caught <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a wild
                        woman</persName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Q. Was she baptized here?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, at <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">the
                        Mission</orgName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Q. Do you know the name they gave her. [sic]</p>
               <p>A. Maria, something.</p>
               <p>Q. They could not find out what her <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Indian</orgName></rs> name was?</p>
               <p>A. No. Juana Maria I t<del rend="strikethrough">j</del>h<del rend="strikethrough"
                     >o</del>ink she was named. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The priests</persName></rs> tried hard
                  to find her life story, but she broke off into gibberish nobody could understand.
                  Had Indians from <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">Santa
                        Barbara</placeName></rs>, <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_ventura"
                        >Ventura</placeName></rs>, <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sy">Santa
                        Inez</placeName></rs> - they could not understand. Understood some words but
                  not right through.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">Q. Did she seem quite happy?</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">A. Happy as a lady. Shw [sic] was dancing when anybody
                     came. Then she </span><del rend="strikethrough"><span type="trope" n="10"
                        >s</span></del><span type="trope" n="10">lift [sic] up her dress and made
                     signs that I made her dress.</span> While I was making her dress she tried to
                  sew too. I had to thread her needle. She took this hand and put it through and
                  handed it through like a shoemaker. She was content enough, if they had kept her
                  from green corn, pumpkins and squash. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                        >Old Man Nidever</persName></rs> told me he thought she would die the day
                  before. She thought she was going to die. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                     >Nidever</persName> thought she would die that night when she came from
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs>. I took
                  baskets that was hanging [sic]. She got up from her bed the night before she went
                  away and took a basket from the sycamore tree and threw the feathers out. One of
                  the new baskets she gave to me. She lived two days after we left (<persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName> and myself for <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>).</p>
               <p>Q. I don't see what objection there could have been to take and show her.</p>
               <p>A. Made money for her. People gave her money here. She did not know what money
                  was. Clothes tickled her. She was only used to birdskin coats. I suppose it was
                  often cold weather and she put the feathers next toher [sic] skin. On <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, if they had worked it
                  right and kept her on her food she might have been alive yet. She was about 45 or
                  50 when we found her, because she walked with a kind of <del rend="strikethrough"
                     >e</del>stoop. Singular part of it, probably seen people before. <span
                     type="trope" n="10">She made signs that she had seen men go b</span><del
                     rend="strikethrough"><span type="trope" n="10">b</span></del><span type="trope"
                     n="10">y.</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">Q. Did she give you any idea that she had seen the men
                     before?</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">A. No. Ships going that way and this, but nobody came
                     for her.</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">Q. Had she anything rough over her head?</span></p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="10">A. Nothing whatever. She held up her hand that way when
                           <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                           Indians</persName></rs> came up and they let her know if she did run they
                     would catch her.</span></p>
               <p>Q. Did you say she spoke some words "Kanake?"</p>
               <p>A. Yes. From one of the men that had the little schooner named "<name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_williams">Williams</name>." She got the name <del rend="strikethrough"
                     >N</del><rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better than
                     Nothing</name></rs>."</p>
               <p>Q. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName> thought
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the
                        priests</persName></rs> hired them to go and get <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                        Indians</orgName></rs> off.</p>
               <p>A. I don't think so. Maybe so. I came here in <date when="1844">1844</date>.
                        <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">The priests</orgName></rs>
                  had all the control.</p>
               <p>Q. What was the <placeName key="#presidio">old Presidio</placeName>?</p>
               <p>A. Barracks for the soldiers.</p>
               <p>Q. How was it you reenlisted in <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_martinet">an
                        English ship</name></rs>?</p>
               <p>A. Left the <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_euphemia">Prussian
                  ship</name></rs>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="endnote">
               <p><hi rend="underline">Note</hi>: After copying the above statements I went down
                  this P.M. (<date when="1882-03-16">amrch [March] 16, 1882</date>) and called on
                     <persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Mr. Carl Ditman</persName> for an
                  explanation regarding certain obscure statements in the above. Being a German and
                  speaking broken English accounts largely for many of the inaccuracies. Regarding
                  the root resembling an onion, he says the Spanish or Mexican name is "Coccometas,"
                  that the little "otter" referred to was a very small one which "she hung up by a
                  string and played with as a cat would a mouse suspened [sic] in the same way."
                  That they had Indians from different tribes to talk with her <hi rend="underline"
                     >but could not recollect which tribe could understand her best.</hi> That the
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Old Man <hi rend="underline"
                           >Nidever</hi></persName></rs> started from <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> for <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf"
                     >San Francisco</placeName> two days before she died and that <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Capt. Nidever</persName> made her coffin before
                  he started.</p>
            </div>
            <byline><hi><persName key="#jte">J. T.</persName>
               </hi></byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
