TO EXPLORE the STRANGE ISLAND of SAN NICOLAS

An Expedition from the University of California Will Visit the Grewsome [Gruesome] Land that is Spread Over with Skulls and Thighbones of a Lost Race.

LOS ANGELES, Cal., Oct. 15.&#8212;An air of mystery pervades each of the little islands in the scant archipelago off the coast of California. San Clemente Island is strewn with enormous prehistoric mortars and pestles, and here and there are numerous evidences that a giant race lived there before the Portuguese navigator, Cabrillo, sailed for conquest up the coast of Alta California in 1542. Santa Catalina is indented by many strange caves, weird grottoes, where one may see remains of a race of fishers and artisans with shells. San Miguel Island has been the scene of titanic erosions of ice, water and sand. The grotesque pillars that lift themselves above the island level, the winding caves that twist from the shores into the heart of the island, and the roaring gulches and canyons denote a spot rich in possibilities for both scientist and dreamer. Santa Cruz Island is used as a pasturage for thousands of sheep, and it, too, is full of absorbing interest regarding extinct races of aborigines. The Smithsonian Institution scientists have gathered tons of stone, shell and bone utensils and personal ornaments from Santa Cruz.

<hi rend="bold">Most Mysterious of All.</hi>

But San Nicolas Island has by far the most abundant evidences of a tribe of unusually tall and strong people who must have vanished almost in a night. Of all the California archipelago[es] this is the most mysterious.

Notwithstanding that the islands&#8212;known on the Pacific Coast as the Channel Islands&#8212;are but from 3 0to [30 to] 50 miles out in the blue of the ocean, they seldom are visited. Every few years an exploring expedition goes to them for a season of scientific study, but, with the exception of Santa Catalina&#8212;a famous Summer resort for California pleasure-seekers and anglers&#8212;a half-dozen visitors do not land at any of them once a year. Today the islands remain as lonely and desolate as they were long before the first whiteface sailed up the coast&#8212;360 years ago. The races which occupied them are as much of a mystery as ever, and so far science is baffled in the effort to determine what sort of folk these aboriginal settlers were, how they lived, what they believed, and especially how they so suddenly and completely disappeared from the face of the earth.

The University of California, at Berkeley, is now about the begin the most thorough exploration ever made of San Nicolas Island, which lies 60 miles off the coast of Ventura and Santa Barbara Counties.

<hi rend="bold">Reminders of a Lost Race.</hi>

As far back as the memory of any person in Southern California runs, hundreds of white skeletons have dotted the valleys and hillsides of San Nicolas. Strange utensils of serpentine, sandstone and steatite are found there among the human bones, and the island and its inhabitants have a history so curious that it is difficult of comprehension.

In 1836 the Franciscan padres in the Santa Barbara Mission, learning that there were but 16 of the strange and almost extinct Indian race then living there, determined to rescue them from the island. They went over in a sloop and succeeded, as they thought, in getting all on board. At the last moment an Indian woman returned for her child, and one of the frequent storms of the Channel Islands springing up, the sloop was driven away without her. The sloop went on the rocks of Point Conception and all on board were lost.

Sixteen years later Captain George Nidever and two men went from the coast on a sloop to hunt sea otter off San Nicolas. On landing, they were, like Crusoe, astonished to find human footprints in the astonished to find human footprints in the sand. They saw no one, however, and a storm compelled them to put to sea.

<hi rend="bold">The Sole Inhabitant.</hi>

It was two years thereafter that the adventurous captain, revolving in his mind the sight of the footprints in the uncanny island, determined to go and discover and bring over the lonely woman of whom he had vaguely heard. Men accompanied him, and at lenght they saw on the surf-beaten shore a woman, with long, tawny hair, dressed in a  queer garb of colored bird skins, and scraping with a bone knife the blubber from a seal.

They surrounded and approached her stealthily, and although suddenly confronted, she did not appear in the least afraid, but smiled, and then falling on her knees, prayed to the sun. She offered no objection when, by signs, she was made to understand that she was to go with them in the boat.

They reached Santa Barbara across the rough sea, and the first thing the Indian woman saw was Dr. S. L. Shaw, now 80 years old, and yet living there, riding a horse. She had never seen or heard of any object like it, and, thinking the man and horse were one, she knelt on the shore and offered her devotions to it. Two weeks afterward the last inhabitant of rock-ribbed, tempest-tossed San Nicolas died from eating food to which she was unaccustomed, and which had been furnished by her rescuers, and the curtain fell on her race forever.

In speaking of that death at a meeting of the Southern California Medical Society the other day, Dr. Walter Lindley said that, if the woman could have been spared a few years of life, a story of one of the strangest races that ever lived in the Southwest, and that had had no contamination with the whites, might have been learned. The woman, known as the "Lone Woman of San Nicolas," has been the subject of a score of romances and poems and food for a lot of philosophy on the Pacific Coast for years.

San Nicolas is 10 miles long and four miles wide a the widest point. Its topography shows a nearly level plateau, with an elevation of 800 to 1000 feet. Two-thirds of the surface is covered with drifting sand and the remainder grows a species of nutritious grass and moss, on which a thousand sheep find pasture. Several springs have been discovered, but their water is slightly brackish. Of late years the island is rarely visited, except by sheep-shearers and shell-gatherers, who make annual trips in schooners, fishing smacks and Chinese junks.

The only safe landing ground at San Nicolas is at Coral Harbor, a pretty cover formed by two sandstone arms thrust out from the main barrier of the shore. The entrance is but six or seven yards across, and the water within is placid as a lake, and sufficiently deep to float a vessel of 20 tons burden.

On the bleak, silvery strip of beach immense white pelicans are to be seen at almost any season of the year, promenading with stately dignity. On the approach of a boat they spread their heavy, pointed wings and vanish over the rocks. Further up the shore of the beach there is a dilapidated shearing shed and a weather-worn shanty belonging to Chinese shell-gatherers, who haunt these lonely cliffs during late Summer and Fall.

Nothing more desolate than the general appearance of the island can be imagined. As far as the eye can trace there are innumerable circular depressions, showing where primitive dwellings once stood. Not a vestige remains of the materials used in the construction of these rancherias. Hundreds of shell mounds are scattered about, and they are found to consist of astonishing numbers of shells of mollusks, the bones of every species of fish found in the channel, skeletons of seals, sea elephants, whales, sea otter, the island fox and various aquatic birds. Without question these animals were used for food by the tribes that once thronged these boundaries. There are also numerous canine skeletons, several of which indicate a species of bull terrier. Judging from the immense quantities of dead land mollusks everywhere, there must have been a time when the island supported luxuriant vegetation. Of all this naught exists today have a few stunted thorn bushes and here and there a cactus forlornly reaching its grotesque arms out of interminable sweeps of sand.

<hi rend="bold">All Sorts of Utensils.</hi>

An examination of some of the mounds discloses all sorts of curious utensils, stone cooking pots, water ollas, mortars, pestles, drills, bone needles and fishhooks, shell beads, charm stones, pipes, cups and a few arrow heads, spear points and swords made of bone. The absence of many weapons proves the peaceful attributes of the islanders. Small imitations of boats and fish, carved from crystallized tale and serpentine, also show a rudimentary knowledge of the art of sculpture.

In many places conical piles of small black pebbles contrast oddly with the white land. In some instances these are closely packed in abalone shells. No trace is seen of the "brush pens," in which the lone woman of San Nicolas for years found her only shelter from cutting wind and sand. Nature, ever unmindful of the individual, long since merged the superhuman efforts of this courageous life into the universal fate of an entire race. Indeed every foot of this strange island is eloquent of the extinction of an almost unheard-of people.

A trip along the west coast of San Nicolas Island over a vast extent of shell mounds sets one to wondering how it was possible for a limited population to consume such prodigious numbers of mollusks. In fact, the infinite variety of mollusca on San Nicholas is said by biologists not to be exceeded by any other known region of equal area. The shore line is of course sandstone, burrowed by the pounding surf into fantastic alcoves, bridges, columns and caves.

<hi rend="bold">Nature's Handiwork.</hi>

Sometimes these savage cuts form rude effigies bearing a suprising likeness to living creatures. One of the most conspicuous is the exact counterpart of the neck, breast and body of a bird, with an alert, hooded head. This piece of nature's sculpturing must be 40 feet long, and, beheld from a distance, it looks quite as perfect as if fashioned by man. There are hundreds of photographs of this freak of nature sold all over California.

Going westward from this gnawed, surf-lashed wall, the ground makes a gentle descent to a wide mesa, terminating in a steep escarpment. The atmosphere from this elevation is so deliciously clear that the eye can readily distinguish the peak tops of all the Channel Islands, several of them being 40 miles away. Immediately at one's feet there stretches away a dreary desert of stupendous barrenness.

A singular characteristic of the place is heaps of the bones of whales, their arrangement and packing so systematically correct as to have withstood a century's sweep of winds over this exposed point. But one human skeleton has ever been found in this part of the island, and its bleached, dismembered aspect was in keeping with the driven desolateness of the spot. The merciless [winds ...] the sand dunes all about, but [...] kindly drift over this "rough [...] man."

All around are the casts of [...] in the shifting sand, ranging [from] fiber to several inches in [diameter ...] semi-petrifications are all intact[, ...] having swept them clean of [the] earth. They yield a metallic [...] tapped with a rock or shell.

A still more remarkable [...] desert is a sparse stone forest [of] columns or trunks of trees [...] indurated sand.

At the extreme west [end of the island] there is a colossal precipice [1,000 feet in] height, its chasmed and [slitted face] softened by a luxuriant [gross of emer]ald moss and lichens.

The most grewsome [gruesome] of all the [sights on] this strange island is to be [seen on the] broad plateau, on the south side [of the] Chinese Camp, at Coral Harbor[. Here] acres of the naked sand are [littered with] hundreds of disjointed skeletons [and pre]sent the most reckless [illustration of the] "ground plan" of humanity that [imagina]tion can picture. [Measurements have] been made by several [scientists of the] thigh, leg and arm bones, and [literally] bushels of skulls and other [parts of the] human frame have been [brought to Los] Angeles from San Nicolas [for investiga]tion.

The general opinion is that [the phy]sique of the Indian race that [swarmed] once over the island was [much larger] than that of any civilized race [of the pres]ent, and that some of the [aborigines must] have been 7 feet 3 inches tall. [Those] of the extinct tribes often [measure ...] inches more around then the [...] of today. Many skulls found [lying about] on the island show that their [possessors] must have suffered death from [a ...] blunt battle ax. No one has [ ever] found a skull on San Nicolas [that shows] marks of a bullet.

There are many collar bones [and shoul]der blades broken and crushed [that] would make it appear that [their owners] were slain with some such [instrument as a] war club or bowlder. Scientists [say that] the favorite weapon of the Aleu[tian sav]age tribes a century or more [ago was a] club or bludgeon, and this fact [fits with] the stray tradition that the Al[eutians came] down and completely destroyed the [origi]nal inhabitants on the Channel [Islands] about the year 1570. 

HENRY G. [...]