<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>
                        <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                        <respStmt>
                              <resp>Editor</resp>
                              <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                        </respStmt>
                        <respStmt>
                              <resp>Publisher</resp>
                              <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                                    Humanities</name>
                        </respStmt>
                        <respStmt>
                              <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                              <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive
                                    Research and Development Team</name>
                              <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                                    Humanities</name>
                        </respStmt>
                  </titleStmt>
                  <publicationStmt>
                        <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                        <availability status="free">
                              <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the
                                    public domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing
                                    images from this digital archive, we request that you cite it as
                                    follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive, Center for
                                    Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
                              <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be
                                    protected by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure
                                    permission for republishing post-1923 material in this archive
                                    have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images, as
                                    well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the
                                    periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                                    Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is
                                    prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                                    holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                                    permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further
                                    reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is
                                    prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                                    holder.</p>
                              <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive
                                    rests exclusively with the user.</p>
                        </availability>
                        <date/>
                  </publicationStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl type="article">
                              <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#dailypress"
                                          >Daily Press</orgName></title>
                              <editor/>
                              <publisher/><biblScope unit="vol" n="7"/>
                              <biblScope unit="issue" n="163"/>
                              <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                                          Barbara</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                                          >California</placeName></pubPlace>
                              <date when="1879-01-29"/>
                              <bibl><title type="article" key="#Stuart1879_Jan29">A Female Crusoe.
                                          The Lone Woman of San Nicolas Island. A Wonderful Romance
                                          in Real Life---Eighteen Years Alone on the Island of San
                                          Nicolas, on the Coast of Southern California</title>
                                    <biblScope unit="page" n="3"/>
                                    <author><persName type="author" key="#ast">Stuart, Absalom
                                                B.</persName></author></bibl>
                        </bibl>
                  </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text xml:lang="en">
            <body>
                  <div type="article">
                        <head><title type="main"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">A
                                                FEMALE CRUSOE</persName></rs>.</title>
                              <title type="sub"><rs><emph><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                                  >THE LONE WOMAN OF SAN NICOLAS
                                                ISLAND</persName></emph>.</rs></title></head>
                        <byline><emph>Correspondence of <title type="article" key="#Stuart1878">The
                                          Winona Republican</title>.</emph></byline>
                        <head><title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">A Wonderful Romance in Real
                                                  Life---<rs><date from="1835" to="1853">Eighteen
                                                  Years</date></rs> Alone on the <placeName
                                                type="island" key="#i_sn">Island of San
                                                Nicolas</placeName>, on the <placeName type="region"
                                                key="#re_socalcoast">Coast of Southern
                                                California</placeName>.</hi></title>
                              <title type="sub"><emph>(Concluded.)</emph></title></head>
                        <p><span type="trope" n="4">A third voyage by <rs><persName
                                                type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr.
                                          N.</persName></rs> and <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">six
                                                others</persName></rs>, four of whom were
                                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                                                >Indians</persName></rs> from <orgName
                                          type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">Santa Barbara
                                          Mission</orgName>, was made to <rs><placeName
                                                type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                          island</placeName></rs> in <date when="1853-07">July,
                                          1853</date>; and, although otter hunting was the main
                                    object of the visit, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                                key="#lw">the Indian woman</persName></rs> was not
                                    forgotten. They landed on the northeast side of <rs><placeName
                                                type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                          island</placeName></rs> early in the day, and having
                                    selected their camping site, all but one, <rs><persName
                                                type="nativeamerican" key="#cook">the
                                                cook</persName></rs>, started for the head of
                                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                                island</placeName></rs>. Near there were observed
                                    fresh footprints leading from the beach to the ridge or higher
                                    elevation, but were soon lost in moss-covered ground, which
                                    ended the search for the day. The following day they were more
                                    successful. One of the party, <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                                key="#cdi">Mr. Brown</persName></rs>, discovered
                                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                                object of their search</persName></rs> at a
                                    distance, and cautiously approaching in an opposite direction
                                    from the <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">balance of
                                                the party</persName></rs>, got quite close to her
                                    without being observed. She was in one of her pens, or wind
                                    breaks, clothed in a garment made of the skins of the shag,
                                    without sleeves, low necked, and, as observed when standing up,
                                    extending almost to the ankles. She was sitting cross legged,
                                    skinning seal blubber with a rude knife made of a piece of hoop
                                    iron driven into a piece of wood. There was no covering on her
                                    head excepting a thick mass of matted hair of a yellowish-brown
                                    color, due to the exposure to the sun and air. The hair was
                                    short, looking as though the free ends had rotted off. She would
                                    occasionally raise her hand and shade her eyes and look toward
                                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the other
                                                men</persName></rs> on a sandy plain near the beach,
                                    whom she evidently saw. There were two or three of the wild dogs
                                    around the enclosure, which began to growl as <rs><persName
                                                type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Mr.
                                          Brown</persName></rs> approached, but ran off at the
                                    bidding of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">their
                                                mistress</persName></rs>. The <rs><persName
                                                type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">balance of
                                                the party</persName></rs> were now signaled in order
                                    that she might be captured if she attempted to escape. To the
                                    surprise of all she made no attempt to get away, but greeted
                                    each one as they approached with a bow and a smile, and
                                    chattered all the while in a dialect which none of them
                                    understood, although <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                          Indians</persName></rs> accompanying <persName
                                          type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName> were
                                    acquainted with several Indian dialects. She was talking
                                    apparently to herself, from the time <rs><persName
                                                type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Mr.
                                          Brown</persName></rs> approached within hearing distance
                                    until she was made aware of his presence.</span></p>
                        <p><span type="trope" n="1">Within the enclosure was a fire smouldering, and
                                    a large ash pile outside showed that to have been her abiding
                                    place for some time. She was very hospitable, preparing a meal
                                    from her limited store of roots, before named, and serving
                                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                                party</persName></rs> with a grace and bearing that
                                    surprised them all.</span><span type="trope" n="3">The
                                    expression of her face was pleasing, her features were regular,
                                    and her complexion was much fairer and her form more symmetrical
                                    than that of the Indian women on the main land; and she is
                                    believed to have belonged to <rs><orgName
                                                type="nativeamericantribes"
                                                key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a different and superior
                                                race</orgName></rs>; which opinion is strengthened
                                    by the fact that <persName type="author" key="#lce">Mons. Leon
                                          de Cessac</persName>, a Frenchman, now engaged in
                                    collecting archæological and other specimens of bygone years on
                                    the <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">Pacific
                                          coast</placeName> of <rs><placeName type="region"
                                                key="#re_northamerica">North</placeName></rs> and
                                          <placeName type="region" key="#re_southamerica">South
                                          America</placeName> for <rs><orgName type="museum"
                                                key="#mu_parismuseum">a Paris museum</orgName></rs>,
                                    finding many things on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                                          >island, San Nicolas</placeName>, similar to those
                                    previously collected in <placeName type="state" key="#st_or"
                                          >Oregon</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                                          key="#re_washingtonterritory">Washington
                                          Territory</placeName> and further north, and unlike
                                    anything found on either <rs><placeName type="region"
                                                key="#re_mld">the main land</placeName></rs> or
                                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the other
                                                islands</placeName></rs>. Also, the skulls and other
                                    bones of the human skeleton found there are unlike those found
                                    in other sections of <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal"
                                          >Southern California</placeName>. A notable observation is
                                    the absence of any evidence of syphilis, a striking contrast
                                    with other human bones found in this latitude.</span> I have had
                              the privilege of examining several skulls exhumed on <rs><placeName
                                          type="island" key="#i_chi">other islands</placeName></rs>
                              showing very plainly the ravages of this disease in those who have
                              passed away probably centuries ago.</p>
                        <p>Near her enclosure were several stakes, between which was stretched a
                              rope made of the seal sinews, supporting seal and sea elephant
                              blubber. And further on were three huts, made of whales' ribs, covered
                              with brush, but giving no evidence of having been lately occupied. By
                              signs and other means of communication she was made aware that they
                              wanted her to accompany them, and without any apparent hesitation, she
                              made ready to follow. She filled a basket&#8212;such as were common
                              among the Indians of this coast for packing on their backs&#8212;with
                              provisions, fishing tackle and other articles, and taking it on one
                              arm and a fire brand in the other hand she followed <rs><persName
                                          type="group"
                                          key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                          company</persName></rs>.</p>
                        <p>In their course to where <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                                          schooner</name></rs> lay at anchor they found a beautiful
                              spring of water issuing from the bank above the beach, under a
                              shelving rock. The cracks, or fissures, in this rock were stuck full
                              of bones, and there were other evidences of an encampment of
                                          <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone
                                          inhabitant of the island</persName></rs>. These bones were
                              used for nourishment, obtained by sucking; they were dried and
                              re-sucked many times, showing that occasionally she was put upon short
                              rations, but at the time of her discovery appeared to have an
                              abundance, such as it was. She retained all her teeth, but they were
                              worn low, supposed to be due to her chewing tough and solid articles
                              of food. Her age appeared to be about fifty years.</p>
                        <p>Further on was another spring near the beach, under the bank. Here she
                              indicated a desire to bathe, and was permitted to do so by the
                                          <rs><persName type="group"
                                          key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">balance of
                                          the party</persName></rs> retiring out of sight. After her
                              bath she joined <rs><persName type="group"
                                          key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                          others</persName></rs>, and went direct to the shore-boat
                              and thence to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                                          schooner</name></rs>. She was prevailed upon to abandon
                              her fire-brand and seal blubber before leaving the beach. Going aboard
                                          <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                                          schooner</name></rs>, she went directly to the stove and
                              warmed herself, indicating that she knew what the stove was for. She
                              ate heartily of the food of <rs><persName type="group"
                                          key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                          crew</persName></rs>, appeared to enjoy it, and it agreed
                              with her. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Mr.
                                          Brown</persName></rs> made her a skirt of ticking, with
                              which, and a sailor's cotton shirt and a black neck tie, her dress was
                              complete. She assisted in making her dress, but could not see to
                              thread her needle. Her sewing was quite rude. She appeared
                              much pleased with her new dress.</p>
                        <p>The following day she went ashore with <rs><persName type="group"
                                          key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                          men</persName></rs>, who made a separate shelter for her,
                              which she occupied about a month, the time spent on <rs><placeName
                                          type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                              otter hunting. She was quite industrious, carrying wood and water
                              without being asked. <span type="trope" n="10">She appeared contented
                                    and happy, frequently singing and chattering to herself.
                                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                                                >The men</persName></rs> could not understand what
                                    she said, nor she they, but <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                                key="#gni">Mr. N.</persName></rs> said it was truly
                                    wonderful how she could converse with them by signs.</span> She
                              occupied a portion of her time making water vessels of grass and
                              asphaltum, a substance plentiful both on <rs><placeName type="island"
                                          key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and <placeName
                                    type="region" key="#re_calcoast">shore of the main
                                    land</placeName>. The grass was plaited into a shape resembling
                              a demijohn, but wider at the top, and lined with asphaltum. She would
                              put in several small pieces of the last mentioned substance then drop
                              on them small stones or pebbles about the size of hulled walnuts,
                              heated sufficiently to melt the asphaltum, and grasping the neck with
                              both hands, the lower end on the ground, give it a rapid rotary motion
                              for several minutes and then empty the stones on the ground. The
                              vessels had a continuous coating on the inside, and are reported to
                              have been water tight, the lining even resisting the heat of the sun
                              when covered with water. She had both stone and earthen vessels in
                              which to boil water and cook if desired. To procure seal blubber she
                              could kill the seals with a club when on land sunning themselves, or
                              snare them with her sinew ropes. She obtained fire by rubbing two dry
                              sticks together. One of them partly flat, had a groove along its
                              entire length; the other was pointed and fitted into the groove, in
                              which it was rubbed rapidly backward and forward until it burned.</p>
                        <p><span type="trope" n="1">As usual a storm compelled <rs><persName
                                                type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva; #lw"
                                                >the party</persName></rs> to leave <rs><placeName
                                                type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                          island</placeName></rs>, and embarking with <rs><persName
                                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">their Island
                                                Queen</persName></rs>, soon found themselves at sea
                                    in a storm. She made signs that she could stop the storm, and
                                    obtaining permission she knelt on the deck facing the quarter
                                    whence the wind came, and commenced muttering something supposed
                                    to be a prayer. <span type="trope" n="10">She soon got up, and
                                          continued the prayer at intervals during the day,
                                          apparently without fear, and when the wind began to abate
                                          she turned to <rs><persName type="group"
                                                  key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                                                  >her fellow voyagers</persName></rs>, and with a
                                          smile made signs that her prayers had been
                                          answered.</span></span></p>
                        <p><span type="trope" n="10">When they came in sight of <placeName
                                          type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz
                                    Island</placeName>, off <rs><placeName type="region"
                                                key="#re_socalcoast">this coast</placeName></rs>,
                                    she told them by signs that it was an island, and indicated from
                                    there how she had seen, from <rs><placeName type="island"
                                                key="#i_sn">her island</placeName></rs>, ships pass
                                    up and down, but never land. Also, that she had seen the
                                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                                                >Nidever party</persName></rs> the previous day to
                                    her discovery as they passed to the head of <rs><placeName
                                                type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                          island</placeName></rs>. She was afraid to make herself
                                    known until she knew that there was no danger to her
                                    person.</span> There were many places of concealment on
                                          <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                          island</placeName></rs>, and unless taken unawares she
                              would have been hard to find.</p>
                        <p><span type="trope" n="3">As she was about to land at <placeName
                                          type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, an ox
                                    team passed, which so delighted her that she talked, laughed,
                                    danced, and gesticulated, and before that excitement ended
                                                <rs><persName
                                                key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh">a man on
                                                horseback</persName></rs> approached which gave her
                                    even more pleasure than the appearance of the ox team. At first
                                    it was supposed that she thought the man and horse constituted
                                    one animal; but, if so, the mistake was soon corrected, for on
                                    landing she went up to the horse and carefully examined it. The
                                    examination gave her additional pleasure; she would turn to
                                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                                key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                                                >her late companions</persName></rs> and laughing,
                                    request them to look at the horse. She straddled the thumb of
                                    the left hand by the two forefingers of the right, and moved
                                    them to represent the horse and <rs><persName
                                                key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh"
                                                >rider</persName></rs> as they passed along the
                                    beach.</span></p>
                        <p>She was taken to the <placeName key="#nideverhouse">house of Mr.
                                    Nidever</placeName>, where she became the center of attraction.
                                          <rs><persName type="group"
                                          key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The Mission
                                          Fathers</persName></rs> took a great interest in
                              her&#8212;sending to <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_losangeles"
                                          >Los Angeles</orgName></rs> and other places, hoping to
                              find some one who could converse with her, but failed. Even the
                                    <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_pepimaros"
                                    >Pepimaros Indians</orgName>, who were said to have had an
                              acquaintance with <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                          key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians on the
                                          island</orgName></rs>, could not understand her.</p>
                        <p><rs><persName type="group"
                                          key="#gni; #sni; #ini; #gnijr; #jacobni; #mrni; #mrfni"
                                          >The family of Mr. N.</persName></rs> became very much
                              attached to her, and although <rs><persName type="seaman"
                                          key="#fremontcpt">the captain</persName></rs> of the brig
                                    <name type="ship" key="#sh_fremont">Fremont</name> offered
                              largely for the privilege of taking her to <placeName type="city"
                                    key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> and placing her on
                              exhibition, it was refused; also an offer of a thousand dollars from
                                          <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#tru">another
                                          party</persName></rs> for a like purpose was refused.</p>
                        <p><span type="trope" n="3">Many people called on her and she received them
                                    kindly, but the afternoon was her favorite time for receiving
                                    calls; when she would put on her shag-skin dress and entertain
                                    her callers with a song-dance. She cared nothing for money,
                                    giving it to the children when given to her. She did not wish to
                                    sleep in a bed, and when in bed, did not desire bed covering,
                                    but was careful not to expose her person. Her manners were not
                                    rude, and in many things she was more refined than many who
                                    enjoy civilized privileges; yet in many things she was very much
                                    like a child. She wanted everything which she saw that appeared
                                    pleasant to the eye or seemed good to the taste, and if fruit
                                    was withheld from her she would plead for it in such a
                                    child-like manner that it was hard to refuse her.</span></p>
                        <p>When found, she was in excellent physical condition, strong and active;
                              but the eating of fruit and vegetables brought on a diarrhæa or
                              dysentery in about three weeks after she landed, and that, in
                              connection with an injury to the spine received by falling from a
                              porch, terminated her life four weeks later, or seven weeks from the
                              time she landed. During her sickness she reluctantly permitted
                                          <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#sni">her kind
                                          hostess</persName></rs> to dress her in flannel
                              underclothes, and took her bed under proper covering, but positively
                              refused to return to her former plain diet, as was proposed by some of
                              those who called to see her. Her dress of shag skins, basket and
                              trinkets were given to <rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#jru"
                                          >Father Gonzales</persName></rs>, of <rs><orgName
                                          type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">the
                                          Mission</orgName></rs>, who, it is said, sent them to
                                    <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>.</p>
                        <p>I may in a future letter give additional particulars concerning this
                              truly interesting personage.</p>
                        <byline><persName type="autho" key="#ast">A. B. STUART.</persName></byline>
                  </div>
            </body>
      </text>
</TEI>
