<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#overlandmonthly">Overland
                     Monthly</orgName></title>
               <editor><persName type="author" key="#bharte">Bret Harte</persName></editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
               <date when="1921-11"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Clifford1921">Hona Maria</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="13"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#jclif">Clifford,
                     Josephine</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Hona
                        Maria</persName></rs></title>
               <title type="sub"><emph>The story of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                           >this lonely Indian woman-hermit</persName></rs>, who lived entirely
                     alone for <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">eighteen
                           years</date></rs>, on one of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                           >the islands of the Santa Barbara Channel</placeName></rs>, is now but a
                     tradition with the present generation.</emph></title></head>
            <byline><hi rend="bold">Written by <persName type="author" key="#jcliff">Josephine
                     Clifford</persName> in <date when="1872">1872</date>.</hi></byline>

            <p>SOUTHWARD from the quaint town of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, beyond the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> Bay&#8212;with its high-arching isles, summery winds and the
               softened splendor of semi-tropical skies&#8212;five leagues out in the ocean, the
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">island of San Nicolas</placeName> lifts its
               brown, rugged outline from the surging waters. Hidden from <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> by <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz"
                  >Santa Cruz</placeName>, an island of greater magnitude, the sun seems to rise
               from the purpled rim of the waters, and to set where the golden seas meet the horizon
               of the golden skies. The waves wash far up the sloping, sandy shore, and, receding,
               leave bright shells, tangled kelp, and smooth, wave-polished stones. The seals sun
               themselves on the crystalized rocks, and gaze at the intruder with almost human eyes.
               The sea-wasps shake their delicate wings in the bright atmosphere; and strange birds
               call from the high branches of unfamiliar trees. Deep pools lie hidden in lonely
               gorges, and fold their secrets forever in theiir [sic] dark bosoms. The wild dogs
               bark from the shelving rocks, and, with uncanny faces dart into the close ravine.</p>
            <p>Years and years ago ere the energies of the white settlers had made their impress
               upon the wilderness along the Pacific shore, <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a tribe of Indians</orgName></rs> existed on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this now desolate
                  isle</placeName></rs>. Of what they thought, suffered, hoped or accomplished, we
               have only scanty tradition. Now and then a pirate's craft anchored along the quiet
               shore, and, departing, told no tale. <span type="trope" n="3">Sometimes the friendly
                  voice of <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the mission
                        fathers</orgName></rs> stole across the calm bay; and the shadow of the
                  Cross, planted in the wilderness, threw its benign influence even over
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                        undeveloped children of the sun</orgName></rs>.</span> But <rs><orgName
                     type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the Fathers</orgName></rs> sleep, and left
               no record.</p>
            <p>Thirty-six years ago the famine found <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this isolated band</orgName></rs>, and clutched
               them with its gaunt, relentless hand. The parched earth refused her sustenance; the
               trees stood bare and leafless in the hot wind; the streams ran dry, and the rocks
               glittered white and salt under the fervid sun. The wild game famished and died; and
               the fierce preyed upon each other. <span type="trope" n="3">With pitying horror,
                  these human beings stared into each other's faces, and, with stoical fortitude,
                  crawled away to die alone.</span> Whether <persName type="group"
                  key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the Mission Fathers</persName> learned of their
               distress, or whether urged by other motives, it is not known; but they fitted out
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a boat</name></rs>, which sailed to
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName> and brought away
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     survivors</orgName></rs>&#8212;eighteen in all. As the <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#bhagroup">rescued islanders</persName></rs> were brought
               down to the shore where <rs><placeName type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                     boat</placeName></rs> was anchored, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">one of the women</persName></rs>&#8212;who afterwards gave her name
               as <rs><persName type="nativeamerian" key="#lw">Hona
               Maria</persName></rs>&#8212;darted away, over the sandy shore, over rough rocks,
               through tangled ravines, with savage eagerness, to bring <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her only child </persName></rs> which, by
               some oversight, had been left behind. They waited for her re-appearance&#8212;they
               waited long. The skies darkened; the winds arose and tossed the unsteady boat from
               her frail anchorage, and <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">the reluctant
                     captain</persName></rs> was compelled to put out to sea; and <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Hona Maria</persName></rs> was left alone on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that desolate, sea-walled
                     isle</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>The thick fog shut down over the ocean, and the heavy swell of the waves tossed
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs> rapidly toward
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>. <span
                  type="trope" n="6"><rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">The rescued
                        Indians</persName></rs> were kindly cared for by the humane people of
                        <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName></rs>; but,
                  either from past suffering or the unaccustomed influences of civilization, they
                  died or dispersed to wilder surroundings.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="12"><rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The
                     boat</name></rs> was wrecked, preventing another expedition to <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>, and for years was
                  not replaced.</span>
               <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Hona Maria</persName></rs> was supposed
               to have died, and no heart turned to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     lonely island</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p><rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">Eighteen solitary
                  years</date></rs> had passed. <span type="trope" n="4">White faces peered over the
                  rocky battlement of mountains, and browned under the <placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_cal">California</placeName> sun. Avenues of communication and commerce
                  were opened, and the mysteries of <rs><placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">the
                        Golden State</placeName></rs> were penetrated. <persName type="frontiersman"
                     key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName>, a resident of <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, fitted <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_nidever">a schooner</name></rs> at <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName>, and, in one of his cruises, anchored at the
                  tragic island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>. On
                  wandering over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, he found traces of human life; ashes yet warm&#8212;a
                  footprint in the soil. But again the storm beat down upon the shore and compelled
                  the small crew to put to sea. With clear skies and becalmed seas they
                  returned.</span><span type="trope" n="1">Again, the smoldering fire&#8212;the
                  trace in the sand; and, after a short search, to their amazement <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Hona Maria</persName></rs>
                        herself&#8212;<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the Hermit
                        Monarch</persName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                        lonely isle</placeName></rs>! Without the least sign of surprise she gazed,
                  for the first time in <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high"
                        >eighteen years</date></rs>, upon human faces.</span><span type="trope"
                  n="10">In unintelligible language, but with expressive, savage gestures, she made
                  them understand that the dogs killed <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>.</span> This was the burden of her
               limited expressions&#8212;this longing for human sympathy amid her tragic
               desolation&#8212;bursting the bondage of unintelligible language, and making the
               grand sorrow of her savage heart known and felt.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1">A rude hut, constructed of interlaced branches, sticks and
                  leaves, constituted her shelter. A fantastic robe of gayly feathered birdskins,
                  neatly dressed and adroitly stitched with fine tendons, by the aid of needles
                  manufactured from fish bones, covered her dusky limbs, and another of brighter
                  hues were ready for time of need, or possibly reserved for her solitary festivals.
                  Many rude treasures, collected during her hermitage, were transferred to <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the boat</name></rs>, and afterward landed at
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</span> With
               astonishment she beheld <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName>. Her rapid glance took in the coast and the placid valley,
               girdled by the rugged mountains, sloping to the bay. From the narrow limits of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her island-home</placeName></rs>, the
               sea only was vast, stretching away beyond the range of vision. The boundless view of
               land presented a new and strange geographical development to her uneducated mind.
                  <span type="trope" n="3">A "<rs><persName key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh"
                        >solitary horseman</persName></rs>" galloping along the smooth beach caused
                  her ecstasies of delight, which she expressed in long, wild peals of laughter and
                  fantastic dances. A team with oxen completed her amusement.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="3">She observed the unfamiliar actions of people and animals
                  with child-like pleasure, yet never forgot <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lwchild">her lost child</persName></rs>, nor the horrible manner of
                  its death.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="3">She was proud of the attention she received, pleased with
                  gifts and kindness, like a child in a new creation.</span> She spoke a dialect
               entirely different from the native Spanish or Indians of the <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> region. A short time previous to her death,
               which occurred six months after her departure from <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">her native island</placeName></rs>, <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#natamwoman1">an Indian woman</persName></rs> was
               found who could interpret her strange tongue. She had not much to tell. A life more
               colorless, devoid of imagery or experience, it is impossible to conceive. The effect
               of long seclusion, upon her mind so crude and undeveloped, can not be conjectured. In
               her solitary abode she knew the ways of the birds of the air and the fishes of the
               sea, and fashioned nets to capture them, which, with seals and roots, furnished her
               sustenance.</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="seaman" key="#tru">Large sums of money</persName></rs> were
               refused by <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> for
               the possession of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                  woman</persName></rs>, as an attractive addition to a museum; but she was kindly
               guarded at his private residence, and in <date when="1853">1853</date> she passed to
               the spirit-land. <rs><persName key="#tbr">The Bishop</persName></rs> took possession
               of her ingeniously manufactured robes and carried them to <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>.</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Hona Maria</persName></rs> sleeps on
               the quiet hillside; and her strange fate, hitherto, has been a dim tradition.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
