<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#sbmag">Santa Barbara
                            Magazine</orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                    <date when="1988-07-01"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>,
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="article" key="#Howorth1988-Cave">The Cave of the Whales</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page" n="43"/><biblScope unit="page" n="64"/>
                        <author><persName type="author" key="#howorth">Howorth, Peter
                            C.</persName></author>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main">The <placeName type="region" key="#re_caveofwhales">Cave of
                            the Whales</placeName></title></head>
                <p>While pursuing the archaeological mystery of the magic stones on <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, <rs><persName
                            type="group" key="#klope; #conti; #gal; #howorth">our
                        team</persName></rs>&#8212;consisting of <persName type="author"
                        key="#klope">Klope</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#conti"
                        >Conti</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#gal">Allen</persName> and
                        <persName type="author" key="#howorth">myself</persName>&#8212;decides to
                    investigate a cavern known as the <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_caveofwhales">Cave of the Whales</placeName>. Sometime in the
                    distant past, the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName> adorned the walls of this
                    huge cavern with numerous paintings and carvings. We are aware that time and the
                    elements have also left their mark on sections of <rs><placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_caveofwhales">the cave</placeName></rs>. Before the images are
                    lost forever, we intend to photograph all the remaining rock art.</p>
                <p>As we enter the 40-feet-deep cave, we notice, chipped into rock, a shark-like
                    figure that guards the entrance. Inside, on the cave's walls, other
                    petroglyphs&#8212;images carved into stone&#8212;depict various sea creatures.
                    Dolphins, killer whales, sharks, swordfish&#8212;the strange etchings suggest
                    many different interpretations. One figure even looks like a goldfish.</p>
                <p>Whatever these figures may have represented to the <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>,
                    nearly all of them possess tall dorsal fins. These images prompted the
                    researchers who first documented the cave in <date notBefore="1956-01-01"
                        notAfter="1959-12-31">the late 1950s</date> to name the spot the <placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_caveofwhales">Cave of the Whales</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Not all of the art in <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_caveofwhales">the
                            cave</placeName></rs> represents marine animals; a double saw[-]toothed
                    line has been cut into the stone at the other side of the cave's entrance. Nor
                    are all the images on the cave's walls petroglyphs. Many
                    pictographs&#8212;painted images&#8212;have also survived.</p>
                <p>Surrounded by figures of leaping dolphins and killer whales, we begin to explore
                    every detail of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_caveofwhales">the
                            cave</placeName></rs>. Although we had first thought the cave interior
                    drab and colorless, our high-intensity lights reveal light green algae covering
                    the surface of the ceiling. I notice a harbor seal skull stashed deep in a
                    crevice, possibly left by some unknown artist to gnaw on as a snack. (The
                        <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Lone Woman</persName> was in the
                    habit of caching seal bones as reserve food supplies.)</p>
                <p>At the head of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_caveofwhales">the
                            cave</placeName></rs> I see a small hole just big enough for a person to
                    squeeze through. Beyond the opening, the sandy floor of a long tunnel stretches
                    into the distance. I clamber in, hoping to find more native rock art.</p>
                <p>After wriggling on my belly for some twenty feet, I come to the end of the
                    tunnel. I can see no paintings or inscriptions. Rolling over to look at the low
                    ceiling, I suddenly notice something moving.</p>
                <p>The ceiling is alive with spiders.</p>
                <p>Black widows and dark brown spiders of all sizes have taken a liking to the spot.
                    Dusty strands of web festoon the rock, hanging like Spanish moss. I don't linger
                    there long.</p>
                <p>Back in the main cavern, all the fearsome sea creatures seem like old friends.
                    Perhaps these animals were friends to the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>; to some tribes, such
                    animals were deities. At any rate, I doubt that the renderings represent hunting
                    activities since no weapons are depicted.</p>
                <p>After exploring the cave, <rs><persName type="group"
                            key="#klope; #conti; #gal; #howorth">our group</persName></rs> hikes to
                    a remote beach to examine a different example of native art&#8212;a three-masted
                    schooner carved into a flat sandstone rock. This petroglyph emerged when a sand
                    dune shifted less than two years ago. The vessel seems to float on a wavy line
                    incised below it. Behind the schooner is the nearly obliterated image of another
                    vessel. Behind this vessel, another wavy line suggests the sea.</p>
                <p>Who made the carving? An Indian or a European? I doubt that the artist was a
                    European because Europeans rarely left representational images. Instead they
                    favored to carve their initials and a date as a record of their visit. But to
                    the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                        >Nicoleños</orgName>, the vision of a huge sailing ship, especially a first
                    sighting, could well have seemed a supernatural event. For that matter, the
                    carving could represent a shipwreck, which would have seemed like a visit from
                    another world to <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                            key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the islanders</orgName></rs>.</p>
                <p>Indeed, history indicates that in <date when="1824">182</date>4&#8212;before the
                        <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                        >Nicoleños</orgName> were removed from <rs><placeName type="island"
                            key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>&#8212;the schooner <emph><name
                            type="ship" key="#sh_begg">John Begg</name></emph> stranded on a rock
                    that lies a short distance from the west end of <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. Could the carving have been a means of
                    recording this event?</p>
                <p>I wonder if the <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Lone
                            Woman</persName></rs> made the carvings, for she had every reason to
                    place importance on the passing of each ship. Moreover, legend has it that she
                    did record passing ships, although the story goes that she left her record in
                            <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_lwcave">a
                    cave</placeName></rs>.</p>
                <p>The identity of the artist who carved the ship petroglyph and the significance of
                    the <placeName type="region" key="#re_caveofwhales">Cave of the
                        Whales</placeName> may remain mysteries of windswept <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. But these images remind
                    us that no matter where we go on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                            island</placeName></rs>, the presence of the <orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName>
                    is with us. From the darkest cave to the most remote beach, we are never alone.
                    Despite the ravages of time and change, the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName> will not be forgotten.</p>
                <byline><persName type="author" key="#howorth">&#8212;P.C.H.</persName></byline>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
