<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#cincommtri">Cincinnati
                     Commercial Tribune</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="45"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="231"/>
               <date when="1885-05-18"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_cinci">Cincinnati</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_oh">Ohio</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#CincinnatiCommercialTribune1885">A Feminine Crusoe.
                     Eighteen Years on a Desert Island—How She Lived and Dressed</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="2"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#fwi">Fred Spalding
                     Witter</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">A <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">FEMININE
                        CRUSOE</persName></rs>.</title>
               <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold"><rs><date from="1835" to="1853">Eighteen
                           Years</date></rs> on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">a Desert
                           Island</placeName></rs>&#8212;How She Lived and
               Dressed.</hi></title></head>
            <byline><emph><rs><persName type="author" key="#fwi">San Francisco
                        Correspondence</persName></rs>
                  <title type="article" key="#Witter1885_DAC">Rochester
               Democrat</title></emph>.&#8212;</byline>
            <p>Seventy miles from <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the
                     shore</placeName></rs> is <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas
                  Island</placeName>, the sixth of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     group</placeName></rs> that cluster around the bay of <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara, California</placeName>. It is celebrated as having
               been the residence for <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs>, of
                     "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Lost Woman of San
                     Nicolas</persName></rs>." As her name is famous, and as her story has been told
               in romance I will give the sbare [sic] facts about her as I found them to be without
               any added ornament, and leave the fiction to the pen of the novelist.</p>
            <p>The <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Island of San Nicolas</placeName> was once
               densely populated[.] This is attested by the skulls and bones and other evidences of
               human abode that are found there. The <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#rfurcompany; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">Alaska Indians</orgName></rs>
               frequently visited <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs> to hunt for the furs of the sea otter. They took their
               women with them on these hunts, and on returning after the hunt was over they left
               them on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> to their
               fate. By order of <rs><orgName type="government" key="#gov_mexico">the
                     Government</orgName></rs> in <date when="1835">1835</date>
               <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the Indians</persName> were removed from
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. <span
                  type="trope" n="7">Just before they were to embark, and carry away every human
                  inhabitant, as it was supposed, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a
                        white Indian woman</persName></rs> begged for the privilege of going ashore
                  for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>,
                  which she had accidentally left.</span> She was gone a long time in a fruitless
               search for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                     offspring</persName></rs>. The wind blew a gale, the water was shallow, there
               was no one who was seeking <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost
                     one</persName></rs>. They set sail, intending to return for <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs>,
               but <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs> becoming
               unseaworthy she was left to her fate. It was generally known that there was
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> abandoned
               on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, but no
               attempt was made for her deliverance. As the world soon forgets, so <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs> was
               forgotten and the year passed away. <span type="trope" n="4"><rs><date when="1851"
                        >After a lapse of sixteen years</date></rs>
                  <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">a man</persName></rs> who landed on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> found
                  that</span> it was inhabited by some one. The footprints of a human being sunk
               deep in the ground were seen. The hardness of the ground was an indication that they
               had been made a long time. From their size they evidently belonged to a woman.
               Circular inclosures made of brush, six or seven feet through, were seen, where some
               one had lived. Near the huts were sticks driven in the ground and dried blubber
               hanging on them, thus prepared for food.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">In <date when="1852">1852</date>
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> was visited again and
                  another hunt was made for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        long-lost woman</persName></rs>. The huts were seen that had been seen
                  before, but the old blubber had been taken away and new food of the kind hung in
                  its place. Wild dogs were found which ran away at the approach of civilized man.
                  In a basket covered with seal skins that they found in a bush-heap was a dress
                  made of shag skins, cut in square pieces, a rope made of sinew and several smaller
                  articles, such as fish-hooks and bone needles. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #tje; #nativeamericans">The discoverers of these
                        proofs</persName></rs> that there lived on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">that island</placeName></rs> a human being scattered them on the
                  ground, and on their return they found them gathered together and placed in the
                  basket again.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4"><rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#ndur; #jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The Catholic fathers of the "Old
                        Mission,"</persName></rs> the foremost in every good word and work, offered
                  a reward to any one who would find <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                        >the lost woman</persName></rs>, and a third effort was made in <date
                     when="1853">1853</date> to discover <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">the prodigal</persName></rs> about whom there was such a mystery
                  and in whom the world of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">this
                        coast</placeName></rs> was beginning to take an interest. Fresh tracks of
                        <rs><placeName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</placeName></rs>
                  were found. They belonged to very small feet, and were like those that were seen
                  in the first attempt to find <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        woman</persName></rs>. Huts made of whale ribs and covered with brush were
                  discovered.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="4">At length an object was seen in the distance that appeared
                  to be moving. <span type="trope" n="4">Going toward it they saw <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> that for
                           <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> had reigned
                           <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Queen of San
                           Nicolas</persName></rs>, her subjects being the wild animals, her robe a
                     dress of bird skins she had made and her throne the hut she had built. She was
                     seated in an inclosure, so that only her head and shoulders could be seen. Two
                     or three dogs were about her that disappeared at the command of <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">their sovereign</persName></rs>. She was
                     seated on some grass that covered the ground and served her as a bed. Her dress
                     was neatly made of bird skins, extending to her ankles, the feathers of which
                     pointed downward. Her head was covered with a thick mat of yellowish brown hair
                     and her shoulders were bare. She was occupied in stripping blubber from a piece
                     of sealskin which she held across her knee and using for that purpose a knife
                     made of an iron hoop. In her hut was a fire, beside which she sat talking to
                     herself and, occasionally shading her eyes with her hand, looked at
                           <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        men</persName></rs> that were in search of her.</span></span>
               <span type="trope" n="4"><span type="trope" n="4"><span type="trope" n="3">She
                        received them with much courtesy, bowing and smiling and showing that
                              <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this lost child of
                              nature</persName></rs> had much of the politeness of a true
                        woman.</span> She took some roots in the bag, roasted them in the fire and
                     gave them to <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        men</persName></rs> to eat.</span> She gathered up all her food, which was
                  her chief concern, owing to the famines she had experienced, washed herself at the
                  spring, and followed <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs> cheerfully to <name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                     bot</name>.</span> On being taken to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> she manifested great delight on seeing the sights of
               civilization. She became a universal favorite, and was presented with many gifts.
               Passengers on <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_panama">the Panama steamer</name></rs>
               [t]hat landed there all wanted to see <rs><placeName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                     >the lost woman of San Nicolas</placeName></rs>. She related by signs her
               experience on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>,
               as she spoke a language that none of the Indians knew and none of <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the Spanish
                     fathers</persName></rs>, versed in Indian dialects, could understand. <span
                  type="trope" n="3">Civilization, which prolongs the life of some, shortened that
                  of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman of San
                        Nicolas</persName></rs>. An excessive love of fruit led to her death in
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> at the age of
                  fifty.</span> She was buried with the honors of <orgName type="church"
                  key="#ch_catholic">the Catholic Church</orgName> by the <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">Franciscan Fathers</persName></rs>, and
               her dress and trinkets were sent to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom"
                  >Rome</placeName> and placed in <rs><orgName type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum"
                     >that receptacle of the world's curiosities</orgName></rs>.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The story of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                        >the lost woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs> will always remain a
                  wonderment. Her ingenuity is seen in the pails she made of grass, made to [hold]
                  water by smearing them with melted asphaltum, and in her bird-skin dresses, her
                  bone needles, her knife of iron hoop and the language she invented and spoke. It
                  is inexplicable to all who have learned her story how a woman could live <rs><date
                        from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> on an island around which
                  the waves were beating a requiem to hope, getting her food and cooking it without
                  even those facilities which are common to the savage, and making her dresses
                  neatly without the aid of needles except what she carved out of bone.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="1">She laid aside one dress for <rs><date from="1835" to="1853"
                        >eighteen years</date></rs> to be worn when the white men should come, of
                  which she had a presentiment. She built her own house, protected herself from the
                  cold, gained supreme control over the wild beasts about her, and preserved her
                  love for men and women for well nigh two decades of human life alone in the wild.
                  With no previous knowledge of civilization, solitude appeared to have educated her
                  for it. An ordinary woman would have perished with despondency in such a desolate,
                  hungry, naked, shelterless outlook.</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
