<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="journal"><orgName type="publication" key="#cfquarterly">California
                     Folklore Quarterly</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor><persName type="author" key="#sbh">Hustvedt, S. B.</persName></editor>
               <editor><persName type="author" key="#atay">Taylor, Archer</persName></editor>
               <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue"> 1</biblScope>
               <date when="1944"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_berk">Berkeley</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Altrocchi1944">The Wild Girl of the Santa Barbara
                     Channel Islands</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="60"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#ral">Altrocchi, Rudolph</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <div>
            <head><title type="section">Notes and Queries</title></head>
            <p>[<persName type="group" key="#sbh; #atay">The editors</persName> will welcome as
               contributions to this section of the <emph><orgName type="publication"
                     key="#cfquarterly">California Folklore Quarterly</orgName></emph> either small
               items of traditional materials or inquiries designed to elicit information about such
               materials. In general, discussion of the materials here offered will be brief.
               Records of facts likely to be lost or overlooked, and inquiries which our readers may
               be able to answer&#8212;such items will be the typical ones.]</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="section">
            <head><title type="section"><emph><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Wild
                           Girl of the Santa Barbara Channel
               Islands</persName></rs></emph></title></head>
            <p>I was very much interested in Mr. Fife's communication in the <date when="1943-04"
                  >April, 1943</date>, issue (I, 149-150) about "<title type="article"
                  key="#Fife1943">The Wild Girl of the Santa Barbara Channel Islands</title>." Allow
               me a couple of remarks.</p>
            <p>In answer to Mr. Fife's question, whether any readers had heard similar versions,
               here is one that was told me in Santa Barbara in 1935.</p>
            <p>This time it was the story of <rs><persName key="#man14">a man</persName></rs> who
               had escaped from a civilized community to one of the islands west of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, preferring to live a wild,
               solitary life. I was given neither the reason nor the date. When he died, so the
               story goes, his relatives wanted to contest his will on the grounds that only an
               insane man would so take to the woods. <rs><persName key="#judge">The
                     judge</persName></rs> decreed, however, "that solitude and the desire for it do
               not necessarily constitute insanity"! I wonder whether this might not be a popular
               variant of the story of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the Santa
                     Barbara girl</persName></rs>, with change of sex, plus testamentary
               embellishments. If this case really happened, there might be a record of the judicial
               proceedings.</p>
            <p>As to her, I think she has little in common with such legends as that of <persName
                  type="fictional" key="#rom">Romulus</persName> and <persName type="fictional"
                  key="#rem">Remus</persName>. These boys were two of many abandoned babes, usually
               twins. For in antiquity when a woman had twins, that was considered proof positive of
               adultery, since one father can only beget one child at a time. Their lives were
               rescued by supernatural means, usually by an animal foster mother; their exploits
               spread through the folklore of many lands in many ages.</p>
            <p>Then there are the modern abandoned babes, reported from <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_in">India</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_africacon"
                  >Africa</placeName>, and even <placeName type="region" key="#re_europe"
                  >Europe</placeName>. Such unwanted children, when they survive, are usually
               subnormal, if not irretrievably bestial. A few, abandoned accidentally, survive by
               their extraordinary wits; chief example in fiction, <name type="fictional" key="#tar"
                  >Tarzan</name>. It so happens that I have made a rather elaborate study, soon to
               be published, of such folkloristic motives.</p>
            <p>As to the <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Santa Barbara
                  girl</persName></rs>, <title type="article" key="#Fife1943">Mr. Fife's
                  story</title> seems to be a rejuvenated version of the tale told, as the editorial
               footnote to his communication suggests, in the <title type="manuscript"
                  key="#Nidever1878"><emph>Life and Adventures of George Nidever</emph></title>. I
               might add that the story was also told, on the basis of Mr. Nidever's, in an old,
               melodramatic French book by <persName xml:lang="fr" type="author" key="#fde">
                  Ferdinand Denis</persName> and <persName xml:lang="fr" type="author" key="#vch"
                  >Victor Chauvin</persName>, <emph><title type="chapter" key="#DenisChauvin1863"
                     >Les vrais Robinsons</title></emph> (<placeName type="city" key="#ci_paris"
                  >Paris</placeName>, <date when="1863">1863</date>), pp. 312-314, as "<title
                  type="chapter" key="#DenisChauvin1863">L'Indienne de Santa Barbara</title>." As
               the title of the book indicates, it treats only of real people accidentally stranded
               in some uninhabited place <emph xml:lang="fr">a la</emph>
               <name type="fictional" key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name>. Quite correctly the
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Santa Barbara
                  woman</persName></rs> was included, for she was involuntarily "wild."</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14">As a matter of fact, she was not wild, in the sense, for
                  instance, of the "wild children." <span type="trope" n="3">On the contrary,
                     according to <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName>,
                     she was most tractable, even amiable, and always laughing.</span>
                  <span type="trope" n="8">She had in common with the "wild children" only the fact
                     that she was of unknown origin and spoke no known language; she had in common
                     with the Robinson Crusoes the accident of shipwreck, whereby, stranded alone in
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">a wild island</placeName></rs>,
                     she survived through her ingenuity and resourcefulness, even achieving a
                     certain contentment.</span></span> Such cases have been rather common,
               especially in the age of exploration, as <rs><persName type="group" key="#fde; #vch"
                     >the above-mentioned French compilers</persName></rs> prove.</p>
            <p>The <rs><persName key="#man14">Santa Barbara man</persName></rs>, on the contrary,
               represents the category of voluntary exiles. Some of them withdrew to the woods
               because of despair, caused by unrequited love. An example of this type was recently
               reported in <emph><orgName type="publication" key="#thetimes">Time</orgName></emph>
                  (<date when="1943-09-27">September 27, 1943</date>, p. 40), "El Tarzan" or
                  <persName key="#pbat">Pacifico Batista</persName>, of <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_itacuara">Itacuarare</placeName>, <placeName type="country" key="#co_arg"
                  >Argentina</placeName>. The photograph of this hairy wild man was reproduced in
                     <rs><orgName type="publication" key="#thetimes">the same
                  periodical</orgName></rs> (<date when="1943-10-11">October 11, 1943</date>, p.
               32). Pacifico's is also an ancient motive; for its exploitation in literature see,
               for example, <persName type="author" key="#jta">J. S. P. Tatlock</persName>, "The
               Lunatic Lover," in <emph>Essays and Studies</emph>, Vol. 14, University of California
               Publications in English (<date when="1943">1943</date>), pp. 43-48.</p>
            <p>I suppose that a classification of these various stories might well turn on the
               meaning of "wild." I see three categories of wild-living people: (1) <span
                  type="trope" n="3"><span type="trope" n="8">Civilized adults stranded accidentally
                     in an uninhabited place, usually an island; greatest example <name
                        type="fictional" key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name>, with many descendants
                     and even ascendants in both fact and fiction. To this category, I repeat,
                     belongs the <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Santa Barbara
                           woman</persName></rs>.</span></span> (2) Civilized adults who voluntarily
               take to the woods, because of love despair, like our friend <persName key="#pbat"
                  >Pacifico</persName>, because they are weary of civilization, like the
                     <rs><persName key="#man14">Santa Barbara man</persName></rs>. (We need not
               discuss here the pious withdrawal from the world of numerous medieval ascetics,
               martyrs, and saints). (3) Children exposed at birth or forsaken in infancy who
               survive by supernatural means, like <name type="fictional" key="#cyrus">Cyrus</name>,
                  <name type="fictional" key="#rom">Romulus</name> and <name type="fictional"
                  key="#rem">Remus</name>, and countless others, or by their wits (<name
                  type="fictional" key="#tar">Tarzan</name>, etc.), or by chance ("wild" children of
               modern times). This third category presents, I believe, a far more extensive
               development in folklore than the others, which, however, often occasion and
               accumulate folkloristic elements.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#ral">Rudolph Altrocchi</persName></p>
            <p><emph><orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucb">University of California,
                     Berkeley</orgName></emph></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
