<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#teachingchla">Teaching
                     Children's Literature: Issues, Pedagogy, Resources</orgName></title>
               <publisher>Modern Language Association of America</publisher>
               <editor/>
               <date when="1992"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_nyc">New York</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ny">New York</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Stott1992">Native American Narratives and the
                     Children's Literature Curriculum</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="47"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#jst">Stott, Jon C.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="excerpt">
            <p><supplied>[...]</supplied></p>
            <p>In presenting novels dealing with native peoples, instructors should notice a basic
               paradox. Traditional literatures were essentially communal. Tricksters, legendary
               heroes, and historical personages were important as they reflected cultural values
               rather than as individuals. Novels, on the other hand, deal with individual
               personalities. Thus we should be aware that, no matter how factually accurate an
               author may be in the treatment of physical and cultural traits of the characters, in
               dealing with the inner lives of specific characters and in methods of presentation,
               the writer of a children's novel about native peoples may be more influenced than he
               or she realizes by the attitudes and conventions of Western literature. This point
               may be demonstrated by comparing two novels by <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#sod; #jcge">nonnative writers</persName></rs> with two native
               writers.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName>'s <emph>Island of the Blue
                  Dolphins</emph> is the account of a California native girl's <rs><date from="1835"
                     to="1853" cert="high">eighteen years</date></rs> of isolation on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">an offshore island</placeName></rs>. In <emph>Julie
                  of the Wolves</emph>, <persName type="author" key="#jcge">Jean Craighead
                  George</persName> describes <rs><name type="fictional" key="#jul">a modern Alaskan
                     Eskimo girl</name></rs> surviving an arctic winter with the aid of a pack of
               wolves. Both are based on extensive research into the cultural and geographical
               aspects; however, in structure and presentation of <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#kar; #jul">the main characters</persName></rs>, both use conventions of
               the Western novel. As survival novels, they follow the pattern of separation,
               survival, rescue, and reunion. The greater part of each focuses on the physical and
               psychological endurance of the central character. "How to do it" chapters detail the
               ways the isolated individual remembers and utilizes the techniques of her culture to
               obtain physical necessities. Chapters centering on the inner life often reveal the
               character recalling the spiritual elements of the social group and understanding
               their value.</p>
            <p>Inherent in the conventions of the survival novel as they are used in these two books
               are adventure and psychological analysis. In life-threatening situations,
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#kar; #jul">the central
                  characters</persName></rs> must display considerable physical ability and inner
               courage. However, by the very nature of their situations, they are unique. They face
               inner and outer pressures not normally encountered by members of the culture. Thus,
               unlike traditional native narratives, <rs><persName type="group" key="#kar; #jul">the
                     characters</persName></rs> are not representative. As <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#kar; #jul">the central figures</persName></rs> in their
               novels, they are the subject of detailed study and their inner conflicts are fully
               presented. Filled with hatred of the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_aleuts">Aleuts</orgName>, who killed her father and brother, <rs><name
                     type="fictional" key="#kar">Karena</name></rs> [<name type="fictional"
                  key="#kar">Karana</name>], in <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>, must learn
               to overcome her intense loathing. <name type="fictional" key="#jul">Julie</name>, who
               is fleeing to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> in
               George's novel, comes to understand the value of the old ways, which she had
               originally scorned.</p>
            <p>In addition to conventions of the survival novel, <persName type="author" key="#jcge"
                  >George</persName> includes in <emph>Julie of the Wolves</emph> elements of
               pastoralism. The contrasts between a sullied, artificial, complex urban world
               representing progress, greed, anxiety, and ambition, and a rural world that is
               natural, pure, and calm, are reflected in that between <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ba"
                  >Barrow</placeName>, and <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ka">Kangik</placeName>,
               on the one hand, and the seal camp and the tundra, on the other. In the end,
                     <rs><name type="fictional" key="#jul">the heroine</name></rs> discovers that
               she cannot recover the ideal world and must return to <rs><name type="fictional"
                     key="#julfather">her father</name></rs>, who has capitulated to the values of
               civilization. <persName type="author" key="#jcge">George</persName> also incorporates
               aspects of the problem novel, a genre widely used in young adult fiction of <rs><date
                     notBefore="1970" notAfter="1992">the past two decades</date></rs>. Julie's
               difficulties are increased by government intervention, which disrupts her happy life
               by sending her to school and by attempting to send <rs><name type="fictional"
                     key="#julfather">her father</name></rs> to <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_viet">Vietnam</placeName>; by her uncle's alcoholism; by peer pressures
               to accept the modern ways; and by the failure of <rs><name type="fictional"
                     key="#julfather">her father</name></rs> to maintain his cultural integrity.</p>
            <p>Neither <persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> nor <persName
                  type="author" key="#jcge">George</persName> would claim to be presenting insiders'
               narratives; they are <rs><persName type="group" key="#sod; #jcge">knowledgeable and
                     sympathetic outsiders</persName></rs>. Two authors who do write from the inside
               are <persName type="author" key="#mpa">Markoosie</persName>, an <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_inuit">Inuit</orgName> from arctic
                  <placeName type="country" key="#co_can">Canada</placeName>, the author of
                  <emph>Harpoon of the Hunter</emph>, and <persName type="author" key="#jhi">Jamake
                  Highwater</persName>, the author of <emph>Anpao: An American Indian
               Odyssey</emph>, who until recently claimed to be of <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_blackfoot">Blackfoot</orgName>-<orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_cherokee">Cherokee</orgName> heritage. In
               both these works we see a mixture of novelistic techniques and conventions of
               traditional narratives. <emph>Harpoon of the Hunter</emph> is a naturalistic survival
               story in which <name type="fictional" key="#karmik">Kamik</name>, a young <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_inuit">Inuit</orgName>, travels with
               several other villagers in pursuit of a rabid polar bear. Although the other members
               of the party are all killed, he survives and is rescued. However, when several
               members of his family and <rs><name type="fictional" key="#karmikwife">his new
                     wife</name></rs> drown crossing broken river ice, he commits suicide, running
               himself onto his harpoon. <name type="fictional" key="#anp">Anpao</name> is a highly
               symbolic, almost surrealistic account of a young man's journey to the Sun. If the
               Sun, who is his father, will remove the scar <rs><name type="fictional" key="#anp"
                     >the youth</name></rs> wears on his face, he may return to earth to marry.
               However, when <name type="fictional" key="#anp">Anpao</name> returns to his village,
               he finds that the arrival of the white man signals destruction to his people. With
               his bride and a faithful few, he travels beneath the waters of a nearby lake, where
               life everlasting can be found.</p>
            <p><supplied>[...]</supplied></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
