<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#latimesmag">Los Angeles
                     Times Magazine</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <date when="1932-10-23"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#McGroarty1932">The Forgotten Woman of San Nicolas
                     Island</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="2"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#jmcg">McGroarty, John
                     Steven</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">SEEN FROM THE <emph>Green Verdugo Hills</emph></title></head>
            <opener><emph><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Forgotten Woman of San
                        Nicolas Isle</persName></rs></emph></opener>
            <byline>A Page Conducted by <persName type="author" key="#jmcg">John Steven
                  McGroarty</persName></byline>
            <p>THERE awhile back, who should hail us on a street of the roaring town but tall,
               young, broad-shouldered <persName key="#lat">Lyn Atkinson</persName>, the man who
               built the great <placeName key="#coolidgedam">Coolidge Dam</placeName> in <placeName
                  type="state" key="#st_az">Arizona</placeName> in jig time and put it there to stay
               until Gabriel blows his horn.</p>
            <p><rs><persName key="#conductor">Conductor</persName></rs>, said this <persName
                  key="#lat">Lyn</persName> to us, <rs><persName key="#conductor">Conductor of the
                     Synagogue</persName></rs>, he said, how would you like to voyage out to sea for
               a couple of days, or maybe three, or until the cows come home, in <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_ship1">a ship</name></rs> that I have?</p>
            <p>It was taking advantage of us. No time was at our disposal. The grindstone at home
               was waiting for our nose. Tethers were on our feet. Work upon which bread and butter
               depended stared us in the face. And, yet, with all that, here was <rs><persName
                     key="#lat">this young fellow</persName></rs> putting before us a temptation
               that we couldd not resist.</p>
            <p><rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_ship1">A ship</name></rs>, and the sea waiting for it.
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_ship1">A bonnie ship</name></rs> with a skipper
               and a cook and everybody else that a ship should have with it. And the blood of long
               generations of sailormen in our veins. The old Phoenicians for ancestors. The
               grindstone faded from memory, and the tethers fell from our feet. And so, with the
               evening tide, we put out to sea.</p>
            <p>Name your port and it is there that we shall sail, said <rs><persName key="#lat">the
                     master of the ship</persName></rs>. And then we saw an opportunity to fulfill
               and [an] old desire. Point her nose to the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Isle
                  of San Nicolas</placeName>, we answered. And <rs><persName key="#lat">the
                     master</persName></rs> said aye, aye, sir.</p>
            <p>It was of an early afternoon that we came upon the coast of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, the sea sunny and quiet as a lake, a great
               flock of gray gulls and pelicans to welcome us, and seals bobbing up, as full of
               curiosity as the proverbial cat.</p>
            <p>Now, in the old books of history and legend, you will see it said that the <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">Isle San Nicolas</placeName> is the loneliest and most
               desolate spot on all God's round earth. It was so spoken of by the earliest voyagers
               and is so spoken of still. And it is, in truth, one of the very loneliest of all
               places. Yet, shining there in the sun, and the wide blue sea around it, that Sunday
               morning, it seemed only as something very beautiful to us.</p>
            <p>We could discern no sign of human life anywhere. <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_ship1">Our ship</name></rs> had to stand well out to sea because of
               the vast beds of kelp that surrounded <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. And, besides, there is not the ghost of a harbor,
               even, on all its thirty miles of shore lines. But, suddenly through the glass,
                     <rs><persName key="#lat">the master</persName></rs> did see signs of life. Down
               to the shore a man came running, waving his hands in signal.</p>
            <p>It is <name type="fictional" key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name>, himself we said. And
               so, in great haste <rs><persName key="#lat">the captain</persName></rs> and
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#latgroup">the sailors</persName></rs> lowered
               a launch and we pushed through the winding channels of kelp to a shallow crescent of
               beach to greet the apparition.</p>
            <p>But he was no apparition at all. Instead he was a man from far-off <placeName
                  type="state" key="#st_me">Maine</placeName> whose home now is <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> where he dwells with a
               famlly, <rs><persName key="#woman1">a woman of Nebraska</persName></rs> for wife, a
               lovely blue-eyed child whose name is <persName key="#frances">Frances</persName>, and
               a Phoenician of the name of <persName key="#daly">Daly</persName> who helps with the
               sheep that pasture on the bleak, windswept hills.</p>
            <p>We had a happy day with them all, and the honor of their company for dinner on
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_ship1">the ship</name></rs>. And all the tales
               of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> they knew
               were told to us.</p>
            <p>We came at last to the one great story that <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName> has to tell&#8212;the story of <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the forgotten woman</persName></rs> who lived
               there alone through <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">eighteen
                     years</date></rs> of what must have been as deep a tragedy as the world has
               ever known. A tale long familiar to us, and to the scene of which we had now at last
               come.</p>
            <p>We could think of little else as the bright day fled. Of little else than
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this brown woman</persName></rs>
               left alone on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that loneliest of
                     isles</placeName></rs> through the long, dragging, desolate, tragic years.</p>
            <p>The way it was, <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the Franciscan
                     Padres of the Santa Barbara Mission</persName></rs>, long ago, learning that
               there was <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a
                     small tribe of Indians</orgName></rs> on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                  >San Nicolas</placeName>, sent <name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a
                  boat</name> to bring them to <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                  Mission</placeName> where they could be baptized in the Christian faith and bent
               to the uses of civilization.</p>
            <p>The feat was duly accomplished. But, as <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada"
                     >the boat</name></rs> was about to sail, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs> discovered that <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her baby</persName></rs> had been left
               behind. A storm was brewing. <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                     >The sailors</persName></rs> would not wait. <span type="trope" n="9">So,
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
                  plunged into the sea, swam to the shore and was left behind, not to be remembered
                  again until <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853">eighteen years</date></rs>
                  had passed.</span></p>
            <p>Then they found her. She had built a hut of whale bones covered with grass, and had
               woven a garb for her body from the feathers of birds. <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">The baby</persName></rs> she had risked
               her own life to save had died when still a baby. Then the <rs><date notBefore="1835"
                     notAfter="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> of a completely solitary life went
               on for her. Never a human voice in her ears, no human hand to touch, no companion
               save the birds and the animals of the sea. The same silent, voiceless sky above her
               day after day. Lost and desolate, with only God to know.</p>
            <p>They brought her then to <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the Mission at Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, poured the waters of Jordan on her head, and in one short
               month laid her in a quiet grave among the many graves that are there and which you
               can see when you go. A grave that was less lonely, indeed, than the living grave
               where she had apent those lonely, tragic years on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>.</p>
            <p>We submit this tale to women of <rs><orgName type="institution" key="#synagogue">the
                     Synagogue</orgName></rs> wherever they may be and who think their lot is hard.
               Let them consider <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman of San
                  Nicolas</persName>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
