<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#seahistory">Sea History
                     Magazine</orgName></title>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="145">145</biblScope>
               <editor/>
               <publisher><orgName type="publisher" key="#maritime">National Maritime Historical
                     Society</orgName></publisher>
               <date when="2013-11" from="2013-11" to="2014-01">Winter 2013-14</date>
               <pubPlace><placeName key="#dne"/></pubPlace>
               <note type="supplied">Source Note</note>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#King2013">Animals in Sea History" Sea Otter</title>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#rki">King, Richard</persName></author>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="40" to="41"/>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">Animals in Sea History</title> <title type="sub">SEA
                  OTTER</title></head>
            <byline>by <persName type="author" key="#rki">Richard King</persName>
            </byline>
            <div type="section" n="1">
               <p>Scott O’Dell’s famous young-adult novel, <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>,
                  tells the tale of a Native American girl named <rs><name type="fictional"
                        key="#kar">Karana</name></rs>. She lives alone on <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, one of the more distant of the
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> off
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">the coast of southern
                     California</placeName>. Early in the story, <name type="fictional" key="#kar"
                     >Karana</name> stands on a cliff and watches men who have sailed here from
                     <placeName type="state" key="#re_russam">a distant country</placeName>:</p>
               <p>The wide beds of kelp which surround <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">our
                        island</placeName></rs> on three sides come close to the shore and spread
                  out to sea for a distance of a league. In these deep beds, even on days of heavy
                  winds, <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">the
                     Aleuts</orgName> hunted. They left the shore at dawn in their skin canoes and
                  did not return until night, towing after them the slain otter.</p>
               <p>The sea otter, when it is swimming, looks like a seal, but is really very
                  different. It has a shorter nose than a seal, small webbed feet instead of
                  flippers, and fur that is thicker and much more beautiful. It is also
                  different in other ways. The otter likes to lie on its back in the kelp beds,
                  floating up and down to the motion of the waves, sunning itself or sleeping. They
                  are the most playful animals in the sea.</p>
               <p><persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott O’Dell</persName> is historically and
                  biologically accurate with much of his novel. He based <name type="fictional"
                     key="#kar">Karana</name> on the true story of <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> who was stranded on
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>
                  <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853">for more than 20 years in the early
                        1800s</date></rs>. But who were <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_aleuts">the Aleuts</orgName>? What were they doing hunting otters
                  here? And would someone in <rs><date notBefore="1800" notAfter="1899-12-31">the
                        1800s</date></rs> have actually thought of sea otters as cute and
                  playful&#8212;as so many of us do today?</p>
               <p><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">The Aleuts</orgName>, or
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">the
                     Aleutians</orgName>, were native hunters from <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_aleutian">the Aleutian Islands</placeName>, which stretch into the far
                  North <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">Pacific</placeName> beyond
                     <placeName type="state" key="#st_ak">Alaska</placeName>. Russian sea captains
                  who sailed past <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_aleutian">these
                        islands</placeName></rs> on their way to <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_nacoast">the coast of North America</placeName> recruited them because
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">the
                     Aleutians</orgName> were skilled in hunting all types of marine mammals with
                  spears from kayaks. The Russians wanted seals, sea lions, elephant seals, and sea
                  otters for meat, blubber, and their beautiful and valuable pelts.</p>
               <p>Russians began hunting seals and sea otters in <rs><date notBefore="1720">the
                        mid-1700s</date></rs>, when they first began exploring the <rs><placeName
                        type="group" key="#i_aleutian; #i_ko">islands of the North
                        Pacific</placeName></rs>. They seem to have killed&#8212;and brought home at
                  great profit&#8212;far more animals than <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_aleuts">the Aleutians</orgName> or Native Americans in the Pacific
                  Northwest had hunted in previous centuries. As animals grew more and more scarce,
                  they sailed their ships farther and farther south, until they were nearly to
                     <placeName type="group" key="#re_upcal">Mexico</placeName>. They searched
                  around <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> off
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">this
                     coast</placeName></rs>, such as <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName>. The extraordinarily dense fur of the sea otter fetched an
                  exceptionally high price at the time, especially when trading with merchants in
                     <placeName type="country" key="#co_china">China</placeName>.</p>
               <p>In <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>, <name type="fictional" key="#kar"
                     >Karana</name> at one point nurses a young sea otter back to health. She names
                  the otter "<name type="fictional" key="#mon">Won-a-nee</name>," or "Girl with the
                  Large Eyes," and goes on to see her living back in the wild as a mother. <name
                     type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name> says: "After that summer, after being
                  friends with <name type="fictional" key="#mon">Won-a-nee</name> and her young, I
                  never killed another otter. I had an otter cape for my shoulders, which I used
                  until it wore out, but never again did I make a new one." <persName type="author"
                     key="#sod">O’Dell</persName> wrote this novel in <date when="1960">1960</date>,
                  about the time that Americans were growing more environmentally aware&#8212;the
                        <rs><date when="1970-04-22">first Earth Day</date></rs> was only a decade
                  away. This does not mean, though, that people in earlier centuries did
                  not consider the sea otter as cute as a puppy. West Coast Native Americans,
                  according to one source at least, portrayed the sea otter in stories as a playful
                  trickster and even as symbol of good luck.</p>
               <p>Early Russian explorers also seem to have considered sea otters as fun-loving,
                  even while they hunted them. The <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#beringexpedition">men of the Bering expedition</persName></rs> in
                     <date when="1741">1741</date> ate the meat from hundreds of sea otters and
                  skinned them for their fur. Naturalist <persName key="#gst">Georg Wilhelm
                     Steller</persName> served up a baby sea otter to heal <rs><persName
                        key="#exleader">his ailing expedition leader</persName></rs>. Yet <persName
                     key="#gst">Steller</persName> saw the otter as an "extraordinarily beautiful
                  and pleasant animal, as well as amusing and comical in its habits." <persName
                     key="#gst">Steller</persName> added: "Not even the most loving human mother
                  engages in the same kind of playing with her children...when the young are taken
                  from them, they cry aloud like a little child and grieve."</p>
               <p>Can you think of any other animal today that we eat and use for products, yet also
                  think of as adorable?</p>
               <p>Hunters and habitat loss rendered sea otters almost extinct along <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_nacoast">the coast of North America</placeName> by
                        <rs><date notBefore="1850" notAfter="1900">the late 1800s</date></rs>. Sea
                  otter populations have since begun to return, but slowly. They remain on the
                  endangered species list. Novels such as <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>
                  teach us about our history with these animals&#8212;and remind us to protect
                  them.</p>
               <p>In the next issue of <title><orgName type="publication" key="#seahistory"
                           ><emph>Sea History</emph></orgName></title>: a Columbia River
                     <emph>dinosaur fish</emph>? For past "Animals in Sea History," go to
                  www.seahistory.org.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
