<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="monograph"><orgName type="publication">Western Americana: Frontier
                     History of the Trans-Mississippi West, 1550-1900</orgName></title>
               <publisher>Research Publications</publisher>
               <editor/>
               <date when="1883"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_nhaven">New Haven</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ct">Caonnecticut</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="monograph" key="#Dawson1901">"Chapter IV. Otter Hunting On the Santa
                     Barbaras," in "California in '41. Texas in '51. Memoirs." </title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="62"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#nda">Dawson, Nicholas</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head><title type="main"> CHAPTER IV.</title></head>
            <div n="1" type="epigram">
               <p>Some of Dye's shipments to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        islands</placeName></rs> proving unremunerative from the great waste in
                  handling such brittle lumber, he closed out the business at <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>. He decided to try otter or
                  seal hunting, and invited me to join him. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#dawsongroup">Our outfit</persName></rs> consisted of three boats,
                  similar to whale boats, and was made by <persName type="frontiersman" key="#jdy"
                     >Dye</persName> himself. They were clinker built, some fifteen feet long, and
                  carried three men each: the hunter on the front seat, with three rifles and a
                  paddle; a hand in midship with a paddle; and a steersman behind, with a paddle and
                  a mast and sail to use when desired. We took provisions and ammunition in the
                  boats.</p>
               <p>Setting out with <persName type="frontiersman" key="#jdy">Dye</persName> as hunter
                  in one boat, I in another, and a man by the name of <persName type="frontiersman"
                     key="#sim">Simmons</persName> in in [sic] the third, we coasted from <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName> down to <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and out to and around <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName> and <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">San Miguel Islands</placeName>, killing a few otter.</p>
               <p>Our mode of procedure was this: We traveled by sail or paddle to a place where
                  otters were known to be found, and waited for a favorable day. Very few spots
                  suitable for camps were found. There must be fresh water, and a place where the
                  boats can land through the surf without capsizing. We often ventured to land at
                  spots where it was risky. This we did by approaching and waiting for a big roller;
                  then, by vigorous strokes&#8212;the steersman keeping her bow straight on&#8212;we
                  would go in on top of it, and be sent so far up as to give time to unload and
                  carry boat and all up out of the reach of succeeding billows.</p>
               <p>The otter were found lying on the kelp with only the head in sight, and always in
                  bunches, or schools. They are shot in the head, and can best be hunted when the
                  water is still. Approaching noiselessly and placing our boats so that the otter
                  were in the center, we would begin the battle, loading and firing rapidly until
                  the otter were all scattered. Then, picking up our game, we would give chase to
                  one of the runaways. Here the difficulty was in keeping track of the game, as they
                  travel under the water and only come to the surface for breath. The hunter has
                  seen the direction of the dive and paddles in that direction, ready to fire when
                  the otter's head comes above the surface. The chase is kept up until the otter is
                  killed or the trail lost; then if no other otter can be started, the hunt is up;
                  and as soon as skinning, fleecing, and drying is through with, a travel is made to
                  another locality.</p>
               <p>Otter hunting is a very exciting business, and somewhat dangerous, as you are apt
                  to think when you hear a bullet whistle past you, it having glanced from a wave as
                  it came from a hunter's gun opposite, who had shot at an otter on a line between
                  you and him. But these risks will be run for an otter skin, worth thirty dollars,
                  and especially when there is rivalry among the hunters.</p>
               <p>At <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> we found an old
                  otter hunter, <persName key="#abt">A. B. Thompson</persName>, who had formerly
                  been in the business with vessels and <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">Alaska Indians</orgName></rs>, and who
                  proposed to go into partnership with us on the halves&#8212;he to furnish a vessel
                  officered and manned, and to provision us; we to furnish boats, guns and
                  ammunition and do the hunting. His offer was accepted; and two Santa Barbara
                  hunters, <persName type="investor" key="#isp">Sparks</persName> and <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nydever</persName>, joined in with us, making,
                  with <persName type="frontiersman" key="#jdy">Dye</persName>, <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#sim">Simmons</persName> and <persName type="author"
                     key="#nda">myself</persName>, five boats. The advantage in having a vessel was
                  that with water and provisions on board the hunters could be lowered at any point,
                  the vessel cruising around until we got through, and in this way places
                  inaccessible for boats could be hunted.</p>
               <p>We first visited <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas
                     Island</placeName>, and, hunting around it, killed several otter. Here we
                  searched on shore for a <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">lone
                        woman</persName></rs> whom we knew to be on the island, but failed to find
                  her, although we found her tracks. Why she was there I had best explain:</p>
               <p>Such of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Santa Barbara
                     Islands</placeName> as had fresh water on them had once been inhabited by a low
                  type of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                        >Indians</orgName></rs>, who eked out a miserable existence by fishing for
                  and eating shellfish. Some were induced to emigrate and join <orgName
                     type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the missions</orgName>, but a remnant
                  remained, and these being about to perish from starvation, an effort was made,
                  headed by the <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats"
                        >priests</persName></rs>, to have them all transported to the <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">mainland</placeName>. <span type="trope" n="9"
                           ><rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">A vessel</name></rs> was
                     sent, and at <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>,
                     after all were on board, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this
                           woman</persName></rs>, from some freak, jumped overboard and swam
                     ashore.</span> A southeast storm coming on, <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#chu; #isp">the captain</persName></rs> made sail without further
                  search. (Since that time I have seen an account of her rescue by <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nydever</persName> and <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charley Brown</persName></rs>, both of whom I
                  knew. They found her while they were on an otter hunt, and carried her to the
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">mainland</placeName>, where she soon
                  died from overeating.)</p>
               <p>On the brig <name type="ship" key="#sh_bolivar">Bolivar</name>, we hunted all
                  points along <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja">Lower California</placeName>
                  to <placeName type="island" key="#i_cerros">Ceros Island</placeName>, then, otter
                  giving out, we abandoned the hunt and beat back against headwinds to <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. Here a general division and
                  setlting up was effected, and I found myself with forty dollars in money and five
                  or six otter skins, a broken arm, and my feet so badly bruised that I could
                  scarcely walk on crutches.</p>
               <p>My physical condition happened in this way: <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_bolivar">The vessel</name></rs> had dropped us on <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_cerros">the island of Ceros</placeName> to hunt, if
                  favorable weather intervened, while she made further search below for otter. The
                  weather continuing boisterous, part of us set out to traverse <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_cerros">the island</placeName></rs> on foot. Soon
                  after we left camp I, in order to get a shot at some spotted seals, ventured too
                  near the brink of a projecting point. My feet flew up, I could find nothing to
                  grasp, and I went over. But I yelled, gave my gun a cast that it might fall flat,
                  and straightened my legs under me to lessen the shock. I do not know how far I
                  fell, but when I came to, my <rs><persName type="group" key="#dawsongroup"
                        >comrades</persName></rs> were around me, I was on a bed of sand, and all
                  around were big rocks detached from the cliff above. On examination it was found
                  that my left arm was broken, and my feet and legs so bruised that I could not
                  walk. One man went back to camp for a sail, from which a litter was made, and I
                  was carried to camp. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#jdy">Dye</persName>
                  attempted to set my arm, but it remains till now a little crooked, and weaker than
                  the other. My feet and ankles, though bloodshot for awhile [sic], in time became
                  as sound as ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
