<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#rochestordemocrat">Democrat
                     and Chronicle</orgName></title>
               <biblScope unit="volume">53</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">88</biblScope>
               <editor/>
               <publisher/>
               <date when="1885-03-29"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_roc">Rochestor</placeName><placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ny">New York</placeName></pubPlace>
               <note type="supplied">Source Note</note>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Witter1885_DAC">Sanitarium of the West. Rambles About
                     San Francisco and Down the Pacific Coast. Stories of Spanish Fathers. Barbara,
                     the Saint--The Lost Woman of San Nicolas--Remains of the Old Museum--Traces of
                     the Mound Builders--Golden Gate.</title><author><persName type="author"
                        key="#fwi">Fred Spalding Witter</persName></author>
                  <note type="supplied">Document Note</note>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">SANITARIUM OF THE
                        WEST</placeName></rs></title>
               <title type="sub">Rambles About <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                     Francisco</placeName> and Down <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">the
                     Pacific Coast</placeName>.</title>
               <title type="sub">STORIES OF <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats"
                        >SPANISH FATHERS</orgName></rs></title>
               <title type="sub"><persName key="#barb">Barbara</persName>, the
                        Saint&#8212;<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The Lost Woman of
                        San Nicolas</persName></rs>&#8212;Remains of the Old Museum&#8212;Traces of
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_moundbuilders">the Mound
                     Builders</orgName>&#8212;<placeName type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate"
                     >Golden Gate</placeName>.</title></head>
            <byline><emph>Correspondence of the <orgName type="publication" key="#rochestordemocrat"
                     >Democrat and Chronicle</orgName></emph>.</byline>
            <dateline><rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">SAN FRANCISCO</placeName></rs>, <date
                  when="1885-03-14">March 14, 1885</date>.&#8212;</dateline>
            <p><rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">The early Spanish
                  fathers</orgName></rs> of <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">the Pacific
                  coast</placeName> gave the missions [sic] towns they founded the names and
               patronage of particular saints that had become worthy of a place in their calendar.
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> was called in honor
               of <persName key="#fran">Saint Francis</persName>, <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> from <persName key="#pete">Saint
                  Peter</persName>, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>,
               which is popularly known as <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">the sanitarium of
                     the Pacific coast</placeName></rs>, by reason of the medicinal properties in
               its climate, bears the name of <persName key="#barb">Barbara</persName>, the saint.
               She was an only child, of great beauty and intelligence. <persName key="#dio"
                  >Descorus</persName>, her father, was an idolater, of noble birth and great
               wealth. <persName key="#dio">Descorus</persName> shut her up in a tower to monopolize
               her affections. He gave her musical instruments and tutors, and fitted up her
               apartments gorgeously. Through a tract, she learned of <persName key="#ori"
                  >Origen</persName>, with whom she found means to communicate and by whom she was
               converted and baptised. <rs><persName key="#dio">Her father</persName></rs> wanted
               her to marry <rs><name type="fictional" key="#man13">a distinguished man of the
                     time</name></rs>, but <persName key="#barb">Barbara</persName> opposed it so
               persistently that he gave it up for a time. On his subsequent return from a long
               journey, he repaired to the tower and asked <rs><persName key="#barb">his
                     daughter</persName></rs> if she would relent and marry the man, when she gave
               him the touching reply that her love for him would not permit her to leave him in his
               old age for a husband. The answer so pleased <rs><persName key="#dio">the idolatrous
                     parent</persName>
               </rs>that he released her from the tower and took her home. On entering her father's
               house and finding it filled with idols, she inquired, "Of what use are these
               ridiculous puppets!" <persName key="#dio">Descorus</persName> upbraided her for her
               want of respect for the gods, and gave her up to punishment for her Christianity. The
               judge tried to shake her faith in the religion of Jesus, but she clung firmly to a
               faith that was [has] taught so many how to live and how to die. <rs><persName
                     key="#dio">Her father</persName></rs> asked to be her executioner, and as soon
               as <rs><persName key="#dio">this unnatural and inhumane parent</persName></rs> had
               struck off her head he fell dead at her feet. Such is the affectious story of
                  <persName key="#barb">Barbara</persName>, a martyr of hystory [history] who has
               given her name and memory to <rs><persName type="city" key="#ci_sb">one of the most
                     beautiful cities</persName></rs> on <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_paccoast">this coast</placeName></rs>. She suffered martyrdom in the
               reign of <persName key="#max">Maximus I</persName>. She is a star of the first
               magnitude in the constellation of saints, and is honored with particular devotion in
               the Latin, Greek, Muscovite and Syriac calendar.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1">Nature has made <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName> beautiful for situation, as the person, life and character
                  of <rs><persName key="#barb">the saint</persName></rs> were whose name it bears. A
                  combination of ocean, bay, mountain, vale, hill, climate and sky contributes to
                  this. <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">The Pacific coast</placeName>
                  which trends from the northwest to the southeast, makes an abrupt turn at
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName>, and runs
                  directly east one hundred miles, so that <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName> sets [sits] a queen on that shore with her feet in the bay
                  and her face to the south and the ocean.</span> The <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_santaynezmts">Santa Ynez mountains,</placeName> 3,500 feet high, are
               parallel to that shore, a few miles north of it, standing like a long row of
               sentinels to watch and defend it. The long narrow valley between them and the sea is
               fifty miles long and five wide, protected from the cold winds of the north by the
               mountains, and from the damp fogs and winds of the ocean by the mountainous islands
               of the shore. In that favored and protected spot of earth, known as <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_sbvalley">Santa Barbara valley</placeName> the climate has
               an average of 54° in winter, 60° in spring, 68° in the summer, all the seasons of the
               year being one even-tempered sweetness, long drawn out. It is a climate that will
               beat <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mentone">Mentone</placeName> in the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_sfrance">south of France</placeName>, or <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_venice">Venice</placeName>, "<rs><placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_venice">the pride of the sea</placeName></rs>," or <placeName
                  type="country" key="#co_greece">Greece</placeName>, the summer land of eloquence,
               poetry and song. <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, a
               town of 5,000 inhabitants, with its palatial residences, adobe houses, masts of
               trade, cultured inhabitants, air redolent of perfume, and the everlasting bloom of
               its roses, lies between the mountains on the one side and the Mega on the other,
               which intervenes between it and the sea.</p>
            <floatingText>
               <span/>
               <body>
                  <lg type="trope-group" n="1">
                     <l>"In the fairest of valleys, on an evergreen shore,</l>
                     <l>By mountains walled in and an ocean before,</l>
                     <l>With her brow on the hills and her feet to the sea;</l>
                     <l><rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName></rs>
                        stands&#8212;the queen that's to be.</l>
                     <l>'Tis the land of all lands where Flora in pride</l>
                     <l>Each month of the year has a rose by her side.</l>
                     <l>Flowers, bright-hued, most fragrant and rare,</l>
                     <l>Like rainbows entwining her, perfuming the air."</l>
                  </lg>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>That which adds health to the climate and gives interest to the scenery of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> are <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> that rest on the placid
               bosom of <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the Pacific</placeName>, over
               which nature has thrown a garment of enchantment. One never wearies looking at their
               smoky, hazy outlines. They are like so many angelic [countenances?] and watch over
               the interests of [?], amusement and commerce. The first in order is the <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa island</placeName>, which is next to the
               largest. <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz island</placeName> is the
               largest, having in it 60,000 acres. It is twenty-seven miles from the shore, and upon
               it are 50,000 sheep. It is particularly adapted to sheep raising as it is free from
               the [?] weed, which is such a detriment to [w]ool growing. There they are allowed to
               [ro]am at will and are rounded up twice a year [at] shearing time. <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> has a very [go]od harbor in
               which ships may anchor safely in a storm. <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">The
                  Anna Capas</placeName> are [th]ree in number&#8212;a trio sisterhood of islands.
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">[San] Miguel</placeName> and <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scatalina">San[ta] Catalina</placeName> are among
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">[these] emerald
                  jewels</placeName></rs> of <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the Pacific
                  ocean</placeName>. [Seve]nty miles from the shore is <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas island</placeName>, the sixth of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the group</placeName></rs> that cluster [around] the
               Bay of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. It is
               [celeb]rated for having been the residence for <rs><date notBefore="1835"
                     notAfter="1853" cert="high">[eighte]en years</date></rs> of "<rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The lost woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs>."
               As her name is famous, and as [her sto]ry has been told in romance, I will give the
               bare facts about her as I found them to be without any added ornament, and leave the
               fiction to the pen of the novelist.</p>
            <p>The island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> was once
               densely populated. This is attested by the skulls and bones and other evidences of
               human abode that are found there. The <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#rfurcompany; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">Alaska Indians</orgName></rs>
               frequently visited <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs> to hunt for the furs of the other [otter]. They took their
               women with them on these hunts, and on returning after the hunt was over, they left
               them on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> to their
               fate. By order of <rs><orgName type="government" key="#gov_mexico">the
                     government</orgName></rs> in <date when="1835">1835</date>, <persName
                  type="group" key="#bhagroup">the Indians</persName> were all removed from
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. <span
                  type="trope" n="7">Just before they were to embark, and carry away every human
                  inhabitant, as it was supposed, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a
                        white Indian woman</persName></rs> begged for the privilege of going ashore
                  for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>,
                  which she had accidentally left.</span> She was gone a long time in a fruitless
               search for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                     offspring</persName></rs>. The wind blew a gale, the water was shallow, there
               was no one who was seeking <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost
                     one</persName></rs>. They set sail, intending to return for <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs>,
               but <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs> becoming
               unseaworthy, she was left to her fate. It was generally known that there was a woman
               abandoned on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>,
               but no attempt was made for her deliverance. As the world soon forgets, so
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman of San
                     Nicolas</persName></rs> was forgotten as the years passed away. <span
                  type="trope" n="4">After <rs><date when="1851">a lapse of sixteen
                     years</date></rs>, <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">a
                        man</persName></rs> who landed on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                        >the island</placeName></rs> found that it was inhabited by some one. The
                  footprints of a human being sunk deep in the ground that was dry and hard, were
                  seen. The hardness of the ground was an indication that they had been made a long
                  time. From their diminutive size they evidently belonged to a woman. Circular
                  inclosures, made of brush, six or seven feet through were seen, where someone had
                  lived. Near the huts were sticks driven in the ground and dried blubber hanging on
                  them, thus prepared for food.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">In <date when="1852">1852</date>
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> was visited again,
                  and another hunt was made for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        long lost woman</persName></rs>. The huts were seen that had been seen
                  before, but the old blubber had been taken away, and new food of the kind hung in
                  its place. Wild dogs were found which ran away at the approach of civilized man.
                  In a basket covered with seal skins that they found in a bush-heap was a dress
                  made of shag skins, cut in square pieces, a rope made of sinew, and several
                  smaller articles, such as fish hooks and bone needles. <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni; #tje">The discoveries [discoverers] of these
                        proofs</persName></rs> that there lived on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">that island</placeName></rs> a human being, scattered them on
                  the ground, and on their return they found them gathered together and placed in
                  the basket again.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">
                  <rs><persName type="group" key="#ndur; #jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The
                        Catholic fathers of the "Old mission,"</persName></rs> the foremost in every
                  good word and work, offered a reward to anyone who would find <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost woman</persName></rs>, and a third
                  effort was made in <date when="1853">1853</date> to discover <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the prodigal</persName></rs> about whom
                  there was such a mystery, and in whom the world of <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_paccoast">this coast</placeName></rs> that had forgotten, was
                  beginning to take an interest. Fresh tracks of <rs><placeName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</placeName></rs> were found. They
                  belonged to very small feet and were like those that were seen in the first
                  attempt to find <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                     woman</persName></rs>. Huts made of whale ribs and covered with brush were
                  discovered. At length an object was seen in the distance that appeared to be
                  moving. <span type="trope" n="1">Going towards it, they saw <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> that for
                           <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> had
                     reigned queen of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>,
                     her subjects being the wild animals, her robe a dress of bird skins she had
                     made, and her throne the hut she had bullt [sic], she was seated in an
                     inclosure so that only her head and shoulders could be seen. Two or three dogs
                     were about her that disappeared at the command of <rs><persName
                           type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">their sovereign</persName></rs>. She was
                     seated on some grass that covered the ground and served her as a bed. Her dress
                     was neatly made of bird skins extending to her ankles, the feather[s] of which
                     pointed downward. Her head covered with a thick mat of yellowish brown hair,
                     and her shoulders rounded in their fullness, were bare. She was occupied in
                     stripping blubber from a piece of sealskin which she held across her knee, and
                     using for that purpose a rude knife made of an iron hook. In her hut was a fire
                     beside which she sat talking to herself, and occasionally shading her eyes with
                     her hand, looked at <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        men</persName></rs> that were in search of her. <span type="trope" n="3">She
                        received them with much courtesy, bowing and smiling and showing that
                              <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this last child of
                              nature</persName></rs> had much of the politeness of a true
                        woman.</span> She took some roots from a bag, roasted them in the fire and
                     gave them to <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        men</persName></rs> to eat.</span> She gathered up all her food which was
                  her chief concern owing to the famines she had experienced, washed herself at the
                  spring, and followed <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs> cheerfully to the boat.</span> On being taken to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> she manifested much delight on
               seeing the sights of civilization. She became a universal favorite and was presented
               with many gifts. Passengers on <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_panama">the Panama
                     steamer</name></rs> that landed there, all wanted to see <rs><placeName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost woman of San Nicolas</placeName></rs>.
               She related by signs her experience on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, as she spoke a language that none of the Indians knew,
               and none of <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the
                     Spanish fathers</persName></rs>, versed in Indian dialects, could understand.
                  <span type="trope" n="3">Civilization which prolongs the life of some, shortened
                  that of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman of San
                        Nicolas</persName></rs>. An excessive love of fruit led to her death in
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> at the age of
                  50.</span> She was buried with the honors of <orgName type="church"
                  key="#ch_catholic">the Catholic church</orgName> by the <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">Franciscan Fathers</persName></rs>, and
               her dress and trinkets were sent to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom"
                  >Rome</placeName> and placed in <rs><orgName type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum"
                     >that receptacle of the world's curiosities</orgName></rs>.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The story of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                        >the lost woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs> will always remain a
                  wonderment. Her ingenuity is seen in the pails she made out of grass that could
                  hold water, by smearing them [with] melted asphaltum, and in her bird-skin
                  dresses, her bone needles, her knife of iron hoop, and the language she invented
                  and spoke. It is inexplicable to all who have learned her story how a woman could
                  live <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">eighteen
                     years</date></rs> on an island around which the waves were beating an
                  inhospitable requiem to hope, getting her food and cooking it without even those
                  facilities which are common to the savage, and making her dresses neatly without
                  the aid of needles except what she carved out of bone.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="1">She laid aside one dress for <rs><date notBefore="1835"
                        notAfter="1853" cert="high">eighteen years</date></rs> to be worn when the
                  white men should come of which she had a presentiment. She built her own house,
                  protected herself from the cold, gained supreme control over the wild beasts about
                  her, and preserved her love for men and women for well nigh two decades of human
                  life alone in the wild. With no previous knowledge of civilization, solitude
                  appeared to have educated her for it. An ordinary woman would have perished with
                  dispondency [sic] in such a desolate, hungry, naked, shelterless outlook. She is,
                  and will remain to the last event of recorded time, an example to the world how
                  the genius of a woman can brighten and what her powers of cheerful endurance can
                  be, on an inhabitable shore, without friends, or tools, or shelter, or clothes, or
                  food, or encouragement. O heroism, thy name is woman.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="7">
                  <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">The Dominican
                     friars</orgName></rs> were the forerunners of civilization on <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_paccoast">this coast</placeName></rs>, and early
                  recognized the advantages and beauties of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                     >Santa Barbara</placeName>, and established <rs><orgName type="mission"
                        key="#mi_santabarbaramission">a mission</orgName></rs> there on a commanding
                  eminence. Its white towers served as a landmark far out to sea, and may be seen
                  glimmering in the sunlight long before any signs of the town come to view. The
                  mission building is 160 feet in length and 30 feet wide with walls six feet thick,
                  the stone hewn out of solid rock. Two solid stone towers run up in front to the
                  height of 57 feet through which winding stairways ascend to the top, and on which
                  melodious chimes of bells have been ringing out tidings of the Catholic faith
                  since the days of the Indians and for one hundred years. They look as dilapidated
                  and as ancient as the bell in <placeName key="#independencehall">Independence
                     Hall</placeName> that rung <rs><orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">our
                        nation</orgName></rs> into being and some of them have had to be recast. A
                  wing of the building extends 220 feet long and 100 feet wide. <rs><orgName
                        type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">This far-famed "Old
                        Mission,"</orgName></rs> the pride of Protestant and Catholic alike, was
                  twenty years in building and is well nigh 100 years old. That event is to be
                  celebrated with centennial exercises next year. In it are wooden wardrobes, hewn
                  out of the wood by the Indians, containing the vestments of the priests brought
                  from <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName>, old and costly,
                  the statues of Saints <persName key="#barb">Barbara</persName> and <persName
                     key="#fran">Francil [Francis]</persName>, <rs><persName key="#fran">the
                        latter</persName></rs> being the patron and saint of the Franciscan order, a
                  garden of choice trees, plants and flowers where a woman is never allowed to
                  enter, the vaults where the fathers and the Franciscan brothers are buried, the
                  tomb of <rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#fmo">the first Catholic bishop of
                           <placeName type="region" key="#local"
                     >California</placeName></persName></rs>, ancient pottery dug out of the tombs
                  of the Indians and <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_moundbuilders"
                     >the mound builders</orgName>, the old Spanish statues of Jesus with
                  representations of blood streaming from side, hands and feet. Everything in and
                  around <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">the Old
                        Mission</orgName></rs> bears the evidence of age. Its furnishings were
                  transported from <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName> under
                  the auspices of its being it was built. The old mill, gone to decay, the adobe
                  houses, crumbled to ruins, the Indian burial ground in which the Indians are
                  buried in trenches, the brick tiled roofs, the excavated mines in which the
                  Indians worked, all cluster around this ancient edifice, show the antiquity of
                        <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_santabarbaramission">this
                        mission</orgName></rs>, and the generations that have come and gone since
                  its foundations were laid. I found there six Franciscan friars, besides
                        <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the
                  fathers</orgName></rs>, wearing the color and dress of that order&#8212;gray
                  gowns, cowls, cables and sandals, living on the plainest food, and sworn to a life
                  of celi[b]acy, chastity, and poverty. They eschew the loveliness of womanhood and
                  the pleasures and gaities of life, wear their sandals and their gray, and shut
                  themselves up in their cells&#8212;those living tombs&#8212;from a world which
                  attracts only to show its emptiness, and elevates only to depress. If the
                  happiness of the soul in future life is proportionate to the abstemiousness of the
                  body in this, what then must be the rewards in store for the Franciscan
                  brotherhood!</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="7">The mounds of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_moundbuilders">the mound builders</orgName> dot <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_paccoast">this coast</placeName></rs> all along from
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_mtshasta">Mount Shasta</placeName> to
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>. They are especially
                  numerous in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and
                  their vessels and implements of war and industry are in the homes, curiosity shops
                  and marts of trade of its citizens. <span type="trope" n="6">Their mounds, telling
                     in silence and yet most eloquently of the pre-historic existence of races in
                     the long-gone-by, rise in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_montecito"
                        >Montecito</placeName>, in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_car"
                        >Carpenteria</placeName>, among the <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_santaynezmts">Santa Ynez mountains</placeName>, and from <placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName> to the Meza. At
                        <placeName type="region" key="#re_princon">Point Rancon [sic]</placeName>
                     several hundred acres are covered at a depth of from two to fifteen feet with
                     the debris of what was once a large populatoin. Relics of all kinds are
                     exhumed&#8212;mortars, pestles, hammers, knives, arrow and lance heads,
                     utensils of various kinds, all laboriously carved from the hardest stone. At
                     one place more than ten tons of relics were dug up. <rs><placeName
                           type="island" key="#i_chi">The islands</placeName></rs> already spoken of
                     are rich in these remains, and large quantities of them have been dug out of
                     their sea-girt homes, where they have rested for thousands of years, and
                     shipped away to foreign museums and colleges, to awaken aspirations that can
                     never be gratified, in students of other lands, to know who, what, where and
                     when were <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_moundbuilders">the
                        Mound Builders</orgName>.</span></span></p>
            <p>The Santa Barbarians are a cultured, refined, amusement-loving people. It appears
               that the best mannered and educated of eastern circles of society, have floated on
               the tidal wave that had broken on that shore, and, in that little [?] between the
               mountains, the islands and the sea&#8212;a sweet valley of rest have settled down to
               breath[e] in its fragrant air, bathe in its ocean tides, and bask in its perennial
               sunshine. I have found in no other community of the same size, not the center of
               great schools so many polite, well-informed man and women, and free public library in
               a building that is an imposing monument to the belevolence, of 4,000 volumes,
               containing departments of shells, minerals and natural history, founded by the
               munificence of a Vale, a Dominick, a Calkins and others, is proof of the culture of
               the place. In the homes of the people I found libraries of classical, scientific,
               historical and periodical lore, shells from all seas properly arranged and
               classified, sea mosses and ferns arranged in like manner and pressed into ponderous
               volumes, geological specimens carefully prepared over their Latin names and placed in
               costly cabinets, birds stuffed in glass coverings, from the gay bird of paradise to
               the unpretentious thrush of the wild wood. The love of amusement among the Santa
               Barbarians is equal to their love of learning. It finds expression in the various
               walks and drives about the city. Horseback riding is common and popular, and ladies
               attain excellence in equestrianship. Carriage drives are numerous and excellent, amid
               scenery that is unparalleled, under skies that are cloudless, and in air that is
               balm-ladened [balm-laden]. The beach of the ocean, hard, smooth and dry, is a good
               road for a ride or drive and well used. The canons of the mountains, wild, weird and
               picturesque, are used for recreations of that character. The foot paths over the
               hills and up the mountains are good places for the exercise of pedestrianship, the
               gaining of health and the enjoyment of pleasure.</p>
            <p>The productions of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> are
               its pride as well as its climate and scenery. It is a land where there is a scant
               rain fall&#8212;no irrigation, and yet the cereals and vegetables and nuts of all
               kinds, of both temperate and tropical regions, grow there. The lima bean, the orange,
               the lemon, the prune, the rubber tree, the cork in its lightness and the aloe in its
               bitterness, all fructify in that soil. Tomatoes ripen the winter through. That is the
               only place on earth where I have found a rose fair once a year. A Santa Barbara
               pumpkin grew last year to the size of 800 pounds. The grape is the being of fruit in
               that latitude in size and sweetness. <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> is the home of "the Centennial grape vine," a section of which
               was taken to the Centenial at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_phil"
                  >Philadelphia</placeName>. It covers a place twenty-five feet long and twenty
               wide. Who has not heard of the twig of grape that a lover gave to the girl of his
               choice to whip her horse with on her homeward way, and in the commemoration of the
               event, she planted it, which afterwards became more distinguished for its fruitage
               than any other vine in <placeName type="county" key="#co_sb">Santa Barbara
                  county</placeName>?</p>
            <p>The distance by ocean from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> to <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">this
                     city</placeName></rs> is 288 miles, and the time in making it is two nights and
               a day. <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_srsteamer">The Santa Rosa
               steamer</name></rs>&#8212;a floating palace&#8212;was my conveyance home from
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">that city</placeName></rs> to
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">this</placeName></rs>. She is 348 feet
               long and 24 feet depth of hold, and has a compound engine of 3,000 horse-power, two
               complete iron decks going the whole length of the boat, nine water-tight bulk-heads
               (which admit of carrying 1,500 tons of water ballast), fifty-eight state-rooms, 188
               berths, six life-boats, eight metal life-rafts, four anchors, 450 cork
               life-preservers, patent logue to measure ahead, 400 electric lights of 6,400 candle
               power. Each state-room is lighted with electricity and heated with steam. <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_srsteamer">The steamer</name></rs> has a gross tonage of
               3,000 tons, and cost $600,000. The cabin is vulcanized cherry and mahogany, and
               upholstered throughout with silk plush and damask imported from <placeName
                  type="country" key="#co_france">France</placeName> especially for <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_srsteamer">the boat</name></rs>. It requires six carcasses
               of beef, twelve sheep, six hogs, six dozen of poultry and 500 pounds of fish and game
               for passengers and crew in her rough trip of a thousand miles. She was built at
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_chester">Chester, Pa.</placeName>, is capable of
               carrying 375 passengers, and was brought around <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_chorn">Cape Horn</placeName> in <date when="1884-02">February of last
                  year</date> by <persName type="seaman" key="#cjo">Captain Johnson</persName>, her
               gentlemanly commander. In the twilight of the morning we entered <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate">the Golden Gate</placeName></rs>, first
               called by that name in the "Geographical Memoirs of California" in <date when="1848"
                  >1848</date>, expressive of the commerce that enters it and the gold within.
                  <persName type="missionfather" key="#jse">Father Junipero</persName> entered in
                  <date when="1769">1769</date>, exclaiming, "there is the port, to which <persName
                  key="#fran">St. Francis</persName> has led us&#8212;blessed be his holy name," and
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">the bay within</placeName></rs>
               was called <placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">San Francisco bay</placeName> in
               honor of <rs><persName key="#fran">the saint</persName></rs>. <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate">The golden gate</placeName> is five miles
               long and from on to two miles wide, and is the long narrow entrance into <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_sfbay">San Francisco bay</placeName>. <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_sfbay">That bay</placeName></rs> is seventy miles long,
               two-thirds of it being south of the entrance and the whole of it being at right
               angles to the entrance. On the right as you enter in, is <placeName key="#fortpoint"
                  >Fort Point</placeName>, garrisoned by United States soldiers and mounted with
               cannon. Its frowning guns are capable, on account of that advantageous position, of
               annihilating the navy of an enemy. Farther down <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_thegoldengate">the channel</placeName></rs> and at the right also is
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_bp">Black Point</placeName>, the residence and
               headquarters of the commandant of <rs><placeName key="#fortpoint">the
                     fort</placeName></rs>. <placeName type="island" key="#i_sleatras">Slcatraz
                  [Alcatraz] island</placeName> on the left, rising a black huge mass of rock above
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">the bay</placeName></rs>, is a
               military prison where officers and soldiers from all parts of <placeName
                  type="country" key="#co_usa">the United States</placeName> are put for offenses
               against military discipline. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_ybi">Goat
                     island</placeName></rs> is soon passed which belongs to <rs><orgName
                     type="government" key="#gov_usa">the govenrnment</orgName></rs>. There are some
               of the water-works of the city. The railroad comapnies have had covitous [sic] eyes
               on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_ybi">Goat island</placeName></rs> for a long
               time. By building a pier to it they can then unite the commerce of land and sea, but
                     <rs><orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">the government</orgName></rs>
               cannot be bribed to sell it. <name type="ship" key="#sh_srsteamer">The Santa
                  Rosa</name> lands at her pier and underneath the stars and stripes that there
               float over the gathered commerce of all nations, we are again at home, in
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">this great city of the Pacific
                     shore</placeName></rs>&#8212;<placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                  Francisco</placeName>.</p>
            <p>In <date when="1847">1847</date>, <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">this
                     city</placeName></rs> had 459 inhabitants. In <date when="1848">1848</date> it
               was a cluster of houses among the sand hills, rimmed around by <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_sfbay">the bay</placeName></rs> like the edge of a
               saucer. Now it has reached the greatness of a population of 250,000, and is the
               financial, commercial, business, legal, intellectual, social, moral, religious and
               news center of the western side of this continent. "<placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName> sat upon her seven hills and ruled the world," but
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> sits upon more than
               twice that number and sways her scepter over a greater empire than that of the
               Romans.</p>
            <byline><persName type="author" key="#fwi">FRED SPALDING WITTER</persName>. </byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
