<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="monograph"><orgName type="publication" key="#bullusgeo">Bulletin of the
                     United States Geological Survey of the Territories</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <date when="1877"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_dc">Washington</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_dc">D. C.</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="chapter" key="#Schumacher1877">Art. III.—Researches in the
                     Kjökkenmöddings and Graves of a Former Population of the Santa Barbara Islands
                     and the Adjacent Mainland</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="56"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#psc">Schumacher, Paul</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head><title type="main">ART. III.&#8212;RESEARCHES IN THE KJÖKKENMÖDDINGS AND GRAVES OF
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">A FORMER
                        POPULATION</orgName></rs> OF THE <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                        >SANTA BARBARA ISLANDS</placeName></rs> AND THE ADJACENT <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">MAINLAND</placeName>.*<note type="end"
                     place="bottom">[<hi rend="superscript">*</hi>See note to Art. II, p. 27. A
                     portion of this paper was published in a German periodical (<orgName
                        type="publication" key="#afuran"><emph>Archiv für
                        Anthropologie</emph></orgName>, vol. viii, p. 223). The descriptions are
                     mainly topographical, rather than archæological.&#8212;<persName key=""
                        >ED.</persName>]</note></title></head>
            <byline>BY <persName type="author" key="#psc">PAUL SCHUMACHER</persName>.</byline>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="section">PLATES 9-22.</title></head>
               <p>In compliance with instructions from the <orgName type="museum"
                     key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName>, given <date
                     when="1875-04-11">April 11, 1875</date>, I at once made preparations for the
                  early start of an expedition to <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">Southern
                     California</placeName>, to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the group
                        of islands in the Santa Barbara Channel</placeName></rs> and the neighboring
                  mainland (Map 1) [Plate 9]. <span type="trope" n="7">The principal aim of the
                     expedition to this region was the collection of implements left by <rs><orgName
                           type="group"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                           former inhabitants</orgName></rs>, the observation of particulars in
                     connection with such finds, the description of the mode of burial practiced by
                     these people, and the delineation of topographical characteristics, together
                     with the preparation of sketches of such former settlements.</span></p>
               <p>With three hired men and a camp-outfit, I left <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf"
                     >San Francisco</placeName> on <date when="1875-05-04">May the 4th</date>, on
                  board of the United States revenue-cutter <name type="state" key="#sh_richru"
                     >Richard Rush</name>, <persName key="#baker">Captain Baker</persName>. On
                        <rs><date when="1875-05-05">the following day</date></rs>, we were landed on
                  the island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> (Map 2)
                  [Plate 10], the most western of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        group in Santa Barbara Channel</placeName></rs>, and seeming to be a barren
                  bank of sand rising from the ocean when approached form the northwest. From the
                  northern bold point to the eastern end, with the exception of a break formed by
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler Harbor</placeName>, the
                  shores are rocky and high; and from here along the southern side, toward the low,
                  sandy west end, a smooth ridge, about 500 feet high, abruptly ends in a bold
                  shore-line. On the north side this brown, dry, and dusty-appearing elevation
                  slopes steeply, and is arrested by immense dunes of drifting sand, which extend
                  from the west end in innumerable ridges of most varied formation, and nearly half
                  the width of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>,
                  to the north point. Sand driven by northwest winds is drifting into the bay, which
                  is being gradually filled in at its northwest side, where the dunes descend in a
                  steep decline to the water's edge, and their base is washed by the ocean. At the
                  entrance of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">the neat little
                        bay</placeName></rs>, in which vessels may find good anchorage and shelter
                  lies an islet, and between it and the eastern end of the bay extends a reef, over
                  which heavy swells usually break, leaving a channel between the rocky islet and
                  the western terminus of the harbor.</p>
               <p>On <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel Island</placeName> are two
                  small perennial springs; one is situated several hundred yards below the
                     <emph>adobe</emph> building at the bay, and the other, with a little better
                  quality of water, on the elevated northern point.</p>
               <p>The vegetation consists of low bushes, cactus, and grass, but no trees. At our
                  visit, <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>, which
                  is a Government possession, was "dried up", being overstocked with starving
                  sheep.</p>
               <p>With much difficulty we moved our camp through the shifting sand up the western
                  shore of <placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler
                  Harbor</placeName>, where the best boat-landing is offered, and found there on
                  shell-mounds room enough to erect our tents.</p>
               <p>The kitchen-middings, or kjökkenmöddings, of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">a former
                     people</orgName></rs> are found all over <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs> where sandy ground is met with. This
                  singular mixture of all kinds of shells, bones, rocks, and flint-chips, spread
                  usually over a space of about a hundred yards square, and to a depth of five feet,
                  although the extent and depth of such shell deposits vary greatly, is found on
                  both sides of the harbor, especially over its northern point, also along the
                  northwest side to the west end, and covers in great masses the low, sandy, western
                  extremity of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>.
                  The deposits of the kjökkenmöddings are much exposed to the strong northwest wind,
                  and, as they are located on loose sand, are laid bare by its action, offering
                  therefore good facilities for surface collections. But of these the casual
                  visitors to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>,
                  mostly persons interested in stock-raising, excursionists, and amateur
                  curiosity-hunters, have picked up or destroyed the best, and much of what was left
                  had been collected several months previously to our visit by <persName
                     type="author" key="#whd">Mr. Dall</persName>, of the <orgName
                     key="#uscoastsurvey">United States Coast Survey</orgName>, during a short visit
                  to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">this island</placeName></rs>. Of the
                  small surface collection made here, I consider an unfinished mortar the most
                  interesting article, showing in its partially rough and incomplete state the mode
                  of manufacturing such a utensil by <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_chumash">the aborigines</orgName></rs>. But my attention was
                  especially given to the finding and exhuming of the old cemeteries, which, as my
                  experience taught me, promises the richest reward. About half-way, and almost in a
                  line between the two springs, near <placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor"
                     >Cuyler Harbor</placeName>, I found a grave-yard, and soon another close by,
                  which yielded about 250 skeletons, and many utensils, implements, and ornaments of
                  stone, bone, and shell. Not far from the upper spring, another burial-place was
                  discovered, which hardly returned any results[.]</p>
               <p>The mode of burying was similar to that previously observed on <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, on the coast of
                     <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, which I described
                  in the Smithsonian Report of <date when="1874">1874</date>. The bodies were buried
                  in the kjökkenmöddings, because the kitchen-refuse offered here the only ground
                  which is firm enough to resist caving, and also to prevent the winds from
                  uncovering the dead, as would occur with loose sand. The skeletons were found from
                  three to six feet under ground, and often from three to four resting one above the
                  other, separated, if at all, by the bones of the whale. The bodies were deposited
                  without any order as to position and direction of the face, being sometimes found
                  face downward, lying on one side, or on the back, or face to face, or crosswise,
                  and the bones in nine cases out of ten disturbed and displaced. This confirms my
                  former opinion that the graves bad been re-opened, and the bones disarranged while
                  fresh bodies were being added. The bodies lay so closely together that at first,
                  they seemed to have been the victims of a fierce battle, buried promiscuously in a
                  pit. Close observation, however, indicates that the interments were made at
                  different times, as implements of shell and bone, skeletons, and remains of
                  perishable partitions, often plainly show by their more or less advanced decay,
                  and by the position in which they are found. It is likewise evident that the
                  burial took place before the decay of the body, although such was not the custom
                  of some interior tribes, because we found the bones of some skeletons buried the
                  deepest, and especially such as were interred separately from the others, in
                  perfect order. Some were even still enwrapped in matting. To find a skeleton at
                  the bottom of a pit, at the depth of about five or six feet, especially if there
                  be none above it, is considered by the practical digger a lucky hit, and causes
                  him to work carefully in the removal of the slabs and whale-bones, and to look for
                  stone-knives, spear-points, or strange stone implements, as it is supposed to be
                  either the grave of a warrior, a chief, or a "medicine-man".</p>
               <p>While on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">this island</placeName></rs>, we
                  were much exposed to the grinding sand, driven in our faces like so much hail by a
                  brisk northwest wind that lasted day and night during our four days' stay. The
                  preparation of food at an open fire became impossible, and most of our provisions
                  were thickly coated with sand. Although we could have secured a boat be longing
                  [belonging] to the schooner <name type="ship" key="#sh_mat">Matinee</name>, then
                  in port, attending to the wants of a number of shearers and awaiting a cargo of
                  wool, a visit to the northwest and west ends of <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sm">this island</placeName></rs> was prevented by a heavy sea, which
                  made a landing impossible. Our party left on <date when="1875-05-09">May 9</date>,
                  on <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_mat">the before-mentioned schooner</name></rs>,
                  and landed in <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner
                     Harbor</placeName> on the island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz"
                     >Santa Cruz</placeName>.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> (Map 3) [Plate 11]
                  is probably the prettiest island of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        group</placeName></rs>; in picturesqueness it equals and in vegetation
                  excels <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>. It
                  is mountainous, with large stretches of rolling land, especially near the eastern
                  and the western ends, where fine valleys, picturesque bluffs, and ravines occur.
                  It is, according to the works of the <orgName key="#uscoastsurvey">United States
                     Coast Survey</orgName>, 22½ miles long, running almost due east and west, and
                  from 1¾ to 6½ miles wide. Its greatest height is 1,700 feet. It has a fair shelter
                  in <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName>
                  and in several places along the east, south, and west sides, such as <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_smugglerscove">Smuggler's Cove</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_coche">Coche Prieto</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_forneyscove">Forney's Cove</placeName>, and others.
                  There is good water in the different springs and creeks found all over
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs> the
                  year round. Timber is found in many places, and quite extensive groves of conifers
                  occur west of <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner
                     Harbor</placeName>, while stunted oak-trees grow on the high rocky hills and
                  sides of the steep gulches, and low willows in the cañons. It is owned by the
                     <orgName type="company" key="#scruzislandcompany">Santa Cruz Island Wool
                     Growing Company</orgName>. Near a good wharf at <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName> stands a substantial
                     <emph>adobe</emph> building, and back of it extends a beautiful valley, about 8
                  miles in length, which afforded us, near its mouth and on the banks of a running
                  stream under old oaks, an excellent camping-ground.</p>
               <p>Our party spent about one month, <date from="1875-05-10" to="1875-06-12">from May
                     10 to June 12</date>, on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">this
                        island</placeName></rs>, during which time we made explorations all along
                  its shores 65 miles in extent. Here we found the United States Coast Survey
                  steamer <name type="ship" key="#sh_hassler">Hassler</name>, <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#taylor">Captain Taylor</persName>, engaged in making
                  soundings round <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                     island</placeName></rs>; and as the Superintendent of the United States Coast
                  Survey, <persName type="military" key="#cpat">Capt. C. P. Patterson</persName>, in
                  view of the fact that the expedition was made at the expense of <orgName
                     type="government" key="#gov_usa">the Government</orgName>, gave permission for
                  the transport of our party to such places as lay in the route of sailing of the
                  courteous and obliging <rs><persName key="#hasslerparty">Hassler
                     party</persName></rs>, it gave us a great advantage in prosecuting our work,
                  and saved much expense in sparing the necessity of chartering a vessel or hiring
                  pack-animals.</p>
               <p>Our main attention was again directed to the finding and examining of graves. From
                  our camp at <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner
                     Harbor</placeName> we made trips to different places on <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs>, taking only the
                  necessary provisions, water, and blankets along with us. We also carried some
                  boxes in shooks, in which temporarily to pack our finds.</p>
               <p>Our first station was at <placeName key="#tinkerscove">Tinker's Cove</placeName>
                  (Map 4) [Plate 12], a narrow fiord-like shelter for small craft only, with high
                  walls on both sides that seem to exclude all possibility of a farther advance.
                  Proceeding from our temporary camp among the rocks near the sand beach of
                     <placeName key="#tinkerscove">Tinker's Cove</placeName>, we climbed the western
                  face of the gorge, and approached the shell deposits first observed while passing
                  on our way from <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel Island</placeName>
                  to <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName>.
                  We found the kjökkenmöddings located on a plane about 50 feet above the sea, which
                  is arrested a little ways from shore by a steep ascent with rocky outcroppings.
                  The ground is rocky, and terminates at the beach in an apron of horizontal
                  stratification, washed by the ocean, and, at low water, quantities of eatable
                  mollusks can be gathered. Two hundred yards to the westward, on the bight of a
                  shelter similar to <placeName key="#tinkerscove">Tinker's Cove</placeName>, but
                  with an inferior landing, is a small spring supplying drinkable water. Great
                  masses of kelp exist in the adjoining inlet and among the outlying rocks (of which
                  but one appears on the map), where we may watch the motions of a great number of
                  seals and sea-lions in catching fish, very abundant in these waters. One of the
                  two burying-grounds discovered here was still well marked with whale-bones above
                  the ground, probably not so conspicuous as shown in the sketch (A) [Plate 21] for
                  the sake of illustration. Both were in the deposits of the accumulated
                  kitchen-refuse, as the surrounding bottom below its shallow subsoil was
                  impenetrable for the tools of these people. In the arrangement of the graves,
                  nothing was observed that materially differed from those on <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>. We only found here more wood
                  in the walling-up of the graves and more charcoal among the <emph>débris</emph>.
                  The graves yielded about 225 skeletons and a moderate addition to our collection
                  in stone and bone articles. From this place we made a reconnaissance in the
                  surrounding country, and noticed many shell-mounds located, rather singularly, on
                  high ridges and mountains, where water is distant and the place bare and much
                  exposed. The shells on such places are better preserved, and it seems as if these
                  people had moved up here the better to avoid contact with the whites while hunting
                  otters around <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName>. The
                  deposits, although very conspicuous by their bright color when seen from the sea,
                  and scattered over large areas, are not deep, and we found by very few flints,
                  some beach-rocks, but no skeletons, and therefore they may be safely termed
                  temporary camping-grounds, as described in the Smithsonian Report of <date
                     when="1874">1874</date>. After almost a week's stay in our picturesque camp,
                  the passing <rs><persName key="#hasslerparty">Hassler party</persName></rs> took
                  us up and brought us back to <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor"
                     >Prisoner Harbor</placeName>.</p>
               <p>We intended to make our next station at <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_smugglerscove">Smuggler's Cove</placeName>, but the heavy breakers
                  prevented us from landing, and we went on to <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_coche">Coche Prieto</placeName> (Map 5) [Plate 13], a small cove on
                  the south side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                        island</placeName></rs>, of which <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName> lies due north across the
                  neck of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs>.
                  We found shell-mounds at the mouth of a dry creek ascending gradually toward the
                  east side of the cañon, while an older layer was found opposite on the west side,
                  or the right bank of the creek. Here again, as in fact all over <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs>, with but one
                  exception, the reason of digging the graves into the kjökkenmöddings, was the
                  difficulty of working the ground which surrounds them, as only the beach is sandy,
                  while back of it the bottom is gravelly and the rising ground bard and rocky. The
                  western cemetery was the larger one; but, although we exhumed 140 skeletons, we
                  made only a moderate addition to our collection of ethnological finds. The first
                  fish-hooks of shells were found in the graves eastward on the small ridge. They
                  are ingeniously made, and I shall speak of them more explicitly farther on. We dug
                  up a square board (<emph>a</emph>) [Plate 22], about 1½ by 2 feet, pretty well
                  preserved, painted with a bright red color, and having small indentations in a
                  depression which is bounded by a raised border. I was told by <rs><persName
                        key="#vaquero">an old <emph>vaquero</emph></persName></rs>, with some Indian
                  blood, that the board was used in connection with hot ashes to whiten the
                  money-shell (<emph>Olivella biplicata</emph>) by a sieve-like action. The same
                  individual explained the use of a perforated stone (<emph>b</emph>) [Plate 22],
                  commonly found, and so readily taken for a war-club head, as a weight to the shaft
                  of the wooden spade. If one is at the first glance inclined to take this implement
                  as the ball of a club, we also must admit the fact that we found many of them
                  split in two, as if caused by the wedge-like action of the spade-handle, and that
                  no stone spades were found, which speaks in favor of the theory that it was used
                  for the purpose stated by the half-breed, who was very positive, and earnestly
                  tried to impress on us the idea by roughly making the implement used by his
                  ancestors as a spade. We also found some wooden relics, which appeared to me to
                  have belonged to a canoe, made of board sewed with strings, and well painted with
                  asphaltum. But, in the opinion of <rs><persName key="#vaquero">the
                           <emph>vaquero</emph></persName></rs>, it was a part of a cradle. I may
                  add here that <rs><persName key="#vaquero">the same half-breed</persName></rs>
                  assured me that he was present, some forty years ago, when <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the last few
                        Indians</orgName></rs> were taken from their <emph>rancheria</emph> at
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName>
                  to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> by <rs><orgName
                        type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the missionaries</orgName></rs>.</p>
               <p>After two days' stay, we returned again to <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName>. The next few days we
                  spent in properly packing our collection made thus far on <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz Island</placeName>, and also in examining the
                  shell-mound located on the right bank of the stream, at its mouth, and where it
                  forms a small fresh-water pond, or lagoon, before disappearing in the loose sand.
                  Avoiding carefully the last resting-place of <rs><persName key="#sailor7">a
                        sailor</persName></rs> buried here some years ago, we found the graves a
                  little south of the supposed astronomical station of the <orgName
                     key="#uscoastsurvey">United States Coast Survey</orgName>. Here we dug up about
                  40 skeletons, bat hardly any implements, except 14 finely-made fish-hooks with
                  barbs, some of bone and some of shells; also some of the tools and many flakes of
                  shells required for the manufacture of such hooks.</p>
               <p>Joining again the <rs><persName key="#hasslerparty">Hassler party</persName></rs>
                  on their way to the south side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                        island</placeName></rs>, we made a landing in a small cove designated as
                     <placeName key="#losalamoscove">Los Alamos</placeName> (Map 6) [Plate 14]. This
                  place is very much the same in appearance, location of the mound, and of the two
                  graves, as that at <placeName type="region" key="#re_coche">Coche
                     Prieto</placeName>. The returns were poor, although we unearthed about 100
                  skeletons. I will mention a piece of fishing-tackle, which was here, as on
                  previous occasions, repeatedly found in connection with fish-hooks and bone
                  fish-spears. It is a piece of a bright shell, varying, say from 2 to 4 inches in
                  its longest measurement, differing in shape, but similar to the design
                     (<emph>c</emph>) [Plate 22], which was fastened at the end of a line, and used,
                  I am convinced by observations in exhuming it and by the explanations of old
                  Mexicans and Indians, to attract the fish somewhat as in our present mode of
                  trolling with a "spoon-hook".</p>
               <p>Next morning we again undertook to land at <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_smugglerscove">Smuggler's Cove</placeName> (Map 7) [Plate 15], near
                  the east end, and this time was success, although the utmost skill of
                        <rs><persName key="#hired1">the officer in the boat</persName></rs> was
                  required to avoid an accident. Here we readily found the cemetery on the gradual
                  ascent of the left bank of the creek, in a thicket of thorny cactus growing all
                  over this extensive shell-heap. Among the articles discovered, my attention was
                  again arrested by a deposit of shell-flakes, as first found at <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_coche">Coche Prieto</placeName>, and afterward at
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName>,
                  some of which were partially worked into fish-hooks, others finished. Other kinds
                  of implements were found, such as double-pointed borers, of coarse, gritty
                  sandstone, flint points, and a whetstone shaped something like a double-edged
                  knife. All of these kinds of articles had been found before, but never such a full
                  assortment in one place. I had before suspected that these objects were used in
                  the manufacture of fish-hooks. I now was convinced of it, and as the tools
                  comprise a complete set, I will illustrate them with several figures taken from
                  the originals, which will be found among the collection sent to <orgName
                     type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">the Smithsonian</orgName>, and will
                  describe the manufacture of the fish-hooks.*<note type="end" place="bottom"><hi
                        rend="superscript">*</hi>I have given a full illustrated description of the
                     manufacture of fish-hooks in the "<orgName type="publication" key="#afuran"
                        >Archiv für Anthropologie</orgName>", vol. viii, page 223
                     <emph>seq.</emph></note> The figures <emph>d</emph> to <emph>h</emph> [Plate
                  22] represent the shell-flakes usually of the red-back abilone, as found in its
                  different stages of finish, while <emph>i</emph> and <emph>k</emph> show finished
                  hooks. The pieces were broken from <emph>Haliotis</emph> shell in coarse flakes,
                     <emph>d</emph>; then perforated like <emph>e</emph> with the flint-point
                     <emph>l</emph>; the hole rounded, as shown in <emph>f</emph>, by the
                  double-pointed borer of coarse, hard sandstone <emph>m</emph>; then its rim worked
                  into the shape <emph>g</emph>, for which any flat sandstone may have been
                  employed. This done, the knife-like whetstone <emph>n</emph> was required to work
                  out the part shaded in <emph>h</emph>. With some additional touches, the
                     <emph>i</emph> was finished, and fastened for use to a line, as shown in
                     <emph>k</emph>. I have purposely illustrated in <emph>k</emph> a beautiful hook
                  of bone, because remarkable for its barb projecting, contrary to the modern style,
                  from the outside of the curve of the hook. The shank of this rare hook showed
                  still a part of the line, attached in the manner as shown, thickly coated and
                  preserved by asphaltum. [These figures are all on Plate 22.]</p>
               <p>While the excavation was being prosecuted by experienced and careful workmen, I
                  searched the neighborhood, and discovered at the point of <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_smugglerscove">the cove</placeName></rs>, which lies
                  about three-fourths of a mile almost due south from the burying-place, unusual
                  signs of a former settlement, and the headstones of the graves, consisting of huge
                  whale-bones, nearly covered up by a luxuriant growth of cactus, so omnipresent on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">this island</placeName></rs>.
                  The slope of the extreme point, which ends abruptly in a high bluff, with detached
                  rocks washed by the sea, was leveled for the better erection of the few houses.
                  Cobble-stones had been planted in a row as an embankment, and the space filled up
                  with earth removed from the elevated portion back of it. This afforded room for a
                  few houses, whose former existence was still plainly indicated by the several
                  depressions. In the graves at the point, a wooden sword of a Roman pattern was
                  found, having its hilt richly inlaid with shells, but in such a decayed condition
                  that it had to be thickly coated with varnish for preservation, whereby the
                  brilliancy of color of the shells and the good appearance in general were much
                  injured. Anything made of shells will part in flakes as soon as exposed to dry
                  atmosphere, and is therefore easily lost, or at least disfigured. The two
                  grave-yards at <placeName type="region" key="#re_smugglerscove">Smuggler's
                     Cove</placeName> yielded about 200 corpses and several boxes of implements.</p>
               <p>Our last camp pitched on this island was at <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_forneyscove">Forney's Cove</placeName> (Map 8) [Plate 15]. Before
                  examining this place, I entertained the hope of a rich harvest, as the
                  shell-deposits are abundant here, and glisten on almost every eminence along the
                  slopes, and even on the tops of the main ridge. The reef that extends from the
                  outer end of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_forneyscove">the
                        cove</placeName></rs> to a rock island, the singular formation of the point
                  with its subterranean passages washed by the sea, and the rocky surroundings on
                  all sides, with its masses of kelp and sea-weed, make this the best portion of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs> as
                  to the multitude and variety of mollusks and fishes. But as water is distant, the
                  nearest being found only in a spring on the other side of the ridge, about two
                  miles to the northeastward from the cave, not considering the climb, I was not
                  surprised to find all these shell-deposits, with but two exceptions, the remaining
                  witnesses of a temporary camp of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_chumash">those people who came here</orgName></rs> from the
                  other side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                     island</placeName></rs> to supply themselves with fish and mollusks. The
                  largest shell-mound close to <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_forneyscove"
                        >the cove</placeName></rs> is surrounded by a fence for a sheep-fold in the
                  time of wool-clip, and we can no longer find any signs of houses or graves,
                  although much of the characteristic material which stamps such places as permanent
                  settlements, such as water-worn rocks, flint chips, whale-bones, &amp;c., is
                  found. About a mile's walk along the shore to the eastward, we found two
                  shell-mounds moderate in circumference, but considerable in height. We found
                  graves on the eastern shell-mound. They were, strange to say, dug in the sites, or
                  depressions, of former houses, three of which contained skeletons. It seems that
                  this shell-mound was the first deserted, and was afterward used for a
                  burying-ground (for which the depressions of the houses suited), to the neglect of
                  the older cemetery, which could be traced, by several remaining skeletons, near
                  the brink of the bight adjacent to the graves. The kenmöddings, as we had occasion
                  to observe them at <placeName type="region" key="#tinkerscove">Tinker's
                     Cove</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_coche">Coche
                     Prieto</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#losalamoscove">Los
                     Alamos</placeName>, and especially here, appear to be located on a sand-bank
                  built by the hands of the aborigines. If the underlying bank had been built by
                  drifts, the winds, in connection with the adjoining sand-beach, would have caused
                  a different shape, if not a different location, of the bank, as it occurs at the
                  above-named places, or would leave traces of its action beyond the limits of the
                  shell-deposits, which is not the case here. This observation was made only on
                  settlements where the ground is rocky. About five miles to the eastward, at the
                  mouth of <placeName type="region" key="#re_poso">Cañada del Pozo</placeName>, but
                  difficult to reach by land on account of its rough topography, is reported an
                  extensive shell-mound, which I readily noticed from <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_hassler">the steamer</name></rs>, but, as a landing is not possible
                  at all times, we were prevented from visiting it. On the north side of <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, between <placeName
                     key="#puntadiablo">Punta Diablo</placeName> and the spring near the west end,
                  may doubtless be found some graves among the many shell-mounds, although most of
                  them, especially those located on high slopes, served as temporary
                  camping-grounds. Between the two before-mentioned places, at the shore, and
                  water-mark, a cave is reported, "filled with human bones and curious implements".
                  I was able to trace the report to <rs><persName key="#fisherman">a
                        fisherman</persName></rs>, who pretended to have discovered the cave by
                  accident. In consideration of the great work required to search all the
                  indentations of a most irregular and dangerous shore at least eight miles in
                  length, accessible only by boat, where the cliffs and innumerable cave-like
                  recesses form such picturesque sights, and spuming, thundering spout-holes reveal
                  hidden abysses, I thought it wise to offer a reward for his guidance to the cave,
                  but even after I had doubled the amount, which was more than a week's good luck in
                  fishing, he failed to put in an appearance for a passage over to the island. It
                  may be that the cave is in existence, but as to human bones and curious things I
                  found myself often deceived.</p>
               <p>While at <placeName type="region" key="#re_forneyscove">Forney's Cove</placeName>,
                  we enjoyed the visits of <persName type="author" key="#rothrock">Dr. J. T.
                     Rothrock</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#loew">Dr. Oscar
                     Loew</persName>, and <persName type="author" key="#henshaw">Mr. H. W.
                     Henshaw</persName>, all members of the scientific corps of Lieutenant Wheeler's
                  exploring expedition. Being on their way to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la"
                     >Los Angeles</placeName>, the rendezvous for the members of that expedition,
                  they made a close connection with <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                        island</placeName></rs> by [the] steamer <name type="ship" key="#sh_hassler"
                     >Hassler</name>, and having a few days' spare time, joined us in our rough camp
                  at Forney's Cove, to observe our excavations, and also do some work themselves in
                  their respective branches.</p>
               <p>Returned again to <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner
                     Harbor</placeName>, we finished the packing of our collection, which amounted
                  already to twenty-five large boxes, and had them properly addressed to a warehouse
                  in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, with which
                  arrangement for their reception had previously been made.</p>
               <p>I wish to say a few words in relation to the early history of <rs><placeName
                        type="group" key="#i_sm; #i_scruz">the two islands</placeName></rs> already
                  worked up.</p>
               <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, and <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, it is well known, were discovered by
                     <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> in <date when="1542"
                     >1542</date>, and named by him San Lucas. He died in a harbor in one of
                        <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_scruz; #i_sr; #i_sm">these
                        islands</placeName></rs>. The record says:&#8212;"He sailed from <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mobay">Monterey Bay</placeName>, and anchored on the
                     <date when="1542-11-23">23d of November, 1542</date>, in a harbor in one of the
                  group mentioned before, and named by him San Lucas....." "On San Lucas, <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#jca">Juan Rodriguez Cabrillo</persName> was buried on the
                     <date when="1543-01-03">3d of January, 1543</date>. The port in which he died
                  was called Juan Rodriguez." There seems to be hardly any doubt that the port
                  selected by <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> among the group
                  as a shelter was the present <placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor"
                     >Cuyler Harbor</placeName>, which is the only well-protected port in
                        <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_scruz; #i_sr; #i_sm">the three
                        islands</placeName></rs>. Water is obtainable in two springs the year round,
                  and is plentiful in the season in which his stay occurred. Further, the record
                     says:&#8212;"<persName type="seaman" key="#bfe">Ferrelo</persName>, his pilot
                  (forced by strong winds to return from his northern trip, made in compliance with
                  the wishes of <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#jca">the dying
                        commander</persName></rs> to proceed as far to the north as possible), dared
                  not to re-enter this port on account of dangerous breakers at its entrance." This
                  corresponds entirely with the appearance of <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler Harbor</placeName> during the time of rough sea,
                  because from the eastern side of the bay to the rock-islet heavy breakers roll
                  over the partially exposed reef and the rocks in the bay a little to the westward
                  of it, so that, coming from the northwest, its way of approach, the entrance seems
                  barred by breakers and impassable. Taking <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler Harbor</placeName> and the ports in <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> and <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName> into consideration as
                  shelters, and comparing their natural formation with the historic record, there
                  seems to be no doubt that the harbor on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
                     Miguel</placeName>, and not <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor"
                     >Prisoner Harbor</placeName> on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                     Cruz</placeName>, as some believe, is the port in which <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> died. We did not spend any time in searching for
                  his grave on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, where
                  the best location is offered between the spring below the house and the east end
                  of the harbor, but, to satisfy my curiosity, we dug in a place at <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName>, which was
                  well described to me in a letter of a southern gentleman, and in a very positive
                  manner, as the grave of <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>,
                  but in vain did we try to enable the Spanish nation to erect for him a monument in
                  commemoration of his noble deeds.</p>
               <p>I left <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz Island</placeName> on
                     <date when="1875-06-12">June 12</date> for <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                     >Santa Barbara</placeName>, where I met <persName key="#hcyarrow">Dr. H. C.
                     Yarrow</persName>, in charge of Lieutenant Wheeler's scientific corps, making
                  researches on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> for
                  Indian remains. I joined him for a day while working at <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_galeta">Galeta</placeName>, and found this place yielding large
                  quantities of all kinds of implements.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the schooner <name type="ship" key="#sh_staroffreedom">Star of
                     Freedom</name>, which I had chartered, arrived with a party on board to convey
                  us to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> (Maps 9
                  and 10) [Plate 16]. We reached <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                        island</placeName></rs> at night-fall on <date when="1875-06-19">June
                     19</date>, with the wind blowing lively, which compelled us to anchor at the
                  south-east end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. We expected a campaign worse, if possible, than that
                  at <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, as <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> appeared to be a faint
                  lump in a thick fog-like cloud of sand, which was whirled densely over our neat
                  craft, although we were a half mile off shore. On the low sandy flat, not far off,
                  the breakers for a distance of half a mile rise to a great height, and cause a
                  roaring like thunder; at intervals, when the burst had passed away and the
                  infuriated wind slackened in the rigging, we heard the howling sea-lions in the
                  kelpy waters, if not at their rookery on the near shore, all of which failed not
                  to impress with its wild charms. In the morning we made our landing, though the
                  sea was rough, and as the swells, caused by a strong current that passes, sweep
                  the shore at an angle, care had to be taken to prevent the boat going broadside
                  on, which would have been sure to capsize her.</p>
               <p><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The island</placeName></rs>, a Government
                  possession, is a mass of soft, coarse, yellowish-gray sandstone, about 600 feet in
                  height; its length is considered 7 miles, and its width 3 miles. The plateau,
                  which seems almost level, falls off on both sides in steep gulches and ravines,
                  where the eye is met by innumerable cave-like outcarvings done by the grinding
                  sand. The northwest end is sandy; dunes stretch across <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> as far as the
                  depression, on the end of which the <emph>adobe</emph> house is located. The
                  vegetation is like that of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
                     Miguel</placeName>, and also ruined by overstocking it with sheep, which are
                  here found in a like starving condition. Near the house on the northeast side we
                  found some malva-bushes cleared of their foliage to the reach of a sheep, which
                  gave them the appearance of scrub-oak trees when seen from a distance. There are
                  few trees near the house, where a strong never-failing spring supplies the
                  necessary water, which has, as on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
                     Miguel</placeName>, a mawkish alkali taste. The shifting sand has almost buried
                  the house erected by the stock-raising company, and with it its old and only
                  inmate, the superintendent. Farther on to the northwest, at the so-called
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_chineseharbor">Chinese Harbor</placeName>, is
                  another spring, with good water. It was on the northwest end, on the dunes, that
                  we found the shell-mounds abundant, although some are found at intervals all along
                  the shore toward the sandy flat on the southeast end, beyond which but few small
                  ones exist. None exist on the southwestern shore; but they appear again at the
                  northwest end about the <placeName type="region" key="#re_chineseharbor">Chinese
                     Harbor</placeName>. The mode of burial on <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">this island</placeName></rs> is different from that on
                        <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_sm; #i_scruz">islands previously
                        investigated</placeName></rs>. The bodies rest in separate graves, which we
                  found were not marked by whale-bones, stones, or other material elsewhere usually
                  employed, and lie on their backs, the feet drawn up, the arms folded over the
                  chest, and the head either resting on the occiput or on the side or sunk to the
                  breast. The skeletons, as a rule, were facing the east, although other directions
                  were observed. Many of the bodies show signs of having been buried in matting
                  coated with asphaltum.*<note type="end" place="bottom"><hi rend="superscript"
                        >*</hi>Asphaltum is plentiful on all <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>, washed ashore among the rocks.
                     A submarine spring of it exists in the channel between <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner Harbor</placeName> and <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and at several places
                     along <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the adjoining
                     mainland</placeName>.</note> Most of the skeletons and implements are laid bare
                  by the winds, and those are often much worn by the grinding action of the sand. In
                  a mound one mile northward of the sand-flat, at the southeast end, we found the
                  whale-bones apparently indicating the last resting-place of those that accumulated
                  the kitchen-stuff, but by digging into it found the ribs of whales to be the
                  remains of houses rather than the marks of graves, planted in a circle, and their
                  natural curve so adjusted as to form the frame of a hut in shape not un-like a
                  bee-hive, which was in some instances quite well preserved.</p>
               <p>Our <emph>modus operandi</emph> was here changed; spade and pick were dispensed
                  with, and our party went over the shell-mounds and carried the relics to heaps,
                  which afterward were conveyed by horses procured from the superintendent to
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_schuboat">our boat</name></rs> in the small
                  cove, and thence taken by water to our camp for a careful packing. On
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this island</placeName></rs> two
                  mortars were found, with the ornaments in high relief, the largest and best made
                  pestles and sculptures in serpentine, representing sea-lions, fishes, and birds,
                  and other objects, showing a superiority in the manufacture of stone implements
                  over the inhabitants of <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_sm; #i_scruz">the two
                        islands before mentioned</placeName></rs>. Remains of fish-books were found
                  plentiful, but, weathered out as they were, could not be saved. Together with the
                  above-mentioned sculptures, several specimens of a hook-like implement were
                  collected, made of serpentine; also a tube and pestle of the same material, the
                  use of which I was unable to trace. The money deposits of shells and stone on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this island</placeName></rs> are
                  very remarkable. They were found before only in graves, buried with their former
                  owner, but here we found in some places on the shell-mounds, apart from the
                  skeletons, numerous small heaps of the shell <emph>Olivella biplicata</emph>, and
                  some of the land-shell <emph>Helix strigosa</emph>; also pebbles of uniform size,
                  about as large as a pigeon's egg, apparently coated with asphaltum, or burnt and
                  blackened by fire; they averaged in quantity from a half to one cubic foot, and
                  were evidently stored there and afterward exposed to the drifts of sand, forming
                  conspicuous diminutive hillocks. We found as many as sixty of these deposits on
                  one shell-mound. This, with the position of some of the implements we observed,
                  seems to point to the fact that the last inhabitants left or were taken off
                  suddenly. We found, for instance, instead of being buried with the dead, many
                  mortars set in the ground to the rim, the pestle either in its opening or lying
                  alongside, as if it had done its duty only some days before. On <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">this island</placeName></rs>, more dog skeletons
                  were found among the <emph>debris</emph> of the deserted hearths than on any
                  preceding one, although in only one instance were we able to collect many of the
                  parts of a full skeleton; but we were more successful in obtaining good skulls.
                  Tradition speaks of an extinct race of dogs that inhabited <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName>. Even in <date when="1857"
                     >1857</date> a reliable gentleman thought be had seen some of these same dogs
                  on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, which he
                  described to me as large, slender, coarse, and hairy canines, resembling rather a
                  coyote or wolf than our better-natured domestic species. Whether the aborigines
                  feasted on this last resort of a starving modern traveler, we cannot tell,
                  although we know that they were not epicures according to our taste, as the many
                  bones of sea-fowls testify. The red-back abalone is abundant among the
                  shell-heaps, although none of this species is found on <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> at the present time,
                  which is proven by the modem shell-deposits accumulated by the industrious
                  Chinese, who dry this shell-fish here in great masses for exportation to
                     <placeName type="country" key="#co_china">China</placeName>. The material for
                  the manufacture of sandstone mortars and pestles is found among the water-worn
                  bowlders on the beach; articles made of serpentine of course had to be brought
                  from abroad. Pots of magnesian mica, or even fragments of them, were not found,
                  and yet the presence of driftwood permitted cooking, as plenty of charcoal bears
                  witness. During our stay on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                        island</placeName></rs>, we obtained 127 mortars and about 200 pestles, and
                  many boxes of smaller implements, trinkets, and ornaments, which swelled our
                  collection considerably.</p>
               <p>At the appointed time, the schooner <name type="ship" key="#sh_staroffreedom">Star
                     of Freedom</name> returned, and we left <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >San Nicolas Island</placeName> on <date when="1875-06-30">June 30</date>.</p>
               <p>Although the time of two months, as proposed for this tour of researches, had
                  nearly been consumed by the great ethnological results obtained on <rs><placeName
                        type="group" key="#i_sm; #i_scruz; #i_sn">the islands already
                        visited</placeName></rs>, and I was eager to do some work on <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> to complete the series of
                  my collections made in the previous year, I could not decide on passing <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, which, even by its
                  historical records, promised such interesting additions to the island collection;
                  yet I was aware of the magnitude of the work I had undertaken to do in eight days,
                  the time <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_staroffreedom">the schooner</name></rs>
                  was to come and take us off, a work which would require a month's diligent
                  activity in order to be exhaustive. If our short visit has, therefore, left much
                  to be done, the cause can easily be traced. But by our visit I was enabled to
                  gather valuable information, and to give such hints as will make a search, if the
                  necessary time is employed, a success, and reward a close observer with much that
                  is new, and probably of still greater interest than the objects found on
                        <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_an; #i_scl; #i_sb; #i_scatalina; #i_sr"
                        >the other islands</placeName></rs>.</p>
               <p>The island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                     Catalina</placeName> (Map 11) [Plate 17] appears to be a long mountain removed
                  from its base and planted in the wide ocean, whose waters are here wonderfully
                  transparent on account of the micaceous bottom. This mountain, about 18 miles in
                  length and 3,000 feet high, descends in innumerable steep gulches and ravines, and
                  often abruptly ends in perpendicular bluffs, some of which are nearly 1,000 feet
                  high. About 5 miles from its northwestern end, <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs> is almost cut in two by a
                  remarkable isthmus, forming on the northern side <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_isthmuscove">Isthmus Cove</placeName>, and on the other, the southern
                  side, the fine but narrow port of <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_catalinaharbor">Catalina Harbor</placeName>. The two parts of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>
                  are connected only by a narrow strip of land not 40 feet above water, and about
                  600 yards from ocean to ocean. It is sparsely timbered with stunted oaks and some
                  willows, with plenty of water in springs, and several wells. Some mining has been
                  done, but to no advantage. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">The
                        island</placeName></rs>, which was discovered by <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> in <date when="1542">1542</date>, belongs to
                     <persName type="investor" key="#jli">James Lick</persName>, and is settled by a
                  few squatters, mostly engaged in stock-raising, fishing, &amp;c. The Government
                  barracks at <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_isthmuscove">the
                        isthmus</placeName></rs>&#8212;quite imposing buildings in this
                  solitude&#8212;are still in good condition, and offer now shelter to picnic
                  parties from <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the neighboring
                     mainland</placeName>, as also to sheep-shearers in the time of wool-clip, some
                  signs of which it strongly bears in the remaining filth and kitchen-refuse of the
                  shearer. Rattlesnakes and centipedes are not scarce, and the former we caught on
                  the very porch of the barracks. In addition to the small gray fox,[*<note
                     type="end" place="bottom">[<hi rend="superscript">*</hi>The animal here
                     mentioned by <rs><persName type="author" key="#psc">the author</persName></rs>
                     is the <emph>Urocyon littoralis</emph> of Baird.<hi rend="superscript"
                           >*</hi>#8212;<rs><persName key="#fvhayden">ED.</persName></rs>]</note>]
                  the only wild animal on <rs><placeName type="group"
                        key="#i_an; #i_scl; #i_sm; #i_sn; #i_sb; #i_scruz; #i_sr">the other
                        islands</placeName></rs>, we find here the ground-squirrel plentiful.</p>
               <p>At the <placeName type="region" key="#re_isthmuscove">Isthmus Cove</placeName>, we
                  found quite extensive remains of a <emph>rancheria</emph>, but all our efforts to
                  find the graves of its former people were of no avail. Back of the marshy bottom
                  at this cove several marks of houses are still noticeable, and there we found some
                  graves. In front of the barracks still can be traced, on the highest ground of the
                  isthmus, some slight depressions in the earth, where formerly houses of the
                  aborigines stood, probably the same which <persName type="missionfather"
                     key="#asc">Padre de la Ascencion</persName>, chronicler of Vizcaino's voyage,
                  mentions in describing a temple with an idol erected on this isthmus. The idol was
                  much looked for, but we only found the hind part of a stone figure representing an
                  animal like a dog. Some pieces of a mortar of a very hard, brick-colored porous
                  rock were found, of which material none had been noticed before. On the other side
                  of the isthmus, at <placeName type="region" key="#re_catalinaharbor">Catalina
                     Harbor</placeName>, the sides rise steeply, and the ground is gravelly and
                  rocky. Here we find no signs of a settlement. With <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_schuboat">our boat</name></rs> we made explorations to the
                  northwest and southeastward, along the eastern shore of <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>. Toward the
                  southwest, within a distance of 6 miles from the cove, we found many minor and
                  shallow shell-deposits over hard ground, and in connection with them very distinct
                  marks of two, three, sometimes five houses, but failed to discover any graves. All
                  these places had been overrun by miners, and we therefore found only fragments,
                  where we otherwise could have made quite a collection in surface-finds. To the
                  northward we visited a shell-mound, at Johnson's place, which returned no
                  surface-finds, being so often visited by picnic parties, neither are graves
                  traceable. Except a few skeletons dug up at the isthmus, no others could we
                  discover within the reach of our boat-excursions during the limited time of our
                  stay. By all the information I could gather, and by the circumnavigation of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>,
                  I am convinced that the southeastern end is the richest part of <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>, and promises a
                  good reward to a collector. There we find many small coves offering fine
                  boat-landings, bold, rocky shores, with an abundance of shells and fish in the
                  kelpy waters. Here also we may find the rocks used by <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the Indians</orgName></rs>
                  for the manufacture of their house utensils, which are claimed to come from
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">this
                  island</placeName></rs>, where they were made and disposed of in canoe-loads among
                  the inhabitants on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName>, taking such necessities in return as <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs> was in want of.
                  Only steatite is found about the isthmus, and, as it appears here, it was only
                  used for making ornaments; but no magnesian mica, of which the cooking-vessels are
                  manufactured, nor did we find any serpentine, of which the beautiful bowls and
                  cups consist. But <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">this
                        island</placeName></rs> is very rich in varieties of minerals, and it is
                  therefore probable such rock is found, which, no doubt, offered a great field of
                  industry to <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                        islanders</orgName></rs>, considering the many utensils we have found
                  already made of this material. According to the reports, there is no doubt that
                  factories existed on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">this
                        island</placeName></rs> which supplied the Indians on <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, even as far as <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_slo">San Luis Obispo</placeName> and <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName>, with their cooking pots, or
                     <emph>ollas</emph>. The rock must be looked for at the southwest end; and if
                  any manufacturing has been carried on there, fragments will be revealed at the
                  different coves, and guide the investigator to the quarries and factories.</p>
               <p>Before leaving <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName>, I
                  wish to mention those which I did not visit, the reason being want of time, and to
                  explain why I gave preference to those explored. The first island I passed was
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, which lies between
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> and <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>. It is 15 miles long and
                  about 10 miles in its greatest width; is much the same in appearance as <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, only not so
                  high&#8212;being about 1,200 feet above the sea&#8212;and more of the rolling-hill
                  order; yet much of its shore-line, which is about 50 miles in extent, is bold and
                  difficult of access. Having had better information as to <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz"
                     >Santa Cruz</placeName> when I began the research on <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName>, I visited <rs><placeName type="group"
                        key="#i_sm; #i_scruz">these two</placeName></rs> first; and as the channels
                  between these <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_sm; #i_scruz"
                        >islands</placeName></rs> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa
                     Rosa</placeName> are only 4 and 5 miles, respectively, I was satisfied that the
                  large collection made comprises about all the forms that may be found on islands
                  lying so close together; or at least I thought there was more probability of
                  adding new forms at a distant island, as, for example, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, which I therefore selected instead. I am
                  well aware of the great deposits of kjökkenmöddings on <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa Island</placeName>, as I was informed of them by the
                  owner, who is a reliable man, and I observed some of them while passing by. I was
                  also told that many implements are scattered over the surface, especially where
                  the contents of a cemetery have become exposed by the winds, and the bare
                  skeletons now bleach in the sun. Moreover, certain parties spoke of caves
                  containing human remains, which may be authentic; but to this sort of promises I
                  was treated on <rs><placeName type="group" key="#i_sm; #i_scruz">the two islands
                        mentioned</placeName></rs>. My time and, what was more important, the amount
                  appropriated for this work had to be taken in consideration, as well as my great
                  desire to get all I could discover.</p>
               <p>East of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, with a
                  channel of 4 1/2 miles between, lies the bold and rocky island of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>, parted in three by narrow
                  passages. I passed <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_an">this
                        island</placeName></rs> from all sides, but could not discover any
                  shell-deposits. It seems quite probable that there are none, as their exists no
                  water on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_an">this
                  island</placeName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Proceeding 38 miles southeast, we reach <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>, the smallest island of <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">the group</placeName>. It has but 2 miles shore-line, is
                  smooth-topped, and about 500 feet high. A small shell-mound is found on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">this island</placeName></rs>, with
                  some fragments of pestles and mortars. There is no water, and it seems to have
                  served as a way station between some of the islands and <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Thirty-five miles southeast from <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>, or about 20 miles due south from <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, lies the island of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, one of those discovered by
                     <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>. It is a large island,
                  measuring about 20 miles in length and 2 in width. The southeast end is high,
                  bold, and rocky, and slopes toward the northwest terminus, which is covered with
                  high dunes for many miles. I was informed by a gentleman of the <orgName
                     key="#uscoastsurvey">United States Coast Survey</orgName> of the existence of
                  large shell-mounds on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">this
                        island</placeName></rs>, especially of one located on the high dune, of
                  great circumference. A whaler, who usually spends the months of May, June, and
                  July on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">Clemente</placeName> to kill
                  sea-lions, told me of natural basins, worn in rock on the high plateau at the
                  southeast end, in which rain-water of the winter is stored, the only water on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs>.
                  Although this natural reservoir may have been very convenient for the aborigines,
                  it is well for the visitors to bring a water-supply from abroad, as it is no small
                  task to reach the water here, and, indeed, on most of <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>. With the exception of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, and <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, no island should be visited
                  without bringing a supply of water. Even on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm"
                     >San Miguel</placeName>, although within easy reach, the water is distasteful.
                  So, also, on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, where a
                  landing on the northeast side, near the house and spring, is not always
                  practicable.</p>
               <p>Finally, I will say a few words as to the age of the deserted settlements on
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs>.
                  According to the records, the southwestern islands were inhabited at the time of
                  the discovery, but not the northwestern group. The appearance of the
                  kjökkenmöddings, which I was enabled to compare with such remains occurring on the
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">Pacific coast</placeName> for a
                  distance of a thousand miles, impresses me as not dating far back by the absence
                  of that ash-like appearance which is due to the effects of time; and when I
                  examined the shell-mound of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                     Catalina</placeName>, corresponding to the very settlement which <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#svi">Viscaino</persName> mentions, I considered it slightly
                  older than those investigated on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                     Cruz</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
                     Miguel</placeName>. I venture, therefore, to say that <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands in the Santa Barbara
                        Channel</placeName></rs> were peopled in the sixteenth and seventeenth
                  centuries by immigration of Indians from the neighboring continent, whose habits
                  in building their towns, implements, weapons, and ornaments they retained, keeping
                  up a close intercourse with the mainlanders. The depopulation of <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> certainly occurred
                  about forty years ago, and is still well remembered by some people living on
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the adjacent mainland</placeName>.
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">The
                           </persName></rs><emph><rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">padres</persName></rs></emph>, about that
                  time, took <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the Indians</orgName></rs> from
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                     >Santa Catalina</placeName>, and probably <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl"
                     >San Clemente</placeName>; while <persName type="frontiersman" key="#iwi"
                     >Captain Isaac Williams</persName>, in the year <date when="1836">1836</date>,
                  then collector of the port of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San
                     Pedro</placeName>, took <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the Indians from San Nicolas</orgName></rs> for
                  the same end, viz, their subjection under <orgName type="mission"
                     key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the missions</orgName>.*<note type="end"
                     place="bottom"><hi rend="superscript">*</hi>In <date when="1811">1811</date>,
                           <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a ship</name></rs> commanded
                     by <persName type="seaman" key="#whi">Captain Whittemore</persName>, belonging
                     to <orgName key="#bp">Boardman &amp; Pope</orgName>, a Boston firm engaged in
                     the fur-trade, brought down from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_si"
                        >Sitka</placeName>
                     <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                           >thirty Kodiak Indians</persName></rs> for the purpose of hunting otters
                     on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, and
                     left them there for two years. A feud arose among the old settlers and the
                     new-comers, which, it is said, caused the extirpation of <rs><orgName
                           type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the male
                           islanders</orgName></rs> at the hands of <rs><persName type="group"
                           key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                           >the well-armed Kodiaks</persName></rs>[.] When, in <date when="1836"
                        >1836</date>, <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the last
                           Indians</persName></rs> were taken from <placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> by <persName type="seaman" key="#whi"
                        >Captain Williams [sic]</persName>, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                           key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> was accidentally left, and <rs><date
                           when="1848">twelve years afterward</date></rs> discovered by <persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nedever [Nidever]</persName>, giving
                     rise to many newspaper accounts.</note></p>
               <p>We left <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina Island</placeName> on
                     <date when="1875-07-06">July 6</date>, and anchored in <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> Bay on <rs><date when="1875-07-10">the
                        10th</date></rs>, having been detained by calm weather, which often prevails
                  in the channel in this season. At <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>, I again met <persName key="#hcyarrow">Dr.
                     Yarrow</persName> and the other members of Wheeler's scientific corps, who told
                  me of their great success at the place called <placeName key="#dospueblos">Dos
                     Pueblos</placeName>. As their excavations had not been finished, and promised
                  still great returns, I communicated the fact, and was requested to do some work
                  there.</p>
               <p><placeName key="#dospueblos">Dos Pueblos</placeName> (Map 12) [Plate 18], on
                     <placeName key="#patera">La Patera rancho</placeName>, is said to be 18 miles
                  distant from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> by the
                  northern coast-road, and, according to the United States Coast Survey map, 16
                  miles in a straight line.</p>
               <p>Here existed once two towns, or pueblos, which originated the name of this place.
                  One town was very prominently located on the mesa-land, on the right side of the
                  stream, near the shore; the other one, below, on the sloping left bank of the same
                  creek. It is said that the creek had been the boundary-line between two tribes,
                  distinct in language as well as in customs. There is also a speculation that this
                  was the place seen by <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, and
                  mentioned as <emph>casas grandes</emph>. However, we found this place remarkable
                  for its kjökkenmöddings, the appearance of its town-site, its old worn trail along
                  the face of the bluff, and, above all, its location, which comprises the cardinal
                  features of a well-located aboriginal coast settlement, overlooking the wide ocean
                  spread before it, with its offerings of fish and mollusks, water near at hand, a
                  fine game country back of it, and a sandy soil easy to work with the primitive
                  tools of these people. The yield of the cemetery was extremely rich in all kinds
                  of implements, although a good part of it had already been worked out by my
                  predecessor. It was observed that some parts of the grave-yard returned the more
                  valuable relics, like utensils of steatite, spear-points, &amp;c., while other
                  places in the same burying-ground compensated our labor with the common mortar and
                  pestle.</p>
               <p>The lower settlement does not indicate as long a period of habitation nor as large
                  a town as the upper one. The graves are located in a sticky, dark ground, slightly
                  mixed with gravel, and difficult to dig up as compared with the common soil of
                  burying-places. The short time left us before the departure of the steamer, after
                  finishing work at the upper cemetery, did not admit of an entire excavation; and,
                  on the other hand, the aspect was not inviting enough, and promised not sufficient
                  work to our enlarged party for a stay to await another steamer, even if my
                  proposed northern trip had left us any time to spare. We had here five
                  working-days for excavation and packing, during which time an addition of
                  seventeen large cases was realized.</p>
               <p>On <date when="1875-07-18">the 18th</date> and <date when="1875-07-19">19th of
                     July</date>, our party moved back to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>, and I started on the following day to <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>.</p>
               <p>After a trip to <placeName type="state" key="#st_or">Oregon</placeName>, which I
                  describe in another place, I returned again to the <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_socalcoast">southern coast of California</placeName>, to make some
                  further researches. My starting-point for this trip was <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_slo">San Luis Obispo</placeName>. I left this place in <rs><date
                        notBefore="1875-01-01" to="1875-01-15">the beginning of January</date></rs>,
                  with <rs><persName type="group" key="#man28; #man29">two men</persName></rs> and
                  the smallest camp-outfit possible, for the <placeName key="#rancholosal">Rancho de
                     los Alamos</placeName>, on which several graves had been reported by one of the
                  owners of the land. Unfortunately, it was not as represented. We also visited
                     <placeName key="#alamopin">Alamo Pintado</placeName> (painted alder), now known
                  as Ballard Stage Station, which is said to have been once a great resort for the
                  Indians in the early times of <orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions"
                     >the missions</orgName>. We made inquiry of the people at the station, and
                  found them utterly ignorant of the existence of such a cave, which, as my
                  informant said, ought to be "within a hundred yards or so" from the station. The
                  geological stratification is not adapted to the formation of caves, and gives no
                  hint where to look for them. After a short, useless search, we were compelled to
                  return for quarters at <orgName key="#ballstation">Bell Station</orgName>. We went
                  back to <placeName key="#graciosa">La Graciosa</placeName>, a small settlement at
                  the boundary-line of <placeName key="#rancholosal">[the] Los Alamos
                     grant</placeName>, and about eleven miles from the ocean shores, near the
                     <placeName key="#sanmarriv">Santa Maria River</placeName>, and there hired a
                  guide to bring us through the mountain-pass to a place at the beach about 5 miles
                  to the southward of <placeName type="region" key="#re_pointsal">Point
                     Sal</placeName>. The existence of a shell-mound in that location was known to
                  me, I having observed it two years ago with the aid of a telescope from the height
                  of <placeName type="region" key="#re_pointsal">Point Sal</placeName>, while
                  engaged in the works of the <orgName key="#uscoastsurvey">United States Coast
                     Survey</orgName>. This <emph>rancheria</emph> is called <orgName
                     key="#ranchosbi"><emph>Ōs-bi</emph></orgName> (Map 13) [Plate 19] by the old
                  Spaniards. Its appearance is a grand sight to an eager collector, on account of
                  the great masses of kjökkenmöddings found here. Along the the shore are low dunes,
                  and back of it a grassy flat, which extends toward the steep foot-hills of the
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_coastrange">Coast Range</placeName>, and
                  affords ample room for a settlement, which we still can trace in many house-sites.
                  The subsoil of the flat is deep, and consists mostly of decayed shells of an
                  ash-like appearance, which are of a greater age than those on the dunes. The
                  dunes, extending half a mile in length and about a hundred yards in width, are
                  covered with glittering shells, bones, great masses of flints, and hundreds of
                  tons of broken rocks and cobble-stones. Stratified rocks on the shore reach out to
                  sea, and must have been formerly, as they are now, rich in shells, the adjoining
                  waters teeming with fish, of which the masses of kitchen-refuse offer convincing
                  proof. The dunes toward the south are high, and partially covered with a luxuriant
                  growth of chaparral and chemisal, the sheltered home of timid rabbits, quails, and
                  other game. Water is especially plentiful in a stream south of the settlement, and
                  of a better quality than in the gulch right north of it.</p>
               <p>Early the next morning I went over the ground, studying the location of the
                  settlement, the nature of the soil, and such signs as would guide me in the
                  discovery of the graves; and, as their marks were still visible above the ground,
                  I had no difficulty in finding a large cemetery close to the beach, which forms
                  here a perpendicular bluff of 50 feet in height. In size, but certainly not in the
                  yield of implements, this grave-yard could be favorably compared with the one on
                  the <emph>mesa</emph> at <placeName key="#dospueblos">Dos Pueblos</placeName>,
                  which returned about fifty boxes of relics, while here hardly four were filled.
                  The large spear-points of chalcedony, one measuring 10½ inches, of which eight
                  were exhumed, were exceptionally valuable. The surface of the grave-yard, under
                  which we found buried at a depth of 5 feet in the average nearly 400 skeletons,
                  measured 600 square feet. If we now take on an average three skeletons one above
                  another, we find that the surface space required for these three bodies was 4½
                  square feet, or 3 by 1½ feet, which would be the most convenient proportion to fit
                  the doubled-up corpse of an aboriginal burial.</p>
               <p>While in camp at <orgName key="#ranchosbi"><emph>Ōs-bi</emph></orgName>, we
                  encountered a heavy winter rain-storm accompanied by snow and hail, from which we
                  had much to suffer under our light shelter, and which deprived us even of our
                  camp-fire.</p>
               <p>On the <date when="1875-01-25">25th of January</date>, we started out to
                     <placeName key="#samission">San Antonio rancho</placeName>, where a cemetery
                  was reported, which we found to be situated opposite the house of the stock-raiser
                     <persName key="#olivera">Olivera</persName> (Map 14) [Plate 20]. This place we
                  found nearly all dug up by the Spaniards for the sake of obtaining some
                     <emph>ollas</emph> and mortars, which are a great addition to their meager
                  household utensils in such an out-of-the-way place. The result of our labors here
                  was very poor. Much disappointed, but with hopes of a change for the better, we
                  went along on our difficult trip toward the mouth of <placeName key="#sanantcreek"
                     >San Antonio Creek</placeName>, over a country which was hardly ever traversed
                  by a wagon, and, properly, should be reserved only for the roaming
                     <emph>vaquero</emph>. About four miles from the mouth of <placeName
                     key="#sanantcreek">the San Antonio</placeName> and a mile from its right bank
                  is <placeName type="city" key="#ci_burtons">Burton's place</placeName>, an old,
                  dilapidated, deserted <emph>adobe</emph> house, and back of it a small pond, near
                  which a cemetery was reported. The house, the lagoon, and even some signs of
                  former Indian huts, were readily found; but, with all the pains we had taken, the
                  burial-place could not be discovered, and yet its location is clearly pointed out
                  by the formation of the surrounding ground to be back of the pond. Likely, the
                  loose and shifting sand of the dunes, between which it ought to be, covered it up.
                  We remained that night in camp near the lagoon, and experienced another heavy rain
                  and hail storm. Wet and freezing, we sallied out early the next morning to make
                  the mouth of <placeName key="#sanantcreek">San Antonio Creek</placeName>, which
                  had much swollen, and had to be crossed at the beach, where its waters mingle with
                  the breakers of the ocean. The crossing of the creek delayed us many hours, and
                  was attended with some danger. We had hardly become dry after last night's
                  exposure in endeavoring to save our light tent, and now we had to plunge into the
                  water to save our equipage, and rescue team and wagon out of the sandy
                  river-bottom. We passed <placeName key="#perdernales">Point
                     Perdernales</placeName>, and dragged over a chain of dunes to the Lompoc
                  landing, now in course of construction. About a quarter of a mile to the northward
                  of this landing, we found quite a shell-deposit, and some signs of houses near a
                  spring, but no graves could be discovered.</p>
               <p>From this point, behind which is the landing, open to the southwest, but partially
                  sheltered against northwest winds, toward the mouth of <placeName type="region"
                     key="#saninriv">San Inez River</placeName>, which is about four miles to the
                  southward, we noticed old shell deposits, especially back of the wharf. The thick
                  growth of chaparral prevents us from advantageously examining this place; perhaps
                  the deposits were accumulated only by temporary visits of the Indians. At the
                  right bank of <placeName type="region" key="#saninriv">San Inez</placeName>, where
                  a large <emph>rancheria</emph> was reported, we found no signs whatever.
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#saninriv">This river</placeName></rs> we
                  could not cross on account of the late rains, and had to take our course up its
                  banks. After a venturous travel over the hills and cañons, we reached the house of
                  the <placeName key="#sanlucrancho">Santa Lucia rancho</placeName>, which estate,
                  by the way, is very large, where another cemetery was reported. But I was soon
                  convinced by the intelligent gentleman that holds it now at rent that nothing of
                  the kind existed.</p>
               <p>From the time we left Olivera's place, our trip was a chain of disappointments,
                  and I therefore hastened to its conclusion. We returned again to <placeName
                     key="#graciosa">La Graciosa</placeName>, and without delay went to <placeName
                     key="#guadalupe">Guadalupe</placeName> on our way to <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_slo">San Luis Obispo</placeName>. At <placeName key="#guadalupe"
                     >Guadalupe</placeName>, a small jug of burnt clay was given to me by a hunter,
                  who picked it up at a southern branch creek of the <placeName key="#saninriv">San
                     Inez River</placeName>, about 10 miles from shore, in a secluded place, where
                  he thought could still be traced the remains of an old Indian hut. It was found
                  alongside of an oven, or furnace, as he calls it, in which he thought it was
                  baked. The furnace, he says, was about one and a half feet high, made of clay,
                  round, and had but one opening&#8212;none for the draft. It was left by him
                  undisturbed.</p>
               <p>From <placeName type="city" key="#ci_slo">San Luis Obispo</placeName> we made a
                  trip, at <rs><date notBefore="1875-02-01" notAfter="1875-02-15">the beginning of
                        February</date></rs>, to <placeName key="#morrobay">Morro Bay</placeName>.
                  We found at <placeName key="#morrocreek">Morro Creek</placeName> signs of an old
                     <emph>rancheria</emph>. Farther north, at Old Creek, are extended shell-mounds,
                  especially the one back of Stone's house, in the cultivated field, near the road
                  leading back into the valley. Although plowed, permission was received for
                  excavations. We found there, as if to give perfection to our ill-luck of the last
                  fortnight, the graves washed out by the creek. Three skeletons, one of which was
                  laid bare and revealed the burying-ground, had still remained in the bank of the
                  stream, which is very swift in the winter, and had worked out here a small bight.
                  Some stone slabs were also found, but our spades soon worked the virgin soil of
                  the bluff. We made search in the bed of the creek for some implements, which may
                  have remained there, but found nothing. They were either washed to sea or carried
                  away by passers-by.</p>
               <p>In conclusion, I will state my opinion that there are but few places left on our
                  coast south of <placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">San Francisco
                     Bay</placeName> which promise returns in Indian relics so valuable as the
                  results of my work during <rs><date when="1875">the last year</date></rs>, and
                  that in a short time, say five years, when the plow of the settler shall have
                  obliterated the last signs which now still guide the collector in finding the
                  graves, the implements that come then to the surface will be destroyed or
                  scattered among different people, and thus forever lost.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
