<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="journal"><orgName type="publication" key="#tidi"
                        >Tidings</orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">39</biblScope>
                    <date when="1904-09-23"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>,
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="article" key="#TheTidings1904_Sep23">Eighteen Years Alone: A
                            Tale of the Pacific (Continued From Last Week.)</title>
                        <biblScope type="page" n="3"/>
                        <biblScope type="page" from="6" to="7"/>
                        <author><persName type="author" key="#eha">Hardacre, Emma
                                Chamberlain</persName></author>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">EIGHTEEN YEARS ALONE.</hi></title>
                    <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">A Tale Of the Pacific.</hi></title>
                    <title type="sub">(Continued From Last Week.)</title></head>
                <div n="3" type="section">
                    <head><title type="seciont">III.</title></head>
                    <p>Tom Jeffrie's [Jeffries'] visit to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                            Nicolas</placeName> was the theme of more than one day's gossip.
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The island</placeName></rs>
                        he described as seven or eight miles long, by three or four in width; the
                        body of the land near six hundred feet above the beach, the plateau falling
                        in steep gulches to the sea. There were quantities of small lark inland, but
                        no other fowl, save sea-gulls, pelicans and shags. Numbers of red foxes were
                        seen in the hills, and droves of curious wild dogs, tall and slender, with
                        coarse, long hair and human eyes. On a flat, near the upper end of
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>, and half hidden by sand dunes, he found the remains
                        of a curious hut, made of whales' ribs planted in a circle, and so adjusted
                        as to form the proper curve of a wigwam-shaped shelter. This he judged to
                        have been formerly either the residence of the chief, or a place of worship
                        where sacrifices were offered. He had picked up several ollas, or vessels of
                        stone, and one particularly handsome cup of clouded green serpentine. <span
                            type="trope" n="5">But of all the wonders of <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, the
                            features on which <persName type="seaman" key="#tje">Jeffries</persName>
                            liked best to dwell were the fine beds of otter and seal in the vicinity
                            of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. So
                            fabulous were his yarns, that the interest of the other hunters was
                            aroused, and early in the following year <rs><name type="ship"
                                    key="#sh_nidever">a boat</name></rs> was fitted out, and
                                <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nidiver</persName>,
                            accompanied by <persName type="seaman" key="#tje">Thomas
                                Jeffries</persName> and a crew of Indians, started on an otter hunt
                            to the wonderful otter-beds seventy miles away.</span></p>
                    <p>A landing was effected near the southern end of <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, and, climbing the cliffs to
                        see where the otter lay, they had a magnificent view of <rs><placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> to the north
                        and east. On the southwest <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the
                            Pacific</placeName> rolled out its azure breadth, unspecked by shore, or
                        raft, or spot of any kind. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The
                                island</placeName></rs> on which they stood seemed a quiet, calm,
                        deserted spot, in the sunshine that then enfolded it. Butterflies hovered
                        over the wild sage upon the knolls; soft breezes rocked lazily the scant
                        grass about their feet; thickets of chaparral dotted the hills; cactus held
                        out waxen trays, where, on burnished mats of thorns, reposed fringed yellow
                        satin flowers; a trailing sand plant, with thick, doughy leaves, wafted from
                        its pink clusters a most delicious odor&#8212;an odor that had in it the
                        haunting sweetness of the arbutus and the freshness of the salt sea
                        wind.</p>
                    <p><rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #tje; #nativeamericans">The otter
                                hunters</persName></rs> did not linger long on the cliff, for on one
                        side they found the rocks swarming with black seal, thousands of them
                        mingling their sharp bark with the heavy roar of sea lions. The otter were
                        thick on the reefs, and a stranded whale lay in the edge of the crinkling
                        surf.</p>
                    <p><rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #tje; #nativeamericans">The
                                party</persName></rs> remained six weeks in camp on the beach. Oars
                        stuck upright in the sand, covered by canvas, composed their shelter; a
                        spring was found midway up the cliff, so that during their stay no one had
                        occasion to go inland or wander far from the otter beds, which were on the
                        side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
                        where their tents were pitched. The seal is caught asleep on the rocks,
                        lassoed or knocked in the head; incisions are made in the flippers, lower
                        jaw, lip and tail, and about four minutes are required by a good workman to
                        skin an ordinary seal. The hides are salted, and, after a week or two,
                        bundled and packed. The otter, most timid of the animals of the sea, is
                        caught in sets [nets] spread upon swaying beds of sea weed, or is shot while
                        lying with head buried in kelp to shut out the sound of a storm. It is very
                        sensitive to noise, and so shy that it takes alarm at every unusual sight.
                        The loose hide is taken from the body with one cut, turned wrong side out,
                        stretched and dried.</p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">Before <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                                    schooner</name></rs> left the vicinity of <placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, a terrible storm
                            arose, lasting for eight days, carrying away a mast and dragging the
                            anchor, so that another had to be improvised of a bag filled with stone.
                            During the tempest, a sailor fancied he saw a human figure on the
                            headland of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                    island</placeName></rs>. Through the washes of spray it seemed
                            to be running up and down the edge of the plateau, beckoning and
                            shouting. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The
                                    captain</persName></rs> was called, but the apparition had
                            vanished. On the eighth day, <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                                    schooner</name></rs> was enabled to run over to <placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> and from there to
                                <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>,
                            where the sailor's story of the beckoning ghost of <placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> haunted for a long
                            time the dreams of the superstitious on shore.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">A second cruise of the <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #tje; #nativeamericans">otter hunters</persName></rs>
                            failed to bring any additional news of the phantom of the sea.
                            Everything on land was just as before; not a leaf had been disturbed,
                            not a track was found.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">In <date when="1853-07">July, 1853</date>,
                                    <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the otter
                                    men</persName></rs> made a third trip to <placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, anchored off the
                            northeast side, and established a camp on shore. The party consisted of
                                <persName type="frontierman" key="#gni">Captain Nidiver</persName>,
                            a fisherman named <persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Carl
                                Detman</persName>, who went among sailors by the sobriquet of
                                    <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Charlie
                                    Brown</persName></rs>, an <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                    key="#cook">Irish cook</persName></rs> and a crew of <orgName
                                type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_missionindians">Mission
                                Indians</orgName>.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">The evening after their arrival, <persName
                                type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> and <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> strolled
                            several miles down the beach, enjoying their pipes and discussing plans
                            for work. It was one of those limpid nights, such as <placeName
                                type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> knows&#8212;a
                            night when the stars shine large and warm from the low sky, when the
                            moon burns with an amber blaze, and fragrance is in the air.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">As <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                    key="#cdi; #gni">the comrades</persName></rs> were about to
                            retrace their steps, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                                >Nidiver</persName> stopped, looked quickly about him, then stooped
                            and closely examined something on the ground. In the weird moonlight,
                            plainly outlined on the lonely shore, was the print of a slender, naked
                            foot.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">"The
                                    woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs>! My God, she is
                            living!"</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">He lifted his voice, and shouted in Spanish that
                            friends were come to rescue her. Overcome by the conviction that
                                    <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost
                                    woman</persName></rs> must have been near when he was in camp
                                    <rs><date when="1851">two years before</date></rs>,&#8212;that
                            it was not a creation of fancy, but a living being, they had seen in the
                                    storm,&#8212;<rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">the
                                    captain</persName></rs> ran to and fro, calling, looking and
                            swearing by turns. Hours were spent by <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi">the two men</persName></rs> in search, but in
                            vain.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">The next day, <persName type="frontiersman"
                                key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> found a basket of rushes hanging in a
                            tree. It contained bone needles, thread made of sinews, shell fishhooks,
                            ornaments, and a partially completed robe of birds' plumage, made of
                            small squares neatly matched and sewed together. <persName
                                type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> proposed replacing
                            the things, but <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                                    >Brown</persName></rs> scattered them about, saying that, if
                            they were picked up, it would be proof that <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the owner</persName></rs> had
                            visited the spot. Inland they discovered several circular, roofless
                            inclosures, made of woven brush. Near these shelters were poles, with
                            dried meat hanging from elevated cross-pieces. The grass was growing in
                            the pens, and nothing indicated their recent habitation. In fissures of
                            perpendicular rocks near the springs were wedged dried fish and seals'
                            blubber; but no sign of the near presence of <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                            hermitess</persName></rs>.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">After several days, <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#gni; #cdi">the men</persName></rs>
                            abandoned the chase. There was no doubt that some one had been on
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                island</placeName></rs> very lately. Either <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, or
                                    <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                                    child</persName></rs> grown to womanhood, had lived there, or,
                            perhaps, both <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                    >mother</persName></rs> and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lwchild">child</persName></rs> had survived until
                            recently. But they must have been dead months at least. The footprint
                            was older than at first supposed. The robe had not been replaced in the
                            tree. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The
                                    captive</persName></rs> perchance died of despair after they
                            left her beckoning in the storm.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">After that, the fishing went on for weeks, and they
                            were about returning home, when <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                                >Nidiver</persName> said he believed a person was hiding on
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                island</placeName></rs>. If she was living, he was bound to find
                            her. If dead, he would find her body if he had to scrape <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> inch by
                            inch. This provoked a laugh of derision. Of course the wild dogs had
                            devoured her remains. But <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                                >Nidiver</persName> was convinced that <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> was
                            afraid; had concealed herself, possibly on the opposite side of
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                island</placeName></rs>, where the shore was precipitous, difficult
                            of access, containing perhaps gulches and caves unknown to them.
                                    <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">The
                                    men</persName></rs> murmured at the delay, were incredulous as
                            to the success of the raid, rebelled at the long tramps over a wild
                            country.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4"><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The old
                                    captain</persName></rs> was firm; suitable preparations were
                            made, and <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                    entire force of otter men</persName></rs> started on their final
                            hunt for a ghost. Near the head of <rs><placeName type="island"
                                    key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> they came across the
                            bone house <persName type="seaman" key="#tje">Jeffries</persName> had
                            described. Rushes were skillfully interlaced in the rib frame work, an
                            olla and old basket were near the door. It stood amidst untrampled
                            weeds. After several days' march, a dangerous climb over slippery rocks
                            brought <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                                >Brown</persName></rs> to a spot where there was fresh footprints.
                            He followed them up the cliffs until they were lost in the thick moss
                            that covered the ground. Walking further, he found a piece of drift
                            wood, from which he concluded <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lw">the person</persName></rs> had been to the beach for
                            fire-wood, and dropped the faggot on her way home. From a high point on
                            the ridge he saw <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                    men</persName></rs> moving about below. Then his eye caught a
                            small object a long way off on the hills. It appeared like a crow at
                            first glance, but it moved about in a singular manner. Advancing toward
                            it stealthily, he was dumbfounded to find that it was the head of a
                            woman, barely visible above the low woven brush sides of her roofless
                            retreat in the bushes.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="4">As <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                                    >Brown</persName></rs> drew nearer, a pack of dogs reclining
                            close to the woman growled; but without looking around <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
                            uttered a peculiar cry which silenced them, and they ran away to the
                            hills. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                                >Brown</persName></rs> halted within a few yards of her, and,
                            himself unseen, watched every movement within the hut. Inside the
                            inclosure was a mound of grass, woven baskets full of things, and a rude
                            knife made of a piece of iron hoop, thrust into a wooden handle. A fire
                            smouldered near, and a pile of bones lay in the ashes. <span
                                type="trope" n="3">The complexion of <rs><persName
                                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
                                was much fairer than the ordinary Indian, her personal appearance
                                pleasing, features regular, her hair, thick and brown, falling about
                                her shoulders in a tangled mat.</span> From the time <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> arrived
                            within hearing, she kept up a continual talking to herself. She was
                            leaning forward, shading her eyes with her hand, watching <rs><persName
                                    type="group" key="#gni; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                                    >the men</persName></rs> crossing the flat below her dwelling.
                            After looking at them with an anxiety impossible to be depicted, she
                            crouched in terror, but immediately started up as if to run.
                                    <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">The
                                    men</persName>
                            </rs> on the flat had not seen her, and <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs>, putting
                            his hat on the ramrod of his gun, alternately lifted and lowered it to
                            attract their attention, then by signs he intimated that <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> was
                            found, and they should spread out so as to catch her if she tried to
                            escape. Before <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                    men</persName></rs> reached the knoll, <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> stepped
                            around in sight and spoke. She gave a frightened look into his face, ran
                            a few steps, but, instantly controlling herself, stood still, and
                            addressed him in an unknown tongue. She seemed to be between forty and
                            fifty years of age, in fine physical condition, erect, with well formed
                            neck and arms and unwrinkled face. <span type="trope" n="1">She was
                                dressed in a tunic-shaped garment made of birds' plumage, low in the
                                neck, sleeveless, and reaching to the ankle. The dress was similar
                                to the one found in the tree. As <rs><persName type="group"
                                        key="#gni; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                        men</persName></rs> came up, she greeted them each in the
                                way she had met <persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                                    >Brown</persName>, and with a simple dignity, not without its
                                effect on both Indians and white men, made them welcome and set
                                about preparing food for them from her scanty store.</span> The meal
                            consisted of roasted roots, called by Californians carcomites; but when
                            was there known a more touching hospitality?</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="1"> Among <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indian
                                crew</persName></rs>, there were several dialects spoken, but none
                            of <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                    party</persName></rs> were able to converse with <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">their hostess</persName></rs>,
                            or understand a word she uttered, and they were forced to try and make
                            her know by signs that she was expected to go with them. <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> went
                            through the motion of packing her things in baskets, shouldering them,
                            and walking toward the beach. She comprehended instantly, and made
                            preparations to depart. Her effects were neatly placed in pack-baskets,
                            one of which she swung over her back, and, taking a burning stick from
                            the fire, she started with a firm tread after <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>
                            to the shore. <span type="trope" n="8">Beside the load <rs><persName
                                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the female
                                    Crusoe</persName></rs> carried, <persName type="frontiersman"
                                    key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> and <rs><persName
                                        type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> had
                                their arms full.</span> Upon reaching <rs><name type="ship"
                                    key="#sh_nidever">the boat</name></rs>, she entered without
                            hesitation, going forward to the bow, kneeling and holding to either
                            side.</span> When <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                                schooner</name></rs> was reached, she went aboard without any
                        trouble, sat down near the stove in the cabin, and quietly watched
                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                men</persName></rs> in their work on board. To replace her feather
                        dress, which he wished to preserve, <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> made her a petticoat of ticking;
                        and with a man's cotton shirt and gay neckerchief, her semi-civilized dress
                        was complete. While <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                                >Brown</persName></rs> was sewing she watched him closely, and
                        laughed at his manner of using a needle. She showed him that her way was to
                        puncture the cloth with her bone needle, or awl, and then put the thread
                        through the perforations. She signified that she wished to try a threaded
                        needle, and <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                            >Brown</persName></rs> good naturedly gave her sewing materials, but she
                        could not thread the needle. <span type="trope" n="10"><rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> prepared
                            it, and gave her an old cloak of Nidiver's to mend, and while she took
                            her first lesson in sewing, she told <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                                    key="#cdi">her teacher</persName></rs> on shipboard, by signs,
                            portions of her life on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                    island</placeName></rs>.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="10">She had, from time to time, seen ships pass, but
                            none came to take her off. She watched as long as she could see them,
                            and, after they were out of sight, she threw herself on the ground and
                            cried, but after a time she walked over <rs><placeName type="island"
                                    key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> until she forgot about
                            it and could smile again. She had also seen people on the beach several
                            times. She was afraid and hid until they were gone, and then wept
                            because she had not made herself known. She said that he had taken her
                            by surprise and she could not run, and she was glad because he would
                            take her to <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">her
                            people</persName>; <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">her
                                people</persName> had gone away with <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                                    >white men</persName></rs> in <rs><name type="ship"
                                    key="#sh_peoresnada">a ship</name></rs>. <rs><persName
                                    type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> understood
                            by her signs that at the time of the desertion of <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> she had
                                    <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">a nursing
                                    baby</persName></rs>, which she represented by sucking her
                            finger, and placing her arm in position of holding an infant at the
                            breast; she waved her hand over the sea, to indicate that <rs><name
                                    type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> sailed
                            away, calling back "Manana" (tomorrow); then she could not find
                                    <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                                    child</persName></rs>, and wept until she was very ill, and lay
                            prostrate for days, in a bed of plants resembling cabbage, and called by
                            Californians "Sola Santa." She had nothing to eat but the leaves. When
                            she revived somewhat, she crawled to a spring, and after a time, as her
                            strength returned, she made fire by rapidly rubbing a pointed stick
                            along the groove of a flat stick until a spark was struck. It was a
                            difficult task, and she was careful not to let her fire go out; she took
                            brands with her on her trips, and covered the home fire with ashes to
                            preserve it.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="10">She lived during her captivity on fish, seals'
                            blubber, roots and shell-fish; and the birds, whose skins she secured
                            for clothing, were sea birds, which she caught at night off their roosts
                            in the seams of the crags. The bush inclosures she made for a screen
                            from the winds, and as a protection while asleep from wild animals. She
                            made frequent excursions over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                                    >the island</placeName></rs> from her main dwelling, which was a
                            large cave on the north end of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                                Nicolas</placeName>. She kept dried meat at each camping station;
                            the food in the crevices by the springs was for the time when, from
                            sickness or old age, she would only be able to crawl to the water and
                            live on what she had there stored out of reach of the dogs.</span></p>
                    <p>That <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
                        had faith in a supreme power was evinced soon after <rs><name type="ship"
                                key="#sh_nidever">the schooner</name></rs> set sail from the fishing
                        grounds. <span type="trope" n="1">A gale overtook them, and <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the passenger</persName></rs>
                            made signs that she would stop the wind. With her face turned in the
                            direction from which the storm came, she muttered words of prayer until
                            the wind had abated, then turned with a beaming countenance and motioned
                            that her petition had been answered.</span> They anchored under the lee
                        of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, where
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                            woman</persName></rs> was highly interested in seeing another island
                        than her own. When they approached the shores of <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, an ox team passed along the
                        beach. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The
                            stranger</persName></rs> was completely bewildered. <span type="trope"
                            n="3"><rs><persName key="#mrni">Captain Nidiver's son</persName></rs>,
                            who had been on the look out for his father's sail, rode down to the
                            landing on a handsome little bronco. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lw">The islander</persName></rs>, who had just stepped
                            ashore, was wild with delight. She touched the horse and examined
                                    <rs><persName key="#mrni">the lad</persName></rs>, talking
                            rapidly, and if the sailors turned away, calling to them to come back
                            and look. Then she tried to represent the novel sight by putting two
                            fingers of her right hand over the thumb of her left, moving them to
                            imitate the horse walking.</span></p>
                    <p><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidiver</persName> conducted
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                            woman</persName></rs> to his home, and put her in charge of
                                <rs><persName key="#sni">his Spanish wife</persName></rs>. The news
                        spreading, <persName type="missionfather" key="#jru">Father
                            Gonzales</persName>, of <orgName type="mission"
                            key="#mi_santabarbaramission">Santa Barbara Mission</orgName>, came to
                        see her; many persons gathered from the ranches round about, and the house
                        was crowded constantly. The brig <name type="ship" key="#sh_fremont"
                            >Fremont</name> came into port soon after, and <rs><persName
                                type="seaman" key="#fremontcpt">the captain</persName></rs> offered
                            <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> the half of
                        what he would make, if he would allow her to be exhibited in <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>. This offer was
                        refused, and also another from a <persName type="seaman" key="#tru">Captain
                            Trussil</persName>. <persName key="#sni">Mrs. Nidiver</persName> would
                        not hear of <rs><persName type="nativeamerian" key="#lw">the friendless
                                creature</persName></rs> being made a show for the curious.</p>
                    <p>(Concluded in Our Next.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
