<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#mexwled">Mexico Weekly
                     Ledger</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="28"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="45"/>
               <date when="1887-02-17"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_mex">Mexico</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_mo">Missouri</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#MexicoWeeklyLedger1887">A Mountain Mystery.</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="4"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">A Mountain Mystery.</hi></title></head>
            <p>Parties returning from hunting trips to the mountains often tell strange tales of
               their experience when miles away from human habitation, of conflicts with grizzly
               bears, mountain lions, etc., but by far the most weird story we have heard is told by
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#man26; #man27">two well-known young men of
                     this place</persName></rs>, who were on a prospecting tour some time since near
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_cobb">Cobblestone Mountain</placeName>, at the
               northern boundary of <rs><placeName type="county" key="#co_ventura">this
                     county</placeName></rs>. The story they tell&#8212;and they are willing to take
               their oath on the truth of the statement&#8212;is about as follows:</p>
            <p>One cold night they were simultaneously awakened about 2 o'clock by the noise of
               crackling brush that had been thrown on the fire. They arose to a sitting posture and
               saw the figure of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">an Indian
                     woman</persName></rs> standing by the fire. She was dressed in a robe of
               gayly-colored material that almost reached to her feet. A glistening necklace,
               evidently of gold and silver, enriched her neck, and hanging pendant from this were a
               number of bears' claws. Her black hair reached below her waist. In her ears were
               large hoop ear-rings of gold.</p>
            <p>Upon seeing <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">the form</persName></rs>,
                     <rs><persName key="#man26">one of the young men</persName></rs> instinctively
               reached for his rifle by his side, while <rs><persName key="#man27">the
                     other</persName></rs> started in amazement at seeing such a sight in the dead
               of the night and thirty miles from any house. When <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">the figure</persName></rs> saw the motion
               made to reach the rifle she motioned for them not to fire and moved down the trail,
               beckoning to them. Before disappearing from view she again beckoned to them, but they
               were too dumfounded to follow.</p>
            <p>The next morning they followed the trail, and after much difficulty traced the
               foot-prints to the base of a high cliff about a mile from their camp. The rest of the
               story is told to this effect: "When I awoke," said <rs><persName key="#man26">one of
                     the young men</persName></rs>, "I was horrified. I couldn't move to save my
               life. I was frozen with astonishment. The next morning we discussed the matter, and
               determined to investigate. So the next night we took our blankets and went to the
               base of the cliff. At about midnight, the same hour <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">the figure</persName></rs> appeared to us, we
               saw a bright phosphorescent light on the brow of the cliff, and I am sure we heard a
               voice calling '<persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">Meeneeah</persName>!
                  <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">Meeneeah</persName>!' several times.
               This is the strangest experience I ever passed through. I never have believed in
               ghosts, but I would like to know what this was. If it was a woman how did she come
               there at that time[,] thirty miles from civilization?"</p>
            <p>An old Indian tradition is to the effect that many, many years ago an Indian
                  maiden&#8212;<persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">Meeneeah</persName>, the
               only daughter of <rs><persName key="#indian13">a chief</persName></rs>&#8212;was lost
               in this region and starved to death near the place called <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_sqfa">Squaw Flat</placeName>. It is said that different camping parties
               have seen the phosphorescent light spoken of in the vicinity where <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#man26; #man27">these young men</persName></rs> were camped.
               Can this be a parallel case with that of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the Indian woman</persName></rs> abandoned on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas Island</placeName> for <rs><date
                     from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs>?"</p>
            <byline>&#8212;<emph><orgName type="publication" key="#venturafp">Ventura (Cal.) Free
                     Press</orgName></emph>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
