<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#gdn">Galveston Daily
                     News</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="45"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="307"/>
               <date when="1887-02-27"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_galveston">Galveston</placeName>,
                     <placeName type="state" key="#st_tx">Texas</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#GalvestonDailyNews1887">An Indian Ghost</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="9"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">An Indian
                        Ghost</persName></rs>.</title></head>
            <p>The most weird story we have heard is told by <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#man26; #man27">two well-known men of this place</persName></rs>, who were
               on a prospecting tour some three weeks since, near <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_cobb">Cobblestone mountain</placeName>, at the northern boundary of
                     <rs><placeName type="county" key="#co_ventura">this county</placeName></rs>.
               One cold night they were simultaneously awakened about 2 o'clock by the noise of
               crackling brush that had been thrown on the fire. They arose to a sitting posture and
               saw the figure of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">an Indian
                     woman</persName></rs> standing by the fire. She was dressed in a robe of gayly
               colored material that nearly reached ther feet. A glistening necklace, evidently of
               gold and silver, enriched her neck, and hanging pendant from this was a number of
               bears' claws. Her black hair reached below her waist. In her ears were large hoop
               earrings of gold.</p>
            <p>Upon seeing <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">the form</persName></rs>
               <rs><persName key="#man26">one of the young men</persName></rs> instinctively reached
               for his rifle by his side. When <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">the
                     figure</persName></rs> saw the motion she motioned for him not to fire and
               moved down the trail, beckoning to them. Before disappearing from view she again
               beckoned, but they were too dumbfounded to follow. The next morning they followed the
               trail, and after much difficulty traced the footprints to the base of a high cliff
               about a mile from their camp. The rest of the story told is to this effect: "The next
               morning we discussed the matter and determined to investigate. So the next night we
               took our blankets and went to the base of the cliff. At about midnight, the same
               hour, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">the figure</persName></rs>
               appeared to us; we saw a bright phosphorescent light on the brow of the cliff, and I
               am sure we heard a voice calling '<persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen"
                  >Meeneeah</persName>! <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen"
                  >Meeneeah</persName>!'"</p>
            <p>An old Indian tradition is to the effect that many, many years ago an Indian
                  maiden&#8212;<persName type="nativeamerican" key="#meen">Meeneeah</persName>, the
               only daughter of <rs><persName key="#indian13">a chief</persName></rs>&#8212;was lost
               in this region and starved to death near the place called <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_sqfa">Squaw Flat</placeName>. It is said that many camping parties have
               seen the phosphorescent light spoken of in the vicinity where <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#man26; #man27">these young men</persName></rs> were
               camped.</p>
            <byline>[Ventura (Cal) Free Press. [sic]</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
