<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#latimes">Los Angeles
                            Times</orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
                    <date when="1889-08-25"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>,
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="article" key="#Kelp1889">Archaeological. Relics of the Oriental
                            Races of Catalina. Interesting Discoveries Under the Hotel
                            Metropole--Stone Implements, Earrings, Beads,Fishhooks, Mortars,
                            Pestles, Arts of the Aborigines, Etc.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page" n="9"/>
                        <author><persName type="author" key="#kelp">Kelp</persName></author>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">Archaeological.</hi></title>
                    <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">Relics of the Oriental Races of <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                        >Catalina</placeName></rs>.</hi></title>
                    <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">Interesting Discoveries Under the <placeName
                                key="#metropole">Hotel Metropole</placeName>&#8212;Stone Implements,
                            Earrings, Beads,Fishhooks, Mortars, Pestles, Arts of the Aborigines,
                            Etc.</hi></title></head>
                <dateline><placeName type="city" key="#ci_av">AVALON (Catalina)</placeName>, <date
                        when="1889-08-17">Aug. 17.</date>&#8212;[Special Correspondence of
                            <rs><orgName type="publication" key="#latimes">THE
                    TIMES</orgName></rs>.]</dateline>
                <p><rs><date when="1589">Three hundred years ago</date></rs>, where the <placeName
                        key="#metropole">Hotel Metropole</placeName> now stands, was a large and
                    populous native village. Exactly who <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                            key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the people</orgName></rs> were and where
                    they have gone to is one of the conundrums proposed to every visitor to
                            <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the sea-girt
                            isle</placeName></rs>.</p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="6">This we do know, that <rs><orgName
                                type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the races
                                who lived here</orgName></rs> have been utterly wiped out of
                        existence to all intents and purposes, and no one can be found among the
                        very aged people among the Indians of the mainland who will claim to be
                        descendants of them.</span></p>
                <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina Island</placeName> was
                    discovered by <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> in <date
                        when="1542">1542</date>, and named by him La Victoria, after one of his
                    fleet. The present name of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                        >Catalina</placeName> was given it by <persName type="seaman" key="#svi"
                        >Vizcaino</persName>, who landed here in <date when="1602">1602</date>,
                    nearly 100 years later. An interesting account of Cabrillo's voyages, written by
                            <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#bfe">one of his
                    pilots</persName></rs>, has recently been found among old papers in <placeName
                        type="country" key="#co_Spain">Spain</placeName>; but perhaps the most
                    satisfactory account is of the voyage of <persName type="seaman" key="#svi"
                        >Vizcaino</persName>. He reports <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                        >Catalina</placeName> as being thickly populated, and makes especial mention
                    of the fact that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                            key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the people</orgName></rs> were adepts at
                    stealing. <persName type="missionfather" key="#ascan">Father
                        Ascancion</persName>, who accompanied this expedition, recorded many
                    interesting facts, and among them was a description of a "<placeName
                        key="#suntemple">Temple of the Sun</placeName>," said to be near
                            <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_catalinaharbor">the two
                            harbors</placeName></rs> and to contain images and idols.</p>
                <p><rs><placeName key="#suntemple">This temple</placeName></rs> was probably what
                    first attracted the attention of scientific men in this direction, and nearly
                    every year since the old padre's account has been translated some one has
                    searched for it; but the account is so indefinite that the location has never
                    been found, though some think it was upon <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl"
                        >San Clemente</placeName>. The preponderance of opinion, however, is that it
                    was on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, and
                    possibly the idols and images may have been covered up and will some day be
                    unearthed.</p>
                <p><rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">The Indians
                            or natives of Catalina</orgName></rs> had two or three principal
                    settlements or villages, one on the site of the present <placeName
                        key="#metropole">Hotel Metropole</placeName>, and the other at the isthmus,
                    with smaller ones at different points where there was water.</p>
                <p>The archæological eye readily recognizes these locations by the peculiar nature
                    of the soil, which looks as though it had been mixed with coal dust or burnt
                    wood. The garden of <rs><placeName key="#metropole">the
                        Metropole</placeName></rs> shows this, being made of earth full of bones,
                    charred wood, ground shell; earth that has been lived on for centuries and been
                    discolored by the occupation.</p>
                <p><rs><date notBefore="1879" notAfter="1881">Eight or ten years ago</date></rs>
                    <persName key="#mjoe">Mexican Joe</persName> and <persName key="#oldbilly">old
                        Billy</persName> were about the only occupants who lived here all the year
                    round. They were familiar with the curious implements found here, but thought
                    nothing of them. One day <persName type="author" key="#psc">Prof.
                        Schumacher</persName>, a representative of several eastern scientific
                    museums and colleges, appeared on the scene. He hired <persName key="#mjoe"
                        >Mexican Joe</persName>, and by the aid of charts and maps began a
                    systematic series of excavations, which resulted in the collection of a fine lot
                    of implements from <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">this
                            island</placeName></rs>, telling the complete history of <rs><orgName
                            type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the unknown
                            inhabitants</orgName></rs> so far as their domestic habits were
                    concerned.</p>
                <p><persName key="#mjoe">Mexican Joe</persName> began to dig from the present
                        <placeName key="#metropole">Metropole Hotel</placeName> site into what is
                    now the street about where the swing stands, and the result was a bonanza to the
                    scientist. At almost every shovelful some stone implement appeared. There were
                    pestles made of hard stone, some from eight inches to two feet in length, others
                    short and thick. The long ones were used much as the apothecary grinds his
                    medicine today, only with these people it was grain or seed that were broken up
                    or crushed, the long stone pestles or clubs being admirably suited for this
                    purpose. They told the story of how at least their grain was crushed, which they
                    probably obtained from <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                        mainland</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The grain must have been held in something, and scores of fine stone vessels or
                    mortars, dug up here by the two excavators, told the story. They were of all
                    sizes; some holding a peck, and two feet high, of soapstone from a quarry found
                    five miles below <placeName type="city" key="#ci_av">Avalon</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Some were very small, holding very little, and they ranged from the largest size
                    down to small ones three or four inches across, evidently intended as paint
                    pots. Several hundred fine mortars were found in the Metropole site village, the
                    shapes resembling those in the accompanying cut.</p>
                <p>Only yesterday an excavation was being made for a new building, when a fine small
                    mortar was dug up, which is of especial interest, as it bears on the side a
                    small rude figure as shown it [in] cut 3. It is the only figure so far found
                    that could be considered as showing that these people had some idea of
                    representing objects by a pencil. The figure, which of course may have been cut
                    by a modern, though I was assured by <persName key="#ken">Mr. Kennedy</persName>
                    that it was on the mortar when found, is a rude attempt at a human form, cut in
                    the soft soapstone with a knife or stone.</p>
                <p>There are other ornaments upon the mortar, of various kinds.</p>
                <p><persName type="author" key="#psc">Prof. Schumacher</persName> found hundreds of
                    objects here: Oval stones, with stones in the center fairly polished, some of
                    which can be seen in the billiard-room of <rs><placeName key="#metropole">the
                            Metropole</placeName></rs>. What these are is a mystery, but, curiously
                    enough, they are found among all the savage and prehistoric tribes of the world.
                    The object which is shown in figure 3 is about three inches thick, and may have
                    been used in a game of some kind, or as a weight to a digging stick. Some
                    contend that they were sinkers or weights to nets, which would be a very
                    plausible idea if there was any reason to believe that the people had large
                    nets.</p>
                <p>These sinkers, as we will call them, are also found on <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> far from the water. While sitting on
                    the Metropole piazza the other day, I saw a gleam on the surface of the garden
                    plot, and found that it was caused by several flatbeads [sic] of abalone shell,
                    really beautiful but very fragile objects&#8212;evidently worn by some dusky
                    belle years ago. These beads, shown in cut No. 4, are remarkably symmetrical; in
                    fact, perfect, and how they were made without tools is a mystery.</p>
                <p>That <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">these
                            people</orgName></rs> were fond of display was very evident by the finds
                    of <persName type="author" key="#psc">Prof. Schumacher</persName>. Hundreds of
                    abalone ornaments were found, cut in graceful curves; many carvings like
                    fishhooks, pendants, curious-shaped stones, some like shoes, others like the
                    human foot, while others seemed to have shapes that had no definite meaning.
                    These, or many of them, can be seen in the curiosity store of <persName
                        key="#elms">Mr. Elms</persName>, the postmaster of <placeName type="city"
                        key="#ci_av">Avalon</placeName>, and hundreds of specimens were taken away
                    by <rs><persName key="#elms">the collector referred to</persName></rs>. In
                    hunting other localities <persName type="author" key="#psc">Prof.
                        Schumacher</persName> found a soapstone quarry on <rs><placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>, and a
                    place where the mortars were made. Many of the latter were found incomplete or
                    broken, just as they had been left, and undoubtedly here were made many of the
                    large and beautiful mortars that have been found by collectors on <placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>. <rs><orgName
                            type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">The Catalina
                            people</orgName></rs> doubtless made them, or some of them, and traded
                    with the Indians of the shore.</p>
                <p><rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">The
                            natives</orgName></rs> were naturally dependent upon fish for a living,
                    and fishhooks are found in great quantities, being made of abalone shell and
                    resembling the modern hook, with the exception that in these ancient specimens
                    the barb is upon the outside. Hundreds of these have been found about the
                    Metropole grounds, and where the excavations were made for the foundations large
                    quantities of material of all kinds were secured.</p>
                <p>The location at the isthmus was preeminently a burying-ground, and during a
                    recent examination <rs><persName type="author" key="#kelp">the
                        writer</persName></rs> unearthed a number of interesting objects. In working
                    it was found that the bodies had been buried in about four layers, the lowest
                    down being naturally the oldest. Here when a man dies many of the household gods
                    were deposited with him. In digging carefully under a body I found that beads in
                    large numbers had either been left around the neck of the deceased or thrown
                    upon the body, probably the former, as when the earth was removed from beneath
                    the skull the beads ran down in a stream. They were of all kinds&#8212;some
                    large, with ornamentation, others of Venetian type, but mostly bits of shell
                    perforated nicely and made from certain small shells. Though rude and rough it
                    must have taken no little time to make them, and they were evidently valued,
                    probably as money and ornaments as well.</p>
                <p>I found a small section still strung upon some vegetable fiber, with pieces of
                    copper wire coiled in a circle, evidently as rings, to connect the ends. Among
                    the beads was one made from a human tooth; others from bones of birds.</p>
                <p>The Venetian beads were identical with some I found being used by <rs><persName
                            type="nativeamerican" key="#indian10">an aged Indian
                        woman</persName></rs> at <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sgabriel">San
                        Gabriel Mission</placeName> some time ago. She informed me that she obtained
                    them from the old <orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">Mission
                        fathers</orgName>
                    <rs><date notBefore="1819" notAfter="1829">sixty or seventy years
                        ago</date></rs>, and these beads we took from these <rs><placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName></rs> graves were
                    probably obtained from the same source.</p>
                <p>That the <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                            >ancient Catalinians</orgName></rs> were musical there is little doubt,
                    as remains of numerous flutes were taken from these graves. Nearly all were
                    broken, but I found one fairly perfect, one which showed the hole and the marks
                    of asphaltum with which it had been wrapped. A perfect one given [to] me by
                        <persName key="#elms">Mr. Elms</persName>, the postmaster at <placeName
                        type="city" key="#ci_av">Avalon</placeName>, which came from <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scl">Clemente</placeName>, shows that the instrument
                    must have produced a very fair noise, as noises go. <persName type="author"
                        key="#psc">Prof. Schumacher</persName> took numbers of these here at various
                    points. Some, as shown in the following cut, were double and connected by a
                    piece of asphaltum.</p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="3">While some very fine flint spearheads have been found
                        here, <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                                >the people</orgName></rs> were undoubtedly of a peaceful nature,
                        seldom going to war. Arrowheads are rare. In the grave at the isthmus I
                        found a bone sword, which could only have been of use in some ceremonial,
                        and it is known that swords made from the bones of whales were
                    used.</span></p>
                <p>Not the least interesting were the objects I took out that were obtained from the
                    Spaniards, perhaps <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> or
                        <persName type="seaman" key="#svi">V[i]zcaino</persName> themselves. One was
                    a large iron ax, which <persName type="author" key="#hru">Mr. H. N.
                        Rust</persName> pronounced of Spanish type. It was covered with rust and
                    scaled easily, but still shows the cloth that had be been carefully wrapped
                    around it. Another was an iron knife, which had been wrapped in a similar way,
                    evidently a treasure, and buried with the owner. In the present article even an
                    enumeration of the articles found could not be attempted, covering as they do
                    every article used by these people, from paint and paint-pots up to the
                    magnificent stone mortars that must have required years to make.</p>
                <p><span type="trope" n="6">Where are <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the people or their
                                descendants</orgName></rs> is an interesting problem. <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The last squaw</persName></rs> was
                        taken from <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas
                            Island</placeName>
                        <rs><date when="1853">some years ago</date></rs>, but <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> and <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> have not
                        been inhabited within the memory of man. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                key="#indian11">An aged Indian</persName></rs>, claiming to be over
                        100, informed me that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the natives</orgName></rs> were
                        encouraged to leave here by the <rs><orgName type="missionfathers"
                                key="#misfats"><emph>padres</emph></orgName></rs>, who gave them
                        homes about <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the
                                missions</orgName></rs>, so that they could convert them. Others
                        claim that they were killed off by disease.</span>
                    <persName key="#mjoe">Mexican Joe</persName> says that when he came here, back
                    in <rs><date notBefore="1850" notAfter="1859">the '50s</date></rs>, Indian dogs
                    were still running wild on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the
                            island</placeName></rs>. It is somewhat curious that so little is known
                    about so interesting a subject, and one that, now <rs><placeName type="island"
                            key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs> bids fair to be such a
                    famous resort, will grow in interest every year.</p>
                <byline><persName type="author" key="#kelp">KELP</persName>.</byline>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
