<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="journal" key="#overlandmonthly">Overland Monthly</title>
               <publisher/><editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="16"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="93"/>
               <date when="1890-09"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <publisher/>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#McDougall1890">A Woman's Log of 1849</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="273" to="280"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#wmcd">McDougall, William
                     H.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <div type="section">
            <head><title type="main">A WOMAN'S LOG OF <date when="1849">1849</date>.</title>
               <title type="sub">FROM THE DIARY OF <persName type="author" key="#mjmc">MRS. JOHN
                     MCDOUGALL</persName>.</title></head>
            <p>[THESE notes are, as their title purports, brief daily jottings at sea, without
               attempt at literary form. They were made on the first outward trip of the "<name
                  type="ship" key="#sh_california">California</name>" &#8212; a name that shall be
               to our children's children a classic, as is the <name type="ship" key="#sh_mayflower"
                  >Mayflower</name>.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#mjmc">Mrs. McDougall</persName> was one of the
               comparatively few women passengers of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_california">that
                     vessel</name></rs> when, on <date when="1849-02-28">February 28, 1849</date>,
               it entered the <placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">Bay of San
                  Francisco</placeName>, &#8212; whose waters it was the first steamship ever to
               break.</p>
            <p>Of that voyage of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_california">our western
                  Argo</name></rs> and its Argonauts much has been written. But of its return trip
               &#8212; for which the world (this province being quite out of it) waited intently
               &#8212; this is, so far as I know, the first published record.</p>
            <p>Concerning most of those who are mentioned in these notes, inquiry has elicited but
               little. Some, however, are of local, and others of national, distinction. The
                  <persName key="#eca">Major Canby</persName> is the <persName key="#eca">General E.
                  R. S. Canby</persName> of the Civil and Indian wars. <persName key="#jstev"
                  >Colonel J. D. Stevenson</persName> was one of the first United States military
               commanders of <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">the Pacific
                  Coast</placeName>, and largely influential in the forming of the State government
               of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. He is still, at the
               age of ninety years, actively engaged in the practice of law in <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, &#8212; the picture of hale
               and courtly age. From him I learned that <persName key="#wpa">Doctor (William C.)
                  Parker</persName> was one of his staff, and now lives at <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sc">Santa Cruz</placeName>; and that the <persName key="#rma">Colonel (R.
                  B.) Mason</persName> is the one who was for a time the Military Governor of
                  <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. The <persName
                  key="#swil">Mr. Willey</persName> is the <persName key="#swil">Rev. Dr. S. H.
                  Willey</persName> to whom <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName> is, perhaps, mainly indebted for its <rs><orgName
                     type="institution" key="#in_ucb">University</orgName></rs>, and who is still
               prominent in educational and religious affairs. To <persName key="#jfol">Captain (J.
                  L.) Folsom</persName>, then Quartermaster, is imputed the distinction of chiefly
               determining the metropolis of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the
                     coast</placeName></rs> to be at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                  Francisco</placeName>, and not at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ben"
                  >Benicia</placeName>, by retaining the federal offices at <rs><placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sf">the former city</placeName></rs>, &#8212; or
               sand-hills, &#8212; which was done against strenuous opposition. <persName key="#owh"
                  >Rev. (O. C.) Wheeler</persName>, who came to the territory as a missionary, has
               been for many years an official of the <orgName type="company" key="#spacrrco"
                  >Southern Pacific Railroad Company</orgName>. <persName key="#mogden">Mrs.
                  Ogden</persName>, was the wife of <persName key="#ogden">Major Ogden</persName>,
               of <persName type="military" key="#psm">General Persifer F. Smith</persName>'s
               company.</p>
            <p>Of <name type="ship" key="#sh_california">the California</name> herself I learn
               merely that, after her disuse in the passenger traffic, she served some years in the
               Australian coal trade, and a few years since was "dismantled and broken up."</p>
            <p><rs><title type="article" key="#McDougall1890">The diary</title></rs> is given
               substantially as written, with some omissions &#8212; not indicated in the text
               &#8212; and a few notes and conjectures indicated by brackets.</p>
            <byline><emph><persName type="author" key="#wmcd">W. H. McD.</persName></emph>]
            </byline>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-01">May 1, Tuesday Morning</date></emph>. &#8212; This is
               the day we are to bid adieu to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                  Francisco</placeName> and, with the exception of leaving <rs><persName
                     type="author" key="#wmcd">my husband</persName></rs> [then absent, I believe,
               at the mines] and three or four friends, I confess I leave it without regret.</p>
            <p>The morning is very gloomy and unpleasant. We left Mr. Bawden's house at half past
               nine o'clock and walked down to the point, <persName key="#jstev">Colonel John
                  Stevenson</persName> and <persName key="#wpa">Doctor Parker</persName> overtaking
               us on the way. <persName key="#owh">Mr.</persName> and <persName key="#mwhe">Mrs.
                  Wheeler</persName>, <persName key="#mgo">Mrs. Goodwin</persName>, <persName
                  key="#jfol">Captain Folsom</persName>, and <persName key="#gri">Mr.</persName> and
                  <persName key="#mgr">Mrs. Grimes</persName> came down to <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">the steamer</name></rs> soon afterward. We sat and talked
               some time, &#8212; made merry, or tried to, but many were the sad hearts. Friends
               were parting, perhaps forever; some with a long and dangerous journey before them,
               and others . . . . where comforts cannot be procured even for gold. <persName
                  key="#baw">Mr.</persName> and <persName key="#mbaw">Mrs. Bawden</persName>,
                  <persName key="#jstev">Colonel Stevenson</persName>, <persName key="#wpa">Doctor
                  Parker</persName>, and myself embarked on <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_whaleboat">a whale boat</name></rs> for <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">the steamer</name></rs> at half past ten. Found <name
                  type="ship" key="#sh_california">the California</name> as cold and cheerless as
               ever, though much cleaner than on her trip up.</p>
            <p>At two o'clock we left <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>
               for <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sa">Saucelito</placeName>, where we have lain
               ever since, getting on water. Had a very poor dinner of roast beef and yams about
               three o'clock. I regretted very much leaving <persName key="#baw">Mr.
                  Bawden</persName>, <persName key="#jstev">the Colonel</persName>, and
                     <rs><persName key="#wpa">the Doctor</persName></rs>, who have shown me great
               kindness since I have been in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName>; <rs><persName type="group" key="#jstev; #wpa">the two
                     latter</persName></rs> seem more like brothers than anything else.</p>
            <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sa">Saucelito</placeName> is a little cove in among
               the hills, a very picturesque place although the hills are barren of trees. Very fine
               water here, and easy of access for vessels.</p>
            <p><emph>Eight o'clock</emph>. &#8212; We are just done tea, and being tired, cold, and
               low-spirited, I determined to go to bed, hoping to waken <rs><date when="1849-05-02"
                     >tomorrow morning</date></rs> in the <placeName type="region" key="#re_mobay"
                  >Bay of Monterey</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-02">May 2, Wednesday</date></emph>. &#8212; Was quite sick
                     <rs><date when="1849-05-01">last night</date></rs>, but after breakfast felt
               able to go on deck and take a look at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo"
                  >Monterey</placeName>. It has one of the most beautiful situations I ever saw, on
               the sides of several hills, which, sloping back from <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_mobay">the bay</placeName></rs>, are partially covered with dark
               pines, and partly with nothing but green grass. It has the appearance of beautiful
               green meadows, but I am told it is all parched up later in the year.</p>
            <p>We arrived here about ten o'clock. <persName key="#eca">Major Canby</persName> and
                  <persName key="#swil">Mr. Willey</persName> came on board. They seem like old
               friends, as we came out from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nola">New
                  Orleans</placeName> together. [Their voyage from that port to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_cha">Chagres</placeName> was on the <name type="ship"
                  key="#sh_falcon">Falcon</name>, the first steamer to sail from <rs><placeName
                     type="country" key="#co_usa">the States</placeName></rs> on the California
               route, leaving <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nola">New Orleans</placeName>
               <date when="1848-12-18">December 18, 1848</date>.] <persName key="#meca">Mrs.
                  Canby</persName> sent me a package of letters, a most beautiful bouquet, some eggs
               and dried apples, by <persName key="#rma">Colonel Mason</persName> ; all very
               acceptable presents, as we had a hard time to get anything to eat on <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_california">the steamer</name></rs>.</p>
            <p>At twelve o'clock we hoisted anchor and went out to sea. The sea is always very rough
               passing <placeName type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName>
                  [<placeName type="region" key="#re_pcarmel">Point Carmel</placeName>?]. Too sick
               to write.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-03">May 3, Thursday Morning</date></emph> &#8212; We were
               awakened <rs><date when="1849-05-02">last night</date></rs> at twelve o'clock by the
               most alarming of all sounds at sea, &#8212; "<rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">The ship</name></rs> is on fire!" Great was the
               excitement; the women and children were screaming; gentlemen, just roused from sleep,
               coming out half dressed, to inquire what was the matter; others running with water.
               It was some time before the ladies would be assured there was no danger. The fire, as
               it was supposed to be, proved to be only the friction of the wheel where it went into
               a mortise, I believe. There would have been danger if it had not been discovered in
               time.</p>
            <p>The sea is still very rough, and neglecting to have our port-holes closed, both
                  <persName key="#gmc">George</persName> [<persName key="#gmc">George
                  McDougall</persName>, her brother-in-law] and I had our staterooms filled with
               water, and he had a fine salt shower-bath.</p>
            <p>At half-past one o'clock we dropped anchor off the port of <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, a very pretty place on an inclined plane
               that ascends gradually from the beach. About midway to the top of the hill is a
               mission with a very fine church, &#8212; gardens, orchards, etc., attached to it.
               With Yankee enterprise it might be made one of the garden spots of the earth, as all
               kinds of fruits and flowers grow almost spontaneously. But the people are so indolent
               that we could get no supplies for <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_california">the
                     ship</name></rs>, not even milk, though we could see from <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">the ship</name></rs> hundreds of cows grazing over the
               hills. The harbor is very bad for ships, as the kelp grows so thick that it is almost
               impossible to get a ship through it. It grows twenty feet long, and is strong as a
               cable.</p>
            <p>In coming to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> we passed
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">an island</placeName></rs> about sixty
               miles from <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the
               coast</placeName></rs>, on which there is <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">a lone woman</persName></rs> living. <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba">The Russians</persName></rs>,
                     <rs><date when="1814">some years ago</date></rs>, had <rs><persName
                     type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">a
                     party</persName></rs> there catching otter; a storm coming up they were obliged
               to put out to sea, leaving <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">some
                     of their party</persName></rs> on shore. They afterwards returned and got them
               all off but <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs>,
               who has lived there alone ever since.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14"><rs><date notBefore="1846">Some three years ago</date></rs>
                  they caught her, but she was perfectly wild and had lost her speech, so they left
                  her.</span></p>
            <p>About four o'clock we hoisted anchor and left <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                  >Santa Barbara</placeName>. Sea rough; seasick!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-04">May 4, Friday</date></emph>. &#8212; Was awakened this
               morning by <persName key="#turner">Turner</persName> [her man-servant], who brought
               me in some tea and nice toast, &#8212; very acceptable, as we do not breakfast until
               after nine. After breakfast went on deck to look at the <placeName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_stjohn">Mission of St. John's</placeName>, situated in a small valley
               surrounded with hills, which at this season of the year are covered with flowers. If
               it could always be spring in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName> it would be a beautiful country, but nine months of the
               year it is parched and barren. They have no lightning here.</p>
            <p>Between three and four o'clock we entered the harbor of <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>, the entrance to which is very narrow and
               sometimes hazardous. After you are in you are completely surrounded with hills
               covered with grass and flowers, but not a tree to be seen. We anchored near the
               shore, on which were two or three small huts and a few graves of foreigners, on the
               side of the hill with a white railing around, in full view to remind us of what may
               be our destiny before we reach home.</p>
            <p>The ship <name type="ship" key="#sh_edith">Edith</name> was in the harbor landing
               government troops, for the line of <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">the United
                  States</placeName> is only four or five miles below. The town of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName> we saw in the distance, some three
               or four miles around <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sdharbor">the
                     bay</placeName></rs>, but it looked barren and desolate. After remaining about
               an hour we set off again a short while before dark.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-06">May 6, Sunday</date></emph>. &#8212; <persName
                  key="#tho">Captain Thomas</persName> read the Episcopal service in the cabin. Most
               of the lady passengers responded. It is the first time I ever heard it at sea and it
               reminded me of home.</p>
            <p>Am now writing in my berth. Have been reading "The Inheritance," by <persName
                  type="author" key="#mturn">Miss Turner</persName>. After tea <persName
                  key="#forbes">Captain Forbes</persName> and <persName key="#mogden">Mrs.
                  Ogden</persName> gave us some sacred music on the accordion and with their voices.
               We have run 251 miles in the last twenty-four hours.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-07">May 7, Monday</date></emph>. &#8212; Great excitement
               last night, &#8212; <rs><persName key="#man20">a man</persName></rs> missing and
               supposed to be overboard. Of course all his faults were buried in the deep with him,
               and he was eulogized as the best fireman, most capable man on the ship, etc. About
               breakfast time he was discovered in the carpenter's room enjoying a comfortable
               sleep. <rs><persName key="#spaniard1">One poor Spaniard</persName></rs> today lost
               seven pounds of gold dust overboard; all, it is said, the poor fellow had.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-08">May 8, Tuesday</date></emph>. &#8212; Doubled
                  <placeName key="#re_lucas">Cape St. Lucas</placeName> about twelve o'clock
                     <rs><date when="1849-05-07">last night</date></rs>. Felt sick all day owing to
               want of proper food, as we have yery [very] little but mutton. Anchored off the port
               of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_maz">Mazatlan</placeName> about ten o'clock
               to-night.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-09">May 9, Wednesday</date></emph>. &#8212; Early <rs><date
                     when="1849-05-09">this morning</date></rs> we came into the bay. After
               breakfast <persName key="#mbaw">Mrs. Bawden</persName>, <persName key="#mgr">Mrs.
                  Grimes</persName>, <persName key="#mogden">Mrs. Ogden</persName>, <persName
                  key="#msmi">Mrs. Smith</persName>, Messrs. <persName type="author" key="#gau"
                  >Gaur</persName>, <persName key="#tho">Thomas</persName>, <persName key="#mur"
                  >Murphy</persName>, <persName key="#brow">Brown</persName>, <persName key="#rma"
                  >Colonel Mason</persName>, and I, went ashore together in one of the ship's boats.
               We went to <placeName key="#motthouse">Captain Mott's house</placeName> and found it
               very cool and pleasant, and the ladies very agreeable. <persName key="#talbott">Mr.
                  Talbott</persName> went with <persName key="#mbaw">Mrs. Bawden</persName>,
                  <persName key="#mgr">Mrs. Grimes</persName>, and myself, to some of the stores,
               bought a few articles, and returned to <rs><placeName key="#motthouse">Mr.
                     Mott's</placeName></rs>, where we had a very fine luncheon of fruits, melons,
               etc. Took a walk to the beach; went into <placeName key="#kellyhouse">Mr. Kelly's
                  house</placeName> &#8212; found it quite a palace. <persName key="#kel"
                  >Mr.</persName> and <persName key="#mkel">Mrs.</persName> and <persName
                  key="#misskel">Miss Kelly</persName> were very agreeable and we had a delightful
               call. <persName key="#talbott">Mr. Talbott</persName> got one of the Custom House
               boats and came off with us to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_california">the
                     ship</name></rs>. Were delighted with <placeName type="city" key="#ci_maz"
                  >Mazatlan</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-10">May 10</date>, Thursday</emph>. &#8212; Entered the
               port of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sblas">San Blas</placeName> this morning.
               Mrs. Bawden's birthday. She treated the ladies to some champagne and cake, and
                  <persName key="#turner">Turner</persName> brought us a very nice lunch, and we had
               a cozy little time in our rooms ; &#8212; as there is a door between we can throw
               them into one.</p>
            <p>The site of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sblas">San Blas</placeName> is very
               romantic, &#8212; hills and valleys overlooking a bay dotted with islands; most of
               them, though, of barren rocks. <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sblas">The
                     town</placeName></rs> itself is a poor, miserable village with thatched houses.
               A large party of Americans arrived here today from across the country, on their way
               to <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. May their golden
               dreams be realized ! as their ideas of comfort never can be.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-11">May 11, Friday</date></emph>. &#8212; A very beautiful
               morning. The passengers very much frightened by <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">the steamer</name></rs> stopping suddenly and with a great
               jar about four o'clock <rs><date when="1849-05-11">this afternoon</date></rs>. Some
               of the machinery out of order and soon rectified.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph>May 13, Sunday</emph>. &#8212; and what a Sunday it is! We are in the port of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_aca">Acapulco</placeName>. The passengers have
               most of them gone on shore, and the natives are flocking on board by dozens, running
               fore and aft, up and clown stairs, chattering in Spanish. It is impossible to read,
               and the day is excessively warm, <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_acapulcobay"
                     >the bay</placeName></rs> is entirely shut in by hills, and there can be no
               breeze. This is probably the best protected harbor in the world.</p>
            <p>We hear at this place of <rs><name type="group" key="#sh_mcdougall5; #sh_mcdougall6"
                     >two ships</name></rs> that are out at sea without a drop of water. Some of the
               passengers came off here in a small boat, procured water, and went off in search of
               their ship, but could not find her. Several other attempts have been made to find the
               ship, but as yet without success. Three or four beacon fires are lighted on the
               different hills tonight. Heaven grant they may see them and be enabled to reach
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_aca">this port</placeName></rs>, for to die
               of thirst must be horrible. <rs><persName key="#jfol">The captain</persName></rs> of
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_california">our steamer</name></rs> is taking on
               a large supply of water, in the hope that we may fall in with them tomorrow. It is
               said here that four men came from <placeName type="country" key="#co_pan"
                  >Panama</placeName> here in <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_whaleboat">a whale
                     boat</name></rs>, alternately sailing and rowing, in eighteen days, &#8212; a
               distance of thirteen hundred miles. It seems almost incredible.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-14">May 14, Monday</date></emph>. &#8212; We left
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_aca">Acapulco</placeName> this morning, and are
               again in the open sea, not to leave it again until we arrive at <placeName
                  type="country" key="#co_pan">Panama</placeName>, if we meet with no misfortune.
               Have not seen anything of the ships that are in distress.</p>
            <p>[Later.] &#8212; About three o'clock this afternoon we came in sight of a sail. The
               captain, thinking it might be one of the ships, came alongside of her, and on hailing
               her and asking if she wanted anything, they cried out, "Water."</p>
            <p>They had been eighty days out from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_val"
                  >Valparaiso</placeName>, and had been on short allowance of water for forty days.
                     <rs><persName key="#jfol">The captain</persName></rs> sent them two large casks
               of water and some fruit and melons, for which they seemed very grateful, and sent in
               return four large hams and a box of champagne, over which we had a very merry dinner
               ; indeed, I have not seen so much enjoyment and good feeling among the passengers
               since we left.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-17">May 17, Thursday</date></emph>. &#8212; We are very
               short of coal, and as there is a pretty fair wind today the engine is stopped and all
               sails set. We are going at the rate of four or five miles an hour, &#8212; slow
               traveling. <rs><persName key="#jfol">The captain</persName></rs> kept us a day at
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sblas">San Blas</placeName>, where there was
               plenty of coal, and did not get any. He is certainly to be blamed for not supplying
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_california">the ship</name></rs> better, but
                     <rs><persName key="#hobbs">Mr. H</persName></rs> &#8212; &#8212; ,
                     <rs><persName type="author" key="#gau">Mr. G &#8212; &#8212; </persName></rs>,
                     <rs><persName key="#mbaw">Mrs. B &#8212; &#8212; </persName></rs>, and
                     <rs><persName key="#mgr">Mrs. G &#8212; &#8212; </persName></rs>, can grumble
               enough for the whole ship, so I take it easy.</p>
            <p>Went on deck after tea. <persName key="#tho">Captain Thomas</persName> sang us "The
               Bride" and "The Rose of Allandale." Afterward <persName key="#forbes">Captain
                  Forbes</persName> got out his accordion and played while he and <persName
                  key="#tho">Captain Thomas</persName> sang. We are over seven hundred miles from
                  <placeName type="country" key="#co_pan">Panama</placeName> yet.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-18">May 18, Friday</date></emph>. &#8212; Last night
                     <rs><persName key="#sailor5">one of the sailors</persName></rs> was heard to
               say something to <rs><persName key="#sailor6">one of his companions</persName></rs>
               that sounded very much like mutiny, and was construed as such by <persName
                  key="#johnson">Mr. Johnson</persName>, who heard it. We reported it to
                     <rs><persName key="#jfol">the captain</persName></rs> and it spread like
               wildfire. Great excitement prevailed, for all expected that before morning blood
               would be shed. Measures were instantly taken to resist an attack. All the gentlemen
               passengers were put on the watch, eight at a time, for four hours. The muskets and
               arms were all brought out of the hold and put in order. Every part of <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_california">the ship</name></rs> was watched. It was
               supposed to be the intention of the sailors, twenty­four in number, to kill all the
               passengers when they were asleep, and then to rob <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">the ship</name></rs>, as there is a large amount of gold
               on board. Very little sleeping was done by any on board, and the watch was kept up
               all night until after breakfast.</p>
            <p>But it proved a jolly morning, for <persName key="#hobbs">Mr. Hobbs</persName>, who
               can make fun out of anything, got some persons to prefer charges against several of
               those on watch. Had a mock court. Mr. "<persName key="#oregon">Oregon</persName>," as
               he is called, was dressed up with <emph>chapeau</emph> and sword, and made orderly
               sergeant to bring up the criminals, who, after some funny remarks and questions, were
               fined six bottles of champagne, which were brought out and drunk in great glee.</p>
            <p>Withal we had a very jolly morning, but before dinner they all got impatient at the
               slow rate we were going, only from half a mile to two miles an hour, and after some
               debate a few questions were written down, signed, and sent in to <rs><persName
                     key="#jfol">the captain</persName></rs>, &#8212; as to how much coal he had and
               when he was going to use it, &#8212; which he answered very satisfactorily to them,
               and they were in better spirits by teatime. But <rs><persName key="#jfol">the
                     captain</persName></rs> seems very much depressed. We have a fine wind,
               however, now. The watch is to be kept up tonight again. Heaven grant we may all get
               safely home!</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-19">May 19, Saturday</date></emph>. &#8212; Another court
               martial this morning served to while away the tedious hours. The men were busy all
               day fixing the wheels, and about three o'clock we were off again with the steam.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-20">May 20, Sunday</date></emph>, &#8212; and a very lovely
               morning. Had two very refreshing showers before eleven o'clock, at which time we
               assembled on deck, and, with a very calm sea below us and a bright sky above,
                  <persName key="#tho">Captain Thomas</persName> read the Episcopal service. It was
               very solemn and impressive, and will long be remembered by me. It seems as though we
               were nearer our Creator amidst the vast ocean, and the prayers and hymns seem
               addressed to Him in person. This evening, <persName key="#mogden">Mrs.
                  Ogden</persName>, <persName key="#mbaw">Mrs. Bawden</persName>, <persName
                  key="#tho">Captain Thomas</persName>, <persName key="#johnson">Mr.
                  Johnson</persName>, and Mr. "<persName key="#oregon">Oregon</persName>," have been
               singing some sacred music on deck. It was really very sweet but made me sad, for
               thoughts of home would intrude.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-21">May 21, Monday</date></emph>. &#8212; Passed today some
               beautiful islands, among them the islands of <placeName type="island" key="#i_mon"
                  >Montroso</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_qui">Quibo</placeName>,
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_qui">the latter</placeName></rs> just one
               mountain standing alone in the ocean. It can be seen with the naked eye for forty
               miles. News again tonight that the coal is out. Mesdames &#8212; &#8212;, &#8212;
               &#8212;, and &#8212; &#8212;, have the fidgets, and keep <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_california">the whole ship</name></rs> in an uproar with their
               scolding. <rs><persName key="#jfol">The captain</persName></rs> is burning up
               everything that can be spared.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-22">May 22, Tuesday</date></emph>. &#8212; Passed <rs><name
                     type="group"
                     key="#sh_mcdougall1; #sh_mcdougall2; #sh_mcdougall3; #sh_mcdougall4">four
                     ships</name></rs>, two large and two small ones. Have been cutting <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_california">the ship</name></rs> to pieces for fuel.
               Burned all the second deck, chicken coops, settees, and everything that could be
               turned into fuel, and still very uncertain about reaching <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_tab">the island of Taboga</placeName>, as the wind and tide are very much
               against us. Have burned several thousand dollars' worth of good timber, yesterday and
               today.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-23">May 23, Wednesday</date></emph>. &#8212; <rs><date
                     when="1849-05-22">Last night</date></rs>, about ten o'clock, we dropped anchor
               about four miles from the island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_tab"
                  >Taboga</placeName>. Directly afterward the awning caught on fire, and there was
               another cause of alarm for the ladies. It was soon extinguished, and no harm done.
               Early this morning <persName key="#forbes">Captain Forbes</persName> took a boat and
               went to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_tab">the island</placeName></rs> for
               coal to take us in to <placeName type="country" key="#co_pan">Panama</placeName>.
               Returned about two o’clock, when we got up steam and came into the port. Arrived
               about five o'clock and anchored very near <name type="ship" key="#sh_oregon">the
                  Oregon</name>. <persName key="#gmc">George</persName> went on board of her and
               found <persName key="#jhu">John F. Hughs</persName> there. Wrote to <persName
                  key="#jhu">John</persName> [her husband] and to <persName key="#wpa">Doctor
                  Parker</persName> for <persName key="#gmc">George</persName>, and sent on board of
               her. About ten o'clock she put out for <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                  Francisco</placeName>. Everything looks very green and beautiful, particularly the
               islands in the bay.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-24">May 24, Thursday</date></emph>. &#8212; About nine
               o'clock we bade adieu &#8212; forever, I hope &#8212; to <name type="ship"
                  key="#sh_california">the California</name>. The tide was so low we had to walk a
               long way on the rough rocks. When we got to <persName key="#far">Mr.
                  Farand</persName>'s house we were very tired. Found <rs><placeName
                     key="#farandhouse">the house</placeName></rs> very cool and pleasant, and he
               was very kind to us and tried to get us a house, but not succeeding we came to the
                  <placeName key="#americanhotel">American Hotel</placeName>, where <persName
                  key="#mbaw">Mrs. Bawden</persName>, <persName key="#mgr">Mrs. Grimes</persName>,
               and I, got one room between us. Have had a great deal of company; most of the
               gentlemen passengers of <name type="ship" key="#sh_california">the California</name>
               have called. I found <persName key="#coo">Mr. Coombs</persName> here.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-25">May 25, Friday</date></emph>. &#8212; Have had company
               all day. <persName key="#hobbs">Mr. Hobbs</persName> and <persName key="#warren">Mr.
                  Warren</persName> took supper with us. <persName key="#larr">Mr.
                  Larrentree</persName> brought us some tea from his stores and <persName key="#mgr"
                  >Mrs. Grimes</persName> made it. Had a very cozy time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-26">May 26, Saturday</date></emph>. &#8212; Roused
                     <rs><date when="1849-05-26">this morning</date></rs> very early, thinking the
               baggage was going off early, but it did not get off until nearly noon. Company all
               day again. <rs><persName type="group" key="#woman11; #woman12">Two English
                     ladies</persName></rs>, who are in distress, were here <rs><date
                     when="1849-05-26">this evening</date></rs> with <persName key="#tho">Captain
                  Thomas</persName> ; seemed very agreeable and I pity them. The men who were to
               take us over to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_cruces">Cruces</placeName> want to
               charge for three or four mules that did not go with the baggage at all, and as
                  <persName key="#gmc">George</persName> will not submit to be humbugged, we have
               determined not to go until <rs><date when="1849-05-28">Monday</date></rs>. The people
               are firing thousands of fire­crackers to-night. It almost deafens us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-27">May 27, Sunday</date></emph> &#8212; at home ! but it
               would puzzle a lawyer to find any Sabbath in <placeName type="country" key="#co_pan"
                  >Panama</placeName>. Shops all open, all kinds of labor going on as usual, and in
               addition, a circus and cock-fight. <persName key="#scl">Mr. St. Clair</persName>
               breakfasted with us, and he and <rs><persName key="#mscl">his wife</persName></rs>
               dined with us. <persName key="#coo">Mr. Coombs</persName> brought me a large box of
               guava jelly. In the evening got all ready to start in the morning for <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_cruces">Cruces</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-28">May 28, Monday</date></emph>. &#8212; Awakened this
               morning at three o'clock by <rs><persName key="#muleteer">our
                  muleteer</persName></rs>, who &#8212; as a great wonder for New Granadans &#8212;
               was punctual to his appointment. But the men who are to carry me did not arrive until
               nearly six o'clock, at which time we set out; <persName key="#sue">Sue</persName>
               [her little daughter] on a native's back and I in a hammock between two men, with six
               others following to rest them. Formed the advance guard, and kept ahead of most of
               the party until we got out about eight miles, when we all stopped on the bank of a
               stream and ate breakfast. Quite a picnic, and all seemed highly delighted so far; but
               they changed their minds soon after, for the roads were very bad. <persName
                  key="#mho">Mrs. Hoyer</persName> was thrown from her horse into the mud. My men
               gave out, and just at dark we met <persName key="#turner">Turner</persName> on a
               fresh mule. I got on the mule man-fashion, (as it would have been very dangerous for
               me to have ridden over that road any other way,) one man leading the mule and one on
               each side of me, while <persName key="#gmc">George</persName> walked on behind. [This
               fashion, it is recorded, had been set by <rs><persName key="#mwhe">the wife of
                        <persName key="#owh">Rev. O. C. Wheeler</persName></persName></rs> and a
               lady companion, while crossing <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_ispan">the
                     Isthmus</placeName></rs>, with the other <name type="ship" key="#sh_falcon"
                  >Falcon</name> passengers, in January.] Thus we went on through the narrow
               mountain passes, in the dark and mud, [attended, as others' tragic experience
               abundantly proved, by imminent peril of murder and robbery,] and got to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_cruces">Cruces</placeName> about eight o'clock. I saw
                  <persName key="#haws">Mr. Haws</persName>, the crazy man, about two miles from
               town, his mule fastened, and he lying on the ground. <persName key="#sue"
                  >Sue</persName> and <persName key="#frank">Frank</persName> got in about half an
               hour after, and we went to bed very thankful that we were safe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-29">May 29, Tuesday</date></emph>. &#8212; The charge of
               the alcalde was twenty dollars for one miserable room and three naked cots for one
               night ! At eight this morning <persName key="#mbaw">Mrs. Bawden</persName>, <persName
                  key="#mgr">Mrs. Grimes</persName>, <persName key="#mho">Mrs. Hoyer</persName>,
                  <persName key="#hobbs">Mr. Hobbs</persName>, <persName key="#gmc"
                  >George</persName>, and myself, started down the river in <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_whaleboat">a whaleboat</name></rs> that <persName key="#hobbs">Mr.
                  Hobbs</persName> had engaged for us. We were nearly used up, but without meeting
               with any accident other than getting very wet &#8212; for it rained, in torrents
               &#8212; and being frightened at two parties of tigers and panthers, we arrived
               safely, at nine o'clock, at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_cha">Chagres</placeName>,
               and went on board <name type="ship" key="#sh_orus">the Orus</name>, a miserable,
               dirty boat.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <p><emph><date when="1849-05-30">May 30, Wednesday</date></emph>. &#8212; <rs><date
                     when="1849-05-30">This morning</date></rs>
               <name type="ship" key="#sh_orus">the Orus</name> got up steam and went down to
               &#8212;&#8212;&#8212; Bay, where we dined. But some of the passengers, being
               discontented, wanted to go on the <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_tay">English
                     steamer</name></rs> [<name type="ship" key="#sh_tay">the Tay</name> (?) of the
               Royal Mail line]. They would not give <persName key="#gmc">George</persName> any
               peace until he agreed to go with them. They gave <rs><persName key="#capttay">the
                     captain</persName></rs> fifty dollars to put [us] on board <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_tay">the English steamer</name></rs>. Retired soon after
               tea, and about ten o'clock we got under way.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="section">
            <p>[The voyage was continued on <name type="ship" key="#sh_tay">the Tay</name> &#8212;
               touching at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_cart">Cartagena</placeName>, "a
               magnificent but ruinous city " &#8212; to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_king"
                  >Kingston</placeName>, <placeName type="country" key="#co_jam"
               >Jamaica</placeName>, at which port they arrived on <date when="1849-06-04">June
                  4</date>.</p>
            <p>At <placeName type="city" key="#ci_king">Kingston</placeName>, "the most lovely spot
               I ever saw," <persName type="author" key="#mjmc">Mrs. McDougall</persName> with her
               brother-in-law and <persName key="#mgr">Mrs. Grimes</persName>, and Messrs. <persName
                  key="#warren">Warren</persName>, <persName key="#hobbs">Hobbs</persName>,
                  <persName key="#true">True</persName>, and <persName key="#perry"
               >Perry</persName>, took rooms at the suburban place of <persName key="#mfer">Mrs.
                  Ferron, a creole lady</persName>, where they remained six days. Visits were made
               to the residence of Santa Ana &#8212; " rather plain in appearance, being a red brick
               house, large, but not fitted with the same taste that most of the residences are"
               &#8212; and to other points of interest.</p>
            <p>On <date when="1849-06-10">Sunday, June 10</date>, the party sailed on <name
                  type="ship" key="#sh_ida">the brig Ida</name>, <persName key="#fou">Captain
                  Foulkes</persName> (?) commanding, for <placeName type="city" key="#ci_phil"
                  >Philadelphia</placeName>. On <rs><date when="1849-06-15">the
                  fifteenth</date></rs> they were becalmed in a perilous passage among the
                  <placeName type="region" key="#hogstye">Hog Stye reefs</placeName> and neighboring
               islands and shoals. Much apprehension was felt. On the next day mention is made in
                     <rs><title type="article" key="#McDougall1890">the diary</title></rs> of a
               "present of a book and a clean towel, from <persName key="#mrswarren">Mrs.
                  Warren</persName>, both very scarce articles." The tedium of the voyage was
               relieved by music, &#8212; of voice and the accordion, &#8212; by rigging-climbing
               for wagers, and on two occasions by the mimicries of <rs><persName key="#fou">Captain
                     &#8212;&#8212; </persName></rs>, who masqueraded in the outer dress of a lady
               passenger.</p>
            <p>The last page of <rs><title type="article" key="#McDougall1890">the
                  diary</title></rs> is quite illegible. <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_ida">The
                     brig</name></rs> came safely to her destination, but on what date I am
               uninformed.</p>
            <byline>
               <emph><persName type="author" key="#wmcd">W. H. McD.</persName></emph></byline>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
