<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="monograph"><orgName type="publication" key="#kroeber">Handbook of the
                     Indians of California</orgName></title>
               <publisher>Government Printing Office</publisher>
               <date when="1935">1935</date>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_dc">Washington</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_dc">District of Columbia</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="chapter" key="#Kroeber1925">The San Nicoleno</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="633" to="635"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#akroe">Kroeber, Alfred
                     Louis</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">THE SAN NICOLENO</orgName></rs></title></head>
            <p><span type="trope" n="6"><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>, the farthest seaward of the <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">Santa Barbara Islands</placeName>, foggy and wind blown, harbored
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a
                        tribe</orgName></rs> of which <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                        >the last survivor</persName></rs> died <rs><date notAfter="1865">more than
                        60 years ago</date></rs>. Four badly spelled words are all that has been
                  preserved of their speech. These suffice to prove it Shoshonean: they do not
                  establish its dialectic relation. A divergent idiom may well have developed in the
                  isolation of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this sand-swept and rocky
                        island</placeName></rs>. It is stated that when <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the last survivor</persName></rs> was
                  brought to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> her
                  speech was thoroughly unintelligible not only to <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the Chumash of the
                     vicinity</orgName> but to the "<orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_pepimaros">Pepimaros</orgName>" of <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> (Pimu, Pipimar, the name of the
                  island), of whom some were sent for from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                     Angeles</placeName></span>.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="6"><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">The last handful of
                     the natives</persName>, who are said to have suffered previously in quarrels
                  with <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">Aleuts</orgName>
                  imported by <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak; #1814huntingparty"
                        >Russian fur hunters</persName></rs>, and whose numbers had probably been
                  diminished by drafts to <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the
                        missions</orgName></rs>, were taken to <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName></rs> in <date when="1835"
                  >1835</date>, soon after secularization. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">A woman</persName></rs> who at the last moment missed
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>
                  was left behind. <date when="1853">Eighteen years later</date>, when <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> was American, she was
                  discovered. Her romantic case aroused the greatest interest, and she was given the
                  best of treatment in her new home at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>; but she died in a few months.</span> More attention was
               bestowed on her humble belongings than on the panoply of many a tribe; and while the
               objects themselves seem all to have been scattered and lost&#8212;the last traceable
               piece perished in the San Francisco fire of <date when="1906">1906</date>&#8212;the
               descriptions, together with random but rather full recoveries from ancient village
               sites, enable a partial insight into the life of this remote little group, the most
               westerly of all Uto-Aztekans.</p>
            <p>Wood was scarce and small on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. There was enough brush for huts, but most dwellings
               were reared on a frame of whale ribs and jaws, either covered with sea-lion hides or
               wattled with brush or rushes. Bone implements were very numerous, and the use of
               several varieties is far from clear. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The
                     island</placeName></rs> may have afforded sufficient timber for plank canoes,
               or dugouts may have been burned from drift logs. Steatite was imported from
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, but is
               represented by small ornaments or charms rather than heavy bowls. Whales must have
               been very abundant and frequently stranded; there is nothing to indicate that they
               were hunted. Sea otters were to be had in comparative profusion, and, to judge from
               the habits of other tribes, their furs formed the most prized dress and the chief
               export in a trade on which the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">San Nicoleño</orgName> must have depended for many
               necessities. Seals, water birds, fish, and mollusks were no doubt the principal food;
               but roots were dug industriously. Baskets are spoken of as of the type ordinary in
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_socal">southern California</placeName>. They
               were often asphalted, hot pebbles being employed to melt and spread the lumps. Water
               baskets were in plain twining, as among the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_chumash">Chumash</orgName>; but the neck was long, much as in our wine
               bottles. <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The lone woman</persName></rs>
               wore a sort of gown of squares of bird skin sewn together; but this does not seem
               wholly aboriginal. The usual dress may be conjectured to have been the scant costume
               of all <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, with capes or
               blankets of woven strips of bird skin added at need. The cylinder-headed wooden war
               club was in use. The dead were buried, as by <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">all the
                     islanders</orgName></rs>, not cremated as on the <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_mld">Shoshonean mainland</placeName></rs>. Of religion we only know
               that there were weather invocations and hunting charms; whether the toloache cult or
               the image form of mourning anniversary had reached the island must remain in
               abeyance; and as to society, there is total ignorance.</p>
            <p>Ghalas-at has been given as the name of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. This is perhaps the native or the Chumash
               pronunciation of Gabrielino Haras-nga.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
