A WOMAN CRUSOE.

Beginning due west of Point Conception on the California coast and continuing at irregular intervals as far south as the Bay of Todos Santos in Lower California, lie the Channel Islands, says Field and Stream. In this ideal region for the yachtsman, the fisherman and the hunter, one comes to feel like a new Crusoe on his primitive isle. And in very truth Crusoe's semi-mythical story was enacted upon one of these same islands, though minus the man Friday and the happy ending.

The castaway in this case was a woman, a Danish emigrant, left ashore through some mischance by the crew of a vessel that had sought shelter behind San Nicholas during a storm, in the early fifties [1850s]. For over seventeen years the lone creature lived unsought and forgotten, though the time at length came, when, on the days the mist-clearing north wind blew, she could climb to the island's highest point and view the ranchers' herds grazing upon the mainland.

And, at last, when hope and reason had both long died, the poor, wild, glibbering [gibbering] creature was found in her wolf's burrow among the hills by the advance guard of the otter hunters' fraternity, who had long wondered at the mysterious footprints they marked upon the lonely sands.