<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#horn">Horn Book
                     Magazine</orgName></title>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="67"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="2"/>
               <editor/>
               <publisher/>
               <date when="1961"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_bo">Boston</placeName><placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ma">Massachusetts</placeName>
               </pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#ODell1961">Newbery Award Acceptance</title>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell, Scott</persName></author>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="311" to="316"/>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><orgName type="publication" key="#horn">THE HORN BOOK
                     MAGAZINE</orgName>
               </title></head>
            <dateline><emph><date when="1961-08">August, 1961</date></emph>
            </dateline>
            <head><title type="sub">NEWBERY AWARD ACCEPTANCE* <note n="1" place="bottom">*Given at a
                     meeting of the <orgName key="#ala">American Library Association</orgName> in
                        <placeName type="city" key="#ci_cl">Cleveland</placeName>, <date
                        when="1961-07-11">July 11, 1961</date>. The Newbery Medal for "the most
                     distinguished contribution to American literature for children " was awarded to
                        <persName type="author" key="#sod">Mr. O'Dell</persName> for <emph>Island of
                        the Blue Dolphins</emph> (<orgName type="publication" key="#houghton"
                        >Houghton</orgName>).</note></title></head>
            <byline>
               <emph>By</emph>
               <persName type="author" key="#sod">SCOTT O'DELL</persName></byline>
            <div type="speech">
               <p><persName type="author" key="#sjoh">SAMUEL JOHNSON</persName> has said that a man
                  may turn over half a library to make a book. It is equally true that a writer may
                  turn over a whole lifetime to make a book. Indeed, this is what I did when I wrote
                     <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>.</p>
               <p>Down the corridors of memory, at the far end of that labyrinth, I saw clearly a
                  certain night.</p>
               <p>I was four years old and I had awakened out of a long sleep. The room was dark.
                  The sea made faint sounds among the eaves, like mice stirring. From far off came
                  the sound of waves breaking upon the beach. Though I listened, I heard nothing
                  else.</p>
               <p>Lying there in my small bed, in the deep night, it suddenly came to me that the
                  house was deserted, that I was alone. Quickly I slid to the floor and groped along
                  the hall to my mother's room. I felt the bed. It was empty.</p>
               <p>At that instant I heard from a distance the sound of music. By some strange
                  alchemy of love and fear and memory, standing there in the empty room, music and
                        <rs><persName key="#msc">my mother</persName></rs> became one. I would find
                  her where the music was. They would be together.</p>
               <p>I tried to open the front door, but it was locked and the back door was locked
                  too. Then I noticed that the window above the kitchen sink was open. I found a
                  chair and climbed upon it and thus reached the window. (To this day I can feel the
                  coldness of unwashed silverware on my bare feet.) I grasped the window sill,
                  squirmed outside, hung for a moment, fell sprawling on the sand, and picked myself
                  up.</p>
               <p>Now the music was clear on the summer air. Against the sky I could see the glow of
                  colored lights. I ran toward it, falling in the deep sand and getting up, running
                  again, shirttails dragging at my ankles.</p>
               <p>I came to a boardwalk. The walk led to a pavilion, to the source of the glowing
                  lights, where clusters of people moved about. But the music was still farther,
                  beyond them; and I went toward it, feeling my way through a forest of legs and a
                  sea of dresses, to a place where couples drifted about.</p>
               <p>There on a platform above them was the music and below the platform, the lights
                  shining on her, was <rs><persName key="#msc">my mother</persName></rs>. Her back
                  was toward me but I knew well the golden hair. With my last breath I ran across
                  the floor, unaware of the eyes that must have been turned upon me. I stretched out
                  my arms and clutched her dress and though she was whirling, held on. As she turned
                  and stared down at this apparition in a nightshirt, at her son, I am forced to say
                  that she was not so glad to see me as I was to see her.</p>
               <p>You will not find this incident in <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>, but
                  you will find its meaning. The human heart, lonely and in need of love, is a
                  vessel which needs replenishing.</p>
               <p>I saw a boy of eight, towheaded and restless, who with other boys of his age went
                  out on Saturday mornings in sun or rain in search of the world.</p>
               <p>This was a small world, but a world in microcosm. It was bounded by the deep water
                  and wharves and mud flats of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San
                     Pedro</placeName> Harbor. By the cliffs and reefs of <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_pfirmin">Point Firmin</placeName> and <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_portbend">Portuguese Bend</placeName>. By the hills of <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_pv">Palos Verdes</placeName>, aflame with wild mustard in
                  spring, lion-colored in summer.</p>
               <p>Many summer days we left the landlocked world and went to sea. How? Each of us on
                  a separate log. The logs had been towed into the harbor in great rafts &#8212;
                  from <placeName type="state" key="#st_or">Oregon</placeName>. They were twelve
                  feet long or longer, rough with splinters and covered with tar. But to each of us
                  young Magellans, they were proud canoes, dugouts fashioned by ax and fire.
                  Graceful, fierce-prowed, the equal of any storm.</p>
               <p>We freed them from the deep-water slips where they waited for the saw mill.
                  Astride, paddling with our hands, we set to sea, to the breakwater and beyond. We
                  returned hours later, the watery world encompassed.</p>
               <p>These memories went into <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>. You will find
                  them in the book &#8212; where <name type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name>
                  leaves <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the Island</placeName></rs> in
                  search of <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the country that lies to the
                     East</placeName>.</p>
               <p>Many mornings we went into the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_pv">Palos
                     Verdes</placeName> Hills. There we turned over every likely rock, looking for
                  small monsters. We thrust our hands down every squirrel and coyote hole in our
                  path. Commonly we found an owl. This was the prize of all prizes. lt was twice the
                  size of your fur, soft-feathered, with great yellow eyes that blinked in the
                  sudden sun.</p>
               <p>What did we do with this creature of the nocturnal air? We killed it, of course.
                  We wrung its neck. We cut off its legs. For the exposed tendons of an owl's legs,
                  when pulled in a certain way, made the tiny claws open and retract in a ghastly
                  simulation of life.</p>
               <p>To this day, indeed to this very minute, I remember these depredations with
                  horror.</p>
               <p>This horror, muted but nonetheless real, you will find in the latter part of
                     <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>. The latter part of the book, only,
                  because <rs><name type="fictional" key="#kar">my Indian girl</name></rs> began
                  where youth begins. In the closed world of selfishness and cruelty where
                  everything, whether of fur or feathers, whether it creeps or walks or flies, is an
                  object of indifferent cruelty.</p>
               <p>Down that dark corridor of time I also saw <persName key="#jiman">Jack
                     Iman</persName>.</p>
               <p>Freckled, with black eyes alert under a bang of black hair, a <rs><persName
                        key="#jiman"><name key="#her">Hercules</name> in miniature</persName></rs>,
                     <persName key="#jiman">Jack</persName> hated me the moment we met. For no other
                  reason, I am certain, than that I was a city boy, lately come to <rs><placeName
                        type="city" key="#ci_histown">his town</placeName></rs>. I also hated him.
                  And for no other reason except that he hated me.</p>
               <p>In all weather, during the school week and even on Sunday, <persName key="#jiman"
                     >Jack</persName> pursued me. In class with his black eyes. On the school
                  grounds with taunts. Off the school grounds with his fists. He was my nemesis. My
                  tormentor. The embodiment to me of all evil.</p>
               <p>Years later I read in the newspaper that <persName key="#jiman">Jack</persName>
                  had become a prizefighter. Sometime later I saw him fight. I went to see him
                  beaten. But the same <persName key="#jiman">Jack Iman</persName> I remembered,
                  only with vaster muscles, was the victor. I went again and again to see him fight,
                  each time hoping for his humiliation. Finally, after a year of fights <persName
                     key="#jiman">Jack Iman</persName> was knocked out and carried groggily from the
                  ring. To my surprise, sitting there at ringside, I somehow felt diminished.</p>
               <p>I went back, using the privilege of a press badge, to his dressing room. I went
                  there to introduce myself, for I was sure he wouldn't remember me, and to quietly
                  gloat.</p>
               <p>Though he was just returning from another world, <persName key="#jiman">Jack
                     Iman</persName> recognized me at once. Unsteadily he came towards me, put his
                  arms around my shoulders and wept.</p>
               <p>That too is in <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>. It lies in the heart of
                  the episode of <name type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name> and <rs><name
                        type="fictional" key="#tut">her enemy</name></rs>, <rs><name
                        type="fictional" key="#tut">the Aleut girl</name></rs>. It also colors the
                  climax of the book. For I believe and wished to say, with whatever power I might
                  summon to the task, that we must forgive our enemies. Further, I believe that the
                  hopes of civilization, unique and obscure as they are, really exist in the act of
                  identification with our enemies.</p>
               <p>Memories come from books, too, from that vital spring, the library. This is one of
                  them, culled from many sources, that in spirit I used.</p>
               <p>At <placeName key="#wranch">Warner's Ranch</placeName>, near my home in <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_ju">Julian</placeName>, the <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Cupenos
                 ">Cupeño
                     Indians</orgName> revolted in <date when="1851">1851</date>. Bereft of their
                  ancestral lands by the Americans, impoverished and abused, they attacked under the
                  leadership of <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Antonio Garra</persName>
                  and burned a few buildings. The citizens of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd"
                     >San Diego</placeName> sprang to arms, rode in pursuit of <persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName> and <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Cupenos">his men</orgName></rs>.
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Cupenos">The
                        men</orgName></rs> scattered into the chapparal, but <persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName> was captured and brought to
                  trial in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>.</p>
               <p>He was first tried for murder, but the evidence was lacking. The charge was
                  changed to theft. This also lacked evidence.</p>
               <p>Hard pressed, the court decided on a charge of treason, based upon the fact that
                     <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName> had not paid his
                  county taxes, and sentenced him to death.</p>
               <p><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName> joked with the firing
                  squad as they marched him out of his cell. <rs><persName type="missionfather"
                        key="#priest1">The attending priest</persName></rs> reprimanded him for his
                  levity and said that his last minutes might more appropriately be spent in
                  prayer.</p>
               <p>To which <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName> replied:
                  "What is the reason? I am nothing. You are nothing. This, too, is nothing. "</p>
               <p>And then, as the procession set off for the grave, he expressed the desire to walk
                  in front, but was overruled by <rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#priest1"
                        >the priest</persName></rs>, who again found his attitude undignified.</p>
               <p>"Why is it undignified? " <persName type="missionfather" key="#priest1"
                     >Garra</persName> asked.</p>
               <p><rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#priest1">The priest</persName></rs>
                  brought the procession to a halt. "I insist that you be more solemn. Kneel and
                  listen to me while I pray. "</p>
               <p><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName> said, "I will listen,
                  if it pleases you. But I will not kneel."</p>
               <p><rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#priest1">The priest</persName></rs> got
                  down on his knees and began to pray, but, upset by what had transpired, botched
                  his Latin.</p>
               <p>"Pardon me, Father," <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Garra</persName>
                  said, "but these are the words you should use for what you are trying to say." And
                  he supplied them from his brief studies at <rs><orgName type="mission"
                        key="#mi_santabarbaramission">the mission</orgName></rs>, years before.</p>
               <p><rs><persName type="missionfather" key="#priest1">The priest</persName></rs> drew
                  himself up and began an argument which lasted until they reached the grave. In a
                  final effort to establish decorum, he suggested that <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">the Indian</persName></rs> ask the pardon
                  of all those present.</p>
               <p>With the rifles pointed at his heart, <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga"
                     >Garra</persName> smiled and said, "Yes, gentlemen, I ask your pardon for all
                  my offenses, and I pardon you in return."</p>
               <p>The rifles put a period to his words and he fell into the open grave.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="3">If <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#aga">Antonio
                        Garra</persName> had killed fifty Americans or ten, his name like Geronimo's
                     would be remembered, but he belonged to <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_Cupenos">a peaceful tribe</orgName> which lived amicably with
                     each other and with the other tribes of <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socal">Southern California</placeName>, whose lives are unknown
                     because they went in peace. <name type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name>
                     belonged to such a tribe.</span></p>
               <p>Places I have known, creatures I have loved are in <emph>Island of the Blue
                     Dolphins</emph>. The islands &#8212; <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                     Cruz</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>,
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_ts">Todos Santos</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_smar"
                     >San Martín</placeName>, the <placeName type="island" key="#i_lc"
                     >Coronados</placeName> &#8212; seen at dawn and at sunset, in all weathers over
                  many years. Dolphin and otter playing. A mother gull pushing her grown brood from
                  the nest, watching them plummet a hundred feet into the sea, then flying down to
                  herd them onto their new home, a rock safe from the tide.</p>
               <p>And finally there is <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car"
                     >Carolina</persName>, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car">the
                        Tarascan girl</persName></rs> of sixteen, who lived on the shores of
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_pat">Lake Pátzcuaro</placeName> in <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_cmex">central Mexico</placeName>. She was one of nine
                  children, the oldest daughter of <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#pfl">Pedro
                     Flores</persName> who took care of the small quinta <rs><persName key="#jod">my
                        wife</persName></rs> and I had rented for the summer.</p>
               <p><span type="trope" n="3"><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_Tarascan">The Tarascans</orgName> are a great people. They were
                     never conquered by the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aztec"
                        >Aztecs</orgName>, the only tribe, incidentally, that did not fall under the
                     Aztec yoke.</span> Nor did the <name type="nationality" key="#spanish"
                     >Spaniards</name>, led by the incredibly cruel <persName key="#nbu"
                     >Guzman</persName>, subdue them. When the Conquistadores took their capital
                  city of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_tz">Tzintsuntsan</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_tz">The Place of the Hummingbirds</placeName>, tortured
                        <rs><persName key="#nbu">their king</persName></rs> by dragging him around
                  the city square attached to the tail of a horse and at last tossed him into a
                  bonfire, <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan">the
                     Tarascans</orgName> retreated into the high mountains.</p>
               <p><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car">Carolina</persName> was tall for a
                     <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan">Tarascan</orgName>,
                  with small bones but broad shoulders. Her eyes were black and deep-set, slanted at
                  the corners, and her black hair fell heavily to her waist. She stood in her bare
                  feet squarely on the earth as if growing from it.</p>
               <p><persName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#car">Carolina</persName>, when she
                  first came to work for us, wore a long red skirt of closely woven wool. As a bride
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#flo">her mother</persName></rs>
                  had received the gift of sixty yards of this red cloth from her betrothed, a
                  custom of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_Tarascan">the
                     Tarascans</orgName>. With it, by winding it around and around her waist, she
                  made a skirt. At night she used it as a blanket for herself and her husband, and
                  later for their children, against the fierce cold of the mountains. For each girl
                  child she cut lengths of the cloth and this in turn became a skirt. The red skirt,
                  the <emph>falda roja</emph> which <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#car"
                     >Carolina</persName> wore, came to her in this fashion. She wore it proudly, as
                  a shield against the world, in the way <name type="fictional" key="#kar"
                     >Karana</name> wore the skirt of cormorant feathers. The two girls are much
                  alike.</p>
               <p>Through them I wanted to say to children and to all those who will listen that we
                  have a chance to come into a new relationship to the things around us. Once,
                        <rs><date notBefore="1660" notAfter="1731">in Defoe's day</date></rs>, we
                  were cunning manipulative children, living in a palace of nature. In her brief
                  lifetime, <name type="fictional" key="#kar">Karana</name> made the change from
                  that world, where everything lived only to be exploited, to a new and more
                  meaningful world. She learned first that we each must be an island secure unto
                  ourselves. Then, that we must "transgress our limits," in reverence for all
                  life.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
