The Lone Woman of San Nicolas

A Tale of Mission Santa Barbara

[...]

INTRODUCTION 

THIS is the story of a lone Indian woman who was marooned on a bleak island in the Santa Barbara Channel. She was rescued after many years, and when she at last reached Mission Santa Barbara she found both joy and sorrow within its shelter. 

Mission Santa Barbara was founded nearly seventy years earlier. From the gentle slopes of the Santa Ins Mountains, this tenth Mission, the "Queen of the Missions," overlooks the ocean and the distant islands of the Santa Barbara Channel. 

Very soon after its founding, Chumash Indians came to the Mission in large numbers. Under the padres' skillful training they learned to build their own adobe houses, which they whitewashed neatly inside and out. Their Indian village was arranged around a large plaza, where the children and young people learned to garden. The older Indians, too, learned many valuable skills&#8212;carpentering, tanning, weaving, sewing, gardening, and cattle raising. Altogether, six hundred Chumash Indians worked faithfully under the guidance of the padres. 

Building activity at Mission Santa Barbara was a continuous process. New and larger structures were built to replace the earlier ones. After Captain Vancouver visited the Mission in 1793, he wrote in his book that he considered Santa Barbara the best-constructed and the best-kept of all the Missions he had seen. At a still later period, the fourth church was constructed. This is the church which is widely known and admired today. Its six-foot-thick sandstone walls are crowned with two massive bell towers. The beauty and grandeur of this Mission building have influenced architecture even beyond borders of California. 

Still other structures at Mission Santa Barbara have endured for more than a century. A large reservoir which collected water from the hills is still in use. The beautiful fountain where Juana looked at her reflection continues to flow today. But standing empty and unused is the long basin where the Indian women formerly washed their clothes and rinsed them in fresh water spouting from a cement bearÕs head. 

Mission Santa Barbara had its difficult period too. When news came that the pirate Bouchard was within a few miles of this Mission, soldiers and Indians prepared to defend it, but he did not attack.

A few years later, enemy Indians attacked it in force. Fires swept over the hills, burned the trees, threatened the Mission, and blackened its vineyards. At another time there was a drought so serious that the people marched through the streets and prayed for rain. 

One of the greatest blows to Mission Santa Barbara, as well as to the other Missions, was the decree of secularization. About ten years after Mexico became an independent nation, the new government decided on a plan which would remove the California Missions from the control of the Church. The first step was to "free" the Indians from the padres' rule. But when few Indians seemed eager for this "freedom," another step was taken. Only Indians who were free would be allowed to vote in their village election. Because most of the Indians were devoted to the padres, even this decree had little effect. 

In the following year, 1834, the actual decree of secularization was passed. This act provided that the Indians and the Mission property were to be removed from the control of the Franciscan padres. Administrators, or "secular" officials, were then to govern both the Missions and the Indians. Inventories were taken at all the Missions, and the new officials in charge received salaries which were paid out of the Missions' earnings. Mexican padres were to replace the Spanish Franciscans. Under this secular control, both the padres and the poor Mission Indians suffered. Mission buildings and ranches were sadly neglected, and Mission prosperity gradually came to an end. 

During this difficult period, however, a new padre came to Mission Santa Barbara in the company of Bishop Diego, California's first bishop. This young Mexican priest, Father Francisco Snchez, was a man of unusual zeal and devotion. For forty-two years he worked among California's Indians and Mexicans. Today he is probably better known readers of <emph>Ramona</emph> as Father Salvierderra, a man beloved by all. In 1853, when the Lone Woman of San Nicolas reached Mission Santa Barbara, it was this same understanding Father Snchez who welcomed her and later baptized her at the Mission which had sheltered many of her people.

MISSION SANTA BARBARA 

CALENDAR

1786 Founding of the Mission, December 4 

1820 Dedication of the present church 

1834 Secularization 

1842 Arrival of Father Snchez 

1846 Sale of the Mission 

1865 Return of the Mission to the Catholic Church

THE LONE WOMAN OF SAN NICOLAS 

THE cold gray fog settled down over the rocky island of San Nicolas, farthest westward of the Santa Barbara Channel Islands. Gelma stood on the beach and shivered. Even her cloak of smooth sea-otter skin could not shut out the cold and dampness of such a day. She stared at the cliff where breakers were dashing high above the jagged rocks, adding their constant pounding roar to the screeching of sea gulls. 

"If only the sun would shine!" Gelma said to her sister. "When I see nothing but fog day after day, I am restless and unhappy." 

The older Indian woman touched Gelma's arm and pointed seaward. "Look!" she urged. "The fog is drifting now. Maybe it will blow away and you can have your sunshine. All of us will be happier if the sun shines." 

Gelma noticed a tiny patch of water where blue waves danced and sparkled in a shaft of light. Suddenly the patch widened, showing the sunlight which soon flooded the island with its warmth. And offshore, tossing about on the choppy waves was a small boat. 

"A boat! A boat!" shouted Gelma. 

Indians hurried out of their huts to see the welcome sight. Gelma darted into her hut and carried her small boy to the shore to watch the arrival of the rowboat. As it came closer she could see several people. Indians were rowing the boat, but three white men were in it too. 

"Those are not Russians," said Gelma, surprised. 

"They are strangers," agreed her sister. "Russian fur traders said they would never come here again. But perhaps these palefaces are traders too.Ó

Gelma watched the village children shouting and laughing as they ran along the narrow strip of sandy beach. Even one day of sunshine brought joy to young and old alike. And now, visitors! She put her small son down on the beach and wished for his sake that all the days could be warm and bright like this one. 

As the rowboat nosed up on the beach, Indians crowded around it. Children tumbled into it and climbed out again, carrying strange fruits in their brown hands. One of the Indians who had come in the boat spoke for the white men in a language that the islanders could partly understand.

"We come from Missions on mainland," he said slowly. 

At first Gelma did not pay much attention to his words. She did not understand "Missions." She was far more interested in the bright clothes the Indians were wearing. Gaily striped blankets were wrapped around their shoulders covering most of their clothes except the blue-gray trousers. It was not until the strange Indians offered fruit to the islanders that Gelma became really interested in their explanations. 

"At Missions we grow beautiful fruit&#8212;apples, peaches, plums, pears, and oranges." The man's words were not so interesting as the sweet fruit he offered. Except for an occasional wild berry, this fruit was the first that Gelma had ever tasted. She ate one piece hungrily, then reached for another to give to her little boy. 

"What are these Missions?" asked the chief of the island. "Tell us more!"

The visiting Indian looked around him and pointed to the barren island where few trees grew and where huts were made of whale skeletons covered with furs. "At Missions are warm huts, comfortable beds, plenty of food three times a day." 

Gelma sighed. Was it possible that any place had such good things? "Does sun shine at Missions?" she asked, trembling at her own boldness. 

The strange Indian nodded and smiled. "Sun all year long," he promised. "Wonderful church and gray-robed padres. Beautiful music!Ó 

Gelma shook her head, not understanding about the church and the padres. She wondered about the music too. There was little music on San Nicolas Island, and that little was mournful and shrill. But at that moment one of the Indians and the white men began to sing a joyous song. The other Indian took something shiny from the bottom of the boat, held it to his lips, and played sweet music that made the islanders long to dance. 

Gelma needed nothing more to persuade her to go away to the mainland, but it was not her place to speak. She had nothing to say about what her people would do. The Mission song ended far too soon to suit her. Then the island chief spoke simply. "Do Indians live at this Mission?" 

The first Mission Indian answered, "Hundreds of Indians live there! Padres sent us here to ask you to come and join us." 

"We play much but we work too," the other added eagerly. 

The Chief called the men of the village into his hut for a council meeting. Gelma listened anxiously to the voices which were louder than usual. She smiled when the Chief announced solemnly, "We go to Mission." 

All the islanders began to crowd closer to the boat until the Mission Indians waved them back. "Wait!Ó they shouted. "We must return to our ship, which is anchored offshore. Then we can bring another rowboat. We have room for only a few this time. While we are gone, get ready everything you wish to take with you!" But the Indians refused to go until they could all leave their island at once. 

After the boat had disappeared into the fog, the Chief called his people together for a few minutes. "Pack only what you really need!" he ordered. "But leave nothing of value behind you for Russian fur traders to steal." 

Gelma took her little boy, hurried to her sisterÕs hut, and began sorting furs and baskets of food. "Always sunshine," she murmured. "Warm days, good food, and wonderful music." She was so happy that she tried to sing the chant the strangers had sung. 

"Why, Gelma!" her sister said. "You are singing for the first time in many years."

Gelma's eyes grew bright. "I am happy for all of us, but mostly for the little one." 

The older woman sorted her few belongings while her children danced in and out of the hut. Never before had there been such great excitement on San Nicolas Island. At last one of the children shouted shrilly, "The boats are coming!" 

The villagers hurried to the beach to watch. When the boats were close to the shore, the Chief gave final orders to his people. "Bring all your supplies to the beach! And toss the fur coverings from your huts into the sea." 

Now that the Indians were ready to leave the only home they had ever known, they were silent&#8212;all but Gelma, who felt nothing but joy over leaving the dismal island. "Take this pile of furs for my baby," she said to her sister's oldest child. 

"No!" cried the girl. "I'll take care of your little boy!" 

At that moment the boats reached shore. "Hurry!" cried the Mission Indians. "A storm is coming! No time to lose! We'll help you!" 

The soldiers showed the Indians where to sit in the bottom of the boat. They pushed women and frightened children into their places. Suddenly Gelma remembered the good furs still covering the whale-bone hut. She and her sister were both widows with no man to help them. She ran back to the hut. In a moment she had stripped off the furs and tossed them into the sea. She was glad to see the breakers snatch them away where no trader would get them. By the time she returned to the beach, the first boat had pushed away from shore. As she stopped to pick up her supplies, impatient hands pushed her into the other boat. 

Separated now from her sister's family and her child, Gelma was frightened among so many strangers. The waves through which they were rowing grew higher with every passing moment. The fog banks were shifting across the blue-gray water and shutting out both the other boat and the island from sight. 

With one hand Gelma clung tightly to her package of furs, and with the other she gripped the edge of the boat. To calm her fears she thought of the perfect days ahead when she and her son would enjoy the warm sunshine and the fine Mission food. 

At last the rowboat drew close to the large, winged ship. Gelma was the first to climb on board and hurry to the wide deck. Standing beside the captain she watched for the other boat to appear out of the fog. Even before she caught a glimpse of it, she heard screams she recognized. Then she saw the crowded boat and her sister trying to quiet the screams of the little girl. But where was Gelma's small boy? What had happened to her child? 

Gelma's heart was like lead. She shouted to her sister, but the little girl's screams drowned out her words. She shook the captain's arm. "Send a boat back! My baby has been left behind!" But the captain only shook his head. 

Panic gripped the young mother. There was no time to lose. If she waited, someone might stop her. She could not forsake her child. She ran to the other side of the ship, tore off her fur cloak and leaped into the water. 

Gelma was a strong young woman, toughened by years of struggle against nature. She swam easily enough for a short distance. But never before had she tried a long swim against mountainous waves and opposing tides. At first she swam breathlessly in a hurry to reach shore. But soon her breath came in gasps that forced her to rest. On and on she swam, steadily, wearily, carried off her course time after time. 

Often the island was swallowed up in a fog bank, but she could tell the right direction by the booming of the breakers against the cliffs. At last a long, sweeping breaker lifted her and swept her high up on the shallow beach. There she lay, too beaten and bruised to be able to move for a long time. 

Staggering, stumbling, she found her way to her hut. But she found no sign of her child. Blankets, food, and baby were gone! She dragged herself out into the bitter cold evening. She called frantically for her child. Then she crept back inside the shelter and sank down in a heap. 

All that night Gelma lay in a stupor. In the morning a streak of sunshine came through the fog and wakened her. She listened a moment for the sound of her baby's breathing, but she heard only the beating of her heart. All at once she clearly realized the dreadful truth. She was alone, alone on San Nicolas Island, miles and miles away from her people. 

Her grief, loneliness, and despair drove her screaming out of the hut. She raced up the rocky shore to a cliff. But there were only the sea gulls to scream back at her. Fog surrounded her island like walls. She knew now that she was completely forsaken and that she should not expect anyone to come back for her. 

Her screaming ceased. She was hungry and cold. She wandered from hut to hut. They were all deserted and empty. She could not find even a blanket or scrap of fur. There was no fire remaining in any of the huts. Because of a shortage of wood, the island houses had been made of parts of whale skeletons covered over with furs. But the furs were gone now, and the white bones of the wide open mouths were all that remained of the village. She pried some mussels away from rocks at the water's edge, scooped them out of their shells, and gulped them down raw. 

"I must make fire to keep myself alive," she thought. "Without fire or clothing I will soon perish." 

Patiently she gathered dried grasses and leaves. In the shelter of her whale-skull hut she ground them to a powder. For hours she twirled a stick around in a small hole, faster and faster, never giving up until a few sparks set fire to the powdery grass. She sighed a long, weary sigh. "Never can I let my fire go out," she muttered to herself. "Now there is no one to help me. I must learn to depend upon myself and I must keep myself strong. Some day I may be rescued!"

Fortunately, that evening Gelma found a worn sea-otter skin, full of small holes which she patched from scraps cut from the ragged edges. It would last her a long time if she wore it only in the coldest weather. 

When roots and shellfish became scarce on the island, Gelma thought of the foods at the Mission&#8212;the juicy peaches, pears, and plums she had sampled. Sometimes in her dreams she was surrounded with mounds of food and her old friends, who were watching her eat it. Then her waking was still harder to bear. 

When Gelma began to feel the cold wintry fogs, she wove grasses into a kind of skirt. But when the wind roared across the island or the wet fog settled on it for days and weeks, there was not nearly enough warmth in her grass skirt and the worn skin cloak. 

The desolate Indian woman searched the island for any supplies that might have been left behind. She found a few flint knives and used them in making bone fishhooks and needles, and for digging roots. Every day she climbed up to the lookout rock, always with a faint hope that a ship might return for her.

Once when Gelma sighted a whale stranded in the shallow water, she shouted for the first time in many moons. She recalled those gay days long ago when all the islanders had cut and dried enough whale meat for the entire season. But with one knife and one pair of hands, only a small amount of meat could be cut. After a few days the odor of the rapidly spoiling meat along the shore sickened Gelma until she could scarcely eat. But her hunger drove her on. She had to eat. 

Years dragged by. There was little difference between the seasons on her bleak island. Rain in winter, fog in summer, and only an occasional sunny day! Gelma could tell the passing of the years by the shortening of the days, when it grew dark earlier than usual. On what seemed the shortest day she made a deep notch in the whale bone at the right of her doorway. 

One day in spring she heard a new sound and found a drift log bumping against the jagged rocks beyond the cliff. Quickly she swam out to it and tugged with all her strength to free it. After many hours she freed it from the rocks and pushed it before her to the shore, where she pulled it up on the beach to dry. 

"A dugout canoe," she murmured to herself. "With it I can paddle to the nearest island. Or when the wind is right I can drift to the mainland." In her thoughts she always added "to my baby." But then she quickly turned her thoughts to something else because she could never be sure whether her child had been sleeping safely in the bottom of the boat or whether&#8212;She dared not think about that. She had to keep busy. 

She spent many long hours digging into the log with her flint knives. It might take a lifetime to hollow out a canoe. Her knives might not last until she had finished it. When she had cut a small hole she laid a fire in it to burn it out. But the log had been soaked with water, and it showed little sign of drying. The dismal fogs kept it too damp to burn. Her fire kept smouldering, and then she would have to relight it. 

As the years dragged by, Gelma cut notches in the log as well as in the whale bone to mark the passage of time. Even with these two records she became uncertain about the exact number of years. She shrugged her bony shoulders. "What difference does the time make?" she thought. "It may be five years or ten. Or it may be all my life." 

Yet each spring with the coming of the new green leaves on the scrubby bushes and with the coming of the green grasses and occasional wild flowers, she again felt new hope. She noticed the large flocks of birds that stopped at her island&#8212;birds on their way to better climates. She could not fly away with them as she wished, but she could at least use them for food. 

Gelma built little bird traps of twigs and grasses. When she found how easily she could catch birds in them, she built many more traps and scattered them over the island. She needed the food desperately. Then after a while she began to think of all the little skins. What a beautiful dress they would make! Unlike anything ever seen before. Of course there would be no one to see her dress, but she would find joy in it, and besides, the feathers would help keep her warm. 

Very carefully she saved every bird skin, tiny or large. She rubbed them with seaweed and dried them tenderly to preserve the pretty feathers. In the long, dreary evenings beside her fire, she sewed these skins together with a fishbone needle and with thread made of fiber. The colors pleased the lonely woman. Yet always she kept whispering, "Mission clothes! Mission clothes!" and then, "Mission food!" until the words formed a sort of chant while she sewed. 

With every passing year there were more gashes on her log and her whale bone. There were more than she could count on all her fingers. Yet no ship had come for her! Sometimes, watching from her lookout on a clear day, she would think she saw a sail; but, before she could be sure of it, a fog bank would blot it from sight. Sometimes she thought she saw people landing on her beach, but always it was just a dream, a dreadfully disappointing dream. 

It had been years now since Gelma had spoken aloud. What use was speech when there was no one to hear her? She thought a great deal and sometimes even moved her mouth in silent words. But only the screaming sea gulls, the barking sea lions, and the constantly pounding waves kept her company. 

For a short time after her return to the island she had thrown fish to the sea lions, hoping to coax them to come close enough to be her friends. Then for a while she had scarcely enough food for herself. At last she decided it was better for the herds of sea lions to catch their own fish, as long as she had to eat whatever she could find and whenever she had the chance. Unlike all other creatures she could not leave the island! 

At last she finished the bird-skin dress and sewed it up over her body. A wild sense of freedom came over her the moment she wore it. She knew that the dugout canoe was little more than half done and that she could not hope to get away from the island. But she could leap from rock to rock and spread her feather-covered arms like wings in her wild dance. From one end of the island to the other she sped, almost like a great bird ready to sail away into the sky. She laughed and shouted wildly at the sea gulls, which screamed back at her and flew away as if mocking her helplessness. 

Her shouting and laughter grew louder as she raced back toward her hut. Even when she saw white men and Indians she paid no attention. They must be another of her many dreams. This time she would not think about them. But when they spoke in a strange tongue she realized it was no dream. 

"Come! Come back to the mainland with us!" they cried. They made their meaning clear by using signs. They tried to tell her that from their whaling ship they had seen the movement of the bright colors as she danced, and they had come to rescue her. 

Gelma was afraid. She was terrified and happy at the same time. She ate the food they offered her; then she climbed silently into the boat, still dazed by the thought of their sudden appearance after eighteen long years of waiting. As they rowed out to the whaling ship, Gelma would not look back at her island prison. Never again did she want to see its cold forbidding shores! On board the ship she ate all the fruit and bread the palefaces offered her. She held out her hand for more. After eighteen years of near-starvation, would she ever have enough food again? She kept shaking her head to make sure it was not a dream. Then she gripped the railing of the ship and knew she was not dreaming. 

Closer to the mainland the fog cleared away. Suddenly the sun shone on a small city of dazzling white houses roofed with red tiles. It shone still brighter on a beautiful building farther up the hill. All of this was much grander than any of Gelma's dreams. Could this be the wonderful Mission she had longed for all these years? After hoping in vain, were her dreams really coming true?

Anxiously she watched the shore, longing for a glimpse of her people, who would be waiting to welcome her. Her heart pounded wildly. Where were all the Indians? She could not see an Indian anywhere. 

When the rowboat at last reached shore, Mrs. Nidever, the wife of the ship's captain, opened her arms and held the forlorn woman tightly. But Gelma was dazed and bewildered. Her eyes kept searching for others, for her own dark-skinned people, to welcome her. Gray-robed Father Sánchez greeted her with a friendly smile and led both the women into the shelter and quiet of the deserted Mission. But Gelma was frightened even more when she saw the strange candlelight flickering on the altar. 

"Where are my people?" Gelma kept asking, over and over again. She repeated her words in a dreadful, wailing chant. But it was many weeks before she had learned enough of her friend's Spanish to understand about the fate of the Indians. When new rulers had given the Indians their freedom, they had left the Mission. Some of them were working on neighboring ranchos and some had disappeared completely. Gelma's heart felt numb. Then her loneliness returned, more dreadful than before. 

Gelma asked the same pitiful questions of every visitor to the Mission. "Where are my people? Where are the Indians from San Nicolas Island?" 

Kindly Father Sánchez showed her all the orchards that the Indians had planted. Perhaps her people had helped to build the sparkling fountain and the laundering trough. They might have helped decorate the wonderful white church. But where were they now? Were some of them in those unmarked graves in the Mission churchyard? 

Gelma shook her head sadly. "Let me become a Mission Indian too. Let me do what I can to help the Mission that once gave shelter to many of my people." 

So the padre spent many hours with her, teaching her about the Mission God. Sometimes Gelma knelt alone on the smooth tiles inside the church. Sometimes she lighted an altar candle and prayed in her native tongue. "Let me see just one of my people! Just one!" she would repeat again and again. 

Days were passing much more swiftly than they had seemed to pass on the island of San Nicolas. In just two weeks Gelma would be baptized in the wonderful Mission church. Often she wandered forlornly up into the hills beyond Santa Barbara. She kept hoping to meet some of her island people. Sometimes she wondered whether she would recognize them after so many years. 

Meanwhile all the people in the village were very kind to her. They gave her more rich food than she could possibly eat. They were planning a big fiesta for the day when she would be baptized Juana María. In return for their kindness, Gelma had promised to dance a new bird dance in the same costume she had been wearing when she came to Santa Barbara.

One morning she was practicing her new dance skipping, leaping, gliding across the balcony of the Nidever house. She could not keep her thoughts on her dance; she kept thinking, instead, of all her people. As she danced close to the railing, she glanced down into the street below. Suddenly she stood still and clung tightly to one of the posts. She stared at a young Indian, dressed in Mission clothes, who was walking past the house. 

"Stop! Stop!" she shouted in her native tongue. 

The young man looked up at her and shook his head. Then he replied in smooth-flowing Spanish that Gelma could not follow. But there was something in his fine, earnest young face that reminded Gelma of her people. As he walked away from her across the field toward the Mission he seemed even more familiar to her. She watched him until at last he disappeared down the long, arched corridors. 

The lonely Indian woman stood on the balcony, lost in her memories. Could it be that her dreams, her new prayers, were about to come true? 

"Gelma! Gelma!" It was Mrs. Nidever calling her. "Come, Gelma! Your lunch is waiting for you!" Gelma looked at her friend a moment and sighed. "I can't eat," she said in halting Spanish. "I must go to the Mission." In a mixture of her two languages she tried to tell Mrs. Nidever about the young Indian who had just walked by and gone to the Mission. "He looks like my people! He looks like my . . . ."

Mrs. Nidever put her arm around the trembling Indian woman. "We can ask Father Sánchez," she said. "He will surely know who the young man is." 

Gelma's dark eyes glowed. "Could&#8212;could I have a new dress to wear?" she asked wistfully. "A Mission dress or else a Spanish dress?" 

Mrs. Nidever showed her an old sea chest, filled with treasures from all parts of the world. "Which would you like to wear, Gelma?" she asked gently. "You may make your choice." 

Admiringly, Gelma chose a long, rustling black dress and a gay embroidered shawl. She longed for beautifully embroidered satin slippers, too, but there were none to fit her feet. "We can make new slippers for you in time for the fiesta," promised Mrs. Nidever. "Now you are dressed just like a Spanish señora!" 

The two women walked across the fields. Gelma lingered a moment to admire her reflection in the beautifully clear water of the fountain. Then she hurried over to the Mission church where Father Sánchez was standing. She waited for Mrs. Nidever to speak. 

"Good evening, Padre! Gelma wants to know if you can tell us about a certain young Indian who passed by our house a short time ago," explained Mrs. Nidever. 

Father Sánchez looked at Gelma's fine new clothing and smiled at her. "Oh, yes! The boy has come from San Gabriel Mission," he answered in a friendly manner. "His name is Juan, almost the same as Juana, which will be your own name after your baptism. He is an orphan, about twenty years old, and he has come to look after our beautiful gardens, that have been long neglected. He is a fine boy! He has a good voice, too, and will be a great help in our choir. And he has strong and willing hands to devote to his Mission." 

Gelma smiled and raised her head proudly. She lifted her rustling skirts a little, the way Spanish ladies did, and tiptoed down the aisle toward the front of the church. Then she knelt on the cool tile floor, bowed her head, and clasped her hands very tightly.

She couldn't be absolutely sure that Juan was one of her San Nicolas people. But in her heart she was sure that he was really her own son. They would both be Mission Indians and do whatever they could to help the good padre. 

At first Gelma prayed slowly, falteringly. Then her words burst forth in torrents of thanks which helped to wash from her memory all the old sorrow of her lonely years. New hope and a new-found happiness were being born within her.
