__pers__The Lone Woman of San Nicolas

A Tale of __org__Mission Santa Barbara

[...]

INTRODUCTION 

THIS is the story of __pers__a lone Indian woman who was marooned on __place__a bleak island in __place__the Santa Barbara Channel. She was rescued after many years, and when she at last reached __place__Mission Santa Barbara she found both joy and sorrow within its shelter. 

orgMission Santa Barbara was founded __date?__nearly seventy years earlier. From the gentle slopes of __place__the Santa Ins Mountains, __org__this tenth Mission, __org__the "Queen of the Missions," overlooks __place__the ocean and __place__the distant islands of the Santa Barbara Channel. 

Very soon after __org__its founding, __org__Chumash Indians came to __org__the Mission in large numbers. Under __org__the padres' skillful training they learned to build their own adobe houses, which they whitewashed neatly inside and out. Their Indian village was arranged around a large plaza, where the children and young people learned to garden. The older Indians, too, learned many valuable skills&#8212;carpentering, tanning, weaving, sewing, gardening, and cattle raising. Altogether, six hundred __org__Chumash Indians worked faithfully under the guidance of __org__the padres. 

Building activity at __place__Mission Santa Barbara was a continuous process. New and larger structures were built to replace the earlier ones. After __pers__Captain Vancouver visited __place__the Mission in __date__1793, he wrote in his book that he considered __place__Santa Barbara the best-constructed and the best-kept of all the Missions he had seen. At a still later period, __place__the fourth church was constructed. This is __place__the church which is widely known and admired today. Its six-foot-thick sandstone walls are crowned with two massive bell towers. The beauty and grandeur of __place__this Mission building have influenced architecture even beyond borders of __place__California. 

Still other structures at __place__Mission Santa Barbara have endured for __date?__more than a century. A large reservoir which collected water from the hills is still in use. __place?__The beautiful fountain where __pers__Juana looked at her reflection continues to flow today. But standing empty and unused is the long basin where __org__the Indian women formerly washed their clothes and rinsed them in fresh water spouting from a cement bearÕs head. 

__org__Mission Santa Barbara had its difficult period too. When news came that __pers__the pirate Bouchard was within a few miles of __place__this Mission, __org?__soldiers and __org__Indians prepared to defend it, but he did not attack.

A few years later, __org__enemy Indians attacked it in force. Fires swept over the hills, burned the trees, threatened __place__the Mission, and blackened its vineyards. At another time there was a drought so serious that __org__the people marched through the streets and prayed for rain. 

One of the greatest blows to __org__Mission Santa Barbara, as well as to __org__the other Missions, was the decree of secularization. About ten years after __place__Mexico became an independent nation, the new government decided on a plan which would remove the __org__California Missions from the control of __org__the Church. The first step was to "free" __org__the Indians from __org__the padres' rule. But when __org__few Indians seemed eager for this "freedom," another step was taken. Only __org__Indians who were free would be allowed to vote in their village election. Because most of __org__the Indians were devoted to __org__the padres, even this decree had little effect. 

In the following year, __date__1834, the actual decree of secularization was passed. This act provided that __org__the Indians and __org__the Mission property were to be removed from the control of __org__the Franciscan padres. Administrators, or "secular" officials, were then to govern both __org__the Missions and __org__the Indians. Inventories were taken at all __place__the Missions, and the new officials in charge received salaries which were paid out of __org__the Missions' earnings. __org?__Mexican padres were to replace __org__the Spanish Franciscans. Under this secular control, both __org__the padres and __org__the poor Mission Indians suffered. __place__Mission buildings and ranches were sadly neglected, and __org__Mission prosperity gradually came to an end. 

During this difficult period, however, __pers__a new padre came to __place__Mission Santa Barbara in the company of __pers__Bishop Diego, California's first bishop. This young __pers__Mexican priest, __pers__Father Francisco Snchez, was a man of unusual zeal and devotion. For forty-two years he worked among __org__California's Indians and Mexicans. Today he is probably better known readers of __org__<emph>Ramona</emph> as __pers__Father Salvierderra, a man beloved by all. In __date__1853, when __pers__the Lone Woman of San Nicolas reached __place__Mission Santa Barbara, it was this same understanding __pers__Father Snchez who welcomed her and later baptized her at __place__the Mission which had sheltered many of __org__her people.

__org__MISSION SANTA BARBARA 

CALENDAR

__date__1786 Founding of __org__the Mission, December 4 

__date__1820 Dedication of __place__the present church 

__date__1834 Secularization 

__date__1842 Arrival of __pers__Father Snchez 

__date__1846 Sale of __org__the Mission 

__date__1865 Return of __org__the Mission to the __org__Catholic Church

__pers__THE LONE WOMAN OF SAN NICOLAS 

THE cold gray fog settled down over the rocky island of __date__San Nicolas, farthest westward of the __date__Santa Barbara Channel Islands. __pers__Gelma stood on the beach and shivered. Even her cloak of smooth sea-otter skin could not shut out the cold and dampness of such a day. She stared at the cliff where breakers were dashing high above the jagged rocks, adding their constant pounding roar to the screeching of sea gulls. 

"If only the sun would shine!" __pers__Gelma said to __pers__her sister. "When I see nothing but fog day after day, I am restless and unhappy." 

__pers__The older Indian woman touched Gelma's arm and pointed seaward. "Look!" she urged. "The fog is drifting now. Maybe it will blow away and you can have your sunshine. All of us will be happier if the sun shines." 

__pers__Gelma noticed a tiny patch of water where blue waves danced and sparkled in a shaft of light. Suddenly the patch widened, showing the sunlight which soon flooded the island with its warmth. And offshore, tossing about on the choppy waves was a small boat. 

"A boat! A boat!" shouted __pers__Gelma. 

__org__Indians hurried out of their huts to see the welcome sight. __pers__Gelma darted into her hut and carried __pers__her small boy to the shore to watch the arrival of the rowboat. As it came closer she could see several people. __org__Indians were rowing the boat, but three white men were in it too. 

"Those are not __trait__Russians," said __pers__Gelma, surprised. 

"They are strangers," agreed __pers__her sister. “__org__Russian fur traders said they would never come here again. But perhaps these palefaces are traders too.Ó

__pers__Gelma watched __org__the village children shouting and laughing as they ran along the narrow strip of sandy beach. Even one day of sunshine brought joy to young and old alike. And now, visitors! She put __pers__her small son down on the beach and wished for his sake that all the days could be warm and bright like this one. 

As the rowboat nosed up on the beach, __org__Indians crowded around it. __org__Children tumbled into it and climbed out again, carrying strange fruits in their brown hands. __pers__One of the Indians who had come in the boat spoke for the white men in a language that __org__the islanders could partly understand.

"We come from __org__Missions on __place__mainland," he said slowly. 

At first __pers__Gelma did not pay much attention to his words. She did not understand ”Missions." She was far more interested in the bright clothes __org__the Indians were wearing. Gaily striped blankets were wrapped around their shoulders covering most of their clothes except the blue-gray trousers. It was not until __org__the strange Indians offered fruit to __org__the islanders that __pers__Gelma became really interested in their explanations. 

"At __org__Missions we grow beautiful fruit&#8212;apples, peaches, plums, pears, and oranges." __pers__The man's words were not so interesting as the sweet fruit he offered. Except for an occasional wild berry, this fruit was the first that __pers__Gelma had ever tasted. She ate one piece hungrily, then reached for another to give to __pers__her little boy. 

"What are __org__these Missions?" asked __pers__the chief of the island. "Tell us more!"

__pers__The visiting Indian looked around him and pointed to __place__the barren island where few trees grew and where huts were made of whale skeletons covered with furs. "At __place__Missions are warm huts, comfortable beds, plenty of food three times a day." 

__pers__Gelma sighed. Was it possible that any place had such good things? "Does sun shine at __org__Missions?" she asked, trembling at her own boldness. 

__pers__The strange Indian nodded and smiled. "Sun all year long," he promised. “__place__Wonderful church and __org__gray-robed padres. Beautiful music!Ó 

__pers__Gelma shook her head, not understanding about __place__the church and __org__the padres. She wondered about the music too. There was little music on __place__San Nicolas Island, and that little was mournful and shrill. But at that moment __pers__one of the Indians and __org__the white men began to sing a joyous song. __pers__The other Indian took something shiny from the bottom of the boat, held it to his lips, and played sweet music that made __org__the islanders long to dance. 

__pers__Gelma needed nothing more to persuade her to go away to __place__the mainland, but it was not her place to speak. She had nothing to say about what __org__her people would do. The __org__Mission song ended far too soon to suit her. Then __pers__the island chief spoke simply. "Do __org__Indians live at __place__this Mission?" 

__pes__The first Mission Indian answered, "Hundreds of __org__Indians live there! __org__Padres sent us here to ask you to come and join us." 

"We play much but we work too," the other added eagerly. 

__pers__The Chief called __org__the men of the village into his hut for a council meeting. __pers__Gelma listened anxiously to the voices which were louder than usual. She smiled when __pers__the Chief announced solemnly, "We go to __place__Mission." 

__org__All the islanders began to crowd closer to the boat until __org__the Mission Indians waved them back. "Wait!Ó they shouted. "We must return to __ship__our ship, which is anchored offshore. Then we can bring another rowboat. We have room for only a few this time. While we are gone, get ready everything you wish to take with you!" But __org__the Indians refused to go until they could all leave __place__their island at once. 

After the boat had disappeared into the fog, __pers__the Chief called __org__his people together for a few minutes. "Pack only what you really need!" he ordered. "But leave nothing of value behind you for __org__Russian fur traders to steal." 

__pers__Gelma took __pers__her little boy, hurried to her sisterÕs hut, and began sorting furs and baskets of food. "Always sunshine," she murmured. "Warm days, good food, and wonderful music." She was so happy that she tried to sing the chant __org__the strangers had sung. 

"Why, __pers__Gelma!" __pers__her sister said. "You are singing for the first time in many years."

Gelma's eyes grew bright. "I am happy for __org__all of us, but mostly for __pers__the little one." 

__pers__The older woman sorted her few belongings while __pers__her children danced in and out of the hut. Never before had there been such great excitement on __place__San Nicolas Island. At last __pers__one of the children shouted shrilly, "The boats are coming!" 

__org__The villagers hurried to the beach to watch. When the boats were close to the shore, __pers__the Chief gave final orders to __org__his people. "Bring all your supplies to the beach! And toss the fur coverings from your huts into the sea." 

Now that __org__the Indians were ready to leave __place__the only home they had ever known, they were silent&#8212;all but __pers__Gelma, who felt nothing but joy over leaving __place__the dismal island. "Take this pile of furs for __pers__my baby," she said to __pers__her sister's oldest child. 

"No!" cried __pers__the girl. "I'll take care of __pers__your little boy!" 

At that moment the boats reached shore. "Hurry!" cried __org__the Mission Indians. "A storm is coming! No time to lose! We'll help you!" 

__org__The soldiers showed the Indians where to sit in the bottom of the boat. They pushed women and frightened children into their places. Suddenly __pers__Gelma remembered the good furs still covering the whale-bone hut. She and __pers__her sister were both widows with no man to help them. She ran back to the hut. In a moment she had stripped off the furs and tossed them into the sea. She was glad to see the breakers snatch them away where __org__no trader would get them. By the time she returned to the beach, the first boat had pushed away from shore. As she stopped to pick up her supplies, impatient hands pushed her into the other boat. 

Separated now from __group__her sister's family and __pers__her child, __pers__Gelma was frightened among __org__so many strangers. The waves through which they were rowing grew higher with every passing moment. The fog banks were shifting across the blue-gray water and shutting out both the other boat and __place__the island from sight. 

With one hand __pers__Gelma clung tightly to her package of furs, and with the other she gripped the edge of the boat. To calm her fears she thought of the perfect days ahead when she and __pers__her son would enjoy the warm sunshine and the fine __org__Mission food. 

At last the rowboat drew close to __ship__the large, winged ship. __pers__Gelma was the first to climb on board and hurry to the wide deck. Standing beside __pers__the captain she watched for the other boat to appear out of the fog. Even before she caught a glimpse of it, she heard screams she recognized. Then she saw the crowded boat and __pers__her sister trying to quiet the screams of __pers__the little girl. But where was __pers__Gelma's small boy? What had happened to __pers__her child? 

Gelma's heart was like lead. She shouted to __pers__her sister, but the little girl's screams drowned out her words. She shook the captain's arm. "Send a boat back! __pers__My baby has been left behind!" But __pers__the captain only shook his head. 

Panic gripped __pers__the young mother. There was no time to lose. If she waited, someone might stop her. She could not forsake __pers__her child. She ran to the other side of the ship, tore off her fur cloak and leaped into the water. 

__pers__Gelma was a strong young woman, toughened by years of struggle against nature. She swam easily enough for a short distance. But never before had she tried a long swim against mountainous waves and opposing tides. At first she swam breathlessly in a hurry to reach shore. But soon her breath came in gasps that forced her to rest. On and on she swam, steadily, wearily, carried off her course time after time. 

Often __place__the island was swallowed up in a fog bank, but she could tell the right direction by the booming of the breakers against the cliffs. At last a long, sweeping breaker lifted her and swept her high up on the shallow beach. There she lay, too beaten and bruised to be able to move for a long time. 

Staggering, stumbling, she found her way to her hut. But she found no sign of __pers__her child. Blankets, food, and __pers__baby were gone! She dragged herself out into the bitter cold evening. She called frantically for __pers__her child. Then she crept back inside the shelter and sank down in a heap. 

All that night __pers__Gelma lay in a stupor. In the morning a streak of sunshine came through the fog and wakened her. She listened a moment for the sound of her baby's breathing, but she heard only the beating of her heart. All at once she clearly realized the dreadful truth. She was alone, alone on __place__San Nicolas Island, miles and miles away from __org__her people. 

Her grief, loneliness, and despair drove her screaming out of the hut. She raced up the rocky shore to a cliff. But there were only the sea gulls to scream back at her. Fog surrounded __place__her island like walls. She knew now that she was completely forsaken and that she should not expect anyone to come back for her. 

Her screaming ceased. She was hungry and cold. She wandered from hut to hut. They were all deserted and empty. She could not find even a blanket or scrap of fur. There was no fire remaining in any of the huts. Because of a shortage of wood, the island houses had been made of parts of whale skeletons covered over with furs. But the furs were gone now, and the white bones of the wide open mouths were all that remained of the village. She pried some mussels away from rocks at the water's edge, scooped them out of their shells, and gulped them down raw. 

"I must make fire to keep myself alive," she thought. "Without fire or clothing I will soon perish." 

Patiently she gathered dried grasses and leaves. In the shelter of her whale-skull hut she ground them to a powder. For hours she twirled a stick around in a small hole, faster and faster, never giving up until a few sparks set fire to the powdery grass. She sighed a long, weary sigh. "Never can I let my fire go out," she muttered to herself. "Now there is no one to help me. I must learn to depend upon myself and I must keep myself strong. Some day I may be rescued!"

Fortunately, that evening __pers__Gelma found a worn sea-otter skin, full of small holes which she patched from scraps cut from the ragged edges. It would last her a long time if she wore it only in the coldest weather. 

When roots and shellfish became scarce on the island, __pers__Gelma thought of the foods at __place__the Mission&#8212;the juicy peaches, pears, and plums she had sampled. Sometimes in her dreams she was surrounded with mounds of food and __org__her old friends, who were watching her eat it. Then her waking was still harder to bear. 

When __pers__Gelma began to feel the cold wintry fogs, she wove grasses into a kind of skirt. But when the wind roared across __place__the island or the wet fog settled on it for days and weeks, there was not nearly enough warmth in her grass skirt and the worn skin cloak. 

__pers__The desolate Indian woman searched __place__the island for any supplies that might have been left behind. She found a few flint knives and used them in making bone fishhooks and needles, and for digging roots. Every day she climbed up to the lookout rock, always with a faint hope that a ship might return for her.

Once when __pers__Gelma sighted a whale stranded in the shallow water, she shouted for the first time in many moons. She recalled those gay days long ago when all __org__the islanders had cut and dried enough whale meat for the entire season. But with one knife and one pair of hands, only a small amount of meat could be cut. After a few days the odor of the rapidly spoiling meat along the shore sickened __pers__Gelma until she could scarcely eat. But her hunger drove her on. She had to eat. 

Years dragged by. There was little difference between the seasons on __place__her bleak island. Rain in winter, fog in summer, and only an occasional sunny day! __pers__Gelma could tell the passing of the years by the shortening of the days, when it grew dark earlier than usual. On what seemed the shortest day she made a deep notch in the whale bone at the right of her doorway. 

One day in spring she heard a new sound and found a drift log bumping against the jagged rocks beyond the cliff. Quickly she swam out to it and tugged with all her strength to free it. After many hours she freed it from the rocks and pushed it before her to the shore, where she pulled it up on the beach to dry. 

"A dugout canoe," she murmured to herself. "With it I can paddle to the nearest island. Or when the wind is right I can drift to __place__the mainland." In her thoughts she always added "to __pers__my baby." But then she quickly turned her thoughts to something else because she could never be sure whether __pers__her child had been sleeping safely in the bottom of the boat or whether&#8212;She dared not think about that. She had to keep busy. 

She spent many long hours digging into the log with her flint knives. It might take a lifetime to hollow out a canoe. Her knives might not last until she had finished it. When she had cut a small hole she laid a fire in it to burn it out. But the log had been soaked with water, and it showed little sign of drying. The dismal fogs kept it too damp to burn. Her fire kept smouldering, and then she would have to relight it. 

As the years dragged by, __pers__Gelma cut notches in the log as well as in the whale bone to mark the passage of time. Even with these two records she became uncertain about the exact number of years. She shrugged her bony shoulders. "What difference does the time make?" she thought. "It may be five years or ten. Or it may be all my life." 

Yet each spring with the coming of the new green leaves on the scrubby bushes and with the coming of the green grasses and occasional wild flowers, she again felt new hope. She noticed the large flocks of birds that stopped at her island&#8212;birds on their way to better climates. She could not fly away with them as she wished, but she could at least use them for food. 

__pers__Gelma built little bird traps of twigs and grasses. When she found how easily she could catch birds in them, she built many more traps and scattered them over the island. She needed the food desperately. Then after a while she began to think of all the little skins. What a beautiful dress they would make! Unlike anything ever seen before. Of course there would be no one to see her dress, but she would find joy in it, and besides, the feathers would help keep her warm. 

Very carefully she saved every bird skin, tiny or large. She rubbed them with seaweed and dried them tenderly to preserve the pretty feathers. In the long, dreary evenings beside her fire, she sewed these skins together with a fishbone needle and with thread made of fiber. The colors pleased __pers__the lonely woman. Yet always she kept whispering, “__org__Mission clothes! __org__Mission clothes!" and then, “__org__Mission food!" until the words formed a sort of chant while she sewed. 

With every passing year there were more gashes on her log and her whale bone. There were more than she could count on all her fingers. Yet no ship had come for her! Sometimes, watching from her lookout on a clear day, she would think she saw a sail; but, before she could be sure of it, a fog bank would blot it from sight. Sometimes she thought she saw people landing on her beach, but always it was just a dream, a dreadfully disappointing dream. 

It had been years now since __pers__Gelma had spoken aloud. What use was speech when there was no one to hear her? She thought a great deal and sometimes even moved her mouth in silent words. But only the screaming sea gulls, the barking sea lions, and the constantly pounding waves kept her company. 

For a short time after her return to __place__the island she had thrown fish to the sea lions, hoping to coax them to come close enough to be __org__her friends. Then for a while she had scarcely enough food for herself. At last she decided it was better for the herds of sea lions to catch their own fish, as long as she had to eat whatever she could find and whenever she had the chance. Unlike all other creatures she could not leave __place__the island! 

At last she finished the bird-skin dress and sewed it up over her body. A wild sense of freedom came over her the moment she wore it. She knew that the dugout canoe was little more than half done and that she could not hope to get away from __place__the island. But she could leap from rock to rock and spread her feather-covered arms like wings in her wild dance. From one end of __place__the island to the other she sped, almost like a great bird ready to sail away into the sky. She laughed and shouted wildly at the sea gulls, which screamed back at her and flew away as if mocking her helplessness. 

Her shouting and laughter grew louder as she raced back toward her hut. Even when she saw __group__white men and Indians she paid no attention. They must be another of her many dreams. This time she would not think about them. But when they spoke in a strange tongue she realized it was no dream. 

"Come! Come back to __place__the mainland with us!" they cried. They made their meaning clear by using signs. They tried to tell her that from __ship__their whaling ship they had seen the movement of the bright colors as she danced, and they had come to rescue her. 

__pers__Gelma was afraid. She was terrified and happy at the same time. She ate the food they offered her; then she climbed silently into the boat, still dazed by the thought of their sudden appearance after __date__eighteen long years of waiting. As they rowed out to the whaling ship, Gelma would not look back at __place__her island prison. Never again did she want to see its cold forbidding shores! On board __ship__the ship she ate all the fruit and bread the palefaces offered her. She held out her hand for more. After __date__eighteen years of near-starvation, would she ever have enough food again? She kept shaking her head to make sure it was not a dream. Then she gripped the railing of the ship and knew she was not dreaming. 

Closer to __place__the mainland the fog cleared away. Suddenly the sun shone on a small city of dazzling white houses roofed with red tiles. It shone still brighter on a beautiful building farther up the hill. All of this was much grander than any of Gelma's dreams. Could this be the wonderful __place__Mission she had longed for all these years? After hoping in vain, were her dreams really coming true?

Anxiously she watched the shore, longing for a glimpse of __org__her people, who would be waiting to welcome her. Her heart pounded wildly. Where were all __org__the Indians? She could not see __org__an Indian anywhere. 

When the rowboat at last reached shore, __pers__Mrs. Nidever, the wife of the ship's captain, opened her arms and held the forlorn woman tightly. But __pers__Gelma was dazed and bewildered. Her eyes kept searching for others, for __org__her own dark-skinned people, to welcome her. __pers__Gray-robed Father Sánchez greeted her with a friendly smile and led __pers__both the women into the shelter and quiet of __place__the deserted Mission. But __pers__Gelma was frightened even more when she saw the strange candlelight flickering on the altar. 

"Where are my people?" __pers__Gelma kept asking, over and over again. She repeated her words in a dreadful, wailing chant. But it was many weeks before she had learned enough of her friend's Spanish to understand about the fate of __org__the Indians. When new rulers had given __org__the Indians their freedom, they had left __org__the Mission. Some of them were working on neighboring ranchos and some had disappeared completely. Gelma's heart felt numb. Then her loneliness returned, more dreadful than before. 

__pers__Gelma asked the same pitiful questions of every visitor to __org__the Mission. "Where are my people? Where are __org__the Indians from San Nicolas Island?" 

Kindly __pers__Father Sánchez showed her all the orchards that __org__the Indians had planted. Perhaps her people had helped to build the sparkling fountain and the laundering trough. They might have helped decorate the wonderful white church. But where were they now? Were some of them in those unmarked graves in __place__the Mission churchyard? 

__pers__Gelma shook her head sadly. "Let me become a __org__Mission Indian too. Let me do what I can to help __org__the Mission that once gave shelter to many of __org__my people." 

So __pers__the padre spent many hours with her, teaching her about the Mission God. Sometimes __pers__Gelma knelt alone on the smooth tiles inside __place__the church. Sometimes she lighted an altar candle and prayed in her native tongue. "Let me see just one of __org__my people! Just one!" she would repeat again and again. 

Days were passing much more swiftly than they had seemed to pass on __place__the island of San Nicolas. In just two weeks __pers__Gelma would be baptized in the wonderful __place__Mission church. Often she wandered forlornly up into the hills beyond __place__Santa Barbara. She kept hoping to meet some of __org__her island people. Sometimes she wondered whether she would recognize them after so many years. 

Meanwhile all the people in the village were very kind to her. They gave her more rich food than she could possibly eat. They were planning a big fiesta for the day when she would be baptized __pers__Juana María. In return for their kindness, __pers__Gelma had promised to dance a new bird dance in the same costume she had been wearing when she came to __place__Santa Barbara.

One morning she was practicing her new dance skipping, leaping, gliding across the balcony of the __place__Nidever house. She could not keep her thoughts on her dance; she kept thinking, instead, of __org__all her people. As she danced close to the railing, she glanced down into the street below. Suddenly she stood still and clung tightly to one of the posts. She stared at __pers__a young Indian, dressed in __org__Mission clothes, who was walking past the house. 

"Stop! Stop!" she shouted in her native tongue. 

__pers__The young man looked up at her and shook his head. Then he replied in smooth-flowing Spanish that __pers__Gelma could not follow. But there was something in his fine, earnest young face that reminded __pers__Gelma of __org__her people. As he walked away from her across the field toward __place__the Mission he seemed even more familiar to her. She watched him until at last he disappeared down the long, arched corridors. 

__pers__The lonely Indian woman stood on the balcony, lost in her memories. Could it be that her dreams, her new prayers, were about to come true? 

"__pers__Gelma! __pers__Gelma!" It was __pers__Mrs. Nidever calling her. "Come, __pers__Gelma! Your lunch is waiting for you!" __pers__Gelma looked at __pers__her friend a moment and sighed. "I can't eat," she said in halting Spanish. "I must go to __place__the Mission." In a mixture of her two languages she tried to tell __pers__Mrs. Nidever about __pers__the young Indian who had just walked by and gone to __place__the Mission. "He looks like __org__my people! He looks like my . . . ."

__pers__Mrs. Nidever put her arm around __pers__the trembling Indian woman. "We can ask __pers__Father Sánchez," she said. "He will surely know who __pers__the young man is." 

Gelma's dark eyes glowed. "Could&#8212;could I have a new dress to wear?" she asked wistfully. "A Mission dress or else a Spanish dress?" 

__pers__Mrs. Nidever showed her an old sea chest, filled with treasures from all parts of the world. "Which would you like to wear, __pers__Gelma?" she asked gently. "You may make your choice." 

Admiringly, __pers__Gelma chose a long, rustling black dress and a gay embroidered shawl. She longed for beautifully embroidered satin slippers, too, but there were none to fit her feet. "We can make new slippers for you in time for the fiesta," promised __pers__Mrs. Nidever. "Now you are dressed just like a Spanish señora!" 

The two women walked across the fields. __pers__Gelma lingered a moment to admire her reflection in the beautifully clear water of the fountain. Then she hurried over to the __place__Mission church where __pers__Father Sánchez was standing. She waited for __pers__Mrs. Nidever to speak. 

"Good evening, __pers__Padre! __pers__Gelma wants to know if you can tell us about __pers__a certain young Indian who passed by our house a short time ago," explained __pers__Mrs. Nidever. 

__pers__Father Sánchez looked at Gelma's fine new clothing and smiled at her. "Oh, yes! __pers__The boy has come from __org__San Gabriel Mission," he answered in a friendly manner. "His name is __pers__Juan, almost the same as __pers__Juana, which will be your own name after your baptism. He is an orphan, about twenty years old, and he has come to look after our beautiful gardens, that have been long neglected. He is a fine boy! He has a good voice, too, and will be a great help in our choir. And he has strong and willing hands to devote to __org__his Mission." 

__pers__Gelma smiled and raised her head proudly. She lifted her rustling skirts a little, the way Spanish ladies did, and tiptoed down the aisle toward the front of __place__the church. Then she knelt on the cool tile floor, bowed her head, and clasped her hands very tightly.

She couldn't be absolutely sure that Juan was one of __org__her San Nicolas people. But in her heart she was sure that he was really __pers__her own son. They would both be __org__Mission Indians and do whatever they could to help __pers__the good padre. 

At first __pers__Gelma prayed slowly, falteringly. Then her words burst forth in torrents of thanks which helped to wash from her memory all the old sorrow of her lonely years. New hope and a new-found happiness were being born within her.
