<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#pacificmonthly">Pacific
                     Monthly</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
               <date when="1907"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_portland">Portland</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_or">Oregon</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Tenney1907">The Hermit of San Nicholas</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="30"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#wten">Tenney, W. A.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                           >The Hermit of San Nicholas</persName></rs></hi></title></head>
            <byline><hi rend="bold">By <persName type="author" key="#wten">W. A.
                  Tenney</persName></hi>
               <hi rend="bold">Illustrated from Photographs taken by <persName type="author"
                     key="#jbr">J. C. Brewster</persName></hi></byline>
            <p>NOW few readers have ever seen in print any account of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicholas Island</placeName>. The name, even, is visible only on
               the recent maps of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. The
               pioneer settlers of <placeName type="county" key="#co_ventura">Ventura</placeName>
               and <placeName type="county" key="#co_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> Counties,
               together with the survivors of the old Mexican race, relate an entertaining tradition
               of what occurred on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this <emph>terra
                        incognita</emph></placeName></rs> at a modern date; but tradition, though a
               convenient foundation for a romance, is not recognized as credible history. Some of
               the pioneer hunters, however, left in writing a thrilling narrative of what they
               personally witnessed on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. <title type="manuscript" key="#Terry1882">This written
                  account</title> of thoroughly reliable eye-witnesses was published in the local
               history of <placeName type="county" key="#co_ventura">Ventura County</placeName>
               while the witnesses were still living. In addition to the uniform recital of a
               generntion not yet extinct, we have a corroborating report in public documents of
               what Government explorers found on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName> at a recent date. <persName type="author" key="#jbr">The
                  photographer</persName>, who accompanied the officials, has furnished us with the
               scenes taken by his camera. With this accumulation of disconnected material,
               accessible to very few readers, because long out of print, we venture to compile a
               connected story in every way historically true.</p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas Island</placeName> is eighty miles
               due south from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ven">Buena Ventura</placeName>, and
               belongs to <placeName type="county" key="#co_ventura">Ventura County</placeName>. It
               is remote from all lines of ocean travel, situated in a storm center, with no
               sheltered harbor for large sea-going vessels, and with a roadstead unsafe for
               anchorage by reason of sudden and violent changes of winds. The pounding of the waves
               on the west side has opened a narrow gateway through the rock into a shallow bay,
               where small boats can comfortably land. The situation of <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> is such that it is difficult to find an
               experienced navigator who is willing to take tourists to the place, especially if
               expected to tarry for many days in the exposed offing.</p>
            <p>For half a century <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this spot of
                     earth</placeName></rs> has been unpeopled except for the last few years by
                     <rs><persName key="#shepherd">a lone shepherd</persName></rs> of a flock of
               sheep.</p>
            <p>By Government survey <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs> is found to be nine miles long and four miles wide, with
               an area of thirty-two square miles. Some fourteen thousand acres are comparatively
               level, with a seemingly rich soil. A few stunted thorn bushes comprise all the
               present timber, though excavations reveal the existence of an extinct forest. Indeed,
               the early fur hunters reported that more than fifty years ago they found a part of
               the tract covered with trees and shrubbery. Modern fires have denuded the whole
               territory.</p>
            <p>Vast quantities of land shells are found in the sand and in mounds, but not a living
               specimen can now be found of that particular species, though they are still extant on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">other islands</placeName></rs> and
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>. That these land
               mollusks were used for food by <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the primitive natives</orgName></rs> is
               self-evident from the segregated mounds of this species.</p>
            <p>Numerous circular depressions are found everywhere, indicating the location of
               prehistoric human dwellings. <persName type="author" key="#sbo">Dr.
               Bowers</persName>, the scientific expert of the Government survey, counted forty of
               these depressions near the boat landing, like the basements of a compact village. The
               mounds of sea shells of all existing species are immense.</p>
            <p>One of the most beautiful varieties of the <emph>haliotis</emph> (abalone) family is
               numerous on the mounds, but so far as known it is now extinct on <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the whole California coast</placeName>. These
               shell mounds are a matter of surprise to every beholder. It is doubtful if the world
               has an equal. They extend over the most of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the island</placeName></rs>, one being about six miles long, a mile in width
               and twenty-five feet deep.</p>
            <p>In some places beautifully polished pebbles are constructed into pyramids of unique
               art. In the mounds of shells are interspersed bones of fowls, fish, seals and whales.
               Manifestly these artificial hills are composed of the refuse separated from the food
               of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the extinct
                     race</orgName>
               </rs>. These silent remains bear unmistakable evidence of the numbers of people who
               here made their homes for probably thousands of years.</p>
            <p>Wherever one turns his eye, broken mortars, pestles, bone implements and ingenious
               ornaments are seen.</p>
            <p>What little has been published about <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName> has long been out of print, and is now inaccecssible to the
               reading public.</p>
            <p>There are shadowy traditions that <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName> was densely populated by <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an interesting
                     people</orgName></rs> when modern history began to draw upon their barbarian
               shores. The discovery was much later than that of the other islands in <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_chi">the Channel group</placeName>. Exactly where and under
               whom the first civilized visitors landed on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >this isolated spot</placeName></rs> we have no record to inform us. It is
               known that <rs><persName type="group" key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba">the
                     Russian fur-traders</persName></rs>, not long before the landing of the
               California gold-seekers, learned that <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName> was one of the most prolific resorts for the sea otter, and
               they took the earliest steps to bag the richest game. They accordingly shipped down a
               strong crew of experienced <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_kodiak">native Alaskan hunters</orgName></rs>, with all needed
               appliances and provisions, and the most improved rifles. <span type="trope" n="11"
                  >The ship sailed away and left <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_kodiak">the imported northern savages</orgName></rs> to do their
                  work until the end of the fur season. Tradition reports that the <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">Kadiaks</orgName> soon, by
                  force of arms, made themselves criminally free with the wives and daughters of
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                        natives</orgName></rs>. Of course the strongest elements in humanity rose in
                  resistance; but what could <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an unwarlike people</orgName></rs> do with no
                  weapons but stone fish spears and stone knives against a much smaller number with
                  rifles and steel daggers?</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="11">There were no civilized spectators to the horrible massacre
                  that followed. Later a report reached <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                     mainland</placeName> that the only survivors left were women and little girls;
                  every male bad been slaughtered. Recent explorers find corroborating evidence of
                  violence. Shallow graves where heaps of skeletons are found in disorder are not in
                  accord with the regulation mode of sepulture where the single body was placed face
                  downward with the feet drawn up beneath, and some personal belongings or ornaments
                  were deposited with the remains.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="11">One of an exploring party for <orgName type="museum"
                     key="#mu_smithsonian">the Smithsonian Institution</orgName> states that many of
                  the skulls of the exposed skeletons show a break in the temporal bone or in the
                  eye socket, as if the owners had been killed by some blunt instrument. The remains
                  confirm the report of a general violence.</span></p>
            <p>Strange to relate, the most reliable printed report of the massacre first appeared in
                  <title type="article" key="#TheBostonAtlas1847">a Boston paper</title>. At that
               early date the Yankees were partners with <orgName type="organization"
                  key="#rfurcompany">the Russians</orgName> in the fur trade on <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the California coast</placeName>. Here is
                     <rs><title type="article" key="#TheBostonAtlas1847">the Boston
                  item</title></rs>:</p>
            <p>A ship owned by <orgName key="#bp">Boardman and Pope</orgName> of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_bo">Boston</placeName>, commanded by <persName type="seaman"
                  key="#whi">Captain Whitemore</persName>, trading on <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs>, took from the port of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_si">Sitka</placeName>, <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_russam">Russian American</placeName></rs> [sic], about thirty <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">Kadiak Indians</orgName>, a part
               of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">the hardy
                     tribe</orgName></rs> inhabiting <placeName type="island" key="#i_ko">the Island
                  of Kadiak</placeName>, to <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands of the
                  Santa Barbara Channel</placeName>, for the purpose of killing sea otter, which
               were then very numerous. <persName type="seaman" key="#whi">Captain
                  Whitemore</persName>, after landing <rs><orgName type="nativemaericantribes"
                     key="#natam_kodiak">the Indians</orgName></rs> on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs> and placing in their hands firearms
               and other necssary implements of the chase, sailed away to <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_baja">the lower coast of California</placeName> and <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_southamerica">South America</placeName>. <span type="trope"
                  n="11">In the absence of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_ilmena">the
                     ship</name></rs> a dispute arose between <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_kodiak">the Kadiaks</orgName> and <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the natives of the
                        islands</orgName></rs>, originating in the seizure of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                        females</orgName></rs> by <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_kodiak">the former</orgName></rs>. <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">The Kadiaks</orgName>
                  possessing superior weapons, slaughtered <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the males</orgName></rs> without mercy, old and
                  young. On the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Island of San
                     Nicholas</placeName> not a male old or young was spared.</span> At the end of
               the year <persName type="seaman" key="#whi">Captain Whittemore</persName> returned to
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>, took
                  <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">the Kadiaks</orgName> on
               board and returned to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_si"
                  >Sitka</placeName>.&#8212;(<title type="monograph" key="#Mason1883">History of
                  Santa Barbara and Ventura Counties</title>, page 255.)</p>
            <p>Not long after <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">the
                     northern hunters</orgName></rs> left, tidings in some way reached <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> of the painful situation on
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>. Deep sympathy was
               awakened at <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions">the
                     missions</orgName>
               </rs> and elsewhere for <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the forlorn women and children</orgName></rs>. A
               purse was easily raised to charter a ship to bring <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     unfortunates</orgName></rs> to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName>, where they could receive aid and sympathy.</p>
            <p>It was in <date when="1835">1835</date> that <persName type="frontiersman" key="#iwi"
                  >Isaac Williams</persName>, once <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#iwi"
                     >Collector of the Port of San Pedro</persName></rs>, superintended a rescue
               party. The schooner <name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada"><emph>Peor es
                  Nada</emph></name>, <persName type="seaman" key="#chu">Captain Hubbard</persName>,
               was chartered. While <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                  schooner</name></rs> was anchored in the offing, <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                     >the crew</persName></rs> had little trouble or delay in "rounding up"
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup; #lw">the whole remainder of the
                     race</persName>
               </rs> at the landing. <span type="trope" n="9">As the last boatload was pushing out
                  through the surf, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one
                        woman</persName></rs>, noticing that something had been left, supposed to
                  have been <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">one of her
                        children</persName></rs>, leaped overboard and rushed up the bank in
                  pursuit.</span> The situation of the surf forbade any delay of the boat with
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup; #lw">its human
               cargo</persName></rs>. The officer intended, when be had put his passengers on board
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the schooner</name></rs>, to return
               with the empty boat for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                     straggler</persName></rs>, but on reaching <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs>, a rising gale admonished
                     <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#chu">the captain</persName></rs> that any
               delay would imperil <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs>
               and the lives of all on board; so he gave orders to weigh anchor and stand for
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName> under close reef. It was
               a terrible head wind, and <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                     vessel</name></rs> was buffeted for eight days before <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">the coast </placeName></rs> could be
               reached. <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#chu">The captain</persName></rs> intended,
               when the storm abated, to return for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                     >the one lost woman</persName></rs>. On reaching <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>, however, he found an order from <rs><persName
                     type="investor" key="#jgo">the owner of the ship</persName></rs> at <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName> to sail at once for that port. There
               was no alternative left for his private plans. At <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo"
                  >Monterey</placeName> a cargo of lumber was taken aboard for <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>. As she approached <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate">the Golden Gate</placeName> a tempest was
               raging, and attempting to cross the bar the <emph><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es Nada</name></emph> capsized, and all on board
               perished. The hulk was seen no more. <span type="trope" n="12">At that date this was
                  the only vessel on <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the California
                     coast</placeName> sufficiently large to make a safe voyage to <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="12">It must be remembered that about the only traffic on
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the California coast</placeName>
                  ess than seventy-five years ago was carried on by a few Eastern ships trading for
                  hides and tallow.</span></p>
            <p><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The woman</persName></rs> had nothing
               to fear from wild animals, for the largest was a native fox about the size of a small
               cat. There was no danger of starvation, for in addition to seals and fish, which she
               knew how to capture and manage, there was an inexhaustible stock of all kinds of
               mollusks only waiting to be picked up, and eggs by the millions deposited in the
               crannies of the rocks by pelicans, cormorants and pigeons.</p>
            <p>The land, too, afforded esculent roots and native fruits. The old dwellings were
               left, and on the beach was landed an unlimited store of driftwood for a renewed cabin
               and fuel. Acquired skill in finding the material and the manufacture of clothing
               supplied that demand. A few domestic dogs left behind were glad to aid in the chase.
               What an amount of freedom there is in having all the world to yourself alone! Nobody
               to steal or cheat, to fight or scold. How broad the feeling when there is no mortal
               in your world that can possibly touch you or anything that you possess or want.
               Hermitage may have compensations.</p>
            <p>The next report from <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the forlorn
                     island</placeName></rs> was in <date when="1850">1850</date>. This was
                     <rs><date when="1835">fifteen years after</date></rs> the <emph><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es Nada</name></emph> made her last
               voyage. Meantime <placeName type="country" key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</placeName> had
               ceded <placeName type="region" key="#re_local">California</placeName> to the
                  <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">United States</placeName>, and a
               semi-barbarism was fast giving place to an urbane civilization. Gold had been
               discovered and <placeName type="region" key="#re_sierranevada">the
                  Sierras</placeName> were swarming with miners. <rs><date when="1850">Just fifteen
                     years after</date></rs>
               <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone woman</persName></rs> had been
               left on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>, <persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName>, a worthy citizen of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, ventured to make a
               voyage in search of otter. He was connected with <orgName type="company"
                  key="#americanfurcompany">the American Fur Company</orgName>. As they were passing
               around <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> to find
               the best point for game, <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >Brown</persName></rs> of <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #nativeamericans">the crew</persName></rs> discovered in the
               wet sand the fresh tracks of a small human foot. He followed the trail from the beach
               until the tracks disappeared in the moss on the upland. He reported to the others,
               but the day was too far spent to continue the search. The next day the hunting trip
               was cut short by a rising gale. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The
                     captain</persName></rs> was compelled to scud away for home. <rs><date
                     when="1851">The next year</date></rs>
               <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> made a second
               voyage. While his men were moving around a different part of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> they came to some stakes
               of driftwood on which were hung strips of seal blubber to dry, out of the reach of
               wild dogs. Here was the work of human hands. Where to look for <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the invisible agent</persName></rs> no one
               could tell. Again the party was here to hunt otter, not for a woman. The weather
               signals were dubious, and the business required haste. A fair catch of otter in those
               days was more lucrative than an average gold mine. Every moment of daylight must be
               economized. A violent storm soon drove the hunters to shelter. When they related on
               shore what they had discovered, the older residents and the dwellers about the
               missions said: "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The lost
                     woman</persName></rs> must be still alive." A general interest was awakened in
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the involuntary
                  hermit</persName></rs>, and <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the Mission Fathers</persName></rs>
               offered a prize of $200.00 to any party that would bring her to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">It was in <date when="1853">1853</date> that <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> determined to take
                  another cruise to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>,
                  and engage in a woman hunt. The prize would pay to make one systematic sweep of
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. On
                  landing he led <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">his crew</persName></rs> to
                  one end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>,
                  where signs had before been seen, and marshalled them in line, as far apart as
                  possible and yet maintain communication. Their united vision covered the whole
                  breadth of territory. In time as they climbed the hill, <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> saw in the distant
                  brush a dark object that seemed to move. At first he thought it was a bird, but as
                  he noiselessly drew near, it assumed the appearance of the back of a human head.
                  It was <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> in
                  a low brush tent without a roof. She did not see <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                        key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs>, but her attention was fixed upon the other
                  men at a greater distance. He gave a signal by raising his hat up and down on the
                  ramrod of his gun. A few dogs near <rs><placeName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                        >the woman</placeName></rs> gave a warning growl, but at a fierce yell from
                  her they disappeared. She was busy peeling the blubber from a seal skin with an
                  iron hoop. Her mass of matted hair was of a yellowish brown color. Her dress was
                  of cormorant skins (shags) cut in squares, extending from the shoulders to the
                  ankles. There was no cover for head or feet. When all chance of escape was cut
                  off, <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> stealthily
                  moved around in front and let himself be seen. <span type="trope" n="1"
                           ><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The woman</persName></rs>
                     made no attempt to flee, but on the contrary she received him with a bow and
                     smile&#8212;with as much grace as he could have been welcomed in a civilized
                     parlor.</span> She greeted all her visitors in the same way. True etiquette is
                  not a mere formality in highly cultured circles, it is an innate instinct of
                  untutored humanity. As <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs> sat down around her she constantly talked, but not a word
                  was intelligible. A few <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">Indians</persName></rs> of the crew
                  spoke several dialects, but they understood not a word. She was the only one left
                  who could speak the language of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>, and she knew no other.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The
                        savage</persName></rs> was endowed with the grace of hospitality. In a few
                  minutes she took from a grass sack two varieties of roots, placing them in the
                  smoldering ashes. When cooked she placed them before her guests; she gave the best
                  and about all her larder contained. Taking a drinking dish, she went to a nearby
                  spring and brought some water.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1">When <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs> made signs for her to go with them to the landing and
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the schooner</name></rs>, at first
                  she failed to comprehend their meaning, but when they made signs for her to gather
                  up her possessions, she caught the idea and began to pack her baskets and sacks
                  with great dispatch.</span> The dried blubber, and all else that could be used for
               food, was gathered up, meager clothing, bone needles, sinew and ornaments were
               packed. The men relieved her from the most of the luggage; and last of all
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
               selected a glowing brand from the fire as an essential for warmth and cooking. It is
               much easier for Indians to transport fire than it is for them by any process they
               know to start it <emph>de novo</emph>.</p>
            <p>When all was in readiness, she led the way down her trail, coming soon to a pure
               spring of drinking water, where seal blubber was hanging to dry; further down the
               grade she led to a fountain for bathing, where she paused to wash her hands and face.
               On reaching the landing, they motioned for her to enter the boat, which she
               cheerfully did. Aboard <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the
                  schooner</name></rs> she sought a place near the cook stove. When food was
               offered, she ate with great relish victuals such as she had never tasted before.
               Indeed, from that time on she preferred the bacon and bread to blubber and shell
               fish. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> at once
               found a piece of bed-ticking and set about making a skirt. This with a sailor's shirt
               and a discarded vest made her quite comfortable.</p>
            <p>The weather signals indicated a prolonged season for hunting, so arrangements were
               made to camp on shore. Poles were leaned against a rock and an old sail spread over
               them for a tent. A short distance away a smaller shelter was arranged for
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>. <span
                  type="trope" n="3">She went about talking to herself and singing as if content and
                  happy. She aided in the work, bringing wood and water.</span> She then finished a
               water bucket which was unique. Into a nicely braided grass basket she placed some
               pieces of asphaltum, picked up on the beach; on these she placed hot stones, and when
               in a liquid state the asphaltum was carefully spread in a uniform thickness over the
               inside. When completed the basket was impervious to water as a tin pail and not much
               heavier. Small drinking dishes were made in the same way. In these vessels water
               could be bottled or food cooked by filling the basket with water and immersing a
               succession of hot rocks.</p>
            <p>Among the otters that were brought into camp for skinning was one on the eve of
               parturition. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The hunter</persName></rs>
               removed the fetus, and stuffed the beautiful skin. <span type="trope" n="3">By
                  gestures <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
                  solicited the care of the toy. Taking it into her tent, she suspended it to a
                  pole, and by the hour she would swing it back and forth, singing to it as to an
                  infant. <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">Eighteen
                        years</date></rs> of hermit life had not abolished the maternal
                  instinct.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="3">She pressed it to her bosom and rocked it to and
               fro,</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="3">In memory of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lwchild">the little one</persName></rs> she lost so long
               ago.</span></p>
            <p>This time <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> was
               allowed a month of successful hunting, then the signs of sky and sea admonished him
               that it was time to leave. On the voyage homeward-bound, however, a fearful gale met
               him. The force of the wind, the boiling and breaking of the sea, the rolling and
               pitching of the creaking vessel seemed fearful to one not accustomed to ocean life.
               The great anxiety of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                     woman</persName></rs> seemed to increase until she fell upon her knees on deck,
               raising her hands and open eyes to the heavens, as if invoking aid from an unseen
               power above. The dramatic scene was short. Soon the smiling face of the sun appeared
               from beneath the retreating clouds, the gale was abated and the seas assuaged. <span
                  type="trope" n="1"><span type="trope" n="10">Then <rs><persName
                           type="frontiersman" key="#gni">the woman</persName></rs> in pantomime
                     conveyed to <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName>
                     the view that it was her intercession with the unseen which mitigated the
                     tempest.</span></span></p>
            <p>When <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the crew</persName></rs>
               with <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the hermit</persName></rs> were
               landing, the first object of interest to attract her attention was a two-wheeled cart
               drawn by a yoke of oxen. She had never seen before any domestic animal except the
               small Indian dogs. She made apt gestures of her surprise at the yoke, the docile
               oxen, the revolving wheels, at the same time talking and laughing. Soon <rs><persName
                     key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh">a horseman</persName></rs> came riding
               down the beach. This seemed still more strange and ludicrous to her. <span
                  type="trope" n="3">Placing two fingers of her right hand astride of her left
                  thumb, she gesticulated the galloping rider with shouts of laughter. She was in a
                  new world, though less than a hundred miles from where she had spent her whole
                  life. Every view awakened surprise and hilarity.</span></p>
            <p><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> took
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the hermit</persName></rs> to
                     <rs><placeName key="#nideverhouse">his own home</placeName></rs> and placed her
               in care of his efficient wife. <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The Mission Fathers</persName></rs>, too,
               assumed an indirect supervision over the new arrival. Visitors from near and far came
               to see <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the human
                  curiosity</persName></rs>, and many donations were left for her comfort. <span
                  type="trope" n="3">She seemed willing to attire herself for exhibition in her suit
                  of birdskins with feather points downward. She had a keen relish for all the
                  varieties of the white man's food, and was extremely fond of fruit. From lack of
                  critical oversight she ate to excess and brought on a serious malady.</span> It
               was supposed that a return to her native diet would furnish a remedy, but she spurned
               clams, fish and seal blubbers. <span type="trope" n="6">In a few weeks the sickness
                  proved fatal, and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the last remnant
                        of a once numerous race</persName></rs> passed away without being able by
                  words to communicate anything about <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">her people</orgName></rs>. The tale of personal
                  sorrow and suffering for <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high"
                        >eighteen years</date></rs>, and the tradition of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the extinct
                        race</orgName></rs> must always remain a blank to the civilized
                  world.</span> At the end of the hermit's life she was given an appreciative burial
               by <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the
                     Fathers</persName></rs>. The two unique dresses, one worn by herself and a
               little one supposed to belong to <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">a
                     deceased child</persName></rs>, together with a basket of spear heads, abalone
               fishhooks, bone needles, sinew-thread and miscellaneous ornaments were packed up by
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the
                     Fathers</persName></rs> and sent to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom"
                  >Rome</placeName>. They were deposited in <rs><orgName type="museum"
                     key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">the cabinet of curiosities</orgName></rs> in <orgName
                  type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">the Vatican</orgName>, where, doubtless,
               visitors may still inspect them. A carefully prepared account of <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the hermit</persName></rs> went with her
               effects to <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">the Vatican</orgName>.</p>
            <p>And what can now be said about the modern <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName>? <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The
                     island</placeName></rs> is still there, but for half a century it has virtually
               been unpopulated. The otters were soon exterminated, so hunters had no motive to
               visit <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the storm-lashed
               isle</placeName></rs>. There are some twenty thousand acres of manifestly rich soil,
               but no homesteaders care to take it. Food and water are abundant. <rs><persName
                     key="#mkim">Some adventurer</persName></rs> has placed on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> a large flock of sheep.
               Periodically the sheep-shearers make a voyage to ply their vocation for a week or
               two, and at intervals a nomadic shepherd makes a tour to look after the lambs. The
               larger part of the year, however, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicholas</placeName> entertains no man. The bleating of the sheep, the cry of the
               lambs, the barking of the inoffensive foxes, the scream of sea fowls chime in with
               hoarse growl of sea lions. The roar of the billows among the cliffs and the muffled
               tones of the ever-beating surf. Nature's desolation reigns supreme.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
