<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#sherald">an Francisco Daily
                     Herald</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="4"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="165"/>
               <date when="1853-11-13"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#SanFranciscoDailyHerald1853">The Wild Woman of San
                     Nicolas</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="2"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                           >The Wild Woman of San Nicolas</persName></rs>.</hi></title></head>
            <p><title type="article" key="#Santiago1853">We have already noticed the fact</title> of
               the discovery of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an extraordinary
                     woman</persName></rs> who was found living alone on the island of <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> on the <placeName type="region"
                  key="re_socalcoast">southern coast of California</placeName>, about sixty miles
               from the country of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.
               Many interesting facts in connection with her history, have been brought to light and
               published, and we are again induced to allude to the subject by the exhibition which
               has been made us of her dress and the implements with which she was wont to occupy
               herself during her solitary banishment. According to the most authentic accounts and
               such as are believed to be reliable, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>, as well as <rs><placeName type="group"
                     key="#i_an; #i_scl; #i_sm; #i_sb; #i_scatalina; #i_scruz; #i_sr">the other
                     islands</placeName></rs>, was once inhabited by <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                     >Indians</orgName></rs>. Owing to a difficulty which occurred about the year
                  <date when="1824">1824</date> or <date when="1825">1825</date>, between
                     <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">some
                     Russians</persName></rs> who had visited <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                  natives</orgName></rs>, the male inhabitants were nearly all killed and the women
               carried away. <rs><date when="1835">About eighteen years ago</date></rs>, the
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">last of those who were
                     left</persName></rs>, some seventeen in number, were taken off, with their own
               consent, by <persName type="seaman" key="#chu">Mr. Hubbard</persName>, captain of
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a small schooner</name></rs> owned
               by <persName type="investor" key="#isp">Mr. Isaac Sparks</persName> of <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <persName key="#jgo">Mr.
                  Gomez</persName> of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName>.
               After <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the party</persName></rs> had gotten
               on board, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one of the
                  squaws</persName></rs> missed <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild"
                     >her child</persName></rs>, and was permitted to go in search of it; but in a
               short time returned lamenting its disappearance and declaring that it had been
               devoured by the wild dogs which infested <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>. In the midst of her lamentations she fell down and
               went to sleep on the beach, and a gale having sprung up, the <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the [sic] schooner</name></rs> was driven to sea and
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> left
               upon the shore. Three months after <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                     schooner</name></rs> touched at <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> in search of her, but no traces of her could be found,
               with the exception of her footprins in the sand. Nearly <rs><date from="1835"
                     to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> have since elapsed, during which time she
               has been left to her lonely fate, supposed to be dead and her history almost
               forgotten.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">In the early part of <rs><date when="1853-09">September of
                        the present year</date></rs>, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr.
                     Niedever</persName> of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>, whilst engaged in otter hunting along <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">the coast</placeName></rs>, touched at
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, and
                  suddenly came upon <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this
                        extraordinary woman</persName></rs>, who was engaged in curing bird-skins,
                  of which her garment was made, and who manifested no surprise or timidity at the
                  appearance of a white man. <span type="trope" n="3">Being of a gentle and
                     confiding disposition, she was readily induced to leave <rs><placeName
                           type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.</span> With her
                  she brought away the curious articles which were yesterday exhibited to us, and
                  which were unquestionably of her own manufacture, as she was at the time found
                  occupied upon them. The most remarkable of the collection is the robe in which she
                  was dressed. It is composed of fifty skins of sea-birds, sewn together with the
                  sinews of seals, of which all her thread is composed. This garment is fastened all
                  round, leaving openings merely for the head and arms, and hangs upon the person
                  like a loose sack, reaching nearly to the feet. The needles used for sewing the
                  garment are of fi[s]hbone, finely wrought and polished, and almost as sharp as
                  those manufactured of steel. She had a curious jug, made of platted grass, and
                  coated on the inside with a black substance resembling asphaltum. It is of a
                  globular form, about nine inches in diameter, with a narrow neck&#8212;the height
                  being about fourteen inches. It was evidently used as a water jug.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">Another ingenious implement is her knife, which seems to
                  have been manufactured out of a piece of hoop, sharpened and fastened in a rude
                  wooden handle, by means of asphaltum and cord of sinews. Among the collection are
                  two fishing hooks and lines&#8212;the former evidently manufactured out of nails,
                  skillfully beat and sharpened, and the latter of dried sinews. Accompanying these
                  are two pieces of cord, of different sizes, as neatly made of numerous strands of
                  sinew as though the work had been performed by machinery. These articles were
                  wrapped in the skin of one of the native animals of <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, from which we may infer that she
                  occupied her time both in fishing and hunting. <span type="trope" n="8">Taking her
                     whole history together she seems to have lead [sic] a life and resorted to
                     expedients strikingly like those attributed to the ideal <name type="fictional"
                        key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name>.</span> In this case the truth is as
                  strange as the fiction. The food upon which she subsisted, at the time she was
                  discovered, consisted of seal meat and roots. Her language was one peculiar to
                  herself, bearing but a slight resemblance to any other known tongue. Upon her
                  arrival in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, several
                  of the Indians in that vicinity, acquainted with the dialects of the different
                  tribes, were taken to her and attempted to open a conversation, but without avail.
                  Their language and hers bore no resemblance to each other whatever. She was
                  therefore unable to make any communications, except by signs. <span type="trope"
                     n="3">Her age appeared to be upwards of sixty, and her manners as simple as
                     those of a child. She was of medium stature, muscular in appearance, and well
                     formed. Her eyes were large, and full; auburn hair, smooth and profuse;
                     forehead low, broad, and intellectual; nose slightly aquiline and finely
                     formed; mouth large, with a haughty, protruding lower lip, a[nd] a well set
                     chin. Upon the whole, her appearance and mien were superior to those of the
                     other Indians in the lower part of <rs><placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                           >the State</placeName></rs>.</span></span></p>
            <p>In <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #sni; #ini; #gnijr; #jacobni; #mrni; #mrfni"
                     >the family of Mr. George Niedever</persName></rs>, she lived very contentedly,
               and apparently gratified with the change; she was evidently much pleased by the novel
               sights which were presented to her, in horses and other large animals. She ate freely
               of many things which were given to her, and seemed particularly fond of shell-fish,
               coffee, liquor, and fruits, but her system was unu[s]ed to such a diet, and after too
               free an indulgence she sickened and died on the <date when="1853-10-18">18th of
                  October</date>. <span type="trope" n="6">She was undoubtedly the last of
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">her
                        race</orgName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p>During the brief period she remained in <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #sni; #ini; #gnijr; #jacobni; #mrni; #mrfni">the family of Mr.
                     Niedever</persName></rs>, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this
                     extraordinary woman</persName></rs>, whose intelligence was most wonderful, had
               acquired a considerable facility in speaking Spanish, and had committed to memory the
               Lord's Prayer, and seemed to comprehend the idea of the omnipotent Being. Previous to
               her dissolution, she was baptized according to the rites of the <orgName
                  type="church" key="#ch_catholic">Catholic Church</orgName>, by <persName
                  type="missionfather" key="#sanchez">Father Sanchez</persName>, of the Franciscan
               Order, and yielded up her last breath with apparent resignation. Had her life been
               extended a few months longer, there is no doubt she would have been enabled to tell
               her own wonderful story, as well as the history of <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her lost child</persName></rs>; but as it
               is, all is now buried in oblivion. The curious articles which we have endeavored to
               describe, were forward[e]d to <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">this
                     city</placeName></rs> at the request of the ladies connected with the <orgName
                  type="church" key="#ch_catholic">Catholic Church</orgName>, and will be exhibited
               at the Fair which they design to open on <rs><date when="1853-11-15">Tuesday
                     next</date></rs>, at the <placeName key="#musicalhall">Musical Hall</placeName>
               on <placeName key="#bushst">Bush street</placeName>, for the purpose of aiding in the
               commendable work of raising funds for the erection of <placeName key="#stmarys">St.
                  Mary's Church.</placeName> They will probably be sold or raffled for during the
               continuance of the Fair, and if so, would prove a rich contribution to a State
               museum.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
