<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#elmira">Elmira (NY)
                            Telegram</orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume"/>
                    <biblScope unit="issue"/>
                    <date when="1913-03-02"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_elm">Elmira</placeName>, <placeName
                            type="state" key="#st_ny">New York</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="main" key="#TheTelegram1913">BEAUTIFUL SANTA BARBARA AN
                            OUT-OF-DOOR PARADISE</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page"/>
                        <author/>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">BEAUTIFUL <placeName type="city"
                                key="#ci_sb">SANTA BARBARA</placeName> AN OUT-OF-DOOR
                        PARADISE</hi></title></head>
                <div type="section">
                    <p>It Is the Riviera of the Great <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast"
                            >Pacific Coast</placeName>, and Was Named For <rs><persName key="#barb"
                                >a Girl</persName></rs> Killed By <rs><persName key="#dio">Her
                                Father</persName></rs>&#8212;<rs><persName key="#barb">Daughter of a
                                Roman General Who Perished a Christian
                            Martyr</persName></rs>&#8212;<placeName type="region" key="#re_upcal"
                            >California</placeName> Found in <date when="1542">1542</date>, and
                        Explored <rs><date when="1592">Just Fifty Years After</date></rs>
                        <persName type="seaman" key="#cco">Columbus</persName> Discovered <placeName
                            type="country" key="#co_usa">America</placeName>&#8212;<placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> Is the Place Where
                        Tired People Come to Soak Up Sunshine&#8212;It Is Rich, But
                        Democratic&#8212;A Single Grapevine Covers an Acre, Produces Ten Tons of
                        Grapes, Is Eight Feet in Circumference at the Base&#8212;Walnuts Yield $200
                        or More to the Acre.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section">Editor Telegram:</title></head>
                    <p>Please inform us how <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName> compares in size with <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_penn">Pennsylvania</placeName>?</p>
                    <p>Ans.&#8212;There cannot be a comparison. <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_cal">California</placeName> has 99,463,681 acres. To get a
                        comparative idea you can take the states of <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_me">Maine</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_vt"
                            >Vermont</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_nh">New
                            Hampshire</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_ma"
                            >Massachusetts</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_ct"
                            >Connecticut</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_ri">Rhode
                            Island</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_ny">New
                            York</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_penn"
                            >Pennsylvania</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_nj">New
                            Jersey</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_de"
                            >Delaware</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="#st_md"
                            >Maryland</placeName>, and spreading them all out together over
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> there would
                        be an uncovered margin of 13,774 square miles, or more than enough in excess
                        to make more than ten states like <placeName type="state" key="#st_ri">Rhode
                            Island</placeName>. <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName> is "some" state.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">NUMBER VII.</hi>
                        </title></head>
                    <p>There is more than one outdoor paradise in <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. In the list do not fail to include
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. The
                        climate has attracted invalids and persons in search of health and pleasure
                        since the earliest settlement of the <placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_paccoast">Pacific coast</placeName>. While <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_upcal">California</placeName> was still a part of
                            <placeName type="country" key="#co_mexico2">Mexico</placeName>, many
                        refined and aristocratic Spanish families made it their home and contributed
                        to the charm of social life. A few descendants of the early Spanish settlers
                        still reside there. They have become thoroughly Americanized, but may easily
                        be identified by their names, their features and complexions and the
                        graceful manners of their race.</p>
                    <p><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">The mission of Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> is the best preserved in <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, its monastery is the most
                        extensive, it is an educational institution of high standard, and its
                        influence is the widest of any in the state.</p>
                    <p>Many people consider <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> the most desirable place of residence for families
                        of wealth and leisure in the <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">United
                            States</placeName>, if not in the world. The climate and environment are
                        very much like those of the <placeName type="region" key="#re_rivera"
                            >Riviera of France</placeName>. It is the only place of resort in the
                            <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">United States</placeName> which
                        has a mountain range on one side of it, and an ocean on the other, and where
                        the climate permits the population to live in comfort the year around. It is
                        often called the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_newport"
                            >Newport</placeName> of the Pacific, but is more democratic and
                        cosmopolitan than the queen of the Atlanic resorts. No social tyranny is
                        recognized; the habits and customs of the people are not so artificial;
                        everybody lives as nearly as possible to nature: [sic] there is no rivalry
                        in dress or dinner parties, or other forms of display; all classes spend
                        most of their time out-of-doors, and the belle of <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> shows to the best advantage in a
                        Khaki suit, astride a mustang climbing a mountain trail, rather than at a
                        ball or garden party. The population is made up mostly of
                        "remitters"&#8212;that is in this instance people who have retired from
                        business, widows of large means, and others who are able to live luxuriously
                        upon the proceeds of investments elsewhere. Many people from <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> spent part of the
                        winters in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>,
                        owning or renting bungalows, which are of all sizes. There are colonies of
                        people from the big eastern cities of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_bo"
                            >Boston</placeName> and <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nyc">New
                            York</placeName>. The richest resident is a petroleum prince, who has
                        figured in the divorce courts.</p>
                    <p>Between <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                            mission</placeName></rs> and the sea runs the main street of the town, a
                        wide, well-paved thoroughfare, more than two miles long, which is lined on
                        both sides with business blocks, banks, mercantile establishments, and the
                        best bookstores and curio shops to be found on the <placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_paccoast">Pacific coast</placeName>. The high class of goods
                        they keep is an index to the wealth and culture of the community. There is a
                        line of trolley cars running from the beach to the mission and a wide and
                        beautiful boulevard follows the shore line for several miles. At the
                        northern end are bath houses, and a bathing pier near a plaza, where a band
                        plays every afternoon. There is sea bathing the year round, and one of the
                        finest bath houses in the land. There are several sanitariums and hot
                        medicinal springs at an elevation of 1,300 feet. One may spend an entire
                        winter in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and
                        follow a different drive or trail every day.</p>
                    <p>In fact, no city in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName> has so many beautiful drives and trails for
                        motors, carriages and saddle horses. The <placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_santaynezmts">Santa Ynez range of mountains</placeName> is
                        broken by innumerable canyons and gorges, and between them lie broad table
                        lands, which are occupied as ranches, olive groves and walnut orchards.
                        There is a drive or a trail through every canyon, and one of them known as
                            <placeName type="region" key="#re_cumbre">La Cumbre trail</placeName>,
                        twelve miles long, offers a continuous panorama of glorious scenery. It
                        crosses the mountains through a pass a little less than 4,000 feet above the
                        seas. Another trail reaches the summit of the range by a climb of twelve to
                        fourteen miles, and is equally attractive. The lowest pass is 2,224 feet,
                        but it is possible to climb nearly 8,000 either on horseback or by
                        motor.</p>
                    <p>In <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> there is no
                        rivalry in architecture or extravagance. The great competition is in
                        flowers, plants and vegetable gardens. Most of the residences are of the
                        villa type, simple and often severe. The ideal house is of shingles, stained
                        brown, with wide porches hidden by climbing roses and other vines and
                        furnished with hammocks and easy chairs. The fact that the temperature
                        rarely varies more than twelve to fifteen degrees from one year's end to
                        another, and is always moderatley warm, enables everybody to live in the
                        open air, and is, of course, a blessing to the infirm and weary, and has a
                        wholesome influence. People from the east go to <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> to be soaked in sunshine, and
                        play golf 365 days in the year. The villa population is quite exclusive and
                        has a society of its own. During the winter season the two great hotels, the
                            <placeName key="#potterhotel">Potter</placeName>, probably as large as
                        the largest on the coast, and one of the finest, and the <placeName
                            key="#arling">Arlington</placeName>, which has recently been erected
                        upon the site of an old house of the same name, are filled with eastern
                        people. During the summer middle west and western people take advantage at
                        the hotels of the lower rates. The <placeName key="#potterhotel">Potter
                            hotel</placeName> is very close to the ocean, where the sea bathers
                        revel, and the great lawn on that side is in fact a perfect ocean of
                        flowers.</p>
                    <p>The <placeName key="#arling">Arlington hotel</placeName> is also attractive.
                        It belongs to <persName key="#ripley">E. P. Ripley</persName>, president of
                        the <orgName type="company" key="#sfrail">Santa Fe railroad</orgName>, and
                        he is the man who controlled the contracting company which built the
                        Lackawanna railroad from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_bing"
                            >Binghamton</placeName> to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_buffalo"
                            >Buffalo</placeName> about <date when="1880">1880</date>. One of his
                        subcontractors was the late <persName key="#jbmc">John B.
                            McDonald</persName>, who made fame and wealth as the builder of the
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nyc">New York city</placeName> subway.
                            <persName key="#ripley">Mr. Ripley</persName> in <date when="1880"
                            >1880</date>, was in a way, Mr. McDonald's financial backer. The writer
                        saw <persName key="#ripley">Mr. Ripley</persName> recently in <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and he looks almost
                        as strong as he did <rs><date notAfter="1883">over thirty years
                            ago</date></rs>. <rs><placeName key="#arling">His hotel</placeName></rs>
                        is built of concrete and steel and is after the mission style of
                        architecture, has 300 rooms and cost nearly a half million dollars. The
                        mission idea is carried out in every room and corridor, the woodwork being
                        left in the rough and stained a dark brown by the use of petroleum. There
                        are no ceilings. The heavy rafters are left uncovered; the walls are rough
                        plaster, painted to match the woodwork; the floors are red tiles and even
                        the bath tubs are of mission design.</p>
                    <p>The mission style of architecture with its strong but simples [sic] lines,
                        [with its ...] Moors and introduced into <placeName type="country"
                            key="#co_mex">Mexico</placeName>, was used by the <orgName
                            type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">Franciscan missionaries</orgName>
                        because they found it the best suited to the climate. That was the reason it
                        was adopted in the south of <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain"
                            >Spain</placeName>. The brick and tile did not reflect, but absorbed the
                        glare of the sun. The cloisters are cool at noonday and the thick walls are
                        proof agianst the dampness of the rainy season. It is being used more and
                        more for public buildings, school houses, hotels, and nearly all the new
                        schools and public edifices are being built after the mision design. The
                        government architects planned the conventional granite for the federal
                        post-office at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rside">Riverside,
                            Cal.</placeName>, but to the end that a harmonious architectrure should
                        prevail in the city, <persName key="#taft">President Taft</persName>
                        directed that the Riverside post-office should conform to the mission
                        style.</p>
                    <p>All about <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barabara</placeName> is
                        attractive. The entire amphitheater inclosed by the <placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_santaynezmts">Santa Ynez mountains</placeName> on the one side
                        and the <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">Pacific ocean</placeName>
                        on the other, is entirely taken up by rich ranchmen, who own large estates
                        and keep most of their lands in natural parks. They visit in automobiles and
                        on horseback; they wear sombreros and comfortable clothing; they take pride
                        in their crops and orchards and brag about their walnuts and their olives.
                        This is the walnut country par excellence, and it is the best paying crop.
                        The trees require ten years to mature, but give no further trouble. It is
                        only necessary to keep down the weeds and loosen the surface of the soil
                        with plow and harrow. Walnut trees are not subject to diseases like fruit
                        trees. The nuts require no refrigeration, cannot spoil on the hands of the
                        grower, and sell for not less than twelve cents a pound on the cars. The
                        average profit to the grower is $200 an acre. Walnut orchards are mostly
                        limited in area. The largest in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName> has only 350 acres, and most of them are of less
                        than twenty acres. But the business is extending rapidly.</p>
                    <p>The walnut acreage will soon be increased when the entire <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_golita">Golita valley</placeName> is irrigated.
                        Irrigation will enable the farmers to extend the walnut and lemon groves and
                        grow more beans, for these three are great staples. <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> has been boring a hold through
                        the <placeName type="region" key="#re_santaynezmts">Santa Ynez range of
                            mountains</placeName> for a large and permanent water supply. The tunnel
                        is seven by nine feet in size and 7,000 feet through the mountain. Aqueducts
                        were designed for both sides and the aqueducts' supply of water for
                        drinking, irrigation, etc., will be enough for a population of 250,000
                        people. No one dreams that <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> will ever have such a population. The new scheme is
                        to irrigate the <placeName type="region" key="#re_golita">Golita
                            valley</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>Writing of lemons, it is worth mention that <persName type="group"
                            key="#crocker">the Crocker family</persName> have an enormous lemon
                        ranch in the <placeName type="region" key="#re_montvalley">Montecito
                            valley</placeName>, just over a ridge from <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, with a large stone packing house
                        and all the appurtenances and ship their crops by the train load. It is the
                        most extensive and complete lemon ranch in <placeName type="country"
                            key="#co_usa">America</placeName>, with 2,000 acres of trees. The crops
                        are truly wonderful. In this temperature, and in a soil of surpassing
                        richness, everything grows. All the plants known to the temperature and
                        semi-temperate regions live happily together. The palm and the pine, the
                        apple and the oleander[,] the maple and the magnolia grow side by side with
                        equal vigor. Roses bloom and strawberry beds give ripened fruit every month.
                        The cultivation of vegetables and small fruits for the local market, is the
                        most profitable kind of farming, however, as hotels and boarding houses
                        consume large quantities of both. The cultivation of flowers and plants is
                        also a profitable business. On the main street of <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> is a concern which imports
                        shrubs, vines, plants and trees from everywhere and acclimates them for
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. You can
                        see nearly a half hundred kinds of palms, camphor and cinnamon trees,
                        papyrus, bamboos of all sorts and sizes, hibiscus, agavas, bread-fruit, and
                        other strange plants that you read about in Robinson Crusoe, the Swiss
                        Family Robinson and other tales of the <placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_southsea">South Sea</placeName> islands.</p>
                    <p>Out in <placeName type="region" key="#re_montpark">Montecito park</placeName>
                        an oil and steel magnate named <persName key="#gillespie"
                            >Gillespie</persName> has a great show place. It took eight years to
                        construct the palace and surroundings at a cost of more than $3,000,000. It
                        is first of all a palm park. But it is more. The home is copied after some
                        Roman villa, and the grounds likewise. This palace and palm park is open to
                        visitors at certain hours each day when <persName key="#gillespie">Mr.
                            Gillespie</persName> is away. The house has a great plunge like to the
                        Roman baths. The water runs into high reservoirs, which as they are located
                        along the descending hillside in front are tapped by pipes from which the
                        palms are watered. <persName key="#gillespie">Mr. Gillespie</persName> has
                        been traveling the world over for many years looking for new varieties of
                        palms[.] He now has about eighty distinct varieties and has sold single
                        plants for as much as $500. A Buffalo man, the head of the <orgName
                            type="company" key="#paac">Pierce-Arrow Automobile company</orgName>,
                        occupies the palace this winter.</p>
                    <p>Some of the finest grapes in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName> are grown about <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> the vines having been imported
                        from <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName> in the
                        early days by the <orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">Franciscan
                            fathers</orgName> who taught the natives how to make wine as well as
                        olive oil. The largest grape vine in the world, it is said, grows in
                            <placeName type="region" key="#re_carpvalley">Carpinteria
                            valley</placeName>, a few miles from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                            >Santa Barbara</placeName>. It was planted in <date when="1843"
                            >1843</date> by a Spanish farmer and has yielded ten tons of grapes in a
                        single season. It spreads over an acre of ground and is supported by
                        seventy-eight posts. If it were not pruned so closely every season it would
                        cover a much larger area. Six inches from the ground the trunk measures
                        eight and one-half feet in circumference, and where it reaches the trellis
                        and begins to spread, about six and one-half feet from the ground, the girth
                        is five feet seven inches. There are several other very large vines int he
                        same neighborhood. One of the largest ever known was cut down and sent to
                        the Philadelphia centennial exposition in <date when="1876">1876</date>, as
                        a sample of California products and was a great advertisment for
                                <rs><placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">the
                        state</placeName></rs>.</p>
                    <p>It will be of interest to all who love the words and music of the song "The
                        Rosary," to know the words were written in <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> by <persName key="#camrogers"
                            >Cameron Rogers</persName>. He is an artist; he lives there and from his
                        studio window there is a most entrancing view. It was set to music by
                            <persName key="#enevin">Ethelbert Nevin</persName>. Nearby to the scenes
                        of beauty in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>
                        one can find the greasy conditions of a rich oil country. Crude petroleum
                        gushes up from the earth and sea at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_summer"
                            >Summerland</placeName>, a town near <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                            >Santa Barbara</placeName>. It is occupied by a colony of Spiritualists.
                        It looks like one of the old fashioned oil towns of <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_penn">Pennsylvania</placeName>. The first petroleum was
                        discovered on the hillside, and the veins were followed down to the ocean,
                        where what the Californians call "submarine wells" have been bo[r]ed and
                        piped and are now flowing regularly. The oil comes up first through the
                        sand, and then piped through the water and thence to the reservoirs on
                        shore. The people of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_summer"
                            >Summerland</placeName> were the first to discover the adaptability of
                        crude petroleum for making roads. It was an accident. The first man to use
                        the crude petroleum on a road was so lazy that he shoveled the refuse from
                        an oil tank into the street to get rid of it, when he should have carted it
                        off to some dumping ground. The oil immediately absorbed the dust, and the
                        heavy metal wheels which passed over it packed it down into a hard, smooth
                        surface like asphaltum which shed the rains and was never muddy or dusty.
                        His neighbors then put oil on the roadways in front of their houses to keep
                        down the dust, and the practice finally became general and is now used
                        effectively in every part of the country[.]</p>
                    <p>The history of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>
                        is very romantic, but <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">the
                                town</placeName></rs> acquired its name from a tragedy, due to a
                        father's killing of his daughter, and after her it was named. <rs><persName
                                key="#barb">Santa Barbara</persName></rs> was one of the early
                        martyrs. She was born in <placeName type="region" key="#re_asiaminor">Asia
                            Minor</placeName>, and was the daughter of <rs><persName key="#dio">a
                                Roman general</persName></rs>. She was converted to Christianity
                        when she was sixteen years old, in the year A. D. <date when="0223"
                            >233</date>, during the reign of <persName key="severus">Alexander
                            Severus</persName>, an emperor frindly to the Christians. His successor,
                            <persName key="#maximinus">Maximinus</persName>, was a thorough pagan
                        and ordered all Christian converts put to death. The father of <persName
                            key="#barb">Barbara</persName> was <persName key="#dio"
                            >Deoscorus</persName>, and he concealed her, hoping to persuade her to
                        recant. When he was unable to do so he inflicted upon her cruel torments,
                        which she bore with wonderful fortitude for a girl of seventeen, and he
                        finally slew her with his own hand. Her piety, her steadfastness for the
                        faith, and her example had great influence with the young Christians and
                        caused her to be canonized by both the Greek and Roman Catholic churches.
                        She suffered martyrdom at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_nico">Nicomedia,
                            Asia Minor</placeName> about <date when="0235">235 A. D.</date> It was
                        not by a monk that <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> was named but by <rs><persName type="seaman"
                                key="#jca">a Portuguese explorer</persName></rs>, as will later
                        apear.</p>
                    <p>Off the coast of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> is <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">an
                                archipelago of mountainous islands</placeName></rs>, the largest
                        being called <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>,
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName> and
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>. When the
                        Spaniards first discovered the country they were all inhabited, but after
                                <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                            mission</placeName></rs> was established <rs><orgName type="group"
                                key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash"
                                >the island families</orgName></rs> were persuaded by the
                                <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats"
                                >friars</persName></rs> to move over to <placeName type="region"
                            key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> and settle near by. <persName
                            type="seaman" key="#jca">Juan Rodnguez [Rodríguez] Cabrillo</persName>,
                        the discoverer of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName>, is buried upon the island of <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, although no trace of
                        his grave remains. He was the first European who is known to have explored
                        the <placeName type="region" key="#re_paccoast">Pacific coast</placeName> of
                        what is now the <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">United
                            States</placeName>. He was a navigator of enterprise, courage and tact,
                        and although a Portuguese by birth, spent most of his life in the service of
                            <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName> like
                            <persName type="seaman" key="#cco">Columbus</persName> and <persName
                            type="seaman" key="#vespucci">Americus Vespucci</persName>, who were
                        Italians.</p>
                    <p>About the middle of <date when="1542-10">October 1542</date>, just fifty
                        years after <persName type="seaman" key="#cco">Columbus</persName>
                        discovered America, <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>
                        landed on the beach of what is now <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName>, and was met by natives in their canoes, who
                        received him with demonstrations of curiosity and kindness, and exchanged
                        presents with him. He remained some time, exploring the surrounding country,
                        which in his reports to <rs><persName key="#riv">the viceroy</persName></rs>
                        of <placeName type="country" key="#co_mex">Mexico</placeName> was described
                        as of great attractiveness and fertility. He crossed to the islands of
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> and <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> and made the latter his
                        headquarters, while he continued his explorations northward to a point many
                        leagues north of the <placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">bay of San
                            Francisco</placeName>, although he never found the <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate">Golden Gate</placeName>. It is
                        difficult to determine how far north he went, but we know from his
                        narratives that he was driven back by bad weather and returned to <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> to recover from a
                        fracture of his right arm, but he grew worse instead of better and on <date
                            when="1543-01-08">January 8, 1543</date>, he died and was buried on
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">that
                            island</placeName></rs>.</p>
                    <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> was given its
                        name by <persName type="seaman" key="#svi">Sebastian Viscaino</persName>,
                        another Portuguese epxlorer, who set sail from <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_aca">Acapulco</placeName> with three large caravels and a
                        transport, carrying 200 soldiers and three Carmelite friars. <persName
                            type="missionfather" key="#asc">Antonio de la Ascension</persName>, one
                        of the friars, took copious notes of all they saw and heard along
                                <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the
                                coast</placeName></rs>, made a map of considerable detail and as
                        directed by the explorer named each bay, cape, island and other conspicuous
                        landmark after the particular saint whose festival occurred nearest to the
                        day of discovery. On <date when="1602-12-04">December 4, 1602</date>, the
                        party landed at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName>, and that being the anniversary of <persName
                            key="#barb">Santa Barbara</persName>, her name was given to the bay and
                        the country that surrounds it.</p>
                    <p>Although <persName type="seaman" key="#svi">Viscaino</persName> was not the
                        first discoverer of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >California</placeName>, his voyage was the most important because of
                        the maps of <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the
                                coast</placeName></rs> and the authentic information which <persName
                            type="missionfather" key="#asc">Padre Antonio</persName> and the other
                        friars were able to furnish <placeName type="region" key="#re_europe"
                            >Europe</placeName> in regard to that part of the world. The island of
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> recieved
                        its name from the fact that one of the early explorers lost there a crucifix
                        of great sanctity, which was found by the natives and restored as the vessel
                        was about to sail. <span type="trope" n="4">A romantic narrative relates how
                            in <date when="1851">18[5]1</date>
                            <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">George Nidever</persName>, a
                            ranchero, of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                                Barbara</placeName>, found human footprints upon the sandy beach of
                            the island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">St.
                                Nichalas</placeName>, close to <placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, which was supposed to be
                            uninhabited. He was reminded of a story that had been widely circulated
                            about <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an Indian
                                    woman</persName></rs> who had been abandoned there and made a
                            thorough search. On the first day he wa unsuccessful; on the second day
                            he found evidences of human existence, including a basket rudely made of
                            reeds; on the [third] day he found three small huts [made] of the ribs
                            of a whale and cove[red] with brush. In one of these huts [was]
                                    <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an Indian
                                    woman</persName></rs>, with long hair fa[ll]ing over her bare
                            shoulders, and we[ar]ing a single garmet made of [the] skins of
                            birds.</span> She showed no ala[rm] but when <persName
                            type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName>, and his
                        co[m]panions, approached she offered th[em] roots and a piece of blubber to
                        [eat.] <span type="trope" n="14">She had entirely lost the faculty [of]
                            speech.</span> When <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr.
                            Nidever</persName> told [her] that she was to accompany him to
                            <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">[the] mainland</placeName>[,] she
                        understood read[ily,] showed much pleasure and gather[ed] together her
                        little belongings, wh[ich] consisted of baskets woven of gra[ss,] jars
                        filled with pebbles and other [little] mementoes. Upon reaching <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Sa[nta] Barbara</placeName>
                        <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName> took her to
                        [his] home, where she was kindly cared [for] until her death three or four
                        ye[ars] later. Although she was never able [to] express herself so as to be
                        under[stood,] she had not forgotten the art of ho[use]keeping, and performed
                        the duties [of] a servant as long as her health p[er]mitted.</p>
                    <p>Investigation developed the [...] that in the year <date when="1835"
                            >1835</date>
                        <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the
                            padres</persName></rs> [sent] <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada"
                                >a schooner</name></rs> to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                                >the islands</placeName></rs> to collect [all] the Indians that
                        remained there [and] take them over to the missions. Wh[en] they were ready
                        to depart <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one of [the]
                                women</persName></rs> could not find <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>,
                        [and] ran from the boat into the woods [...] search for her. Before her
                        return [a] violent storm arose, and as there [was] no harbor and the
                        anchorage was [...] secure, it became necessary to [...] out into the open
                        sea[.] <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">The
                            cap[tain]</persName></rs> intended to return for <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, [...] for
                        several days the ship was dr[iven] southward by the violence of the [gale]
                        and finally landed its passengers [...] <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp"
                            >San Pedro</placeName>, now the port of <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_la">[Los] Angeles</placeName>. A few days later <rs><persName
                                type="group" key="#chu; #isp">the [cap]tain</persName></rs> started
                        northward with a [...] of lumber for <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mo"
                            >Monterey</placeName>, intending [to] stop at <rs><placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and take on
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">[the]
                            woman</persName></rs>, but another gale capsized <rs><name type="ship"
                                key="#sh_peoresnada">[the] schooner</name></rs> and all hands were
                        lo[st. <span type="trope" n="8">So] <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> was forgotten and re[main]ed
                            for sixteen years alone, like <name type="fictional" key="#rcr"
                                >Ro[bin]son Crusoe</name>.</span> It was believed that <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">[the] child</persName></rs>
                        died shortly after the deser[tion,] from exposure to the weather.</p>
                    <p>Until the discovery of gold in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >[Cal]ifornia</placeName>, and the rapid development [of] <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sac">Sacramento</placeName> and o[ther] places
                        farther north <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Bar[bara]</placeName> was second only in importance [to] <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_mo">Monterey</placeName>, on <rs><placeName
                                type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs>. The
                        terr[...] occupied by <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the
                                missionaries</orgName></rs> [was] divided into four districts, in
                        each [...] which was a presido, or military [p]rison, and the officers
                        exercised [...] civil and military jurisdiction. <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_mo">[Mon]terey</placeName> was the official seat of the
                        [gov]ernor, and the commandant at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                            >S[anta] Barbara</placeName> was second in author[ity.] Thus it happend
                        that after the d[eath] of <persName key="#arrell">Governor
                            Arrellago</persName>, in <date when="1825">182[5</date>, ...] <persName
                            key="#argu">Captain Arguello</persName>, commandant [of] <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, exercised authority
                        [un]til a new governor arrived. After [the] Mexican war <persName
                            key="#argu">Arguello</persName> remained [at] <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and became one of [the] most
                        influential men of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                            >Cal[ifornia</placeName>,] where he resided for thirty-four y[ears.]
                        Another important commander [...] <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> was <persName key="#rompsr">Lieutenant [Rom]mualdo
                            Pacheco</persName>, and of a promin[ent] family. He left a son,
                            <persName key="#rompjr">Romualdo</persName>, [who] became governor of
                        the state, and [a] member of the house of repre[senta]tives. His family
                        still reside in [the] neighborhood.</p>
                    <p>At the time of the arrival of <persName type="frontiersman" key="#jcfre"
                            >Ca[ptain] John C. Fremont</persName> and his little [...] in <date
                            when="1846">1846</date>, <persName key="#rcar">Lieutenant Raimundo
                            Ca[...]</persName> was commander at <placeName key="#presidio">the
                            presidio</placeName>, [and] <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                            misssion</placeName> and the property [which] surrounded it were held by
                            <persName key="#nicden">Nichola[s ...] Den</persName> and <persName
                            type="seaman" key="#danhill">Daniel Hill</persName>, two Ameri[cans]
                        under a lease from the <orgName type="government" key="#gov_mexico">Mexican
                            [... gov]ernment</orgName> for a yearly rental of $1,[...] The lease
                        covered all the lands [...] buildings of the missionary except [the] church
                        and the monastery. Some li[...] head of cattle, 1,700 head of sheep [...]
                        many horses were also included. [The] bishop of the <placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_cal">California</placeName> diocese [en]deavored in vain to
                        resist the a[...] of the government, and his death [was] hastened by his
                        failure. He died [in] <date when="1846">1846</date> and is buried in
                                <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                            Mi[ssion]</placeName></rs> church.</p>
                    <p><persName type="seaman" key="#danhill">Daniel Hill</persName>, the lessee,
                        was a [Cape] Cod sea captain who first visited <rs><placeName type="region"
                                key="#re_calcoast">[the] coast</placeName></rs> in command of a
                        trading ve[ssel] in <date when="1882">1822</date>, en route to the
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_hawaii">Haw[aiian] Islands</placeName>,
                        and was so much taken [with] the climate and surroundings of <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">S[anta] Barbara</placeName>, that he brought
                        his [wife] and family and settled there in 1[...] starting a trading store,
                        bought [...] and cattle and became the richest [man] in the community.
                        Nicholas A. [...] an Irish physician, married H[ill's] daughter. He arrived
                        in <date when="1836">1836</date> and [prac]ticed medicine while he raised
                        ca[ttle.] Before his death he, too, had be[come] very rich and was the owner
                        of [...] large ranches as well as 10,000 ca[ttle.]</p>
                    <p>Several of the residences of [the] Spanish and Mexican colonial p[...] are
                        still standing, although they [have] been considerably altered on mo[...]
                        lines. The best description of life [in] <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                            >Santa Barbara</placeName> at that period may [be] found in Dana's "Two
                        Years Be[fore] the Mast," which in the days of [...] youth was a universally
                        popular [...]</p>
                    <p>(To Be Continued.)</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
