<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#harpers">Harper's New
                     Monthly Magazine</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">97</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">582</biblScope>
               <date when="1898-11-01"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_ithaca">Ithacay</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ny">New York</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Bennett1898">Our Seaboard Islands of the
                     Pacific</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="852" to="862"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#jbe">Bennett, John E.</persName></author>
                  <note type="supplied">Sara can put document note here</note>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">OUR SEABOARD
                        ISLANDS</placeName></rs> ON <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">THE
                     PACIFIC</placeName>.</title></head>
            <byline>BY <persName type="author" key="#jbe">JOHN E. BENNETT</persName>.</byline>
            <p>THERE are upon the southwest extremity of <placeName type="country" key="#co_usa">the
                  United States</placeName>, and distributed along <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> for three hundred miles, from the
               latitude of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName> to that of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName>, <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">certain islands</placeName></rs>, nine in number and
               of various areas, about which neither geography nor history has much to say. These
               are the only seaboard islands on <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the
                  Pacific</placeName> belonging to <orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">the
                  United States</orgName>, if we do not consider those of <placeName type="state"
                  key="#st_ak">Alaska</placeName>, and those numerous tiny aits or eyots in the
               waters of <placeName type="region" key="#re_sound">the Sound country</placeName>, nor
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_hawaii">the Hawaiian group</placeName>. There are
               from <placeName type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate">the Golden Gate</placeName> to
               the <placeName type="region" key="#re_britline">British line</placeName> a few rock
               reefs or single cones sitting like black stacks here and there in the sea, and at
               greater or less distances from the bluffy shores; but these have no claim to be
               spoken of as islands; that dignity belongs alone to those insular elevations in the
               ocean lying south of the thirty-eighth parallel, and ending, for us, at the
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mexicanborder">Mexican boundary</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Nature, however, taking no note of political division-lines, has not stopped at this
               point the southern trend of her island deposition, but she has carried them on across
               the line, along the mountainous coast of <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja"
                  >Lower California</placeName>, where they are found under the names of San Marten,
               San Geronimo, Cerros, Los Lobos, and so on, to the equator.</p>
            <p>None of these are large, and the entire aggregate area of the nine belonging to us
               does not exceed three hundred and fifty-one square miles, or less than two hundred
               and twenty-five thousand acres. Separately they grade in size from one hundred and
               seventy-six square miles, which is the area of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, to less than two square miles,
               which is that of both <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>
               and the largest of <placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the Farallones</placeName>.
               The others, measured in square miles, are <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz"
                  >Santa Cruz</placeName>, 115; <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa
                  Rosa</placeName>, 112; <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
               Miguel</placeName>, 183; <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                  Clemente</placeName>, 72; <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>, 36; and <placeName type="island" key="#i_an"
                  >Anacapa</placeName>, 12. They lie in the arid region, at an average distance of
               thirty miles from <rs><placeName type="city" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName></rs>, and they are uniform in their aspect of desolation. For
               the most part their surfaces present the characteristics of table-lands; some are
               rounded hummocks; but <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName> is formed of two mountains, which pinch into sharp peaks
               three thousand feet high, and spread below them a jumble of ridges and ravines, the
               broken surface occasionally interrupted by small plateaus.</p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#I_far">The Farallones group</placeName> is a granitic
               dike, but the others are mostly lava. It is a heavy black basalt that lies massed in
               its hardened meltings, and shows a surface often of smooth rounded lumps or
               semi-spheroids, revealing the contracting effects of the extrusion of heat.</p>
            <p>Sometimes along with the basalt there is country rock such as is found on
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName></rs>. This
               rock has, by the action of the weather, become degraded, and often at the mouth of a
               canyon on the lee side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the
                     island</placeName></rs> there is spread a pleasant level of land. It has been
               formed by the detritus borne down from the higher areas by the canyon's stream. This
               has been deposited here, and it has built up the ocean floor beside the roots of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the island</placeName></rs>. As it
               arose, the sea was pushed back, until a little flat was made, and it stands there now
               covered with its scrub oak, its juniper, or its wild gray grass, and meets the water
               with a crescent shore, upon which the little wavelets softly lap as they rock in from
               the stilly bay.</p>
            <p>But upon the opposite side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, where the southwest winds, sweeping over the broad
               field of the Pacific, throw the blue waters against the black gaunt rocks, the wild
               elements war and play havoc. The white-frothed breakers roll and boom and burst, and
               the feathery spray is flung high against the scowling cliffs, until their face is
               varnished with a bath of spume.</p>
            <p>And all along the cliffy coasts of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">those
                     sea-girt islands</placeName></rs> there have been hewn by the waves' resistless
               action great caverns, with high arches above the entrances, and burrowed deeply by
               successive chambers into the bowels of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs>. <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                  Cruz</placeName> abounds with these wonders of marine erosion, the largest of
               which is <placeName type="region" key="#re_paintedcave">Painted Cave</placeName>. It
               is a succession of arches, the outermost the highest, the others grading down as
               depth in penetration is attained. Branching from either side of this range of
               compartments are other openings, so that a labyrinth of recesses appears. For fifteen
               hundred feet into the interior of the <placeName type="region" key="#re_paintedcave"
                  >Painted Cave</placeName> the light will enter, and there can be seen upon the
               walls and ceilings the infinite brilliant frescoes, red, green, yellow, and their
               blends, deposited by the oozing mineral waters from above.</p>
            <p>On the lee side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                  islands</placeName></rs> these grottos are floored with the stillest, softest,
               serenest waters. The sea about the sheltered coasts is intensely blue and, when under
               the shade of a bluff or beneath the roof of a cave, where the calms allay the waters
               into glassy sheets, your boat will appear to be sitting upon the top of a neither
               world, which spreads its innumerable population of fish and other life. Far down
               gardens of maidenhair, algæ, and sea-ferns are seen, curved or laced by paths of
               white sand, against which goldfish, the mackerel, sheep's-head and the yellowtail
               show their floating bodies in repose, or moving slowly with rhythmic motion of gills
               and tail. And over all that scene there is an atmosphere pellucid, balmy, soft as the
               cloudless azure which overhangs it, and the sea is a shimmering breast of sunshine.
               The breeze brushes your cheek like silken velvet, fans you into dreamy moods, or
               suffuses you with gentlest slumbers.</p>
            <p>But on the weather side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs> the water is rough, and this agitation of the surface
               impairs your vision into the abyss below: a tapestry of froth edges the line of
               shore, and the surging, ebullient billows drive in from the sea, plunge into the
               caves, explode, roar, and fill them with their fury.</p>
            <p>But the results of the erosion of the sea at the base of these island rocks are not
               more curious than those of the rain and sun upon the cliffy faces of the lava.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">The patient artists of nature have worked upon a surface
                  scarified into strange devices by the contraction of the heated mass, and the wild
                  scheme of embellishment has been accentuated and elaborated in remarkable details.
                  What primarily were depressed lines have become deep gashes; smooth rounded bulges
                  have been worn into jagged protuberances, sharp points, and keen hatchetlike
                  blades of enormous size.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">Much of this fantastic sculpturing strikingly resembles the
                  effects of architecture. The castellated style predominates, and you are impressed
                  with the profusion of spires, turrets, and towers, and parapets edging the outline
                  of the tops with merlons and crenelles. And then there are Byzantium domes and
                  Grecian columns, the entire filigreed with the tracery of the
               arabesque.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">And not alone have wave erosion and that of water from the
                  clouds in their processes of island degradation wrought marvels in nature-carving,
                  but the wearing action of the wind has been scarcely less effective. On <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, more perhaps than upon any
                  other of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>,
                  is this phenomenon observable. Upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                        island</placeName></rs> there is a singular subsidence, forming a canyon
                  some hundreds of feet deep and half a mile across. It contains many little peaks
                  of cerulean slate draped with vari-colored foliage and sitting upon a ground of
                  white sand which has been blown thither by the winds. These winds at some seasons
                  strike strongly over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        islands</placeName></rs>, and effects of their exertions are everywhere
                  presented. Now such is seen in a broad pebbly surface swept clean, the mosaics
                  smoothly polished; again the feathery tiles have rasped the hard dark rocks,
                  gouged them with the emaciated hollows, ofttimes threatening the very security of
                  their posture. The sharp fine particles give teeth to the blasts, and these gnaw
                  at the structure of whatever interposes.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">At <placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the
                     Farallones</placeName> the erosive agents have worked with queer caprice. This
                  rock being granite, has been acted upon by the sea at all levels, and throughout
                  the long period when it has been rising out of the watery depths. Through a long
                  narrow hole, slanting, and communicating with the ocean, there comes at intervals
                  a terrific stream of air, forced by the spasmodic heaving of the waves against the
                  lower orifice.</span>
               <rs><orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">The government</orgName></rs>, which
               uses <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_far">this island</placeName></rs> for
               light-house purposes, enclosed the upper end with the nozzle of a fog-horn, and every
               few seconds there was blown an ear-splitting brawl, which was heard far out at sea
               and above the din of the breaking rollers. It was allowed to roar only in foggy
               weather, but it was eccentric in that it would only sound at high tide. When the tide
               was low, although the weather might be very thick, the thing was silent. For lack of
               its warning a ship went ashore upon the island rocks, and then it was that
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#gov_usa">the government</placeName></rs>
               abandoned its location on the wind hole and erected a steam-siren, or mechanical
               fog-horn, which has since very faithfully performed the necessary service.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="5">Another singular perforation in this island rock is a
                  passageway about two hundred feet long, interested by several globose
                  enlargements. One enters it on hands and knees, proceeds eighty feet, when it
                  suddenly widens into a chamber about thirty feet in breadth and six or seven feet
                  high. On the farther side the channel again contracts, proceeds, branches, becomes
                  labyrinthine, and finally emerges to the surface in small unexplored holes. As
                  though a ghastly circumstance was needed to make this boring grimly interesting,
                  it is related that the first white person who entered this globular apartment
                  found in it the skeleton of a woman. Her bones were delicate, and her teeth were
                  freshly white. Who she was, how she came there, and for what reason, all this was
                  sealed to the discoverer of her remains. These were withdrawn into the open and
                  interred beneath a cairn of stones.</span></p>
            <p>There is but little vegetation upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs>, and that much of the same character as is found upon
                     <rs><placeName type="city" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName></rs>.
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, however,
               differing from the others in the numerous springs of fresh water&#8212;a circumstance
               which has been availed of to make it a resort&#8212;has considerable verdure and may
               groves of trees. Among these is the <emph>Lyono thamnus</emph>, a tree not found
               elsewhere than upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                  islands</placeName></rs>. It has a stout branched trunk, and bears white blossoms
               in June. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">This island</placeName></rs>
               is also decorated with various charming and refreshing flowers&#8212;white lilacs,
               tree-poppies, and lavender, with ferns and lichens draping gloomy walls or weaving a
               carpet over the broken surface. <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                  Cruz</placeName> also has a good stream of water, which allows the growth of
               considerable vegetation.</p>
            <p>But upon <rs><orgName type="island" key="#i_chi">the other islands</orgName></rs>
               there is little else than a bleak desert, a waste of sand and cacti, the latter
               interspersed with blackthorn, the glistening fleshy ice-plant covering terraces and
               terraces of bluffs, which rise step by step to the plateaus above. A sparse growth of
               grass brought up by the winter rains heightens the tawny aspect to a light faint
               green, but the immense herds of sheep with which all these places are populated soon
               eatthis off back to the bare brown earth; or if it is not devoured while green, it
               dries into an ashy herbage&#8212;scant fodder for the hungry mouths.</p>
            <p>These winter rains also supply the chief water sources of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>. They are caught in
               holes in the rock surface called water-pots; in these the fluid collects, and for
               several months after the lapse of the humid season it may remain sufficiently fresh
               to be palatable: but after it stagnates or evaporates there is little of potable
               moisture accessible, and vegetation would soon perish were it not for the heavy fogs,
               which during three months of spring are so dense upon <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> and deposit such heavy dews as to
               amount almost to showers. On <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                  Clemente</placeName> there is a well from which a brackish liquid is pumped, and
               on <placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the Farallones</placeName> there is a
               mineral spring&#8212;pure water agreeably impregnated with iron and sulphur. But
               beyond this the water-supply is not material, and frequently, in periods of long
               drouths, with feed all consumed and water scarce, great sacrifices are made in sheep
               life by the owners of these animals. There are in all perhaps sixty thousand sheep
               maintained upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                  islands</placeName></rs>, and the number has a constant tendency to increase in
               excess of the possible food-supply. When such a condition is conceived to have been
               reached, a flat of wholesale execution goes out, and then it is that
                  <emph>matanzas</emph>, or great abattoirs, are erected, in which thousands of
               sheep are killed merely for their pelts, tallow, and glue. In <date when="1875"
                  >1875</date>, on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz
                  Island</placeName>, twelve thousand were thus slaughtered, and in <date
                  when="1887">1887</date> twenty-five thousand were in like summary manner taken
               off.</p>
            <p>The few persons who herd these sheep comprise the populations of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>. An exception to this
               is presented by <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>, which, being a resort, has several thousand inhabitants,
               gathered principally into its village, <placeName type="city" key="#ci_av"
                  >Avalon</placeName>. The owners of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs> are the proprietors of the sheep. In the early
               fifties, when these lands were taken possession of, in some instances by the parties
               who now own them, they were stocked with about two hundred sheep apiece. Fenced in by
               their fluid barrier, there was no possibility of the animals' escaping, and small
               danger of the preserved over being invaded by thieves. The stock was left to their
               own shift, and their owners concerned themselves with other affairs in divers parts
               of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>. But soon the sheep
               had so multiplied that the island principalities came to be veritable El Dorados.
               Thousands of dollars of annual income were derived from them, and are to-day, though
               when first seized upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs> were covered with heavy growths of rich grasses, which
               had accumulated upon them through successive years of unmolestation, and which it
               took even a large number of animals a long time to eat off, and the areas would then
               support larger flocks than now. In those days, too, which were the early period of
               California's settlement, the prices of wool and mutton were much in excess of present
               quotations; so that a very few years of the earlier returns which these gentlemen
               acquired through their island estates made them comfortably rich.</p>
            <p>Of animals <emph>feræ naturæ</emph> upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >these islands</placeName></rs> there are several species&#8212;wild hogs on
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> and <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, wild goats on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> and <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>. Both of these were placed
               there by whites, though the year of their introduction is not known. Originally
               domestic, they have returned to a state of nature through neglect. Rats and mice are
               also upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>,
               having been cast thither by vessels wrecked upon their rocks; there are also a small
               red fox and a skunk, which are indigenous mammals; but there are neither serpents,
               frogs, not poisonous insects, these noxious things never having been transported
               thither.</p>
            <p>The tourist exploring the interior of the island caves will experience an unpleasant
               shock when, after proceeding far into the grotto, he discovers that the place has
               inhabitants; and the splash, panic, and roar which follow tell him that the occupants
               are sea-lions. Quickly he must needs speed out, for they will plunge straight toward
               him, dive under him, and he must be wary, else they will upset his boat, and once he
               is in the water they will attack him, with possibly fatal results.</p>
            <p>Sea-lions are abundant about all of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs>. At <placeName type="island" key="#i_an"
                  >Anacapa</placeName> there is an enormous kelp-bed, where they breed and have
               their metropolis. These carnivora are not fur-bearing, but are covered with hair
               which grows upon a thick, unelastic hide. The hide has few uses, and the flesh is not
               palatable, though Indians find many services for the former, and the latter has
               furnished innumerable meals to both whites and natives. About <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>, too, there is a variety of
               shell-fish, the most notable of which is the haliotis, or abalone. It is a univalve,
               which seizes hold of a rock with its strong, muscular foot, and floats idly upward
               upon the surface, its broad scooped shell shielding its body like a dark umbrella.
               When disturbed it will suddenly contract, collapse, and its shell will be drawn over
               the body tightly against the rock. These abalone are much sought, and their fisheries
               sustain a numerous population of Italians and Chinese. The shell is iridescent, the
               nacre being variegated blue and green or pink and white; they are exported to
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_london">London</placeName>, where they are worked
               up into mother-of-pearl of commerce, and so employed in the manufacture of buttons
               and ornaments. The flesh of the animal is dried, and becomes a hard, soap-colored
               ball as large as a woman's fist. It is sent to <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_china">China</placeName>, where it is used as food. The shells bring $30
               per ton, while $90 is paid for a like quantity of the desiccated meat.</p>
            <p>Upon <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, the farthest
               seaward of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>,
               lying about sixty miles off shore, there are innumerable remnants of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an aboriginal
                     population</orgName></rs>. <span type="trope" n="5">Evidences appear upon all
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> of
                  their [sic] having been the abode of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">a race
                        of people</orgName></rs> who have passed; but at <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> appear all the specimens that are found
                  elsewhere, and many that have not been duplicated by any other spot. Immense
                  mounds of abalone shells, some half an acre in extent, are among these
                  curiosities, revealing the sites of periodic feasts of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                        islanders</orgName></rs> upon this fish.</span> Among these piles are
               scattered the shells of the limpey, mya, mussel, and other mollusks, while [white]
               stone mortars and pestles, implements of bone and ornaments of teeth, are both
               numerous and curious.</p>
            <p>On a knoll two miles from <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> beach is an Indian burial-ground. A dozen or more grim
               skeletons with their whitened skulls lie upon the shore, denuded of the sand in which
               they were once interred. The wild winds have swept it away, and the rains and fogs
               and the bleaching suns have been striving to dissolve and eradicate them, but they
               still remain. Some of the skulls show evidences of the tragic manner in which
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">their
                     owners</orgName></rs> met their deaths. <span type="trope" n="11"><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#rfurcompany; #natam_inuit">The
                     Innuits</orgName>, it is said, coming down from the Alaskan archipelagoes, fell
                  upon <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">these
                        harmless children of the south</orgName></rs>, massacred the man, and after
                  a little while abandoned the women and the young, and carried off all they could
                  steal.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="3">This was long after <date when="1542">1542</date>, when
                     <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, the Spanish navigator,
                  visited <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>,
                  and found them tenanted by <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">a mild
                        and vigorous people</orgName></rs>, who, revelling [sic] in the soft ether
                  of their climate, found their sustenance in the plenitudinous spontaneity of
                  nature.</span></p>
            <p>After the invasion of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#rfurcompany; #natam_inuit">the Innuits</orgName> and their departure,
                  <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">those who remaine</persName>d managed to
               maintain themselves until <date when="1835">1835</date>, when <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#misfats; #ndur; #aji">the Franciscan friars</persName></rs>
               went to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>, and
               gathering them all into boats, took them to <rs><placeName type="city" key="#re_mld"
                     >the mainland</placeName></rs>, where they were mingled with <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_missionindians">the
                  neophytes</orgName></rs> of <rs><orgName type="mission" key="#mi_mainlandmissions"
                     >the missions</orgName></rs>. It is related that after <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the last boat</name></rs> had pushed off from <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>
               <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> screamed for
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>,
               which, in the excitement of the movement aboard the transports, she had forgotten.
                  <span type="trope" n="9">She jumped out of <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_peoresnada">the vessel</name></rs> and sped away to seek it.
                        <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">The boat</name></rs> continued
                  its passage, and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                        woman</persName></rs> was left to her fate.</span>
               <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">The baby</persName></rs> died, but
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone and miserable
                     creature</persName></rs> remained the solitary inhabitant of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the place</placeName></rs> for many year. In her old
               age she was rescued and brought to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName>, where she died soon after her arrival.</p>
            <p>Of all the several islands <placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the
                  Farallones</placeName> are the most remarkable, for the fact that they comprise
               the rookeries of vast numbers of sea-fowl, which assemble there and breed. These lie
               opposite <placeName type="region" key="#re_sfbay">the bay of San
                  Francisco</placeName>, and they are used by <orgName type="government"
                  key="#gov_usa">the government</orgName> for a light-house station. The maintenance
               of this requires the residence upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_far">the
                     island</placeName></rs> of a small colony of persons who in the service of
                  <orgName type="government" key="#gov_usa">the government</orgName> consent thus to
               banish themselves from society. <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_steamer1">The
                     light-house steamer</name></rs> visits them every three months, then restocks
               their larder. Aside from this their only communication with civilization is by an
               occasional tag which may stop there to allow its captain to spy abroad from the
               light-house tower for incoming craft. Sometimes such a landing is not possible, owing
               to the height of the sea, and weeks may pass before the waters will subside so such
               can be effected.</p>
            <p>At nearly all times a strong cool wind prevails, and often in the afternoon it is
               sifted through with fog. A high board fence has been erected to protect the
               vegetation in the tiny patch of the light-house-tender's garden from being uprooted
               by the wind. But even with that, plant life does not thrive&#8212;or rather it
               thrives excessively, so that foliage becomes rank, and the fruit is a failure through
               growing too fast. Cabbages spring up, rush quickly into an abundance of green heavy
               leaves, but will not head. Onions and potatoes become immense in stalk and foliage,
               but will not "bulb" or "tuber." The cause of this is the strong guano soil in which
               the plants are grown; and the guano is deposited by the wild sea-fowl, which infest
               all the <placeName type="island" key="#i_far">Farallones</placeName>, three in
               number, making of them, in the opinion of ornithologists, the greatest bird islands
               in the world.</p>
            <p>There are eight varieties of these birds. They are the guillemot, commonly called the
               murre, the gull, the auk or auklet, the sea-pigeon, the shag or cormorant, the ashy
               petrel, the tufted puffin or sea-parrot, and the rock-wren. The first of these, the
               murre, dominates in number and importance upon <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_far">the island</placeName></rs>. It is a kind of duck, with a black
               head, white breast, and bluish back, and sits upright like a penguin. Its food is
               vegetable, dissection never having revealed the presence of fish. Its eggs are
               valuable for food, and until recently and for many years they were extensively
               gathers and sold in the <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>
               market, about fifteen thousand dozen yearly being disposed of there, purchased mainly
               by restaurants and boarding-houses, at an average price of twenty five cents per
               dozen. The egg is about twice the size of that of a hen, is white or bluish-green,
               and flecked with brown. When fresh it is indistinguishable from the hen product, but
               it soon develops a fishy taste. The murre lays one egg upon a nest of roots or grass,
               and proceeds to incubate the next generation. At night, when she is off duty, the
               male succeeds her. If unmolested, the nest will thus be covered until the young is
               hatched, when it will be guarded for a few weeks, then escorted off into the
               indefinite distance of the sea.</p>
            <p>But if the murre is disturbed by an egg-hunter and its single egg taken, it will
               return and replace its successively stolen ovum until eight have been laid. It is
               loath to leave its nest even when the despoiler approaches, and when he comes up she
               leans away from him and moves over to the far side of the nest. But presently,
               yielding to the alarm within her breast, she emits a sudden squawk and flies off,
               flushing the entire rookery as she moves toward the sea, leaving the pickers to fill
               their pouched shirts with the booty. They must hurry the work, for as soon as the
               eggs are uncovered the gulls hover close and become thick upon the scene. These then
               men much fight off, for they brazenly interpose themselves and battle with the humans
               for the possession of the eggs.</p>
            <p>The opportunity being open, the gull sweeps down upon the murre egg, seizes it in its
               mouth and goes sailing aloft; cracks it in its bill and gobbles what of its contents
               it can, the residue falling on the rocks below; then it takes another swoop away and
               balances itself to spy out a new egg.</p>
            <p>The gull's egg also is palatable. It is slightly smaller than that of the murre,
               whitish and speckled, three eggs being a litter. The eggs of the other birds are
               worthless for human uses, but their nests are raided by gulls and by each other. The
               albuminous fluid of the cormorant egg will not coagulate, and the puffin's egg has a
               repulsive fishy flavor. This bird has black plumage, with red beak and feet, while
               the cormorant is a large light blue bird, and flies in pairs. The sea pigeon is dark
               slate with some white in its wings; it has red feet, and lays a light blue egg. The
               auk is as large as a pigeon, and is nocturnal in its habits. The patrel has a musky
               smell, by the odor of which its nest is easily traceable.</p>
            <p>The murres make their nests high up, and often in the open, but the others hide
               theirs in the crevices of the rocks. Their note is loud, shrill, not pleasing to the
               ear; all except the cheery little rock-wren, whose liquid warble is a sweet,
               harmonious solo in the concern of shrieks and screams which ascend from the thousands
               of feathered throats.</p>
            <p>That <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs> were a
               great repository of edible eggs became known in <rs><date notBefore="1850"
                     notAfter="1859-12-31">the early fifties</date></rs>. At the time of the
               discovery of this fact provisions were scarce and gold was plentiful in <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, and the rookery eggs offered
               in the markets of <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">that city</placeName></rs>
               brought one dollar a dozen. The opening of this new and free opportunity to acquire
               wealth precipitated numbers of people upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >the islands</placeName></rs> and in the business of egg-gathering. Quarrels
               ensued between the competitors as to their respective "rights" in the premises, with
               the result that a company was formed among a number of the pickers, which bought out
               the claims of the others. This company managed to hold on to its advantages for some
               years, not, however, without experiencing contests and encroachments, until the
               bickerings ultimately grew so fierce as to attract the attention of the United States
               district attorney at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>.
               He sent a detachment of government soldiers there and deported every egg-picker.</p>
            <p>Following this the murres and gulls were permitted for a season to lay and hatch in
               safety; but later, the government revealing no desire for revenue from the eggs,
               those on the island allowed them to be picked on shares. This introduced a company of
               about eighteen Greek and Italian egg-pickers into the nidus-robbing enterprise; but
               disputes soon again arose, and ultimately to re-establish peace upon the islands it
               became necessary to forbid permanently any traffic in the eggs. This has accordingly
               been done by a recent order from Washington.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
