<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#mornbul">Morning
                     Bulletin</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="60"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="10,199"/>
               <date when="1897-02-16"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_rochamp">Rockhampton</placeName>,
                     <placeName type="state" key="#st_qland">Queensland</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="country" key="#co_aus">Australia</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#TheMorningBulletin1897">The Islands of Mystery.
                     Remains of a Giant Race</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="6"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">THE ISLANDS OF
                        MYSTERY</placeName></rs>.</title>
               <title type="sub">REMAINS OF <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">A GIANT RACE</orgName></rs>.</title></head>
            <p>The deserted <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> of
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the Pacific</placeName> have at last
               undergone a thorough exploration by <persName type="author" key="#cho">Professor
                  Charles Frederick Holden</persName>, says the <emph>Glasgow Mail</emph>,
               <!--Obviously, if and when we find this we need to link it here. | RM -->with the
               result that much of absorbing interest regarding <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the extinct
                     inhabitants</orgName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these
                     lovely i[s]les</placeName></rs> has been discovered. He visited <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, and <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, and made many excavations and many rich
               finds. <span type="trope" n="7">Giants once lived in the exquisitely lovely
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, for many
                  skeletons have been found there more than seven feet high.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="11">Tradition has it that <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#rfurcompany; #natam_aleuts">the warlike tribes</orgName></rs> of
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_aleutian">the Aleutian Islands</placeName>
                  came down in boats more than a century ago and practically exterminated
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        Channel Islanders</orgName></rs>. Certain is it that most of <rs><orgName
                        type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        unhappy wretches</orgName></rs> met death by violence, for nearly all the
                  skulls discovered are crushed by blows from blunt instruments. The club is the
                  weapon of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">the
                        Aleutian savage</orgName></rs>, and this seems to fit the tradition.</span>
               A few escaped, and up to about sixty years ago <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the remnants of the
                     tribe</orgName></rs> were still living on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                  >San Nicolas</placeName>. In <date when="1835">1835</date>
               <rs><persName type="group" key="#ndur; #aji; #misfats">the Franciscans of the Santa
                     Barbara mission</persName></rs>, learning that there were but <persName
                  type="group" key="#bhagroup">sixteen of the strange Indian race</persName> then
               living, determined to rescue them. They went over in <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">a sloop</name></rs> and succeeded in getting all on board.
               At the last moment <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an Indian
                     woman</persName></rs> returned for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs>, and one of the frequent storms of
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the Channel Islands</placeName> springing
               up, <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the sloop</name></rs> was driven away.
                  <span type="trope" n="6">It went on the rocks of <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName>, and all on board were lost. So only
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs> was
                  left, and she was soon forgotten.</span> In <date when="1851">1851</date>,
               however, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain George Nidever</persName>
               visited <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> to hunt
               sea otter, and was amazed to find human footprints in the sand. <rs><date when="1851"
                     >Two years later</date></rs> he returned to investigate the matter, and
               succeeded in capturing <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the remaining
                     Indian</persName></rs>, now an old woman. She was dressed in birdskins, and was
               engaged in scraping blubber from a seal. They took her to <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, where she lived for several years, and was
               known far and wide as <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">"the lone woman
                     of St. Nicholas."</persName></rs> But she never learned enough English to be
               able to tell anything of the life and tradi[t]ion of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">her strange
                     race</orgName></rs>. <persName type="author" key="#cho">Professor
                  Holden</persName>, in his exploration just concluded, found many large mounds in
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, one 300 feet long by
               50 feet wide, composed of abalone shells, which were brought from the sea two miles
               distant, thus showing evidence of a large population. He found objects of stone,
               bone, and shell piled in heaps. There were pendants, rings, beads, and curious
               objects in pearl among them, proving that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the extinct people</orgName></rs> loved
               ornamentation. That they played games was shown by the finding of perforated and oval
               stones, and many small and peculiarly shaped instruments. Some of the mortars picked
               up were very high and narrow, others so heavy there was great difficulty in rolling
               them down to the ship. One showed evidence of ornamentation with abalone. Sculptured
               forms of miniature sea lions and whales carved from serpentine prove a love of art in
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     aborigines</orgName></rs>. According to <persName type="author" key="#cho"
                  >Professor Holden</persName>
               <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     islanders</orgName></rs> depended for food on abalone, fish, and possibly
               roots. Consequently they belonged to an advanced period of the stone age. <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>, twenty miles long by three
               wide, <persName type="author" key="#cho">Professor Holden</persName> found contained
               much evidence of ancient habitation. Possibly 300 years ago it had a large
               population. One square mile of its area was covered with skeletons, shells, and
               ancient implements and mortars, some weighing one hundred pounds. <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName> is a high mountain
               ridge, the only landing places being the mouths of canyons. <persName type="author"
                  key="#cho">Professor Holden</persName> declares that <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> were inhabited for many centuries,
               for he found heaps of abalone shells on the seashore, covered with twenty feet of a
               deposit, which he calculates required centuries for its formation. <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">The islands</placeName></rs> have been a mine of
               archæologic treasure ever since <date when="1872">1872</date>, when the first
               systematic exploration was made by <persName type="author" key="#wha">Mr. W. G. W.
                  Harford</persName>. From the graveyards were unearthed a large number of
               skeletons, each surrounded by marvellous examples of the products and handiwork of
               the long past dead. <span type="trope" n="7">The graves, as described by these
                  investigators and others, make an interesting story of themselves. The skeletons
                  lay crowded together in every conceivable position, sometimes superimposed three
                  or four deep, those below, forgotten and unmarked, ruthlessly disturbed to make
                  room for the last interment. Some of the graves had rude boxes constructed of the
                  huge flat bones of whales, in which the dead were deposited. The early sea
                  captains related gruesome tales of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        islands</placeName></rs>, where, within yawning skeletons of whales, lay the
                  grinning and bleached bones of men, exposed to view by the ceaseless shifting of
                  the sands.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="5">One type of the remarkable finds made in the graves is the
                  gigantic soapstone, or steatite, pots, which stand absolutely alone as monuments
                  to the cleverness of <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        early inhabitants</orgName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs>. Some of them are fully two and
                  a half feet in diameter, almost globular in form, with very thin walls, and
                  carefully polished over their entire inner and outer surfaces. It is astounding
                  how these ancient peoples carved and modelled such symmetrical and fragile vases
                  from this material, but nevertheless fully three-fourths of the vessels used for
                  cooking and ceremonial purposes were adroitly fashioned from it.</span> For most
               of the pipes, gorgets, mortars, animal figures, pendants, net sinkers and the like
               the same stone was utilised. A shudderingly facetious use for some of these colossal
               stone jars was as a headgear for the dead. Numbers of skeletons were unearthed with
               skulls completely encased in the orifices of the vases. Half a dozen hair brushes
               were unearthed from graves. They are made from the fibre of the soap plant, or a
               species of yucca, bunched together in the semblance of a miniature whisk broom, the
               top, or handle, formed by heavily coating one end for several inches with bitumen.
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> is the only one of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> that is
               at all visited. A few sportsmen go there yearly for the magnificent bird shooting and
               unsurpassed sea fishing. The others are rarely ever approached. <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">St. Nicholas</placeName> is the most interesting of them
               all. <span type="trope" n="6">It is a melancholy spot for the visitor, for every acre
                  of it has its tale or tales of an extinct civilization.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="3">That <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the people</orgName></rs> that once enlivened
                  its shores and cliffs were peaceful is shown by the absence of weapons of offence.
                  The weapons found there are those used in the household and the chase.
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">These
                        gentle savages</orgName></rs> are fishermen by choice, and they must have
                  been sturdy and persistent whalers, judging by the myriad remains of these
                  deep-sea leviathans that <persName type="author" key="#cho">Professor
                     Holden</persName> found upon <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                        islands</placeName></rs>.</span> The great bones of whales were built into
               rudely artistic structures so compactly that they have withstood the ravages of storm
               and sand for centuries. <span type="trope" n="6">The only actual record of
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this
                        interesting savage race</orgName></rs> that we have previous to the
                  disastrous attempt by <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the
                        missionaries</orgName></rs> to remove the remnants of it, as told above, is
                  the log of <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Captain Juan Rodriquez
                     Cabrillo</persName>, the Portuguese navigator, who sailed up <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the Californian coast</placeName></rs> in
                     <date when="1542">1542</date>. He stopped a day or two at each of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the Channel Islands</placeName>, and reported that
                  they were inhabited by a "<rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">vigorous
                        and lusty race of natives</orgName></rs>, who thronged the shores of the
                  bays and headlands," and seemed greatly mystified by <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_salvador; #sh_lavictoria">the ship</name></rs>. <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">The islands</placeName></rs> remain, but
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                        natives</orgName></rs> are no more.</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
