<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#newyorkher">New York
                            Herald </orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume"/>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">116</biblScope>
                    <date when="1891-04-26"/>
                    <pubPlace/>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="article" key="#Miller1891">""Mrs. Robinson Crusoe of
                            California. De Foe's Hero Outdone by an Heroic Indian Woman of Cunning
                            Intelligence. Twenty-five years alone. Joaquin Miller's Quaint Sketch of
                            the Lonely Denizen of an Island Off the Western Coast."</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page" n="13"/>
                        <author><persName type="author" key="#jmill"> Miller, Joaquin.
                            </persName></author>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lw">MRS. ROBINSON CRUSOE</persName></rs>, OF <placeName
                                type="state" key="#st_cal">CALIFORNIA</placeName>.</hi></title>
                    <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="fictional" key="#rcr">De
                                    Foe's Hero</persName></rs> Outdone by an <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Heroic Indian Woman of Cunning
                                    Intelligence</persName></rs>.</hi></title>
                    <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold"><date from="1835" to="1860">TWENTY-FIVE YEARS
                                ALONE.</date></hi></title>
                    <title type="sub"><hi rend="bold">Joaquin Miller's Quaint Sketch of the
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Lonely Denizen of an
                                    Island</placeName></rs> Off the <rs><placeName type="region"
                                    key="#re_paccoast">Western
                    Coast</placeName></rs>.</hi></title></head>
                <div type="section">
                    <p>A GREAT deal has been written about <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                key="#lw">the extraordinary little woman</persName></rs> who lived
                        all alone on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">one of our
                                islands</placeName></rs> for <date from="1835" to="1853">nearly a
                            quarter of a century</date>, but some of the facts seem to have escaped
                        notice. <span type="trope" n="3">I shall write them down here as briefly as
                            possible for the use of the coming <rs><persName type="author"
                                    key="#dde">De Foe</persName></rs>.</span>
                        <span type="trope" n="8">In the first place <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs>,
                            although an Indian, was almost white and of extraordinary intelligence
                            and sensibility.</span></p>
                    <p>The late <persName key="#bri">Dr. Brinkerhoff</persName>, of <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, who attended her in
                        her last illness, told me that he thought perhaps she was not of Indian
                        extraction at all. But to get on with the facts. When <rs><orgName
                                type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the Jesuit
                            priests</orgName></rs> founded their settlement at <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> they began to gather
                        in all the docile or friendly Indians and utilize as well as civilize them.
                        After some years they found out that <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_sn">one of the small islands</placeName></rs> lying off
                        about twenty miles from their harbor of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                            >Santa Barbara</placeName> was inhabited. <span type="trope" n="3"
                                    ><rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">The
                                    priests</orgName></rs> visited <rs><placeName type="island"
                                    key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and found <rs><orgName
                                    type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the most
                                    intelligent and gentle people</orgName></rs> there that had yet
                            been discovered on the continent. They were loyal, affectionate, and
                            loved their <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">narrow and lonely
                                    little home</placeName></rs> in the sea above all things.</span>
                        They had never visited <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the main
                            land</placeName>. They had no wood to build boats with, and so
                            <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the long black and barren
                            mountain of land</placeName> away to the south was as inaccessible to
                        them as is the moon to us.</p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="5">They had queer little houses of stone on the one low
                            cliff, and they were very skillful in spearing fish and capturing all
                            sorts of sea birds. They made mocassins [sic] for their feet out of
                            sealskins, for seals were and are to this day so abundant there that you
                            can scarcely walk about without treading on some of the little baby
                            seals. And all along to right and left, as you pass by, you see the
                            mild-eyed mother seal nursing her baby at her breast, as she half rests
                            and reclines against a rock, and lifts her kind, human eyes to yours, as
                            if to ask you please not hurt her little hairy baby.</span></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="main">THEIR FOOD AND CLOTHING.</title></head>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="5">I found the eggs of water fowl so plentiful when I
                            visited <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this little
                                    island</placeName></rs>
                            <date notBefore="1871">almost twenty years ago</date> to gather material
                            for an English magazine that it was absolutely impossible to walk about
                            without crushing great numbers under foot.</span>
                        <span type="trope" n="3">And <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                    key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">these simple natives</orgName></rs>
                            dressed their bodies not in furs, but in feathers. They skinned the sea
                            lions and out of the skins they made remarkably beautiful garments of
                            all hues and fashions.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="3">And this wonderful skill in all their simple walks
                            of life, together with their perfect docility&#8212;for it seems they
                            knew nothing at all about war or even an[g]er&#8212;tempted <persName
                                type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the monks</persName> to
                            undertake the transportation of the whole tribe, numbering less than two
                            hundred, to their settlement at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb"
                                >Santa Barbara</placeName>.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="3">And so they sent <rs><name type="ship"
                                    key="#sh_peoresnada">their ship</name></rs>, and contriving to
                            get <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                                    >the simple and confiding islanders</orgName></rs> all on board
                            they hoisted sail for <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                                mainland</placeName>.</span></p>
                    <p>After a time <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the poor prisoners</orgName></rs> became
                        alarmed, and fearing they were to be taken from <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_sn">their beloved island</placeName></rs> forever, attempted
                        to escape over the sides of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                                ship</name></rs> into the sea. <span type="trope" n="9">But
                                    <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                                    >the cunning Spanish soldiers and sailors</persName></rs> had
                            taken precautions against this, and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lw">only one</persName></rs> managed to leap into the sea
                            and swim back to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                                    island</placeName></rs>.</span></p>
                    <p>Now <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the
                            monks</orgName></rs> told various stories about this woman's reason for
                        escaping back to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the lonely
                                island.</placeName></rs> One was to the effect that she had hidden
                        away <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                            babe</persName></rs> in the rocks on consenting to go on board <rs><name
                                type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs>, so as to make
                        sure that it at least should not be torn from its happy little home in the
                        sea and made to serve the strangers, and then finding she was being carried
                        away to return no more, she, in her desperation, dashed through her guards
                        and so got away. A kindlier story is to the effect that <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lwmother">her mother</persName></rs> hid
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                                babe</persName></rs>, but that she did not know it and thought it
                        had been forgotten. Still another version of the story runs to the effect
                        that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                            child</persName></rs> was about to be devoured by numbers of dogs that
                        were left behind, and that she leaped into the sea to save it. But this is
                        the most unkindly and the hardest of all the versions of this extraordinary
                        story. For to believe this last is to believe that <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the little
                            child</persName></rs> was indeed destroyed by the dogs; since
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                            mother</persName></rs> when found there and taken to <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>
                        <date when="1853">nearly a quarter of a century ago</date> was found
                        entirely alone.</p>
                    <p>My own notion of the matter is that <rs><orgName type="missionfathers"
                                key="#misfats">the Jesuit fathers</orgName></rs> entrusted the
                        capture and transportation of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the simple natives</orgName></rs>
                        entirely to some cruel leader of their few seamen and soldiers; that with
                        the usual high handed audacity of the early Spaniards he decoyed them all on
                        board, and only this one could get away. I see no reason for believing there
                        was any baby in the case at all.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="main">LEFT ALONE FOR YEARS.</title></head>
                    <p>And now years and years rolled by. A beautiful little city blossomed out at
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, only
                        twenty miles away from <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                lonely woman</persName></rs> on <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_sn">her silent little island</placeName></rs>. A huge stone
                        cathedral, still standing there with its frieze of human skulls set in
                        stonelike cement, was reared by the hands of the converts and the captives;
                        but she saw nothing, knew nothing of this. For her there was no change day
                        after day, <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">year after year</date></rs>. The
                        same rise and fall of the sea, the same solemn march of the seasons, the
                        same silent marching and countermarching of the stars above her and about
                        her on the edge of the sea, the same endless, awful monotony of the rising
                        and the going down of the sun and the moon and the stars. And that was all.
                        It seems incredible to think that any set of human beings could have been so
                        entirely brutal as to leave <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                >this woman</persName></rs> there <rs><date from="1835" to="1853"
                                >all these years</date></rs> so utterly and so desolately alone.
                            <span type="trope" n="8">She did not even have the goats of <name
                                type="fictional" key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name>, to say nothing
                            of <persName type="fictionel" key="#friday">his man Friday</persName>
                            and like creatures.</span> She had only the dogs. And they became so
                        numerous and so wild, as we shall presently see, as to be the greatest
                        terrors.</p>
                    <p>But it should here be explained as a sort of justification of <rs><orgName
                                type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the Jesuit
                            fathers</orgName></rs> that they had hardily got their religious
                        settlement solidly founded when they were recalle[d] by the King of Spain,
                        or at least made powerless by the confiscation of nearly all their
                        privileges and their property. And so other people took their places, and
                        time swept on.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="main">WAITING FOR SUCCOE [SUCCOR].</title></head>
                    <p>After years and years gold was found in <placeName type="state" key="st_ca"
                            >California</placeName> and ships began to sail by in great numbers. One
                        ship after another reported seeing a lone figure like that of a human being
                        standing on a little pyramid of heaped up stones and looking out after the
                        ship till lost to sight.</p>
                    <p>Finally inquiry in and around <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                            Francisco</placeName> revived the story about <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone woman</persName></rs> who
                        had been left for <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">so many years</date></rs>
                        on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and
                        the circumstances as I have set them down, so far as the facts were known at
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>But everybody was busy getting gold. We had no lighthouse or government
                        stations then as now. Our acquisition of the vast seashore out here was new.
                        We had not yet explored or set foot on the half of our possessions. And so
                        time still swept on and <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                lone w[o]man</persName></rs> was still left with her wild dogs in
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the desolate little
                                island</placeName></rs> off the salubrious harbor of <placeName
                            type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>.</p>
                    <p>And now one of the great steamers carrying gold and passengers, <name
                            type="ship" key="#sh_generalscott">the General Scott</name>, was wrecked
                        on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_an">a still smaller
                                island</placeName></rs> not far off.</p>
                    <p>The wreckers and others saw <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                woman</persName></rs> not infrequently now. And the story went about
                        that the little pyramid of rocks was gradually growing higher and
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone and desolate
                                figure</persName></rs> that mounted it taller and taller as time
                        went by.</p>
                    <p>Finally the American spirit could endure this idea of lone and endless
                        captivity no longer. <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi">Two
                                men</persName></rs> from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_bo"
                            >Boston</placeName> and some others from I know not where hired <name
                            type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">a small ship</name> and sailed straight
                        for the relief of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the poor
                                desolate prisoner</persName></rs>. She stood high and lone on the
                        heap of stones and waited for their coming.</p>
                    <p>And what could have been her thoughts? Would they, too, pass on and away to
                        the left and to the right as a thousand other ships had passed? Would they
                        come to her? Could they come? And what if they should come? Would they
                        devour her; [sic] as the wild dogs that gathered about her were waiting to
                        devour her? Landing without trouble, for the ocean here is still and restful
                        as a rule, they walked away over the sea birds' eggs and through the swarms
                        of seal straight up toward <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                feather clad figure</persName></rs> on the high heap of stones. It
                        did not attempt to run away.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="main">HER PITIABLE PLIGHT.</title></head>
                    <p>And here is the grimmest and most pathetic part of it all; she could not run
                        away without danger of being devoured by the horde of wild dogs that
                        literally sat in a circle around her, waiting, watching for her to come
                        down.</p>
                    <p>She had been years building her little fortress, and she had built it with
                        all the care and skill of a trained engineer. Here was a stone house for her
                        provisions; there a cell for water, and here one worn and crooked pass where
                        she could possibly beat back the dogs with her club as long as she had
                        strength. But when strength failed her? She had not been unmindful of
                        failing strength in the end, however, and so had built a little tower on
                        top, where she could at the last lie down and die.</p>
                    <p>One of <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the rescuing
                                party</persName></rs> told me that she surely could have held out
                        but a little time longer.</p>
                    <p>Strange as it may seem, she laughed at the pity offered her. She would not
                        come down to them, but when they came up into her little retreat she laughed
                        outright and hid her face in her rich robe of feathers. <span type="trope"
                            n="14">In fact, as this same man told me, she laughed almost
                            continually, perhaps to the poor creature's only form of
                            expression.</span> For, of course, she could not understand one word
                        that any one spoke to her. <span type="trope" n="6">And one of the
                            interesting things about it all is when they got her to <placeName
                                type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> not one of
                                    <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                    key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">her tribe</orgName></rs> was left
                            alive to talk with her.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="14"><persName key="#bri">Dr. Brinkerhoff</persName>,
                            who was then the principal citizen in <placeName type="city"
                                key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <rs><persName
                                    key="#brinkwife">whose widow</persName></rs> is still there to
                            verify all that has been said, told me that he took from <rs><name
                                    type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the boat</name></rs> himself when
                                    <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                                    party</persName></rs> got back from <rs><placeName type="island"
                                    key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> with her and that she
                            began to laugh as soon as he took hold of her hand to help her ashore.
                            And he further told me that as he walked up <rs><placeName type="city"
                                    key="#ci_sb">town</placeName></rs> with her toward <placeName
                                key="#brinkhouse">his house</placeName> they met <rs><persName
                                    key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh">a man in the street on
                                    horseback</persName></rs>, and that on the sight of
                                    <rs><persName key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh">this man
                                    on horseback</persName></rs> she sat right flat down in the dust
                            and laughed and laughed as if she could never stop laughing.</span></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="main"><persName type="showman" key="#pba">BARNUM</persName>
                            WANTED HER.</title></head>
                    <p>Of course the strange story and the news of the rescuing from <rs><placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> soon spread
                        all over the world. <persName type="showman" key="#pba">Barnum</persName>
                        sent <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#tru">a man</persName></rs> all the
                        way from his <placeName type="city" key="#bridgeport">Bridgeport</placeName>
                        home to secure her for his "greatest show on earth," and the <orgName
                            type="government" key="#castate">State of California</orgName> promised
                        to make ample provision for her comfort and well being at home.</p>
                    <p>But before <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#tru">Barnum's
                            agent</persName></rs> arrived or <rs><persName type="nativemerican"
                                key="#lw">the poor little laughing creature</persName></rs> had
                        fairly ceased to laugh at the sight of the first horse she had ever seen she
                        felt ill.</p>
                    <p>All was done by the good people of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                            Barbara</placeName> that could possibly be done. <span type="trope"
                            n="3">She had the best of care and certainly the best of physicians
                            attended her. But she rapidly declined and one day while sitting on the
                            grass eating a piece of watermelon she suddenly turned her face away to
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her
                                island</placeName></rs>, looked a moment, and then sank down on the
                            grass, dead!</span></p>
                    <p>They found a great many fishhooks hidden away in her new clothes and also a
                        number of needles, for fishhooks and needles were the wonder and the delight
                        of her heart, and this gave rise to the idea that was getting ready to swim
                        back to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">her
                        island</placeName></rs>. But <persName key="#bri">Dr.
                            Brinkherhoff</persName> assured me that she was perfectly content in
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and had no
                        notion of running away. He said, with reason, that it was but natural that
                        she should, after her long enforced habits of hoarding of things, hide away
                        fishhooks and needles, as the two things were important to her in her
                        pitifully limited vision of life.</p>
                    <p>She left many things of very cunning workmanship still to be seen in
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>. But her
                        gorgeous robe of feathers, made entirely from the few green feathers found
                        on the heads of certain ducks and composed of more than one thousand pieces
                        was sent to <rs><persName key="#pop">the Pope</persName></rs> and is to be
                        seen in <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">the
                        Vatican</orgName>.</p>
                    <p>She caught these ducks with fishhooks made of bone and sinew. She sewed her
                        robe of ever so many pieces together with sinews taken from the backs of
                        seal, her only needle being a sharpened bone. No wonder that all the wealth
                        of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, to her, was
                        not worth so much as a few fishhooks and needles.</p>
                    <byline><persName type="author" key="#jmill">JOAQUIN MILLER.</persName></byline>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
