SAN NICOLAS ISLAND, TREASURE HOUSE OF THE ANCIENTS: PART I

<emph>By</emph> BRUCE BRYAN

THERE is no first record of San Nicolas Island in reality, because its existence was known in a vague sort of way long before it was ever mentioned in writing. Presumably it was first visited by a half-naked band of Indian warriors, paddling a great hollowed war-canoe through stormy waters to its barren wastes that offered nothing more than the seafood abounding about its shores. Were these Indians fleeing from the tide of the rising Pueblo races, or were they seeking a new home because of dissensions and rivalry in their own cultures on the California coast? Whatever the underlying cause, the fact remains that only a hardy, aggressive race could have built up a permanent abode on the volcanic segment known as the "Passing Isle".

For years it has been customary to associate the name of San Nicolas Island with a sand[-]swept, wind[-]torn, desert spot in the vast Pacific, where a howling gale is eternally raging and where heavy seas constantly thunder down upon its rocky coast. Fishermen go there occasionally&#8212;that type of roving seaman who will go anywhere for gain&#8212;since nowhere in the world do better or more enormous quantities of deep sea fish abound. Pirates, smugglers, and rum-runners, too, haunt its vicinity. But rarely do they land, and when near the island they remain a good way off-shore. It is feared through the curious natural phenomena of the elements that seem to have marked it for their own, and through which it has acquired an evil name. Yet as a field for archaeological research it has proven itself a veritable storehouse.

Numerous theories have been advanced from time to time as to the origin of the Indian tribes of California, and especially those of the outlying Channel Islands. Some ethnologists have regarded them as the descendants of those prehistoric people who once inhabited most of the Southwest now attributed to the Cliff Dwellers and Pueblos. They believe that the later house-building aborigines drove out these people and forced them to move on to California, where some of them took refuge along the coasts, while others ventured out onto the islands and set up a culture of their own. Here they built up commerce with other islands and the mainland, as evidenced by the many relics of their ancient trading found today.

Seemingly supporting this theory is the fact that the California tribes are an older racial type than the Pueblos or Cliff Dwellers. Skulls of both the coast and island Indians reveal distinct dolichocephalic types, whereas those of the more advanced inhabitants of the Southwest are clearly brachycephalic, or roundheaded. Too, the Pueblos indulged in the custom of early applying a cradle-board to the heads of their infants, thereby causing them to grow to maturity with a peculiarly flattened cranium in the occipital. No traces of such artificial deformities have ever been found on either the coast or islands. But many articles of trade from both areas have often been unearthed, from soapstone images to pottery fragments and burnt shards. If there was ever a meeting point of the two opposing cultures, it probably was in northern Death Valley, where Pueblo shards of the most primitive black-on-white design and earliest coiled-ware are found in typical California Indian shell-mounds.

In 1926 the Los Angeles Museum of History, Science and Art sent an expedition to San Nicolas Island, farthest to sea of the entire Channel Group, where it remained for two months, from October 15th until December 14th. Composed of Charles W. Hatton, of the Museum's Indian Department, Arthur R. Sanger, private collector, and the writer, as field archaeologist for the institution, the expedition returned with one of the largest and most complete collections of prehistoric Indian remains ever assembled on one trip. Among the material brought back and now on exhibition in the Museum are great stone mortars and carved pestles, bone- and shell-ornaments, beads of intricate and delicate carving, war-axes and clubs, abalone-shell fishhooks, and a number of fine examples of small fish images carved out of soapstone and pearl shell. Four complete skeletons were found, together with a heterogeneous collection of human and animal bones.

Several hitherto unestablished facts were proved by this trip, among others the certainty that the ancient Indian who dwelt in the most primitive of Stone Age environments on this barren island was possessed of all the physical characteristics, as to mind and body, of the average twentieth century human being! And yet each of the four complete skeletons shows some indication of disease. The most interesting of these is a large one of a native who lived to be an old man, which was discovered to have a disease of the spine that has contorted it entirely out of shape, evidencing that this particular creature must have been a hopeless cripple in his lifetime, in fact, a badly distorted hunchback.

No organized expedition had visited San Nicolas for the purpose of scientific research for years, although in the past a number of well-known museums had made lesser investigations, among them the Smithsonian Institution and the Southwest Museum. Dr. William A. Bryan, director of the Los Angeles Museum, had long been contemplating a trip to one or another of the Channel Islands for the purpose of learning more of the habits and life of the islanders from what is left of their culture. San Nicolas was finally settled upon as being the most fertile field in that it is the most remote and least known. The remains on the nearer islands have been pretty well cleaned up, but inasmuch as it is situated over a hundred miles offshore and is constantly swept by tempestuous gales which drive great sheets of stinging sand before them, San Nicolas presents another aspect of the case.

Completely encircled by dense beds of kelp through which small boats must thread a precarious path, it is a desert place where nothing grows except a few straggling weed-clumps and cactus-beds and perhaps four inches of buckthorn grass on small stretches of the uplands. The sand is forever being shifted in great dunes from place to place, uncovering one graveyard for the purpose of concealing another beneath tons of billowing grains. Enormous quantities of it are blown into the ocean and it is a fact that on one of the days toward the close of the expedition's stay there, the combined forces of wind and rain had caused the north shore to present a muddied belt of water extending out through the breakers for half a mile. It is for this reason, since the island is gradually being blown into the sea, that it is often referred to as the "Passing Isle".

Much prominence has been attached to it from time to time, however, through newspaper and magazine accounts of the celebrated "Lost Woman" who was once marooned there for a number of years. Just where truth begins and fiction ends in these stories is difficult to determine, but it is certain that there was such a creature, and it is to this fact that archaeology owes a great debt. Through her it can form a fairly accurate conception of what the ancient islander resembled, since this woman was removed from the place after having lived there alone for an indefinite period. As to the term of her isolation, accounts again vary. Some put it at twelve years, some at eighteen, and most at twenty.

Briefly, according to Holder's "Channel Islands of California", one of the few incomplete and out-of-date authorities of the subject, the history of the "Lost Woman" is this: For some time the ancient islanders had been decimated by the raids of warlike tribes on the islands about them, and possibly by tribes from the mainland, although the Indians of the coast are not generally considered to have been as aggressive as those of the isles. The Nicoleños also suffered periodic attacks at the hands of the Russians, who made marauding trips down from the Aleutian Islands in search of otter, seal, and sea elephant, and who not only preferred other people's game but were not at all averse to including in it the hapless natives. The men were killed and the women carried off.

In 1830, however, undoubtedly urged by the Spanish mission fathers, the Mexican government, then holding California, sent a boat under the command of a certain Captain Sparks, an otter hunter, to remove the few remaining Indians from San Nicolas to the mainland. There, it was thought, they could be afforded better protection and incidentally be converted to the ways of God. This boat, the <emph>Better Than Nothing</emph>, rounded up and started back with the few aborigines who were found on the island. But suddenly one of them, a woman, cried out that she had left her baby in the rush. Owing to the conditions of wind and tide so well known, the boat could not turn about and put back to shore. So the woman jumped overboard and swam in.

The <emph>Better Than Nothing</emph> left her there, and that was the last that was seen of her for a fifth of a century. Years afterward, Captain Nidever, a Santa Barbaran, at the request of the Mission of Santa Barbara, made a special trip to the island in search of the woman, whom evidently some chance fisherman had caught sight of wandering about the shore. After three trips, Nidever did find and bring her back. She had attempted to hide from him and twice had succeeded, but the last time he gave chase and caught her, persuading her that he did not intend to harm her.

Although Indians were brought from all over the surrounding country, none could understand a word of her language. The question, therefore, naturally arises: How did Captain Sparks of the <emph>Better Than Nothing</emph>, know that she jumped overboard to go back after her child? No child was found with her, and certainly none was brought with her to the mainland. A few of her words, though their meaning was not recognizable, were said to be of Shoshonean origin. Her birdskin dress and various other accouterments were sent to the Vatican museum in Rome by the mission fathers. Nidever himself cared for the woman, but she died within six weeks, the belief being that the new food she was obliged to eat did not agree with her. She had been found living in a hut made of whalebone and ribs with a brush fence erected about it to break the wind, and a covering of seal skins.

Leaving from the California Yacht Club at Wilmington in a fifty-foot cabin cruiser, powered with a Diesel engine, the Los Angeles Museum expedition's first glimpse of San Nicolas, at seven o'clock the next morning, was one of a great gray and brown mountain looming out of the sea against a rising sun, and encircled at the top by floating mist wraiths. Although the trip over in the rather small "Idle Hour" was fairly rough, in the early morning the ocean was calm enough to land provisions and equipment.

It is at this time that the seas that rush against the island are supposed to be calmest, and the first morning was spent in unloading. Among the stores was Mr. Sanger's seven-tube radio, including a number of heavy batteries. After being rowed ashore, all these had to be carried up a sixty- or seventy-foot bluff. Quarters were taken up at the shack of the single inhabitant of the isle, old Captain Nelson, whose unique position was a combination of caretaker of the island and sheepherder to the 2,500 head of half-wild sheep that roam its expanse. With the aid of a wooden sled attached to his decrepit mare, "Mary", the last of the Museum's stores were brought up and safely established at the camp.

The first few days were spent in exploring the island and locating various sites in which to dig. Unlike most excavations, the order of approach here was different, since there were no strata by which to go. The method of procedure was sometimes to work together, and more often to work a place alone, thereby having three separate research jobs going at one time. The sand was soft on the shell-mounds, or kitchen-middens, and it was not too much trouble for one man to move several tons a day. But after having dug down often to a depth of five or six feet, next morning the site would be found filled level again through the action of the wind.

The west end of the island, which juts out into a small point, or spit, is literally one vast kitchen-midden composed of hundreds of shell-heaps. The south shore, however, was practically barren. Moreover, this side is washed by the heaviest seas, and doubtless the Indians early decided that here was an unprofitable place in which to live. The east shore juts into a long spit of sand almost a mile long, but it has the fewest mounds of all, though here there are many indications of a much older habitation.

Except for approximately one hundred and fifty yards of encircling shoreline the entire island is in reality a plateau, some eight hundred feet in height, and remarkably flat on top for miles about. On the eastern half of this table is found the scant vegetation that exists here, the western part being little more than sandy waste with curious stretches of lime-formations much resembling small stalagmites and stalactites. A number of evidences of Indian dwelling places were found on the highlands, those above the west end seeming much older than the others as evidenced by the hard nature of the soil and the scarcity of remains. But at times a great sand mound rises up, covered in the sun with a glittering shell-heap, where here and there a bone-needle, an awl, some fishhooks, exquisitely carved, or the top of a skull might be discovered exposed to the air.

Arriving at the ages of the various relics found is a difficult question and can only be done approximately. No trace of Spanish remains of the era of the <emph>conquistadores</emph> was uncovered, nor is there any record of one ever having put foot on the shores of San Nicolas, though they visited every other island of the Channel Group. Legend persists that Cabrillo, the intrepid leader of the Spaniard geographers who first sailed through these waters, is buried in a lead coffin somewhere on Santa Rosa Island, a distance of over fifty miles away. Sanger has been looking for this grave for over twenty years, but so far has found not the slightest clue.

It is certain that all of the objects encountered on San Nicolas are at least one hundred years old, since the last natives were removed in 1830, with the exception of the so-called "Lost Woman", who was taken off in 1850 and who could not have left many relics by herself. Nevertheless, the nature of the soil goes a long way in aiding the archaeologist to determine the approximate period at which a particularly hard formation of sandstone, which must be hacked into with the aid of a pick and which yields up a skeleton or parts of one, was soft, loose sand as on the mounds. Again it is a matter of osteology to arrive at the age of a handful of human teeth found in a somewhat similar formation, and which are so decayed that holes are worn through the hard, bright enamel. In each case, similar finds were removed from each other by a distance of five miles in a straight line.

Near a sample of such teeth as these, Mr. Hatton unearthed the body of what must once have been a great chief. It was situated in a grave on the west end, buried in the conventional flexed posture, and had to be cut out of sandstone of rocklike tenacity. Between the hands of this skeleton, which lay on its face, was a large white spear-head. The rest of the day was spent in carefully sifting out of the sand hundreds of small, square abalone-shell beads and the larger pendants, from the quantity of which he must have had a coat sewn. Curiously, three other skeletons lay close to this one, all in a direct line, the head of each pointed toward the west. Only two skulls were brought in, however, including the first and that of a woman who had been interred with only a necklace of large reddish beads.

Merely skimming the tops of those mounds that appeared to be less productive than others brought to light an almost unbelievable quantity of material. Likewise the amount of castaway shells and bones gleaming on the surface was enormous. By crossing one of these great middens on hands and knees and using the eyes even casually many little shell fishhooks, bone-awls, harpoons, needles and the like were picked up. Sometimes on top of the mounds and sometimes on the sides were found bowls of stone and soapstone. Often these were revealed by a faint showing of the rim, to which they were buried in the sand. The larger mortars had to be dragged for miles on crude wooden sleds over the sands.

Great numbers of the relics found, especially the stoneware, were smashed most completely and thoroughly. This work of demolition was undoubtedly done by the Indians themselves, and in a most businesslike manner. That queer part of the religious belief of the ancient American Indians, which is often encountered among other aboriginal tribes in various parts of the world, may account for this wholesale destruction of personal utensils and household ware. It was thought by the old Indians that any implement a man manufactured was like himself possessed of a soul, or spirit. Therefore, when he died his bowls and other artifacts were broken and buried with him, or close to him. In this way were they "killed", so that their spirits might serve him in the next world!

Several different methods of effecting this breaking seem to have been practiced on San Nicolas. For instance, many of the bowls on the plateau were discovered with the bottoms alone smashed out. On the mounds toward the west end they were literally broken into the smallest of fragments. Others merely had a hole chopped into them. And in order to save themselves the labor of making new ones, later Indians utilized these last by plugging up the holes with asphaltum, a tarry substance washed up on the rocks by the sea. One of the mortars brought in by the expedition shows a serrated line of chips around its rim, indicating the method by which they were sometimes demolished in a professional way.

At times a series of fragments were unearthed that would fit together perfectly to form a complete bowl. These were gathered up, the fragments numbered, and brought back for restoration at the Museum. But the old inhabitants of San Nicolas apparently foresaw that something like this would happen even to their broken utensils. Craftily they worked out a plan to prevent it. The archaeologist might find a broken mortar of ten pieces, nine of which went into place perfectly. The tenth would be a fragment of another bowl! And the missing piece was never found, which leads one to think that it was probably either ground into dust or thrown into the ocean.

For the first week or longer, everything come upon by the expedition had either been found before by some previous explorer or else was hopelessly scattered by action of the stinging sand and wind. Experience quickly demonstrated the futility of digging haphazardly. To tum up anything at all, surface indications must first be revealed. Otherwise one might dig on forever. In addition, it was decided that it would be wise to construct several large screens to sift every inch of sand about a burial. This was a precaution taken to save a skeleton down to the minutest beads and the smaller finger and toe bones.

The first complete and untouched grave was found on the west central plateau by Mr. Sanger, through the fact that the top of a bleached skull protruded above the sand. When dug out and developed the skeleton was found to be lying half on its side in a flexed position. The head was quite upright, having slipped with the shifting of the earth. The skeleton was that of a young man with a very Mongolian cast of skull. A curious ossification had joined the pelvis together in one piece so that it resembled nothing so much as a saddle. Buried with it were a stone-axe, two throwing-stones shaped like doughnuts, and a dish made of abalone-shell with the perforations plugged with the usual asphaltum.

In an old bulletin reporting a former trip by the Smithsonian Institution to this island in the last century, it was stated that most of the bodies were buried facing eastward. Contrary to this, those found by the Los Angeles Museum expedition showed no indication of orientation according to some ritual. It was also found that the average depth of the graves was about eighteen inches, although this seemingly shallow interment may have been due to the moving of the sand dunes.

Three other skeletons were found and developed for transportation, besides several almost complete ones. Every so often a scattered pile of bleached bones, which gave every appearance of being the last evidences of some wholesale slaughter, were stumbled upon. It is impossible to say whether these are due to the uncovering action of the wind, or whether previous collectors had dug them out, taken only what they wanted, and left the rest to decay.

<emph>(To be concluded in the May issue.)</emph>