<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="journal"><orgName type="publication" key="#art">Art and
                     Archaeology</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="29"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="4"/>
               <date when="1930-04-01"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_con">Concord</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_nh">New Hampshire</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Bryan1930">San Nicolas Island, Treasure House of the
                     Ancients: Part I</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="147" to="156"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#bbr">Bryan, Bruce</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">SAN
                        NICOLAS ISLAND</placeName>, TREASURE HOUSE OF THE ANCIENTS: PART
                  I</hi></title></head>
            <byline><emph>By</emph>
               <persName type="author" key="#bbr">BRUCE BRYAN</persName></byline>
            <p><span type="trope" n="11"><hi rend="bold">T</hi>HERE is no first record of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> in reality, because
                  its existence was known in a vague sort of way long before it was ever mentioned
                  in writing. Presumably it was first visited by a half-naked band of Indian
                  warriors, paddling a great hollowed war-canoe through stormy waters to its barren
                  wastes that offered nothing more than the seafood abounding about its shores. Were
                  these Indians fleeing from the tide of the rising <orgName
                     type="nativeamiercantribes" key="#natam_pueblo">Pueblo races</orgName>, or were
                  they seeking a new home because of dissensions and rivalry in their own cultures
                  on the <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">California coast</placeName>?
                  Whatever the underlying cause, the fact remains that only a hardy, aggressive race
                  could have built up a permanent abode on the volcanic segment known as the
                  "Passing Isle".</span></p>
            <p>For years it has been customary to associate the name of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName> with a sand[-]swept, wind[-]torn,
               desert spot in the vast Pacific, where a howling gale is eternally raging and where
               heavy seas constantly thunder down upon its rocky coast. Fishermen go there
               occasionally&#8212;that type of roving seaman who will go anywhere for
               gain&#8212;since nowhere in the world do better or more enormous quantities of deep
               sea fish abound. Pirates, smugglers, and rum-runners, too, haunt its vicinity. But
               rarely do they land, and when near <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> they remain a good way off-shore. <span type="trope"
                  n="5">It is feared through the curious natural phenomena of the elements that seem
                  to have marked it for their own, and through which it has acquired an evil name.
                  Yet as a field for archaeological research it has proven itself a veritable
                  storehouse.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="7">Numerous theories have been advanced from time to time as to
                  the origin of the Indian tribes of <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                     >California</placeName>, and especially those of the outlying <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>. Some ethnologists have
                  regarded them as the descendants of those prehistoric people who once inhabited
                  most of the Southwest now attributed to the <orgName type="nativeamiercantribes"
                     key="#natam_pueblo">Cliff Dwellers and Pueblos</orgName>. They believe that the
                  later house-building aborigines drove out these people and forced them to move on
                  to <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, where some of
                  them took refuge along the coasts, while others ventured out onto <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> and set up a culture
                  of their own. Here they built up commerce with other islands and <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, as evidenced by the many
                  relics of their ancient trading found today.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="7">Seemingly supporting this theory is the fact that the
                  California tribes are an older racial type than the <orgName
                     type="nativeamiercantribes" key="#natam_pueblo">Pueblos or Cliff
                     Dwellers</orgName>. Skulls of both the coast and island Indians reveal distinct
                  dolichocephalic types, whereas those of the more advanced inhabitants of the
                  Southwest are clearly brachycephalic, or roundheaded. Too, the <orgName
                     type="nativeamiercantribes" key="#natam_pueblo">Pueblos</orgName> indulged in
                  the custom of early applying a cradle-board to the heads of their infants, thereby
                  causing them to grow to maturity with a peculiarly flattened cranium in the
                  occipital. No traces of such artificial deformities have ever been found on either
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs>
                  or <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">islands</placeName></rs>. But many
                  articles of trade from both areas have often been unearthed, from soapstone images
                  to pottery fragments and burnt shards. If there was ever a meeting point of the
                  two opposing cultures, it probably was in northern <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_dval">Death Valley</placeName>, where Pueblo shards of the most
                  primitive black-on-white design and earliest coiled-ware are found in typical
                  California Indian shell-mounds.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="7">In <date when="1926">1926</date> the <orgName key="#lamus"
                     >Los Angeles Museum of History, Science and Art</orgName> sent an expedition to
                     <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, farthest
                  to sea of the entire <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                        Group</placeName></rs>, where it remained for two months, from <rs><date
                        from="1930-10-15" to="1930-12-14">October 15th until December
                     14th</date></rs>. Composed of <persName key="#cwha">Charles W.
                     Hatton</persName>, of the Museum's Indian Department,<persName key="#asa">
                     Arthur R. Sanger</persName>, private collector, and <rs><persName type="author"
                        key="#bbr">the writer</persName></rs>, as field archaeologist for
                        <rs><orgName key="#lamus">the institution</orgName></rs>, the expedition
                  returned with one of the largest and most complete collections of prehistoric
                  Indian remains ever assembled on one trip. Among the material brought back and now
                  on exhibition in <orgName key="#lamus">the Museum</orgName> are great stone
                  mortars and carved pestles, bone- and shell-ornaments, beads of intricate and
                  delicate carving, war-axes and clubs, abalone-shell fishhooks, and a number of
                  fine examples of small fish images carved out of soapstone and pearl shell. Four
                  complete skeletons were found, together with a heterogeneous collection of human
                  and animal bones.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="7">Several hitherto unestablished facts were proved by this
                  trip, among others the certainty that the ancient Indian who dwelt in the most
                  primitive of Stone Age environments on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                        >this barren island</placeName></rs> was possessed of all the physical
                  characteristics, as to mind and body, of the average twentieth century human
                  being! And yet each of the four complete skeletons shows some indication of
                  disease. The most interesting of these is a large one of a native who lived to be
                  an old man, which was discovered to have a disease of the spine that has contorted
                  it entirely out of shape, evidencing that this particular creature must have been
                  a hopeless cripple in his lifetime, in fact, a badly distorted
               hunchback.</span></p>
            <p>No organized expedition had visited <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName> for the purpose of scientific research for years, although in
               the past a number of well-known museums had made lesser investigations, among them
               the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName>
               and the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_southwest">Southwest Museum</orgName>.
                  <persName key="#wabr">Dr. William A. Bryan</persName>, director of the <orgName
                  key="#lamus">Los Angeles Museum</orgName>, had long been contemplating a trip to
               one or another of the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel
                  Islands</placeName> for the purpose of learning more of the habits and life of
                     <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                     islanders</orgName></rs> from what is left of their culture. <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> was finally settled upon as
               being the most fertile field in that it is the most remote and least known. The
               remains on <rs><placeName type="group"
                     key="#i_an; #i_scl; #i_sm; #i_sb; #i_scatalina; #i_scruz; #i_sr">the nearer
                     islands</placeName></rs> have been pretty well cleaned up, but inasmuch as it
               is situated over a hundred miles offshore and is constantly swept by tempestuous
               gales which drive great sheets of stinging sand before them, <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> presents another aspect of the case.</p>
            <p>Completely encircled by dense beds of kelp through which small boats must thread a
               precarious path, it is a desert place where nothing grows except a few straggling
               weed-clumps and cactus-beds and perhaps four inches of buckthorn grass on small
               stretches of the uplands. The sand is forever being shifted in great dunes from place
               to place, uncovering one graveyard for the purpose of concealing another beneath tons
               of billowing grains. Enormous quantities of it are blown into the ocean and it is a
               fact that on one of the days toward the close of the expedition's stay there, the
               combined forces of wind and rain had caused the north shore to present a muddied belt
               of water extending out through the breakers for half a mile. It is for this reason,
               since <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> is
               gradually being blown into the sea, that it is often referred to as the "Passing
               Isle".</p>
            <p>Much prominence has been attached to it from time to time, however, through newspaper
               and magazine accounts of the celebrated "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">Lost Woman</persName></rs>" who was once marooned there for <rs><date
                     from="1835" to="1853">a number of year</date></rs>s. Just where truth begins
               and fiction ends in these stories is difficult to determine, but it is certain that
               there was such a creature, and it is to this fact that archaeology owes a great debt.
                  <span type="trope" n="7">Through her it can form a fairly accurate conception of
                  what the ancient islander resembled, since <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs> was removed from the place after having
                  lived there alone for an indefinite period.</span> As to <rs><date from="1835"
                     to="1853">the term of her isolation</date></rs>, accounts again vary. Some put
               it at twelve years, some at eighteen, and most at twenty.</p>
            <p>Briefly, according to Holder's "<title type="chapter" key="#Holder1910">Channel
                  Islands of California</title>", one of the few incomplete and out-of-date
               authorities of the subject, the history of the "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">Lost Woman</persName></rs>" is this: <span type="trope" n="11">For
                  some time the ancient islanders had been decimated by the raids of warlike tribes
                  on <rs><placeName type="group"
                        key="#i_an; #i_scl; #i_sm; #i_sb; #i_scatalina; #i_scruz; #i_sr">the islands
                        about them</placeName></rs>, and possibly by tribes from <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, although the Indians of
                  the coast are not generally considered to have been as aggressive as <rs><orgName
                        type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">those of
                        the isles</orgName></rs>.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="13">The <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Nicoleños</orgName> also suffered periodic attacks
                  at the hands of the <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                        >Russians</persName></rs>, who made marauding trips down from the <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_aleutian">Aleutian Islands</placeName> in search of
                  otter, seal, and sea elephant, and who not only preferred other people's game but
                  were not at all averse to including in it <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the hapless natives</orgName></rs>. The men were
                  killed and the women carried off.</span></p>
            <p>In <date when="1830">1830</date>, however, undoubtedly urged by the <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">Spanish mission
                  fathers</persName></rs>, the <orgName type="government" key="#gov_mexico">Mexican
                  government</orgName>, then holding <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_upcal"
                     >California</placeName></rs>, sent <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a
                     boat</name></rs> under the command of a certain <persName type="investor"
                  key="#isp">Captain Sparks</persName>, an otter hunter, to remove <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#bhagroup">the few remaining Indians from San
                     Nicolas</persName></rs> to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName>. There, it was thought, they could be afforded better
               protection and incidentally be converted to the ways of God. This boat, the
                     <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better Than Nothing</name></emph>,
               rounded up and started back with <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the few
                     aborigines who were found on the island</persName></rs>. But suddenly one of
               them, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs>, cried
               out that she had left <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                     baby</persName></rs> in the rush. Owing to the conditions of wind and tide so
               well known, <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the boat</name></rs> could not
               turn about and put back to shore. <span type="trope" n="9">So <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> jumped overboard
                  and swam in.</span></p>
            <p>The <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better Than Nothing</name></emph>
               left her there, and that was the last that was seen of her for a fifth of a century.
               Years afterward, <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName>,
               a Santa Barbaran, at the request of the <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_santabarbaramission">Mission of Santa Barbara</orgName>, made a special
               trip to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> in
               search of the woman, whom evidently some chance fisherman had caught sight of
               wandering about the shore. <span type="trope" n="4">After three trips, <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidever</persName> did find and bring her back.
                  She had attempted to hide from him and twice had succeeded, but the last time he
                  gave chase and caught her, persuading her that he did not intend to harm
                  her.</span></p>
            <p>Although Indians were brought from all over the surrounding country, none could
               understand a word of her language. The question, therefore, naturally arises: <span
                  type="trope" n="9">How did <persName type="investor" key="#isp">Captain
                     Sparks</persName> of the <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Better
                        Than Nothing</name></emph>, know that she jumped overboard to go back after
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her
                  child</persName></rs>?</span> No child was found with her, and certainly none was
               brought with her to <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>.
               A few of her words, though their meaning was not recognizable, were said to be of
               Shoshonean origin. Her birdskin dress and various other accouterments were sent to
               the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">Vatican museum</orgName> in
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName> by <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">the mission
                     fathers</persName></rs>. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                  >Nidever</persName> himself cared for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, but she died within six weeks, the belief
               being that the new food she was obliged to eat did not agree with her. She had been
               found living in a hut made of whalebone and ribs with a brush fence erected about it
               to break the wind, and a covering of seal skins.</p>
            <p>Leaving from the <orgName key="#cayachtclub">California Yacht Club</orgName> at
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_wilca">Wilmington</placeName> in a fifty-foot
               cabin cruiser, powered with a Diesel engine, the Los Angeles Museum expedition's
               first glimpse of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, at
               seven o'clock the next morning, was one of a great gray and brown mountain looming
               out of the sea against a rising sun, and encircled at the top by floating mist
               wraiths. Although the trip over in the rather small "Idle Hour" was fairly rough, in
               the early morning the ocean was calm enough to land provisions and equipment.</p>
            <p>It is at this time that the seas that rush against <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> are supposed to be calmest, and the
               first morning was spent in unloading. Among the stores was Mr. Sanger's seven-tube
               radio, including a number of heavy batteries. After being rowed ashore, all these had
               to be carried up a sixty- or seventy-foot bluff. Quarters were taken up at the shack
               of the single inhabitant of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     isle</placeName></rs>, old <persName type="author" key="#nnel">Captain
                  Nelson</persName>, whose unique position was a combination of caretaker of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and
               sheepherder to the 2,500 head of half-wild sheep that roam its expanse. With the aid
               of a wooden sled attached to his decrepit mare, "Mary", the last of the Museum's
               stores were brought up and safely established at the camp.</p>
            <p>The first few days were spent in exploring <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the island</placeName></rs> and locating various sites in which to dig. Unlike
               most excavations, the order of approach here was different, since there were no
               strata by which to go. The method of procedure was sometimes to work together, and
               more often to work a place alone, thereby having three separate research jobs going
               at one time. The sand was soft on the shell-mounds, or kitchen-middens, and it was
               not too much trouble for one man to move several tons a day. But after having dug
               down often to a depth of five or six feet, next morning the site would be found
               filled level again through the action of the wind.</p>
            <p>The west end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>,
               which juts out into a small point, or spit, is literally one vast kitchen-midden
               composed of hundreds of shell-heaps. The south shore, however, was practically
               barren. Moreover, this side is washed by the heaviest seas, and doubtless
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     Indians</orgName></rs> early decided that here was an unprofitable place in
               which to live. The east shore juts into a long spit of sand almost a mile long, but
               it has the fewest mounds of all, though here there are many indications of a much
               older habitation.</p>
            <p>Except for approximately one hundred and fifty yards of encircling shoreline
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the entire island</placeName></rs> is
               in reality a plateau, some eight hundred feet in height, and remarkably flat on top
               for miles about. On the eastern half of this table is found the scant vegetation that
               exists here, the western part being little more than sandy waste with curious
               stretches of lime-formations much resembling small stalagmites and stalactites. A
               number of evidences of Indian dwelling places were found on the highlands, those
               above the west end seeming much older than the others as evidenced by the hard nature
               of the soil and the scarcity of remains. But at times a great sand mound rises up,
               covered in the sun with a glittering shell-heap, where here and there a bone-needle,
               an awl, some fishhooks, exquisitely carved, or the top of a skull might be discovered
               exposed to the air.</p>
            <p>Arriving at the ages of the various relics found is a difficult question and can only
               be done approximately. No trace of Spanish remains of the era of the
                  <emph>conquistadores</emph> was uncovered, nor is there any record of one ever
               having put foot on the shores of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>, though they visited every other island of the <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Group</placeName>. Legend persists that
                  <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, the intrepid leader of the
               Spaniard geographers who first sailed through these waters, is buried in a lead
               coffin somewhere on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa
                  Island</placeName>, a distance of over fifty miles away. <persName key="#asa"
                  >Sanger</persName> has been looking for this grave for over twenty years, but so
               far has found not the slightest clue.</p>
            <p>It is certain that all of the objects encountered on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> are at least one hundred years old, since the
               last natives were removed in <date when="1830">1830</date>, with the exception of the
               so-called "<rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">Lost Woman</persName></rs>",
               who was taken off in <date when="1850">1850</date> and who could not have left many
               relics by herself. Nevertheless, the nature of the soil goes a long way in aiding the
               archaeologist to determine the approximate period at which a particularly hard
               formation of sandstone, which must be hacked into with the aid of a pick and which
               yields up a skeleton or parts of one, was soft, loose sand as on the mounds. Again it
               is a matter of osteology to arrive at the age of a handful of human teeth found in a
               somewhat similar formation, and which are so decayed that holes are worn through the
               hard, bright enamel. In each case, similar finds were removed from each other by a
               distance of five miles in a straight line.</p>
            <p>Near a sample of such teeth as these, <persName key="#cwha">Mr. Hatton</persName>
               unearthed the body of what must once have been a great chief. It was situated in a
               grave on the west end, buried in the conventional flexed posture, and had to be cut
               out of sandstone of rocklike tenacity. Between the hands of this skeleton, which lay
               on its face, was a large white spear-head. The rest of the day was spent in carefully
               sifting out of the sand hundreds of small, square abalone-shell beads and the larger
               pendants, from the quantity of which he must have had a coat sewn. Curiously, three
               other skeletons lay close to this one, all in a direct line, the head of each pointed
               toward the west. Only two skulls were brought in, however, including the first and
               that of a woman who had been interred with only a necklace of large reddish
               beads.</p>
            <p>Merely skimming the tops of those mounds that appeared to be less productive than
               others brought to light an almost unbelievable quantity of material. Likewise the
               amount of castaway shells and bones gleaming on the surface was enormous. By crossing
               one of these great middens on hands and knees and using the eyes even casually many
               little shell fishhooks, bone-awls, harpoons, needles and the like were picked up.
               Sometimes on top of the mounds and sometimes on the sides were found bowls of stone
               and soapstone. Often these were revealed by a faint showing of the rim, to which they
               were buried in the sand. The larger mortars had to be dragged for miles on crude
               wooden sleds over the sands.</p>
            <p>Great numbers of the relics found, especially the stoneware, were smashed most
               completely and thoroughly. This work of demolition was undoubtedly done by
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     Indians</orgName></rs> themselves, and in a most businesslike manner. That
               queer part of the religious belief of the ancient American Indians, which is often
               encountered among other aboriginal tribes in various parts of the world, may account
               for this wholesale destruction of personal utensils and household ware. It was
               thought by the old Indians that any implement a man manufactured was like himself
               possessed of a soul, or spirit. Therefore, when he died his bowls and other artifacts
               were broken and buried with him, or close to him. In this way were they "killed", so
               that their spirits might serve him in the next world!</p>
            <p>Several different methods of effecting this breaking seem to have been practiced on
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. For instance, many
               of the bowls on the plateau were discovered with the bottoms alone smashed out. On
               the mounds toward the west end they were literally broken into the smallest of
               fragments. Others merely had a hole chopped into them. And in order to save
               themselves the labor of making new ones, later <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">Indians</orgName></rs>
               utilized these last by plugging up the holes with asphaltum, a tarry substance washed
               up on the rocks by the sea. One of the mortars brought in by the expedition shows a
               serrated line of chips around its rim, indicating the method by which they were
               sometimes demolished in a professional way.</p>
            <p>At times a series of fragments were unearthed that would fit together perfectly to
               form a complete bowl. These were gathered up, the fragments numbered, and brought
               back for restoration at <rs><orgName key="#lamus">the Museum</orgName></rs>. But
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the old
                     inhabitants of San Nicolas</orgName></rs> apparently foresaw that something
               like this would happen even to their broken utensils. Craftily they worked out a plan
               to prevent it. The archaeologist might find a broken mortar of ten pieces, nine of
               which went into place perfectly. The tenth would be a fragment of another bowl! And
               the missing piece was never found, which leads one to think that it was probably
               either ground into dust or thrown into the ocean.</p>
            <p>For the first week or longer, everything come upon by the expedition had either been
               found before by some previous explorer or else was hopelessly scattered by action of
               the stinging sand and wind. Experience quickly demonstrated the futility of digging
               haphazardly. To tum up anything at all, surface indications must first be revealed.
               Otherwise one might dig on forever. In addition, it was decided that it would be wise
               to construct several large screens to sift every inch of sand about a burial. This
               was a precaution taken to save a skeleton down to the minutest beads and the smaller
               finger and toe bones.</p>
            <p>The first complete and untouched grave was found on the west central plateau by
                  <persName key="#asa">Mr. Sanger</persName>, through the fact that the top of a
               bleached skull protruded above the sand. When dug out and developed the skeleton was
               found to be lying half on its side in a flexed position. The head was quite upright,
               having slipped with the shifting of the earth. <span type="trope" n="7">The skeleton
                  was that of a young man with a very Mongolian cast of skull.</span> A curious
               ossification had joined the pelvis together in one piece so that it resembled nothing
               so much as a saddle. Buried with it were a stone-axe, two throwing-stones shaped like
               doughnuts, and a dish made of abalone-shell with the perforations plugged with the
               usual asphaltum.</p>
            <p>In an old bulletin reporting a former trip by the <orgName type="museum"
                  key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian Institution</orgName> to this island in the last
               century, it was stated that most of the bodies were buried facing eastward. Contrary
               to this, those found by the Los Angeles Museum expedition showed no indication of
               orientation according to some ritual. It was also found that the average depth of the
               graves was about eighteen inches, although this seemingly shallow interment may have
               been due to the moving of the sand dunes.</p>
            <p>Three other skeletons were found and developed for transportation, besides several
               almost complete ones. <span type="trope" n="6">Every so often a scattered pile of
                  bleached bones, which gave every appearance of being the last evidences of some
                  wholesale slaughter, were stumbled upon.</span> It is impossible to say whether
               these are due to the uncovering action of the wind, or whether previous collectors
               had dug them out, taken only what they wanted, and left the rest to decay.</p>
            <p><emph>(To be concluded in the May issue.)</emph></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
