<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="journal"><orgName type="publication" key="#catholicworld">Catholic
                     Library World</orgName></title>
               <biblScope unit="volume" n="49"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue" n="8"/>
               <editor/>
               <publisher/>
               <date when="1978"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName key="#dne"/></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Thompson1978">Scott O'Dell - Weaver of Stories</title>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#sth">Thompson, Sally Anne
                     M.</persName></author>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="340" to="342"/>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <div type="section">
            <p><hi rend="bold"><persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> is the
                  recipient of the <date when="1978">1978</date> Regina Medal Award from the
                     <orgName key="#catholicla">Catholic Library Association</orgName>. When
                     <persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> receives this silver medal
                  on <date when="1978-03-28">Tuesday, March 28</date>, during the <orgName
                     key="#catholicla">CLA</orgName> Convention in <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sl">St. Louis</placeName>, he will become the 20th author and/or
                  illustrator to be recognized for a lifetime dedicated to children's
                  literature.</hi></p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott
                        O'Dell</persName> - Weaver of Stories</hi></title></head>
            <byline><hi rend="bold">by <persName type="author" key="#sth">Sally Anne M.
                     Thompson</persName></hi></byline>
            
            <p><emph><persName type="author" key="#sth">Sally Anne M. Thompson</persName>, Librarian
                  at <orgName type="institution" key="#in_theresa">St. Theresa School</orgName>,
                     <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ph">Phoenix</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_az">Arizona</placeName> is the <date when="1978"
                     >1978</date> Chairman of the <orgName key="#regmedcomm">Regina Medal
                     Committee</orgName>.</emph>
               <hi rend="bold">I</hi>nternationally respected author <persName type="author"
                  key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> has been selected as the 20th recipient of the
               Regina Medal Award. In addition to this latest achievement, <persName type="author"
                  key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> has received three Newbery Honor Awards (for
                  <emph>The King's Fifth</emph>, <emph>The Black Pearl</emph> and <emph>Sing Down
                  the Moon</emph>); the Newbery Medal (for <emph>Island of the Blue
               Dolphins</emph>); and in <date when="1972">1972</date> was the recipient of the Hans
               Christian Andersen Medal (awarded for the complete works of an author).</p>
            <p><rs><orgName type="publisher" key="#houghton">Scott O'Dell's publisher</orgName></rs>
               records "we're proud of what he has given to the international children's book
               community, proud of the fine literature he has created for children&#8212;and very
               proud to be his publisher." It is worthy to note that <orgName type="publisher"
                  key="#houghton">Houghton Mifflin Company</orgName> has published <emph>all</emph>
               of O'Dell's children's books, beginning in <date when="1960">1960</date> with
                  <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>.</p>
            <p>Viewing the majority of his work, one discovers several qualities ever present. The
               quality woven into the grain of his rich tapestry is his own personal
               philosophy. No where does he overtly share innermost feelings or beliefs. These are
               felt or witnessed but not verbalized. From his writings though, we appreciate the
               fact that <persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> is an individual with
               a strong moral sense. He has spent his life intricately meshing bits of his own moral
               fiber into his books, and ultimately into the minds of his readers. His style is
               perceptive, complete with insights, as he skillfully creates depths of texture and
               fiber within his characters. <persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName>
               expresses his point of view discretely through means of symbols and imagery, as
               manifested in <name type="fictional" key="#wty">Tyndale</name>'s not allowing his
               life to be saved by the killing of another human being in <emph>The Hawk That Dare
                  Not Hunt By Day</emph>.</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">The author</persName></rs> is realistic in his
               approach to life. Good is not always rewarded&#8212;<name type="fictional" key="#esa"
                  >Esteban</name> was sentenced to five years in prison for his part in <emph>The
                  King's Fifth</emph>. Evil is not always punished&#8212;<persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#cca">Kit Carson</persName> pillaged, looted, and killed
               as viewed in <emph>Sing Down the Moon</emph>, but became one of our nation's folk
               heroes. People do not always live happily ever after&#8212;<name
                  type="fictional" key="#ccl">Caleb Clegg</name> remained a haunted, driven man even
               after finding the ship's log that proved his innocence in <emph>The Dark
               Canoe</emph>. Woven throughout most of O'Dell's work is his kinship with the sea and
               his abiding love of <placeName type="region" key="#re_sw">the Southwest</placeName>.
               According to <rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">the author</persName></rs>: "my
               father was a railroad man so we moved a lot, but never far. Wherever we went, it was
               into frontier country like <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                  Angeles</placeName> . . . And <placeName type="island" key="#i_ri">Rattlesnake
                  Island</placeName>, across the bay from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San
                  Pedro</placeName>, where we lived in a house on stilts and the waves came up and
               washed us under every day. And sailing ships went by. That is why, I suppose the feel
               of the frontier and the sound of the sea are in my books." The sea is constant in the
                  <emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph>, in Roman's diving for <emph>The Black
                  Pearl</emph> off the coast of <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja"
                  >Baja</placeName>, with the <rs><persName type="group" key="#jcle; #ccl">Clegg
                     brothers</persName></rs> out from <placeName type="island" key="#i_ni"
                  >Nantucket</placeName> in <emph>The Dark Canoe</emph>, and as a vehicle for
               transporting Tyndale's valuable translations in <emph>The Hawk That Dare Not Hunt By
                  Day</emph>.</p>
            <p>After a cruise with his wife <persName key="#ehall">Elizabeth</persName> from
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San Diego</placeName> up to the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_colriver">Columbia River</placeName> on the ship <name
                  type="ship" key="#sh_arcticstar">Artic Star</name>, the <emph>Cruise of the Artic
                  Star</emph> evolved. Into <rs>this delightful book</rs> is spun the texture of the
               cruise and the "frontier." It is decorated and personalized with characters relevant
               to the historical and geographical ports of call along the way.</p>
            <p>The best in historical fiction is consistently exemplified by <persName type="author"
                  key="#sod">O'Dell</persName>. His stories detail qualities which insure
               satisfaction for the reader and lasting interest in his books. Historical events,
               facts and characters recapture the flavor of the time, captivating the reader by
               allowing him to enter a world of romantic appeal, totally encompassed in authentic
               language and custom. Yet, the historical data does not appear as cold facts as in a
               documented commentary, but comes alive as warm essentials.</p>
            <p>O'Dell's stories cause the reader to ponder the effects people have upon each other;
               the character, conduct, morality and ethical values; enabling one to see that human
               nature was the same then as now. Picturesque language, scrupulously accurate details
               such as a church that took three generations to build, all add dimension to the
               authenticity of the stories.</p>
            <p>Readers are helped to understand the past, what the struggle of man has been and why
               people have acted as they have. "Children don't relate to names of battles, dates of
               treaties, to statistics. Like us, they relate to individuals, to emotions they can
               feel within themselves, to stories that arouse their curiosity," said <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName>.</p>
            <p>Perspective and balance are part of the lesson of history and the thoughtful reader
               will see this reflected in the problems and issues of each era <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> covers, from <rs><date from="1861"
                     to="1865">the Civil War period</date></rs> to <emph>The 290</emph>, the whaling
               days of <emph>The Dark Canoe</emph>, the explorations of the Spanish of <emph>The
                  King's Fifth</emph>, to the realization that the <orgName type="military"
                  key="#mi_army">United States Army</orgName> did march the <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_navajo">Navajos</orgName> to <placeName
                  key="#fortsumner">Fort Sumner</placeName> as did <name type="fictional" key="#bmo"
                  >Bright Morning</name> in <emph>Sing Down the Moon</emph>.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> uses history to his advantage.
               He wrote me that "<emph>The Hawk That Dare Not Hunt By Day</emph>
               was very difficult to write because of the material and technical matters.
               I want to acquaint young people with the origins of the language they speak. Also to
               remind them that there are men whom they can emulate to advantage."</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">The master weaver</persName></rs> weaves his
               ideas of human relationships as evidenced in the close family bond between parents,
               child and grandmother in <emph>Journey to Jericho</emph>; man's place in the
               universal scheme, witnessed in Karana's fight for survival; the oft lamented theme of
               man's inhumanity to man in the brutality and cruelty measured out to the Indians
               three hundred years ago by the Conquistadors in <emph>The King's Fifth</emph>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">A</hi>s the reader relates to O'Dell's characters he can come to
               grips with himself, gain an understanding of self. The characters such as <name
                  type="fictional" key="#tba">Tom</name>, <name type="fictional" key="#kar"
                  >Karana</name> and <name type="fictional" key="#esa">Esteban</name> embody the
               hopes and ideals of the reader. This has appeal as a source of challenge and
               enjoyment. Part of this lies in having one's imagination stimulated. <persName
                  type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> breathes life into his characters with
               painstaking craftsmanship; flesh and blood personalities. Characters that are real,
               that live and move in a rotating world. Characters that are not static,
               but individuals that are ever growing, changing and unique in their actions. They
               live their lives as <rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">the author</persName></rs>
               sees them, realistically portraying the whole spectrum of human life with no quick
               and easy solutions to serious problems. The convictions of <rs><persName
                     type="author" key="#sod">the author</persName></rs> are so skillfully tied into
               the pattern of the work that the individual fibers are taken for granted.
                     <rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">The author</persName></rs> hopes that
               the reader is capable of formulating a set of values and a sense of responsibility
               through understanding the complexities of concepts of truth and honesty, as depicted
               by specific situations and vicarious experiences that give insight into the
               characters groping to deal with their problems.</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName>, with rare talent, is able to
               accurately depict characters through revealing speech and incident. He does not tell
               his reader how life is, or how people are capable of behaving, he merely creates the
               situations that force his characters to be themselves.</p>
            <p>He has not subjected his reader to stereotypes that have been common especially in
               books written <date notAfter="1975">before the mid 1970's</date>. Instead, his
               females are respected as individuals, active participants with characteristics
               suitable to their roles. In <emph>The King's Fifth</emph>, the Indian girl <persName
                  key="#zia">Zia</persName> acts as guide and interpreter for the Spanish explorers;
                  <persName type="group" key="#kar">Karana</persName> embodies all the qualities one
               could possibly achieve as she survives her <date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen year
                  isolation</date> on the <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"><emph>Island of
                        the Blue Dolphins</emph></placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>O'Dell stories entertain the reader, hold his attention and make him care about the
               dilemmas of the characters. The reader can vicariously experience the defeats and
               victories of each character. Perhaps this is because he writes about situations
               pertinent to the human condition; the constant battle between good and evil [is]
               obvious even to the pre-adolescent reader. <persName type="author" key="#sod"
                  >O'Dell</persName> is capable of subtly and skillfully weaving this message
               between the written lines of his stories, much as the Navajo weaves her rug, thread
               by thread, to form a complete and beautiful expression of herself.</p>
            <p><emph>Child of Fire</emph> portrays the seriousness of brutality as a way of life.
               But the grim details are used for a purpose; to give the reader as accurate a picture
               as possible of the events taking place in the story and of its setting.
                  <persName type="author" key="#sod">O'Dell</persName> has given the reader what has
               meaning for him. He offered the following explanation to my inquiry about this work:
               ". . . I've been a director, in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd">San
                  Diego</placeName>, of an organization called <orgName key="#crash">Crash,
                  Inc.</orgName> We're funded by <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">the
                  State</placeName> and <placeName type="county" key="#co_sdcounty"
                  >County</placeName> and deal with Chicanos and blacks in several experimental
               houses, <placeName key="#tranquility"> Tranquility Home</placeName>, <placeName
                  key="#halfway">Halfway House</placeName>, and others. I know these kids pretty
               well. What I've written is an attempt to present their problems, how they solve them
               for themselves, and what, if anything, can be done about their solutions. The book
               was a celebration of the Chicano spirit, rather than a put down."</p>
            <p><persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> has made a memorilble
               contribution to the world of children's literature. At an age when most people are
               secure in relaxed, comfortable retirement, <rs><persName type="author" key="#sod">the
                     master weaver</persName></rs> is busily working at his loom, researching and
               writing. <emph>Carlota</emph>, published in <date when="1977">1977</date>, is his
               most recent contribution. His writings have and will stand the test of time, because
               his message is so potent and accurate that it speaks to all
               generations.</p>
            <p>Thus does <persName type="author" key="#sod">Scott O'Dell, master weaver</persName>,
               qualify for <persName key="#wjm">Walter de La Mare</persName>'s quote ". . . only the
               rarest kind of best in anything can be good enough for the young."</p>
            <div type="section">
               <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">Books by <persName type="author" key="#sod"
                           >Scott O'Dell</persName></hi></title></head>
               <p>(all published by <orgName type="publisher" key="#houghton">Houghton
                     Mifflin</orgName>)</p>
               <list>
                  <item n="1"><emph>The Black Pearl</emph> (<date when="1967">1967</date>)</item>
                  <item n="2"><emph>Carlotta</emph> [<emph>Carlota</emph>] (<date when="1977"
                        >1977</date>)</item>
                  <item n="3"><emph>Child of Fire</emph> (<date when="1974">1974</date>)</item>
                  <item n="4"><emph>Cruise of the Artic Star</emph> (<date when="1973"
                     >1973</date>)</item>
                  <item n="5"><emph>The Dark Canoe</emph> (<date when="1968">1968</date>)</item>
                  <item n="6"><emph>The Hawk That Dare Not Hunt By Day</emph> (<date when="1975"
                        >1975</date>)</item>
                  <item n="7"><emph>Island of the Blue Dolphins</emph> (<date when="1960"
                        >1960</date>)</item>
                  <item n="8"><emph>Journey to Jericho</emph> (<date when="1969">1969</date>)</item>
                  <item n="9"><emph>The King's Fifth</emph> (<date when="1966">1966</date>)</item>
                  <item n="10"><emph>Sing Down the Moon</emph> (<date when="1970"
                     >1970</date>)</item>
                  <item n="11"><emph>Treasure of Topo-El-Bampo</emph> (<date when="1972"
                     >1972</date>)</item>
                  <item n="12"><emph>The 290</emph> (<date when="1976">1976</date>) </item>
                  <item><emph>Zia</emph> (<date when="1976">1976</date>)</item>
               </list>
               <p><emph>Author's note: Quotations in this article are from promotional materials
                     supplied by <orgName type="publisher" key="#houghton">Houghton
                        Mifflin</orgName> and from a personal letter from <persName type="author"
                        key="#sod">Scott O'Dell</persName> to <rs><persName type="author" key="#sth"
                           >the author</persName></rs>.</emph></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
