<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#sherald">San Francisco
                     Daily Herald </orgName></title>
               <publisher><orgName type="publisher" key="#foy">Foy,
                  Nugent&amp;Co.</orgName></publisher>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">132</biblScope>
               <date when="1853-10-11"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Santiago1853">From Santa Barbara. </title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="2"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#san">Santiago</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">From <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                        Barbara</placeName>.</hi></title>
               <title type="sub">[Correspondence of the <orgName type="publication" key="#sherald"
                     >San Francisco Herald</orgName>.]</title>
               <title type="sub">ARRIVALS AT <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">SANTA
                     BARBARA</placeName>____IMPROVEMENTS IN TRADE____THE <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                     >NATIVES</orgName></rs> AND THEIR HABITS____MORE OF THE <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamericans" key="#lw">WILD WOMAN</persName></rs>____CAPTAIN
                  BURKE'S RETURN____SQUATTER TROUBLES BECOMING SETTLED____QUARTZ GOLD AND COPPER
                  ORE____ACCIDENT____THE WEATHER____<orgName type="mission"
                     key="#mi_santabarbaramission">MISSION OF SANTA
               BARBARA</orgName>.</title></head>
            <dateline><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">SANTA BARBARA</placeName>, <date
                  when="1853-10-07">Oct. 7, 1853</date>.</dateline>
            <p><rs><persName type="author" key="#editorher">EDITOR OF THE
                  HERALD</persName></rs>:&#8212;<date when="1853-10-06">Yesterday</date> was a busy
               day at <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">this place</placeName></rs>. We had
               five arrivals&#8212;the steamers <name type="ship" key="#sh_goliah">Goliah</name> and
                  <name type="ship" key="#sh_thomashunt">Thomas Hunt</name>, and the brig <name
                  type="ship" key="#sh_fremont">Fremont</name>, from <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>; the steamer <name type="ship"
                  key="#sh_losangeles">Los Angeles</name>, from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sd"
                  >San Diego</placeName>, and the brig <name type="ship" key="#sh_joinville">Prince
                  de Joinville</name>, from the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Island of Santa
                  Rosa</placeName>. The beach at the landing-place was strewn with goods of every
               description. In no other day <date when="1853">this year</date> has so much
               merchandise been unladen here. Though <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> exhibits no improvement in number of buildings or increase in
               population, still its trade has augmented very considerably. The valleys back of, and
               surrounding it, has <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>
               alone as their mart, and yearly the wants of the native Californians become greater
               and more extravagant. Though they refuse to adopt some of our labor-saving
               inventions, they show a disposition rivalius [sic] in dress and imitate us in many of
               our habits. In horseback exercises they certainly have nothing to learn, but in their
               vehicles it would be difficult for any people to be more clumsy; and yet they
               steadily decline substituting our style of carts or wagons instead. Occasionally one
               of the wealthier classes indulges in the use of a carriage, and when they do,
               invariably they choose the oldest and clumsiest style.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="14">A short time since I called to see the <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamericans" key="#lw">Wild Indian woman</persName></rs>, of whom
                        <rs><orgName type="publication" key="#sherald">your paper</orgName></rs> has
                  already spoke.</span> She is living with <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                  >Mr. George Nidever</persName>, an old trapper, who has been on <rs><placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">this coast</placeName></rs> for the <date
                  from="1835" to="1853">last eighteen years</date>. She was brought by <rs><persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">this gentleman</persName></rs> from the
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Island of San Nicolas</placeName>, seventy
               miles distant, and not, as before published, from the <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Island of Catalina.</placeName> No person has yet been found
               that can speak or understand her language. <span type="trope" n="10">By signs she has
                  told <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. N.</persName></rs> that
                     <persName type="nativeamericans" key="#lwchild">her child</persName> was killed
                  and torn to pieces by the wild dogs with which <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> is overrun.</span> Her only dress
               was a sort of gown, sitting high upon the shoulders and reaching nearly to the knees,
               made of the skins and feathers of wild ducks, sewed together with the sinews of the
               seal. The handicraft shown in the manufacture of her needles, sewing stuff, baskets,
               water vessels&#8212;to make all of which a piece of the blade of an old knife seems
               to have been her only tool&#8212;is certainly curious. The water jugs are made of
               split sea-grass woven tightly together in flask form, and the borrom and part of the
               sides daubed over with asphaltum, springs of which are on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>. She has a piece of
               netting made of sinews, some eight feet square, the knitting of which is precisely
               similar to that made for fishing. <span type="trope" n="11">Her food seems to have
                  been chiefly the fat of the seal. Of this she brought some twenty pounds with her.
                  It is rancid and smells awfully; still she relishes it.</span> She is very fond of
               shell-fish, coffee, and liquor of every sort; but does not care for beef, pork,
               bread, nor tea. <span type="trope" n="3">In person she is by far the best looking
                  Indian, male or female, that I have ever seen on <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socalcoast">this coast</placeName></rs>. She has a large, full eye;
                  her forehead is low and broad; her nose slightly aquiline and finely formed; her
                  mouth is rather large, and indicates great firmness; he protruding lower lip gives
                  a haughty tone to her look, and her well set chin fully sustains this trait. She
                  is of medium stature, very masculine in appearance, and shows very little evidence
                  of advanced age.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="6">Undoubtedly she is the last of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericans" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">her
                  race</orgName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p>By the <name type="ship" key="#sh_wednesday">steamer of Wednesday</name>, <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#burke">Captain Burke</persName>, once a noted man on
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">this coast</placeName></rs>,
               arrived here, after an absence of <date from="1840" to="1853">thirteen years</date>.
                  <persName type="seaman" key="#burke">Capt. Burke</persName> settled in <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> in <date when="1825"
                  >1825</date>, and married into one of the wealthy native families. He is
               father-in-law to <persName key="#jke">John Keys, Esq.</persName>, one of the heaviest
               merchants south of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, and
               universally known for his princely hospitality.</p>
            <p>The troubles which threatened some time back in reference with Squatters, are nearly
               subsided, and a very good feeling exists between the American and native
               population.</p>
            <p>I was shown <date when="1853-10-07">to-day</date> some specimens of quartz gold and
               copper ore taken from a spot about fifty miles distant. Both are very rich.</p>
            <p>A <persName key="#man8">young man</persName> from <rs><placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">your city</placeName></rs> fell from his horse <rs><date
                     when="1853-10-06">yesterday</date></rs>, while riding in company with <persName
                  key="#mcc">Mr. McCahill</persName>, of the firm of <orgName type="company"
                  key="#co_taaffe">Taaffe, McCahill &amp; Co.</orgName>, and sustained severe,
               though not serious injury to his right ankle.</p>
            <p>The weather here for a few days past has been excessively hot, owing to the great
               fires in the mountains in the vicinity.</p>
            <p>Should any of the good people of <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">your
                     city</placeName></rs> ever deem in worth their while to visit <rs><placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sb">this town</placeName></rs>, let me advise them not to
               leave it without visiting <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the old
                     Mission</placeName></rs>, or rather what remains of it. <rs><placeName
                     type="mission" key="#mi_sb">The Church</placeName></rs> is now one of the
               finest in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> in exterior
               appearance, and internally it is the best adorned and most tastefully arranged that I
               have yet seen. It contains eleven large paintings and about twenty small ones, all of
               them excellently executed&#8212;indeed, a few are <emph>chef d'ouvres</emph>. The
               ruins of <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">what was once a large Mission
                     settlement</placeName></rs> lie scattered in every direction about
                     <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the Church</placeName></rs>.
               Especially interesting amoung these ruins are the almost complete vestiges of a
               viaduct, reservoir, mill, and holy bathing houses. The walls, arches, cement and
               stone-work of each of these are in good condition; but they now stand merely the
               evidence of former use. A <persName key="#friar1">Friar</persName> of the Franciscan
               order officiates at <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                     Mission</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <byline><persName type="author" key="#san">SANTIAGO</persName>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
