MILES OF HUMAN BONES.

DISCOVERIES OF __group__A PARTY WHO WENT TO __place__SAN NICHOLAS.

__place__The Island Entirely Destitute of Productive Soil&#8212;A few Sheep Found There.

__place__The party who recently went to __place__San Nicholas island on a prospecting tour with a view to taking up goe[v]rnment [government] land, returned after a two days visit on __place__the island. They concluded not to exhaust their rights on land so valueless.

From __pers__Frank Fazzio, who took them over, some interesting details of the trip is [are] learned. __place__The island is about four miles wide by twelve miles long and is located some 70 miles off __place__this coast, almost due south of here. The soil has all been blown off and the rocks are almost entirely bare and destitute of soil, giving __place__the whole island a very barren appearance. On the western side sand is about the only thing seen and this has been blown from the beach clear to the top of __place__the island, 700 or 800 feet high. On the other side of __place__the island, the east side, they found human bones for a distance of five miles, along __place__the beach. They were very think and looked as if it has been a graveyard. They also discovered the remains of huamn bodies on __place__the ridge which runs lengthwise through __place__the island. In some places two skeletons were seen close together as if they had been buried together in the same grave. The wind had blown off what covering of soil that had been thrown over them and it looked quite ghastly. Bones were thickly strewn along __place__this ridge for upwards of three miles. From appearances upwards of 3000 or 4000 __org__Indians must have been buried there.

A shanty which had been built on the west side was found buried clear to the roof in sand. There are now about 2000 sheep on __place__the island and from a sort of rough grass they seem to keep fat. __group__The party went into a __place__cave which afforded __pers__an Indian woman, the sole occupant of __place__the island, a home for __date__seven years. It seems that when her party was leaving __place__the island, that she jumped overboard and swam ashore in the night. Years went by before she was taken off. __group__The party enjoyed the trip immensely, but say __place__the island is not worth much.