MILES OF HUMAN BONES.

DISCOVERIES OF A PARTY WHO WENT TO SAN NICHOLAS.

The Island Entirely Destitute of Productive Soil&#8212;A few Sheep Found There.

The party who recently went to San Nicholas island on a prospecting tour with a view to taking up goe[v]rnment [government] land, returned after a two days visit on the island. They concluded not to exhaust their rights on land so valueless.

From Frank Fazzio, who took them over, some interesting details of the trip is [are] learned. The island is about four miles wide by twelve miles long and is located some 70 miles off this coast, almost due south of here. The soil has all been blown off and the rocks are almost entirely bare and destitute of soil, giving the whole island a very barren appearance. On the western side sand is about the only thing seen and this has been blown from the beach clear to the top of the island, 700 or 800 feet high. On the other side of the island, the east side, they found human bones for a distance of five miles, along the beach. They were very think and looked as if it has been a graveyard. They also discovered the remains of huamn bodies on the ridge which runs lengthwise through the island. In some places two skeletons were seen close together as if they had been buried together in the same grave. The wind had blown off what covering of soil that had been thrown over them and it looked quite ghastly. Bones were thickly strewn along this ridge for upwards of three miles. From appearances upwards of 3000 or 4000 Indians must have been buried there.

A shanty which had been built on the west side was found buried clear to the roof in sand. There are now about 2000 sheep on the island and from a sort of rough grass they seem to keep fat. The party went into a cave which afforded an Indian woman, the sole occupant of the island, a home for seven years. It seems that when her party was leaving the island, that she jumped overboard and swam ashore in the night. Years went by before she was taken off. The party enjoyed the trip immensely, but say the island is not worth much.