<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#sdru">Sacramento Daily
                            Record Union </orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume"/>
                    <biblScope unit="issue"/>
                    <date when="1881-02-19"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sac">Sacramento</placeName>,<placeName
                            type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="article" key="#SacramentoDailyRecordUnion1881">"Pacific Coast
                            Items." </title>
                        <biblScope unit="page" n="8"/>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold">PACIFIC COAST ITEMS.</hi></title>
                </head>
                <p>More fine marble has been found in <placeName type="state" key="#st_utah"
                        >Utah</placeName>.</p>
                <p>A steam flour mill is talked of in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_fabr">Fall
                        Brook</placeName>, <placeName type="county" key="#co_sdcounty">San Diego
                        county</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Squirrel poison killed a number of horses for <persName key="#stanfarm">a
                        Stanislaus farmer</persName> the other day.</p>
                <p><persName type="group" key="#valmen">Some Vallejo gentlemen</persName> are about
                    to send <persName key="#man25">a man</persName> to <placeName type="state"
                        key="#st_ak">Alaska</placeName> to locate mines. <placeName type="county"
                        key="#co_grant">Grant county, New Mexico</placeName>, offers $100 per head
                    for scalps of hostile <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_apache"
                        >Apaches</orgName>.</p>
                <p><orgName type="publication" key="#calist">The <emph>Calistogian</emph></orgName>
                    figures the wine product of <placeName type="county" key="#co_napa">Napa
                        county</placeName> to be 2,910,750 gallons.</p>
                <p>There are at present twenty-two buildings in <placeName type="city"
                        key="#ci_astoria">Astoria, Or.</placeName>, in course of erection.</p>
                <p>A large number of beaver and other fur-bearing animals have recently been trapped
                    in <placeName type="county" key="#co_jackson">Jackson county,
                    Oregon</placeName>.</p>
                <p>The staff of surveyors from <placeName type="county" key="#co_sbern">San
                        Bernardino</placeName> on the <orgName type="company" key="#socalrail"
                        >Southern California Railroad</orgName> are in the canyon, heading toward
                        <placeName type="city" key="#ci_tem">Temecula</placeName>.</p>
                <p>Forty-seven men and women, new arrivals from <placeName type="country"
                        key="#co_sz">Switzerland</placeName>, came to <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_son">Sonoma valley</placeName>
                    <rs><date when="1881-02-16">last Wednesday</date></rs> to permanently locate
                    there.</p>
                <p>Stone coal is now the main excitement in the region of <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_tmgl">Ten-Mile and Looking-Glass, Douglas county,
                        Oregon</placeName>. The impression is that the coal exists under most of the
                    hills of that region.</p>
                <p>Near <placeName type="city" key="#ci_canville">Canyonville, Douglas county,
                        Or.</placeName>, <persName key="#boy5">a 12-year-old boy</persName> was
                    hunting and met two panthers. He wounded one, and was attacked by the animal.
                    Help arrived and both panthers were killed.</p>
                <p>After the late flood, farmers along <placeName type="region" key="#re_bearcreek"
                        >Bear creek, Jackson county, Oregon</placeName>, were busy gathering up
                    rails that had lodged in the willows. The rule is that all rails that are washed
                    on a man's land are considered to be his property.</p>
                <p>The annual report of <persName key="#evarts">P. Evarts</persName>, the
                    Superintendent of the Eureka and <orgName type="company" key="#palrail">Palisade
                        Railroad</orgName>, shows that during the year <date when="1880">1880</date>
                    the net profit was $248,232 94. The same official reports of the <orgName
                        type="company" key="#rhrail">Ruby Hill Railroad</orgName> that its net
                    profit was $80,741 18.</p>
                <p>The work of preparing the old broom factory at <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_soval">South Vallejo</placeName> for a fish cannery is progressing.
                    About $30,000 will be represented in the enterprise. About seventy hands will be
                    employed, and the canning capacity will be 200 cases daily. Canning will begin
                    in about a month.</p>
                <p><placeName type="city" key="#ci_han">Hancock</placeName> is the name bestowed on
                    the new town in the copper district in <placeName type="region" key="#re_mason"
                        >Mason Valley, Esmeralda county, Nev</placeName>. The name was given last
                    fall during the campaign, when it was said it could produce more fights to the
                    quart of whisky than any town of its size in <rs><placeName type="state"
                            key="#st_nv">the State</placeName></rs>.</p>
                <p>In the Art Loan Exhibition at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                        Barbara</placeName> there is a bone needle, a memento of <rs><persName
                            type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the Indian woman</persName></rs> of
                        <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas Island</placeName>, who
                    was rescued by <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain
                        Nidever</persName>. When the tribe was removed to <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, by accident <rs><persName
                            type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this woman</persName></rs> was left
                    behind, and for <date from="1835" to="1853">a long term of years</date> she
                    lived alone on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>.</p>
                <p>At <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sanfe">Santa Fe, New Mexico</placeName>, the
                    other day, a new railroad company known as the <orgName type="company"
                        key="#jvhsrail">Jemez Valley Hot Springs Railroad Company</orgName>, was
                    organized. This is the first company of the kind ever organized by citizens of
                    the Territory. The road will run from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_berna"
                        >Bernalillo</placeName> to the famous <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_jemezsprings">Jemez Hot Springs</placeName>, a distance of about
                    thirty miles.</p>
                <p>A number of citizens of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_lead">Leadville,
                        Co.</placeName>, have asked that the saloons, gaming houses, theaters and
                    bagnios be closed on Sunday. <persName key="#attorney">The City
                        Attorney</persName> was instructed to draw up an ordinance to that effect,
                    including also the business houses. The <orgName key="#merchasc">Merchants'
                        Protective Association</orgName> have called a meeting to protest.</p>
                <p>At <placeName key="#clarkranch">Clark Ranch</placeName>, near <placeName
                        type="city" key="#ci_lead">Leadville, Col.</placeName>, a miner named
                        <persName key="#miner">Gavin</persName> was recently, while in his cabin,
                    buried under a snow-slide. The fire was out, and soon he was in darkness. He
                    must escape, so he began to dig a tunnel. He worked till his hands were benumbed
                    and frozen. He worked thus for six days and escaped, but is not expected to
                    live.</p>
                <p>The principal losses of cattle in <placeName type="state" key="#st_wy"
                        >Wyoming</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_co"
                        >Colorado</placeName> and <placeName type="state" key="#st_neb"
                        >Nebraska</placeName> have been on the <placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_laramie">Laramie plains</placeName> and along the line of the
                    railroad toward the east and on the south, and the severest have been on the
                    ranges between the <placeName type="region" key="#re_nplatte">North</placeName>
                    and <placeName type="region" key="#re_splate">South Platte rivers</placeName>,
                    east of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_jules">Julesburg</placeName>. In the
                    sections mentioned 10 to 15 per cent. of the cattle have died, and in some
                        <placeName type="state" key="#st_co">Colorado</placeName> herds the loss has
                    gone as high as 50 per cent.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
