<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#dailypress">Daily
                     Press</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">162</biblScope>
               <date when="1881-04-13"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="review" key="#GFM1881">An Earthly Paradise. A Stranger's View of
                     Santa Barbara, and Her Surroundings</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="4"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#gfm">M., G. F.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head><title type="main"><rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">AN EARTHLY
                           PARADISE</placeName></rs>.</title>
                  <title type="sub">A Stranger's View of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                        Barbara</placeName> and her Surroundings.</title></head>
               <byline>(Correspondence of the <!--add ref to this doc when acquired-->Clinton[,]
                  Mass., <orgName type="publication" key="#clintoncourier"
                  >Courier</orgName>.)</byline>
               <dateline><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">SANTA BARBARA, Cal.</placeName>, <date
                     when="1881-01">Jan. 1881</date>.</dateline>
               <p>At <placeName type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName> the
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">[co]ast of California</placeName>
                  makes a sudden turn from a southerly to an easterly direction, and runs east and
                  west for fifty miles. About midway on <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socalcoast">this coast</placeName></rs> facing toward the south and
                  entirely surrounded by mountains lies <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>. The cold winds have no chance to get at this little
                  valley, protected as it is by the <placeName type="region" key="#re_santaynezmts"
                     >Santa Inez range</placeName>. [sic] which rises 4,000 feet above the sea. The
                  normal southerly direction of the coast line is continued from <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName> to below <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName> by <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#i_chi">high and mountainous islands</placeName></rs>, on
                  one of which, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName>,
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an Indian
                     woman</persName></rs> spent <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen
                        years</date></rs> alone. <rs><title type="article" key="#Hardacre1880_SM"
                        >The story</title></rs> of this woman's solitary confinement was given in
                  full in <title type="article" key="#Hardacre1880_SM"
                     ><emph>Scribner's</emph></title> for <rs><date when="1880-09">September
                        last</date></rs>. <rs><placeName type="region" key="#i_chi">These
                        islands</placeName></rs> form a barrier against all storms and soften the
                  asperity of all winds blowing from the sea. There we see that nature has done all
                  in her power to make the climate perfect.</p>
               <p>The mean winter temperature is 58° F. and the difference between the Winter and
                  the Summer is only 15°; then it is never cold in the Winter or hot in the Summer.
                  It is very seldom that a frost is experienced, and therefore the flowers bloom the
                  year through. Formerly nearly all the houses were made of adobe, but since the
                  Americans have come, neat little cottages and elegant dwellings have sprung up,
                  and fine business blocks have been built. A great many of the old adobes still
                  exist, however, and add a picturesque appearance to <rs><placeName type="city"
                        key="#ci_sb">the town</placeName></rs>. They are built of sun-dried bricks
                  and retain their muddy color; the roofs are covered with tiles. Imagine a red
                  earthenware drain-tile cut in halves longitudinally, making a semi-cylinder; these
                  are placed in rows on their convex surfaces, lapping over like shingles; then to
                  cover the cracks between two tiles, a third is placed over them on its concave
                  face. The whole makes a heavy and not very protective, but yet a very picturesque
                  covering.</p>
               <p>The main business thoroughfare is <placeName key="#state">State
                  street</placeName>, and extends back two miles, directly from the steamboat wharf.
                  The smaller streets branch off to the right and left like lesser arteries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head><title type="section"><placeName key="#arling">THE
                     ARLINGTON</placeName></title></head>
               <p>[is] the principal hotel, and is unequalled [sic] south of <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>. The grounds are filled with choice
                  varieties of semi-tropical plants and deer captured in the mountains. Nearly every
                  little cottage has its pretty garden patch, and the people seem to vie with each
                  other [in] keeping their grounds neat and inviting. In many of these gardens can
                  be seen from seventy-five to ninety varieties of roses, geranium hedges,
                  heliotrope, and fuchsias trained over the piazzas and full of blossoms, calla
                  lilies four feet high and almost as common as weeds. The streets are shaded by the
                  peculiar eucalyptus and the pepper tree. The eucalyptus or blue gum is a native of
                     <placeName type="country" key="#co_aus">Australia</placeName>, and grows
                  straight and spindling to an immense height. The pepper has all of the grace of
                  the willow, and is in addition an evergreen which in the Winter is covered with
                  long panicles of bright red berries. In <rs><placeName type="region"
                        key="#re_socal">this country</placeName></rs> these trees grow so fast that
                  in five years they will shade a house. In short, <rs><placeName type="city"
                        key="#ci_sb">the whole town</placeName></rs> is one continuous garden.</p>
               <p>On <rs><date when="1881-11-24">Thanksgiving day</date></rs>
                  <rs><persName key="#preacher">one of the local preachers</persName></rs> delivered
                  a sermon in which he showed that his congregation had cause to be profoundly
                  thankful for their good fortune in having such a place as <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> to live in, discoursing to some length
                  on the different advantages of the same. Then, thinking he had dwelt long enough
                  on earthly matters, he proceeded to say that the best of things must have an end,
                  that they all must die some time and go to another world. He then endeavored to
                  describe the abode of the blessed, and exhorted his listeners to so live that they
                  should go there after death. In short the general impression left on the minds of
                  his hearers was that heaven was really a very good place to go if&#8212;if [sic]
                  they could not live in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName>. It is needless to say that the inhabitants of
                        <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">this earthly
                     paradise</placeName></rs> thought it a remarkably fine sermon.</p>
               <p>Among the foothills, about 300 feet above the sea level, stands</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head><title type="section"><rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">THE OLD
                           MISSION</placeName></rs></title></head>
               <p>built by <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats">the Spanish
                        padres</orgName></rs>, <rs><date notAfter="1781">one hundred years
                        ago</date></rs>. It is built of adobe and sandstone in the Moorish style of
                  architecture, is painted white, and with its two towers is a land mark for the
                  country around. <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">This
                        Mission</placeName></rs> is a curious and interesting place. It is still
                  kept up and there are five monks residing there at the present time. The walls are
                  eight feet thick, and are covered on the inside with pictures, some of which were
                  painted in <placeName type="country" key="#co_spain">Spain</placeName>, long
                  before <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the Mission</placeName></rs>
                  itself was built. There are also a great many carvings in wood, marvelously well
                  done; these were executed by the Mexican Indians. We made the acquaintance of
                     <persName type="missionfather" key="#francoir">Padre Francoir</persName>, who
                  showed and explained to us the many interesting features of the place. In the
                  vestry room we saw the antique vestments of <rs><orgName type="church"
                        key="#ch_catholic">the Church</orgName></rs> heavily wrought in gold and
                  silver by the Spanish nuns; huge solid silver candlesticks and golden anchors.
                  Then with great care <persName type="missionfather" key="#francoir">Father
                     Francoir</persName> unlocked a little gold casket, and lying beneath a glass
                  plate was disclosed a bit of a bone formerly belonging to <persName key="#barb"
                     >Santa Barbara</persName> herself. Away up in the old tower is a chime of
                  bells, not especially musical, but "Like sweet bells jingled, out of tune and
                  harsh." They seem to think it is necessary to ding them at all hours of the day
                  and night, and they certainly do make a most infernal racket. At a little distance
                  in the rear are <rs><placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sb">the
                     Mission</placeName></rs> water works, which furnish <rs><placeName type="city"
                        key="#ci_sb">the city</placeName></rs> with water. The water is brought from
                  a mountain ca–on and is exceedingly hard.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head><title type="section">REMARKABLE EQUESTRIANISM.</title></head>
               <p>The amusements prevalent here are, first, horseback riding&#8212;every one
                  rides&#8212;they use the little broncho ponies and the great Mexican saddles,
                  which almost cover up diminutive steeds. But to see riding, one must see the
                  Mexicans themselves. Imagine a swarthy skinned, black-haired individual in a white
                  sombrero and fiery red necktie, galloping along a little "calico" horse, with long
                  flapping stirrup leathers, a Mexican bit and bridle, with the lines ending in a
                  lash, which is twirled in the right hand of the rider. How they can ride! Not
                  according to our severe method in the East, but easily and gracefully. It is said
                  they can spread a blanket on the ground, run a horse onto it and turn him there. I
                  have seen them ride along at full speed and pick a hat from the ground. They are
                  like Centaurs. So much for the "Greaser." He can ride and throw the riata. These
                  are his only accomplishments. <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">The
                        town</placeName></rs> is fast becoming a New England settlement. The
                  Mexicans are being pushed to the wall and very bitter they feel toward the
                  Americans, who are taking possession of <rs><placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                        >their beautiful country</placeName></rs>.</p>
               <p>Another amusement is picnic[k]ing on the beach and surf bathing; the water is so
                  warm that one can go in any season of the year. A ride of six miles up into the
                  mountains takes one to the <placeName type="region" key="#sulspr">Hot Sulphur
                     Springs</placeName>, where one can take a bath in different springs in the
                  rocks with the temperature varying from 115 degrees F. to 50 degrees; 115 degrees
                  is fully hot enough, and just about as much as one can stand. <rs><placeName
                        type="region" key="#sulspr">These springs</placeName></rs> are said to be a
                  sure cure for all rheumatic complaints.</p>
               <p>A ride of fifteen miles takes one to the big ranches of <placeName key="#holranch"
                     >Hollister</placeName>, <placeName key="#cooranch">Cooper</placeName> and
                     <placeName key="#storanch">Stow</placeName>. <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#holl; #coop">The first two men</persName></rs> raise almonds, English
                  walnut[s], (which are grown in their perfection here), apricot s [sic], limes,
                  etc. <persName type="frontiersman" key="#coop">Cooper</persName> raises the same
                  variety, but devotes the greater part of attention to olives and to the production
                  of olive oil. He is now producing an immense quantity, and although his price per
                  bottle is 25 cents more than that of the French oil, he cannot begin to supply the
                  market. <rs><placeName type="group" key="#holranch; #cooranch; #storanch">These
                        ranches</placeName></rs> were formerly over-run with grasshoppers, which
                  came over from the <emph>mesa</emph> (table-lands) opposite, in clouds. Now the
                  farmers go over in the breeding season and plow all of the eggs under ground. In
                  this way they avoid the huge swarms.</p>
               <p>The farmers here cannot afford to raise vegetables for the market, the Chinese
                  gardeners being their competitors. It is astonishing to see how cheaply they can
                  afford to sell. A family can get all they can use in a day for five cents; for
                  example, one can get two bunches of celery, two quarts of tomatoes, some turnips
                  and a carrot, for the regular sum of five cents. They raise as a general thing six
                  crops a year from a single piece of ground.</p>
               <p>In the character of any one who has lived any time in <placeName type="state"
                     key="#st_cal">California</placeName>, cordiality is the first thing noticed;
                  the ability to tell big yarns is the next; (by the way I hope the readers of the
                     <!--add ref to this doc when acquired--><orgName type="publication"
                     key="#courant"><emph>Courant</emph></orgName> will not think that I have lived
                  here long enough to be influenced.) Every where the stranger is welcomed and made
                  to feel at home immediately. It is so different here in this respect from cold
                     <placeName type="region" key="#re_ne">New England</placeName>. I suppose it is
                  all due to the climate. In my next letter I hope I may have something interesting
                  to say of a journey on horse-back from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName> to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los
                     Angeles</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
