<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#queanage">Queanbeyan
                     Age</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume"/>
               <biblScope unit="issue"/>
               <date when="1879-05-07"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_quean">Queanbeyane</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_nsw">New South Wales</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#TheQueanbeyanAge1879">A Female Crusoe</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="4"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#dne"> </persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">A <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">FEMALE
                        CRUSOE</persName></rs>.</title></head>
            <p>THE <orgName type="publication" key="#sfcall">San Francisco <emph>Call</emph>
                  [sic]</orgName> contains <title type="article" key="#SanFranciscoChronicle1879">an
                  interesting account</title> of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">an
                     Indian woman</persName></rs> who was accidentally abandoned on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas Island</placeName>, off the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">coast of South California</placeName>, and
               spent <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high">18 years</date></rs>
               alone there before she was rescued. The fact of her existence was discovered by
                     <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">a man</persName></rs> who went
               from the <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">mainland</placeName></rs> to hunt
               for others [otters], and who found footprints sunk deeply in the ground. He was
               unable to follow up these indications for <rs><date when="1853">nearly three
                     years</date></rs>, when <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >one</persName></rs> of <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">a party who accompanied
                     him</persName></rs> came suddenly upon <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the object of their search</persName></rs>. She was in a small
               circular enclosure made of brushwood, about 5 feet high and 6 feet in diameter, with
               a small opening on one side. She was clothed with a garment made of skins of the
               shag, a species of duck that can neither walk nor fly. This garment reached almost to
               her ankles when she stood erect. She was sitting cross-legged, skinning seal-blubber
               with a rude knife made of a piece of hoop-iron driven into a piece of wood. There was
               no covering on her head, except a thick matted mass of hair, of yellowish-brown
               colour, probably owing to exposure to the sun and weather; it was, in short, as if
               the ends had rotted off. There were some wild dogs on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, a few of which kept near her, and
               seemed to regard her as a mistress. She had lived on a plant resembling cabbage,
               called by Californians palo santo, and a root known by the name of cocomite
               [corcomite], also blubber of the various kinds of seals, &amp;c. She had a rude
               apparatus for catching shellfish, and strong fishing lines made of seal sinews, which
               seemed to indicate that she fished in the ocean. <span type="trope" n="3">The
                  expression of her face was pleasing, her features were regular, her complexion
                  much fairer, and her form more symmetrical, than that of the Indian women on the
                  adjoining mainland. Some suspect that she belonged to <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aleuts">a tribe much further
                        north</orgName></rs>,</span> [sic] <span type="trope" n="10">She could not
                  understand anything said to her in any of the Indian dialects of <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_socal">South California</placeName>; but she had a
                  wonderful capacity for conversing by signs.</span> She retained all her teeth, but
               they were worn low, supposed to be due to her chewing tough and hard articles of
               food. Her age appeared to be 50 years. She bowed to all who came near her, greeting
               them with a smile. <span type="trope" n="1">She accompanied <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">her
                        discoverers</persName></rs> to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">their
                        vessel</name></rs>, but her conduct at once convinced them that she retained
                  the virtue of female modesty.</span> She showed singular dexterity in making water
               vessels from grass and asphaltum, a substance which is plentiful both on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and the
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">mainland</placeName></rs>. She
               seemed to recognize the various appliances of civilization. She died about seven
               weeks after reaching the <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_mld"
                     >mainland</placeName></rs>, partly from dysentery, brought on by eating fruits
               and vegetables. <persName type="missionfather" key="#jru">Padre Genzalez
                  [sic]</persName>, the superior of the <orgName type="mission"
                  key="#mi_santabarbaramission">mission of Santa Barbara</orgName>, has sent her
               dress of shagskins and her baskets and implements to <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName>, to the <rs><orgName type="museum"
                     key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">Museum of the Propaganda</orgName></rs>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
