THE LOST WOMAN.

A Grossly Erroneous Version of the Story.

<hi rend="bold">Joaquin Miller Writes History to Suit Himself&#8212;The Location of the Channel Islands&#8212That "Castle."</hi>

The story of the Indian woman who lived for eighteen years alone on San Nicolas island has been written of frequently and by some of our best writers. Mrs. Helen Hunt Jackson thought the theme worthy an article from her pen, and Mrs. Lucy A. Brinkerhoff furnished a readable and well-written sketch. Hardly a newspaper in the state has lacked one or more articles concerning the lone dweller on the faraway island. Indeed the subject has been written up so many times that I supposed everyone must be acquainted with the salient points of the story. In this, however, I was mistaken for even now comes the Cincinati Times Star with an account of the story written by no less a person than Joaquin Miller, the long-haired poet of the Sierras. To a person unfamiliar with the truth concerning the lost woman, Mr. Miller's sketch would be found very romantic and interesting, but to people who are in possession of the truth smacks too strongly of the novelist for it is grossly erroneous in almost every part. Probably Mr. Miller has bcome so habituated to the use of the well-known poetic license that he finds it impossible to restrain his pen to the straight and narrow path of truth.

I do not purpose to infli[ct] the whole known history of the remarkable woman upon my readers. I simply wish to note some of the grossest errors fa[llen] into by Mr. Miller, and perhaps show that the people living on the coast are not the hard-hearted race he would make them out.
 
First, I wish to call attention to the error Mr. Miller makes in regard to the location of San Nicolas island. He says it is only twenty miles from Santa Barbara. To people who live here this statement is preposterous. Santa Cruz is the nearest land off shore from Santa Barbara and by a straight line that is twenty five miles distant. But the woman lived on San Nicolas island, which is still more distant. By reference to the chart issued by the U. S. Coast and Geodetic Survey we find San Nicolas is forty-nine miles from Santa Cruz, and that by a straight line drawn from Santa Barbara to San Nicolas the distance is seventy-seven and one half miles. But to draw this line we must pass over the great island of Santa Cruz.

Mr. Miller says the steamer Winfield Scott was wrecked on a still smaller island than San Nicolas, not far away. This is an error also. The steamer was wrecked on the middle Anacapa, distant forty-nine miles from San Nicolas. Wouldn't a person need a wonderful pair of eyes and a powerful glass to enabel an object no larger than a woman to be seen forty-nine miles away[?] Yet Mr. Miller says: "The wreckers and [ot]hers saw the woman [not] infrequently."

Prof. George Davidson, of the [U.] S. Coast and Geodetic Survey, in commenting on the savage of Cabrillo through the Santa Barbara Channel and speaking of the Santa Barbara island which lies between the mainland and San Nicolas says "Supposing he (Cabrillo) sailed from the north harbor of Santa Catalina island to the throat of the Santa Barbara channel reckoned as lying between Anacapa island and Point H[ueneme] he passed not nearer than fifteen miles to Santa Barbara island and fourty-two miles to San Nicolas island. The former (Santa Barbara) is visible in clear weather with a sharp loockout; the latter (San Nicolas) is not visible unless by extrodinary refraction."

What did Mr. Miller mean when he used this expression, "and so the long, black and barren mountains of land away to the south was as inaccessible to them as the moon is to us." There is no land south of San Nicolas island. The vast, the boundless waste of the Pacific ocean only is seen or found.

He says: "They had queer little houses of stone [on] the one low cliff." This assertion will be a genuine surprise to any one who has made a study of the island aborigines. The fact is, ordinarily their dwellings were mean shelters made of brush and their most pretentious buildings were made by thrusting the ribs of stranded whales into the ground around a circle: the upper ends brought together to a peak, and the whole covered with the skins of seals and similar animals, the seams being sewed together with sinews.

Mr. Miller draws a very pathetic picture of the lone woman standing on a pyramid of heaped-up stones[,] watching the ships pass by. He tells how she spent years in building her little fortress, "and she built it with all the ease and skill of a trained engineer." This and the little tower she had built on top, "where she could at last lie down and die," make a mighty pretty little edifice, and we actually hesitate ere we lay our vandal hands on it and topple it over. But we must. The cool, calm, unaffected, unromantic fact is, that it is all arrant bosh&#8212;the most unmitigated sentimental rot&#8212;good for fiction, but mighty mean for fact. The woman built no castle at all. She accepted her lot and was contented to industriously accumulate provisions without wasting her time in posing as a feathered biped on a pile of rocks.

Now, one word as to why the woman was not rescued sooner. The island on which she lived is a good ways from Santa Barbara. It is a difficult place on which to land&#8212;there is only one place where it can be done in safety&#8212;and the prevalence of heavy gales of wind in many months of the year prevents most people from ever visiting it, yet many attempts were made, though it was not certain the woman was alive. Mr. Miller affirms that the ocean at San Nicolas is smooth and the landing easy. This is all guess work on his part, and I do not believe he ever was on the island at all. He probably mistook it for Anacapa.

I will close this article by quoting from the statement of John Nidever, who commanded the party that rescued her. There were four Mission Indians, Charles Brown and an Irishman in the company (nary a Boston bean [setor] in the lot, though Miller says the [...]

[...] the ground within the enclosure, and which no doubt served as a bed.

Within the enclosure&#8212;made of whale ribs, covered with brush&#8212;was a smouldering fire, and without a large pile of ashes and another of bones, which would indicate that this had been her abode for a long time. To the surprise of Brown, the woman recieved him with much dignity and politeness, bowing and smiling with ease and self-possession. As fast as the men came up she greeted them in the same way. The men seated themselves on the ground around, the woman all the while talking, (womanlike) although not a word of hers could be understood, although one Indian spoke several dialects. From a sack or bag made of grass she took some roots, known among the Californians as the "carcomites," and another root whose name I did not learn, and placed them in the fire. When they were roasted she offered them to us to eat. We were now desirous of taking her on board the schooner. We commenced by making signs for her to go with us, but she seemed unable to comprehend them till we intimated that she must gather up all her food, when she set about the work with the greatest alacrity." After she arrived in Santa Barbara Mr. Nidever took her to his home where she lived from that time on. Capt. Henry Carnes saw the woman and describes her as being rather small, with weather-beaten dark skin.	LORENZO G. YATES.