<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#flpopmo">Frank Leslie's
                     Popular Monthly</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
               <date when="1892-12-01"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city"/><placeName type="state" key="#st_ny">New
                     York</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Eames1892">Three Weeks on a Weird Island</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="671"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#nea1">Eames, Ninetta.</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><date notAfter="1892-10-31">THREE WEEKS</date></rs> ON
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">A WEIRD
                  ISLAND</placeName></rs>.</title></head>
            <byline>BY <persName type="author" key="#nea1">NINETTA EAMES</persName>.</byline>
            <p>FAR up in the intense ebony of the sky the stars were having a gala time of it,
               elbowing each other to blink at mortals, or flinging a brilliant rocket down the
               sweeping curve of the vast dome that met the invisible sea line. Though the evening
               was far advanced, we were in no mood to exchange the warm, sweet ocean breeze for the
               stifling air of the cabin.</p>
            <p>There were five of us sprawling about the cockpit: the <persName key="#rbra">Rev.
                  Rollo Brand</persName>, my uncle <persName key="#ebru">Edward Bruner</persName>,
                  <persName key="#bor">Professor Borland</persName>, his son <persName key="#lbor"
                  >Leroy</persName>&#8212;a college youth about my own age&#8212;and <rs><persName
                     type="author" key="#nea1">myself</persName></rs>. Captain Conlan's angular
               figure was dimly outlined at the wheel, and my eyes lazily took note of the tiny
               flare that was regularly omitted from his short pipe. A pause had fallen upon the
               conversation, and the comprehensive hush of the ocean night was unbroken save for the
               ripple of water under the bows, and the occasional strain and creak of the rigging.
               Little used to the sea, there was to me a penetrating mystery in this vague
               commingling of the firmaments, and our conscious nearness to the great pulsating
               heart of the deep. Mr. Brand's cordial voice gave an electric jar to my mood.</p>
            <p>"What time are we making, <persName key="#conl">captain</persName>?"</p>
            <p>The black silhouette at the wheel jerked its lantern jaws first to leeward, then
               aloft at the black hollow of the canvas and the inky spire of the mast.</p>
            <p>"Well, sir, 'cordin' to my ree'nin', 'bout five knots an hour. If this breeze keeps
               stiddy there won't be no need to fire up the engine.["]</p>
            <p>We were aboard the small auxiliary steam sloop <emph><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_hattie">Hattie</name></emph>, bound for <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, one of the <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> off the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_socalcoast">Santa Barbara coast</placeName>.</p>
            <p>"We'll likely reach <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs> by sunrise," <persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName>
               remarked, letting his hand rest affectionately on my shoulder.</p>
            <p>"Hardly that early, sir," <persName key="#conl">the captain</persName> rejoined,
               shifting his position, and giving an audible puff to his pipe by way of emphasis.
               "You see it's eighty miles to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that thar
                     island</placeName></rs>, and startin' at three this afternoon, I take it we'll
               be makin' good time if we're ashore in the mornin'."</p>
            <p>My heart leaped in anticipation, and uncle's fingers fell to beating a gentle tattoo.
               Though past the prime of life, I knew he keenly sympathized with my youthful
               enthusiasm. Was I not bound for <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">a wild,
                     uninhabited island</placeName></rs>, the scene of many a bygone aboriginal
               battle, and the home of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a lone
                     woman</persName></rs> for <date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen long
                  years</date>? Indeed, the latter thought was more or less uppermost in the minds
               of all the party, as Mr. Brand's next words proved.</p>
            <p>"I wish I could get at the sober truth of that lost-woman story. It has been so
               exaggerated by romance writers that one doesn't know what to believe."</p>
            <p><persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName> straightened himself with a prodigious
               shrug, and said, heartily:</p>
            <p>"Why, as to that, I can give you the plain facts, for I heard them a dozen times from
                  <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> himself, who
               brought her off <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>
               <rs><date when="1853">nearly forty years ago</date></rs>. Boy that I was, I well
               recall how people flocked to see <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                     woman</persName></rs>, <rs><persName key="#eames">father</persName></rs> among
               them, with me holding on to his hand. Somehow I had imagined she was tall and
               swarthy, with an untamed air and a fierce, guttural voice. I saw instead a little
               woman with lightish hair and eyes, and ruddy cheeks singularly unwrinkled for one
               upward of fifty years old. Her feet and hands were small, and her voice and manner so
               coaxing and gently that the children in particular felt greatly drawn to her."</p>
            <p>"Do you mean to tell me she was not an Indian?" questioned <persName key="#rbra">Mr.
                  Brand</persName>, greatly interested.</p>
            <p>By the light streaming through the companion-way we saw <rs><persName key="#ebru">my
                     uncle</persName></rs> slowly shake his head, but before his puzzled thought
               found utterance Professor Borland's suave voice interposed:</p>
            <p>"There is little doubt in my mind that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                     >the woman</persName></rs> was an Aztec. History tells us the first explorer of
               all these <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> was the
               Spanish navigator <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>, who came
               here in <date when="1542">1542</date>. He speaks of <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">these
                     island races</orgName></rs> as being a superior people, and the account he
               gives of their appearance and habits, and my own ethnographic research, convince me
               they were descendants of the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_aztec"
                  >Aztecs</orgName>, once the most renowned nation in <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_mex">Mexico</placeName>. Though hardly more than half a century has
               elapsed since they thronged <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs>, their extinction is now so complete as to make even
               their name a matter of conjecture."</p>
            <p>When <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> ceased speaking,
                     <rs><persName key="#ebru">uncle</persName></rs>, who had listened to him with
               deference, gave a preparatory cough, and continued:</p>
            <p>"Well, I suppose you want to the story from the beginning, which dates back to <date
                  when="1835">1835</date>, when <persName key="#gni">John [sic] Nidever</persName>
               used to go otter hunting on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>, or <emph>Ghalashat</emph>, as <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the natives</orgName></rs>
               called <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. In those
               days <rs><orgName type="group" key="#rfurcompany; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">the
                     Alaska Indians</orgName></rs> came down every season for skins. They were a
               cruel race, and made war upon <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the islanders</orgName></rs>, who were peaceful in
               their habits and comely to look upon. Their stone weapons were a poor makeshift
               against the superior implements of war carried by <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">the Indians</orgName></rs>. Finally
                     <rs><orgName type="group" key="; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">the
                     Alaskans</orgName></rs> mastered them utterly, killing all the men and boys,
               and keeping the woman for slaves during their stay on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>"When the season for seal hunting was past <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#rfurcompany; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">the Indians</orgName></rs>
               went back to <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_russam">their northern
                     home</placeName></rs>, leaving the unhappy women on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. Years afterward those who survived the
               hardships of their lot were rescued by <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the good padres of the Missions of Santa
                     Barbara</persName></rs> and <placeName type="city" key="#mi_ventura">San
                  Buenaventura</placeName>, who sent over the little schooner <emph><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es Nada</name></emph> to bring them away.
               When <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the unfortunates</persName> were all
               aboard one of them made frantic signs that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs> was left behind. <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#chu; #isp">The kind-hearted captain</persName></rs> allowed
               her to return to fetch it. She staid so long, and a stiff wind rising, <rs><persName
                     type="group"
                     key="#1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                     >the men</persName></rs> feared <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                     vessel</name></rs> would be grounded on the rocks, and so set sail without her.
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#chu; #isp">The captain</persName></rs> had
               every intention of returning for <persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                  woman</persName>, but several weeks later the <emph><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es Nada</name></emph> literally fulfilled her
               name&#8212;'Worse than Nothing'&#8212;by capsizing off the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_thegoldengate">Golden Gate</placeName> and going to pieces. She was the
               only craft on <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName>
               larger than an Indian canoe or the boats of the seal hunters.</p>
            <p>"Though it was rumored a woman was left on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>, no man was willing to risk his life in an open boat across
               nearly a hundred miles of intervening sea. As years passed people talked less and
               less of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the forlorn
                  creature</persName></rs>, the general opinion being she must have long since
               perished from want and exposure. <rs><orgName type="missionfathers" key="#misfats"
                     >The priests</orgName></rs> continued to offer two hundred dollars for her
               recovery, but despaired of ever having a demand for the money.</p>
            <p>I think it was in <date when="1851">185</date>1 that <persName key="#gni">John [sic]
                  Nidever</persName> and <persName type="seaman" key="#tje">Tom Jeffries</persName>
               made a trip to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> after sea
               otter. In the wet sand of the benach they saw the footprints of a human being.
               Judging from the size, they were those of a child or woman. A quarter of a mile
               inland were three round pens made of brush. Beside these inclosures were stakes of
               driftwood with strips of blubber drying on them. <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #tje; #nativeamericans">The men</persName></rs> looked about for
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, but a
               gale commencing to blow, they hurried back to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever"
                     >the schooner</name></rs>, anchored in the lee of <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>"<rs><date when="1852">A year later</date></rs>
               <persName key="#gni">Nidever</persName> again visited <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. <persName type="missionfather" key="#jru"
                  >Father Gonzales</persName> had assured him the tracks he had seen must have been
               those of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost
               woman</persName></rs>. The brush pens were just the same in appearance, but the
               blubber on the stakes was freshly cut. They saw sneaking about the stakes seven or
               eight wild dogs about the size of coyotes. On catching sight of <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #nativeamericans">the strangers</persName></rs>
               these gaunt black-and-white animals disappeared in the brush, yelping
               discordantly.</p>
            <p>"After closely inspecting the place <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #natam_missionindians">the men</persName></rs> discovered a
               basket of Indian make in the crotch of a dwarf tree. Inside this was neatly folded a
               gown made of shag skins, and a few needles and fishhooks carved out of abalone
               shells. For several hours they continued to search the head of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, but seeing nothing of
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>,
               concluded to fall to killing otter, there being an unusual number of feeding upon the
               luxuriant kelp covering a mile or two of the ocean bed off shore. On the fifth day a
               norther began to blow, and dreading disaster to <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_nidever">the boat</name></rs>, they got aboard, and for eight days
               used their utmost skill to keep from being driven out to sea.</p>
            <p>"It was some time in <date when="1853-07">July of 1853</date> that <persName
                  key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> again landed at <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, this time determined upon bringing away
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>. He had
               with him <rs><persName type="group" key="#cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                     >four companions, besides several Indians</persName></rs>. They anchored
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the vessel</name></rs> off the middle
               of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, on the
               northeast side, and leaving <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">a couple of Indians</persName></rs> in
               charge, <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col">the rest</persName></rs>
               went ashore. Again they found the tracks leading up the beach to a high ridge clad in
               soft sea moss. Here they saw pieces of driftwood still wet from the surf, showing
               they had been recently brought up by some one. There were also three more of the
               brush pens, but no signs of an inhabitant. Finally, <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                     key="#cdi">one of the men</persName></rs> discovered something moving, a long
               way off. At first they took the object for a crow, there being many of these birds on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. It
               proved, however, to be the head and shoulders of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> showing above a pen. Hastening forward, they
               were greeted by the snarls of two dogs crouching before the inclosure. The animals
               were of the same species as those seen upon a former visit.</p>
            <p>"As <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                     >the men</persName></rs> approached they cautiously encircled the pen, thinking
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> might
               attempt to escape. To their surprise she showed unmistakable pleasure at seeing them,
               and rising from her squatting posture, received them with much politeness; chattering
               meanwhile like a magpie. No one understood a word she said, though <rs><persName
                     type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indians</persName></rs>
               were familiar with the various dialects of <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_socalcoast">the southern coast</placeName>. Her yellowish-brown hair hung
               in a tangled mat, the ends having the peculiar appearance of being rotted off. She
               wore a dress of shag skins cut in squares and sewed together, the feathers all
               pointing one way. In a corner of the hut was a dull fire, with some dry grass spread
               alongside for a bed. She had been occupied stripping blubber from a piece of seal
               skin, using a rude knife for the purpose, made of a bit of old iron hoop.</p>
            <p>"<persName key="#gni">John [sic] Nidever</persName> easily persuaded <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> to go with him,
               allowing her to take along such things as seemed of value to her. She packed in a
               basket all her stock of dried blubber and "cacamites"&#8212;a small wild
               onion&#8212;and even the bones she had stored to suck when other food failed her. Nor
               did <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                     >the men</persName></rs> object when she brought aboard the head of a seal, the
               brains putrefied and oozing. This eager economy of food told its own sad story of
               years of famine in this desolate spot. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >One</persName></rs> of <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                  party</persName></rs> made a petticoat of ticking and gave it to her, with a man's
               shirt and necktie. She wore these articles with a childlike appreciation of their
               warmth and colors. She was apparently perfectly cheerful and contented, and did all
               in her power to assist <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the men</persName></rs>
               during the four weeks they yet remained on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the island</placeName></rs> hunting seals. From the first <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the poor creature</persName></rs> showed a
               marked preference for their food, which she ate with the keenest relish. On reaching
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, <persName
                  key="#gni">Nidever</persName> took her to <rs><placeName key="#nideverhouse">his
                     own home</placeName></rs>, where she was treated with the utmost kindness.
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">The Spanish
                     padres, Gonzales, Sanchez and Jimeno</persName></rs>, and <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_missionindians">Indians from the
                     various missions</orgName></rs>, came to see <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, but her language
               ever remained a mystery. In a few months <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the happy, grateful creature</persName></rs> died, surrounded by her
               new friends, who mourned her sincerely."</p>
            <p>"Did no one learn the fate of her child?" <persName key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName>
               inquired.</p>
            <p>"Oh, yes. I forgot to say <rs><persName type="group" key="#nideverfamily">the
                     Nidevers</persName></rs> gathered from her signs that the wild dogs devoured
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her little
                  girl</persName></rs>."</p>
            <p>Though I had heard the tragedy many times, its recital in the solemn stillness of
               midnight at sea brought an intimate and painful realization never produced before.
               Indeed, the horror of it haunted me far into the night, through the cradling of the
               billows and the sonorous snores sounding from the neighboring bunks. Through my
               excited imagination I heard the scraping tread of the watch stumping the deck, with
               now and then the jerk of the sheet to the pulling of the sail. At last I slept
               heavily and dreamlessly.</p>
            <p>"Land, ho!" bawled a hoarse voice. I was on my feet in an instant, rubbing my eyes
               and fumbling about in the gray dawn for my trousers. Fishing my missing boot out of
               the lunch basket, I hastily drew it on, caught up the first hat I could lay my hand
               to, and made a wild dash up the companion ladder.</p>
            <p><rs><persName key="#charles">A grizzled old tar</persName></rs> was steering, while
                     <rs><persName key="#conl">the captain</persName></rs> and <rs><persName
                     key="#johnson2">another sailor</persName></rs>&#8212;<rs><persName
                     key="#charles; #conl; #johnson2">these three</persName></rs> comprising the
               crew of the <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie">Hattie</name></emph>&#8212;were
               gazing over the lee bow at a dark oval mass stretched along the leaden water.</p>
            <p>"Yes, <persName key="#charles">Mr. Charles</persName>, it's <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, an' that black lump to starb'd is <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_johnrock">Beggs Rock</placeName>, all of seven miles off
               the northwest spur of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                  island</placeName></rs>. Watch a bit, an' you'll see the faint line of breakers
               showing the sunken ridge that jines the two," <persName key="#conl">Captain
                  Conlan</persName> explained, lowering the glass from his keen little eyes and
               giving it to me. "Now, <persName key="#johnson2">Johnson</persName>," turning briskly
               to <rs><persName key="#charles">the sailor</persName></rs>, "fall to smartly lad, an'
               fire the engine. This cat's-paw ain't shovin' us ahead much, an' we don't want to be
               all day comin' to anchor!"</p>
            <p>It was a fair morning, the pale tints of the sky brightening into pearl-colored
               vapors shot through by the silver and saffron arrows of the yet unrisen sun. Every
               vestige of the night was disappearing in the tender glory of the awakening day. The
               glossy surface of the sea broke into white flame along the eastern horizon, and
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> stood out sheer and
               forbidding through the roseate veil enveloping its surf-bitten walls. The light
               breeze was soft and refreshingly salt, and stirred the blood like a rare cordial. I
               was intent on watching the somersaults of a school of porpoise directly on our
               starboard beam, when <persName key="#bor">Professor Borland</persName> accosted me
               with cold irony:</p>
            <p>"Young man, I will thank you for my hat. You will find yours in the bucket, where you
               probably dropped it last night."</p>
            <p>Stammering an apology, I uncovered not only my head but my ears, the crown being so
               much too large for me. <rs><persName key="#bor">The professor</persName></rs>
               carefully adjusted the old lop-rimmed felt to his scholarly brows, and bowing
               stiffly, marched aft to greet <persName key="#conl">Captain Conlan</persName>.</p>
            <p><persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName> always said there was no man in <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_ven">San Buenaventura</placeName>, or, for that matter, in
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> either, who was half
               a match in learning for <persName key="#bor">Professor Borland</persName>. He was
               considered [an] authority on the geology and archæology of all this section, and it
               was due to this fact that he was going to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>. He had been employed by the <orgName type="government"
                  key="#gov_calmining">State Mining Bureau</orgName> to make a report of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this island</placeName></rs>, and that
               the work might be thoroughly accomplished was granted <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#ebru; #rbra; #lbor; #nea1">four assistants</persName></rs>. It was in the
               aforesaid capacity that <rs><persName key="#ebru">my uncle</persName></rs>, <persName
                  key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName>, <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and
                  <persName type="author" key="#nea1">myself</persName> were induced to spend two
               weeks with him on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. As
               for me, from earliest recollection I had dreamed of visiting <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">this furthest island from the coast</placeName></rs>,
               which my imagination had vested with unique possibilities of adventure. Now viewed
               from the vessel's deck, it looked but an insignificant bit of barren rock dropped
               down in the brimming expanse of <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the
                  Pacific</placeName>. Indeed, it was difficult to believe it measured nine miles in
               length, with an average width of half that distance.</p>
            <p>The <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie">Hattie</name></emph> steamed rapidly
               through the slow undulations of water that flashed a myriad jewels under the radiant
               flood of the mounting sun. The morning picture was brilliant and full of unwonted
               exhilaration. Our speculations became frequent and excited. The bed of the sea was
               marvelously distinct through a hundred feet of transparent pale-green brine, floating
               a wilderness of kelp of richest amber and gold. In and out of these graceful branches
               splendidly painted fishes darted in inconceivable numbers. All manner of strange
               finny and crustacean creatures wallowed among sea palms, ferns and mosses, or lay
               supine like mottled bowlders trailed over by attenuate grasses and vines.</p>
            <p>A loud cry from the stern. A moment later and a colossal dripping block rolled out
               from under the keel, heaving <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie">the
                  vessel</name></rs> to a noble swell that sent every landlubber tumbling. Then
               another enormous animated mass hove in sight off the port quarter, and still another
               not a dozen yards to starboard, until the <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie"
                     >Hattie</name></emph> rocked crazily amidst no less than a dozen Pacific
               whales, gamboling with the ease and swiftness of the lightest animal. A moment longer
               and we were out of these agitated seas and gazing back at the inoffensive monsters,
               now spouting with great gusto and a noise like the hollow blowing of a blast. A
               round, mustached face popped above the crisp ripples, and surveyed us with large,
               luminous eyes. <rs><persName key="#bor">The professor</persName></rs> made use of his
               glasses.</p>
            <p>"Ah," he said, with a discriminating frown, "a Phoca! <rs><persName key="#conl">Young
                     man</persName></rs>, you will observe that is a pinniped mammal by its forelegs
               being flippers and its head resembling a dog's, though there is no external
               development of the auris."</p>
            <p>"Begging yer parding, mister, but that critter's a seal. I've knowed 'em nigh on to
               fifty year, and time an' again killed 'em fur ile," <rs><persName key="#conl">the old
                     sailor</persName></rs> earnestly interposed, knuckling his forehead
               respectfully to us.</p>
            <p>"So it is, my good fellow; but you see I prefer the Latin name <emph>Phoca</emph>.
               Strike up a tune, boys, and let him show his appreciation of music."</p>
            <p><persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and I started a college song, while <persName
                  key="#johnson2">poor Jack</persName> stared in ludicrous embarrassment a full
               minute, and then fell to lustily swabbing the deck.</p>
            <p>The sea lion had ducked his head, but the instant we commenced singing he reappeared,
               paddling so close that his flat nose almost touched the side. As our voices ceased he
               either dived or quickly widened the distance between us, but invariably showed
               himself pressing nearer when we again took up the strain.</p>
            <p>Meanwhile a flock of gulls wheeled about us, and finally two of their number settled
               upon the gaff, their gluttonous eyes peering down through the rigging. A land bird,
               one of the plover species, momentarily perched upon the jib boom, then gave a
               friendly pipe, as if heralding a welcome ere he flew back to the shining sand of the
               beach.</p>
            <p>We were now a quarter of a mile abreast <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, with the sea as placid as a lake. Two sandstone arms
               were thrust from the man barriers of the shore, forming a pretty cove called
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_coralharbor">Coral Harbor</placeName>. The
               entrance was but six or seven yards across, and the water within sufficiently deep to
               float a schooner of twenty tons burden. The propeller of the <emph><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_hattie">Hattie</name></emph>, however, had become so clogged with kelp
               that to save time we proposed being rowed ashore in <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_hattie">the dinghy</name></rs>.</p>
            <p>The first to enter the rocking cockleshell alongside was <persName key="#bor"
                  >Professor Borland</persName>, a canvas bag containing various tools slung across
               his shoulder, and a hammer and hooked pole firmly grasped in his hands. Evidently he
               intended wasting no time, and called to <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and me
               to follow him, which we did with alacrity.</p>
            <p>"<rs><persName type="group" key="#ebru; #rbra; #lbor; #nea1">You boys</persName></rs>
               can get breakfast under way, for I shall be as hungry as a wolf when I return from my
               tramp," he remarked, grimly observant of the dampening effect of his words.</p>
            <p>How I loathed the thought of cooking and eating, with the prospect of a whole island
               to explore!</p>
            <p>Boxes of provisions and cooking utensils were stored aboard, until <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_hattie">the dinghy</name></rs> was well down in the water.
                     <rs><persName key="#johnson2">The younger of the sailors</persName></rs> plied
               the oars, though my hands itched for the work. As we skimmed over the waving marine
               forest we heard <persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName> shout, and looking back,
               saw him dangling from his line a huge halibut. One need but drop a baited hook to
               immediately secure one of the multitudes of fish thronging these waters.</p>
            <p>My eager gaze again sought the bleak, sandy shore. On a silvery strip meeting the
               creamy lip of the bay several immense white pelicans promenaded with stately dignity.
               At our approach they spread their heavy, pointed wings and vanished over the
               truncated rocks. Leaping to the beach, we rushed headlong up the sand dunes,
                     <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> puffing violently, but
               keeping manfully to the front.</p>
            <p>"Bless me! Gasteropods by the ton!" he cried, delightedly, making a dive for one of
               the numerous shell mounds now everywhere in sight, and beginning to dig like a
               beaver.</p>
            <p>To our surprise we now perceived <placeName key="#cabin">a small, weather-stained
                  cabin</placeName> a few rods beyond. Running to it, we flung aside the burlap door
               curtain, and sniffed disgustedly.</p>
            <p>"Chinamen's camp! Opium, dried fish, and their usual accumulation of filth!"</p>
            <p><persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> pointed to ill-smelling blue garments and
               wooden-soled shoes stacked beside a tea box on which were heaped a motley array of
               chopsticks, pipes and green rice bowls swarmed over with flies and ants.</p>
            <p>Outside <placeName key="#cabin">the cabin</placeName> were piles of beautiful abalone
               shells of larger size and richer tints than any I had ever before seen.</p>
            <p>"These fellows must be off shell gathering. <rs><persName key="#bor"
                     >Father</persName></rs> says they take away millions of abalones from
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> every year. Have you
               ever seen the meat dried? It looks like the hoof of a colt. I hope they have a boat,
               so we can borrow it."</p>
            <p>Here <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> helped himself to a preserved ginger
               root, fishing it out of its plethoric jar by the deft use of his knife blade. The
               sweet, pungent syrup made us thirsty, and we hurried off in search of water. There
               was a fine spring close at hand, but like all the water on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> it was slightly
               brackish.</p>
            <p>Fixing upon a suitable spot to pitch the tent, we fell to carrying up the luggage,
               and whatever drift we could pick up high and dry. The novelty of our task made it
               pleasurable, though we both agreed that <rs><date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen
                     years</date></rs> of this sort of grubbing would be unendurable. That a weak
               woman had survived this lamentable experience struck us anew with amazement and pity.
               We soon had a fire crackling merrily, and a kettle boiling for coffee.</p>
            <p>By this time <persName key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName> and <persName key="#ebru"
                  >Uncle Ned</persName> joined us, loaded with all manner of camp "truck." They were
               both as jovial and boisterous as two boys. Nothing would do but <persName key="#conl"
                  >Captain Conlan</persName> and <rs><persName key="#charles; #johnson2">the two
                     sailors</persName></rs> must come up to breakfast with us, and hallooing to
                     <rs><persName key="#bor">the absorbed professor</persName></rs>, we made a
               jolly party, kneeling or squatting about in the sand, eating our gritty bacon and
               potatoes and drinking coffee out of tin cups with wonderful zest. Indeed, our
               appetites were so sharpened by our long fast and the unaccustomed salt freshness of
               the air that we enthusiastically agreed with <rs><persName key="#charles">the old
                     sailor</persName></rs> that "wittles was bloomin' good!"</p>
            <p>The <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie">Hattie</name></emph> was bound for
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina Island</placeName>,
               and, twenty miles off <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
               mainland</placeName>, and thence to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San
                  Pedro</placeName>. This was our only chance to send a message to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_ven">San Buenaventura</placeName>, so a couple of letters
               were written with dispatch, and intrusted to <persName key="#conl">Captain
                  Conlan</persName> to mail. It was understood he was to return for us <rs><date
                     notAfter="1892-10-31">at the end of two weeks</date></rs>. After a hearty
               handshake all around <rs><persName key="#charles; #conl; #johnson2">the
                     "crew"</persName></rs> were escorted back to <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_hattie">the dinghy</name></rs> by <persName key="#bor">Professor
                  Borland</persName>, who appeared to have a parting word to say to <rs><persName
                     key="#conl">the captain</persName></rs>.</p>
            <p>Though it was <rs><date notAfter="1892-10-15">the middle of October</date></rs>, the
               day was summery and the sky fleckless. Before noon <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_hattie">the little vessel</name></rs> ran up her colors and got under
               way, steering due east across the scintillating blue floor of the sea, her white
               sails swelling to the rising breeze and a long line of frothing wake unrolling at her
               stern. We answered the parting salute of her flag by loud cheers and the waving of
               our hats. Finally I called impatiently to <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> to
               "Come ahead," and made a dash up the nearest sand ridge.</p>
            <p>As far as eye could trace there were countless circular depressions showing where
               primitive dwellings once stood, though not a vestige remained of the material used in
               the construction of these <emph>rancherias</emph>. Hundreds of shell mounds were
               thickly scattered between these circles. They consisted of vast numbers of mollusks,
               the bones of every species of fish found in these waters, the skeletons of seals, sea
               elephants, whales, sea otter, the island fox, and various aquatic birds. These
               animals were evidently employed as food by <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the natives</orgName></rs>. There were no trees,
               only stunted thorn bushes, barely two feet in height, and now and then a cactus
               forlornly stretching its grotesque arms out of the interminable sweeps of sand.
               Everywhere were dead land shells, but not a living specimen to be found.</p>
            <p>"There must have been a luxuriant vegetation here at one time to have supported such
               quantities of land mollusks," <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs>
               thoughtfully observed, as he critically examined one after another of the bleaching
               shells.</p>
            <p>There was something contagious in his free-hearted abandon to relic hunting. Under
               its stimulus we emulated him to good purpose, unearthing from the mounds all sorts of
               unique utensils, stone cooking pots, ollas, mortars, pestles, drills, bone needles
               and fishhooks, shell beads and other ornaments, charm stones, pipes, cups, and a few
               arrow heads, spear points and swords made of bone. The absence of numerous weapons of
               hostility proved the peaceful attributes of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the islanders</orgName></rs>. There were also small
               imitations of boats and fishes, carved from crystallized tale and serpentine,
               betraying in this people a certain rudimentary knowledge of the art of sculpture.
                  <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> brought <rs><persName key="#bor">his
                     father</persName></rs> a perforated disk of beautifully polished serpentine.
                     <rs><persName key="#bor">The professor</persName></rs> was exuberant, and said,
               with animation:</p>
            <p>"These disks are very rare, and greatly sought after by archæologists. Their purpose
               is not positively determined, but I have the word of <rs><persName
                     type="naativeamerican" key="#indian9">an old Mission Indian</persName></rs>
               that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this
                     interesting race</orgName></rs> made use of them in a favorite game."</p>
            <p>In many places there were conical piles of small black porphyritic pebbles,
               contrasting oddly with the white sand. In some instances these pebbles were closely
               packed in abalone shells, and carefully covered with the same. Even <rs><persName
                     key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> could offer no plausible solution of
               this singular custom. We searched in vain for any relics we could distinctly trace to
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lost woman</persName></rs>,
               but Nature, ever unmindful of the individual, had long since merged the superhuman
               efforts of this courageous life into the universal fate of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">an entire
                     race</orgName></rs>. Every foot of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> was dumbly eloquent of the labor, the oppression and
               the extinction of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">this almost unheard-of people</orgName></rs>.</p>
            <p>"Who knows but <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">that little Aztec
                     woman</persName></rs> liked this life, after all?" <persName key="#lbor"
                  >Leroy</persName> paused in his slow nibbling of a cacamite, and let his eyes rest
               absently on the hazy outline of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                  Clemente</placeName>, lying off the southeast coast of <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. "Now, there's <rs><persName key="#sclhermit"
                     >the old hermit</persName></rs> who has lived alone on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName>
               <rs><date notAfter="1830" to="1892">more than twenty-six years</date></rs>. He has
               the 'right of way' to more than a hundred square miles of island, and seems as
               chipper as a cricket. His only companions are two large dogs, who are as crazy to get
               away from <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> as
                     <rs><persName key="#sclhermit">their master</persName></rs> is to stay there.
               Whenever a boat leaves <rs><persName key="#sclhermit">the old fellow</persName></rs>
               has to tie them up. No one knows his history, or even his name. Of late years he has
               been hired to look out for the sheep pastured there, but he spends a lot of time
               hunting, and is said to be a famous shot. There are no end of ducks and reedbirds in
               the marshes, and on the high lands plenty of mountain sheep, wolves and foxes. He
               told <rs><persName key="#bor">father</persName></rs> nothing could induce him to
               leave <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName>, and pointed out
               the foot of a high bluff where he intended to be buried. It's rather puzzling to know
               who'll do the planting, unless the funeral is indefinitely postponed."</p>
            <p>Laughing immoderately, we both started on a brisk tramp westward, keeping to the
               coast over a vast extent of shell mounds, which set us wondering how a limited
               population could possibly have consumed such inconceivable numbers of mollusks. The
               shore line was, of course, sandstone burrowed by the sea into fantastic alcoves,
               bridges, columns and caves, that were startlingly picturesque and suggestive of
               romantic concealments and adventure. From this gnawed and broken wall the ground
               makes a gentle ascent to a mesa, terminating in a steep escarpment from which we
               could look over some miles of what appeared to be a tillable level. At this high
               altitude, the atmosphere being clear, we could easily distinguish the peaked heights
               of all the <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName> but
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, where the brave
                  <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName> is said to be buried.</p>
            <p>Finding more to interest us along the sea, we returned to our explorations of the
               cavernous strata above the wash of the surf.</p>
            <p>"Shades of smugglers! but wouldn't this be a place for the secret stowing of bales!
               Who knows but Cabrillo's lost treasure is hidden in that black-mawed chamber!" I
               exclaimed, conscious of a boundless appreciation of these weird recesses, and a
               half-hope that my random thought might have a reality.</p>
            <p>As there was no response from <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName>, I glanced back,
               and beheld him standing as if petrified on a ledge below, his face white as chalk and
               his black eyes horribly dilated.</p>
            <p>"What's the matter?"</p>
            <p>I sprang to his side and clutched his arm, my eyes darting to the point on which his
               gaze was frozen. A Chinaman was hanging by one hand to a shelly projection, his head
               twisted over his shoulder so his ghastly face turned our way, the protruding eyes
               staring at us with the blank regard of the dead.</p>
            <p>"My God! <persName key="#charles2">Charlie</persName>, it's a&#8212;a corpse!" he
               chattered.</p>
            <p>Holding on to each other, we drew nearer the awful thing. The tawny arm from which
               the stiffened body was suspended was bared by the falling back of the wide blue
               sleeve, and showed the cords distorted and moist streaks of blood. The hand attached
               to this arm was wholly invisible, clamped in the viselike grip of one of the
               monstrous abalones fastened to the rock. We could see by the swollen and lacerated
               wrist how the poor fellow had struggled before the rising tide swept over him and put
               and end to his agony.</p>
            <p>We were hurrying away when a harsh jargon reached our ears. The next moment four
               Chinamen emerged from an arched portal, looking anxiously to right and left as they
               stumbled over the stones. We shouted to them, and their astonishment at seeing us
               almost deprived them of motion. I broke the spell by signing toward their dead
               comrade. The sight loosened their tongues into a perfect babel of rasping gutturals.
                  <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> looked sympathetic.</p>
            <p>"I guess they feel pretty bad about it. Poor fellows! See them pulling him over. Ugh!
               Good Heavens!"</p>
            <p>The last ejaculation is a smothered cry as the oldest Chinaman, with a well-aimed cut
               of his spade, severs the wrist of the corpse close to the unflinching abalone.</p>
            <p>"Him a big foolee!" he contemptuously remarked, emphasizing his words with a brutal
               kick.</p>
            <p>With a qualm at my stomach, I made for the top of the reef, Leroy's long legs after
               me. Neither of us spoke a word for some minutes, but struck for camp as if for a
               wager. It was a long walk and a hot one, with the sun getting the best of our backs,
               and the sand miring our feet a good share of the way. Besides, neither of us could
               free our mind from the dead Chinaman, and thoughts of this kind are a weight to the
               feet. We were in fact so preoccupied with the grewsome incident that we forgot to
               look up specimens for <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs>. Seeing
               our empty hands, he greeted us somewhat surlily as we reached camp. <persName
                  key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName> was pensively ruminating on a skull and
               crossbones, which he told us he had found on the hill, and <persName key="#ebru"
                  >Uncle Ned</persName> was energetically macerating abalones for supper in one of
               the ancient mortars. <rs><persName type="group" key="#rbra; #ebru">These two kind
                     hearts</persName></rs> were shocked by our story, but <persName key="#bor"
                  >Professor Borland</persName> began a search among his heaped-up relics till he
               brought forth a mammoth dish-shaped shell.</p>
            <p>"Was that Haliotis highly colored like this one?" scrutinizing <rs><persName
                     key="#lbor; #nea1">the two of us</persName></rs> sharply.</p>
            <p>"No sir, I think not. It was just an ordinary abalone, only uncommonly
               big&#8212;more'n a foot across, I should judge."</p>
            <p>"Just as I supposed," shaking his head dejectedly. "The red abalones, once so
               plentiful here, are now totally extinct. Such a pity, such a pity!" he added, with
               profound pathos, while tenderly passing one shapely hand over the beautiful
               wine-tinted shell on his knee.</p>
            <p>And now the delicious night came down and wrapped us about like a soft cocoon. One by
               one the stars swung their glowing lamps in the great tent of the sky, and the curved
               blade of a young moon dipped low above the shadowy promontory of the western slope.
               We "turned in" early, and the rhythmic rhyme of the sea lulled us quickly to deep
               slumber.</p>
            <p>Such a glorious sea bath as we had at sunrise! Every one of us went in, and our
               floundering and spouting were hardly exceeded by the school of whale outside the
               harbor. <rs><persName type="group" key="#conl; #bor; #rbra; #ebru; #lbor">The
                     rest</persName></rs> had taken their dripping figures to the beach, when I
               decided to have a final plunge off an overhanging rock. Upon blithely coming to the
               surface a shout of alarm reached me.</p>
            <p>"A shark! Quick, <persName key="#charles2">Charlie</persName>, for God's sake!"</p>
            <p>In his agony of fear <persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName> waded toward me with
               outstretched hands.</p>
            <p>I glanced with horror over my shoulder, and saw the black fins of the monster plowing
               swiftly in my track not a dozen yards behind. I pushed ahead with a fury that fairly
               frothed the water about me, and was almost strangling from haste and fright when I
               felt the lift of uncle's strong arm, and my feet touched bottom.</p>
            <p><rs><persName key="#bor">The professor</persName></rs> stepped anxiously forward.</p>
            <p>"The creature was so close, I hoped you would be able to notice if there was anything
               peculiar about his pectoral fins," he said, seriously.</p>
            <p>"Oh, yes, sir. They looked to me exactly as large as a ship's sails," I dryly
               replied, meeting his eyes with composure.</p>
            <p>He drew up his portly figure with an insulted air, and stalked away amid the
               good-natured laughter of <rs><persName type="group" key="#conl; #rbra; #ebru; #lbor"
                     >the others</persName></rs>.</p>
            <p>That morning we came across dozens of canine skeletons, some indicating a species
               similar to the bull terrier, and the others undoubtedly belonging to the small wild
               dog found here by <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Mr. Nidever</persName>.
                     <rs><persName key="#ebru">Uncle</persName></rs> proposed accompanying <persName
                  key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and me on a further exploration of the west end of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. As we
               followed the coast, we saw thousands of shags and pelicans decorously patrolling the
               rocky points, and a few leopard seals disporting in the surf. Owing to the present
               scarcity here of these animals and the otter, seal hunters no longer come regularly
               to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, but put in their
               time to better advantage on the rocks of <placeName type="island" key="#i_an"
                  >Anacapa</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara
                  Island</placeName>, the two smallest of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >the Channel group</placeName></rs>.</p>
            <p>As we neared the scene of yesterday's tragedy we heard a succession of scraping
               blows, and over the sandstone cliff discovered half a dozen Chinamen making use of
               crowbars to pry off the abalones from the rocks. Their large baskets were nearly
               filled with the mollusks already secured. These shell gatherers fought every foot of
               their way over sharp, slippery stones, with the heavy swells of the sea disputing
               their advance. They loosened the abalones by means of the powerful leverage of the
               crowbars, deftly catching them as they fell before the hungry surf sucked them under.
               The work was extremely laborious and attended with more or less danger; yet half a
               hundred tons of these shells are annually sent to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf"
                  >San Francisco</placeName> for ornamental purposes, while immense quantities of
               the dried meat is shipped to <placeName type="country" key="#co_china"
                  >China</placeName>, where it is highly esteemed as food.</p>
            <p>After watching the Chinamen a spell, and answering their interrogations as to how we
               "Come allee same <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nic'las</placeName>" we
               turned our faces across a wide, high desert of stupendous barrenness. Here and there
               were vast beds of the extinct red abalones, the interior of their shells glinting
               with irridescent mother-of-pearl linings. We also saw bones of whales collected in
               separate heaps, their arrangement and packi[n]g so mathematically exact as to have
               withstood many years of the constant sweep of the wind over this exposed portion of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. There
               were besides mortars and pestles by the score, and a multiplicity of sea urchins and
               starfish, with frequent piles of rare olivalus and edible limpets. Indeed, the
               infinite variety of mollusca on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName> is probably not exceeded by any other region of equal
               area.</p>
            <p>"There is one thing sure," <persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName> said,
               positively; "<rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                     >these natives</orgName></rs> never died from starvation, as some writers
               affirm. The supply of shellfish is sufficient to support a population of thousands.
               Hello! what's this?"</p>
            <p>On the arid slope before us lay a jumbled human skeleton, its bleached, dismembered
               aspect in keeping with the driven desolateness of the spot. The merciless wind had
               heaped the sand dunes all about, but spread no kindly drift over this "<rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">rough sketch of man</placeName></rs>." All about were
               the casts of roots of trees in the shifting sand, ranging all the way from coarse
               fibre to several inches in diameter. These semi-petrifactions were intact, the wind
               having swept them clear of the loose earth. They gave a metallic ring when we tapped
               them with a shell or a rock.</p>
            <p>A still more singular feat[u]re of the place was an extensive stretch of what
               appeared to be the petrified stumps of trees. These broken columns were of indurated
               sand from a few inches to three and four feet in height. Speaking of this stone
               forest afterward, <persName key="#bor">Professor Borland</persName> said he believed
               a terrible drought had cracked the ground, and the fissures had been filled in by
               sand, which in time became sufficiently solidified to stand upright, the soil about
               them meanwhile being gradually blown off by the wind.</p>
            <p>While wondering at these strange formations a little fuzzy creature, no larger than a
               house cat, scampered between the stumps, and raising my Winchester, I took aim and
               fired. The animal dropped dead, and upon examining it we concluded it was one of the
               foxes peculiar to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                  island</placeName></rs>. It was the first land animal we had yet seen, and we soon
               determined there was no other kind in existence on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, unless one excepted the kangaroos mouse and a
               diminutive lizard, or the flocks of sheep pasturing on the eastern plateau. As for
               poisonous reptiles, there were none to be found, though various beetles, butterflies,
               crickets and flies are quite as familiar a sight here as in a Ventura home field.</p>
            <p>I slung my fox over my shoulder by his black tail, and we journeyed ahead, our
               pockets bulging with specimens, and <rs><persName key="#ebru">[my]
                  uncle</persName></rs> barbarically equipped with stone tomahawk and battle club.
               At the extreme west end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> we came upon a colossal sandstone wall a thousand feet
               in height, its chasmed and slitted face softened with a luxuriant growth of emerald
               cliff moss, lichens and delicate creepers. Issuing from the innumerable cervices were
               lengthened strands of water falling silverly and cool adown the moss, pausing anon in
               their sheert descent to overflow the polished cups of the rocks.</p>
            <p>We viewed this ponderous masonry with enchantment, the beaded green of its drapery
               and the liquid resonance of the sparkling streamlets proving deliciously refreshing
               after the glare and uniform color of the desert we had just been traversing.</p>
            <p>Returning late, we shot enough plover on the way to make a savory stew for supper.
                  <persName key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName> had been fishing during out absence,
               and as a result we had also fried barracuda, rock cod and bonito, a layout of fresh
               meats highly satisfying to our prodigious appetites.</p>
            <p><rs><persName key="#bor">The professor</persName></rs> did not join us until the
               young moon was doing her best to light the dishwashing. He was jaded and hungry, but
               immensely elated with his day's work.</p>
            <p>"To-morrow I will show you something worth seeing," he declared; but further than
               this he vouchsafed no particulars.</p>
            <p>In the morning we made an early start, <rs><persName key="#bor">Leroy's
                     father</persName></rs> taking the lead, and we dutifully following [sic] him up
               the summit south of the camp. We found the elevation six or seven hundred feet. When
               nearing the highest bank <rs><persName key="#bor">our scientific
                  friend</persName></rs> came to a stand, and by the ecstatic movements of his hands
               and head we judged he had gained the point of special interest.</p>
            <p>We quickened our steps, and a minute later saw with amazement that all the naked sand
               beyond was littered with hundreds of disjointed skeletons. It was the most reckless
               display of the "ground plan" of humanity imagination could conceive.</p>
            <p>"Now <emph>this</emph> is something to be thankful for!" <rs><persName key="#bor">the
                     professor</persName></rs> devoutly ejaculated, his eyes beaming with excess of
               emotion.</p>
            <p>Suddenly his attention was arrested by something suggestive in Mr. Brand's tall
               figure. The next instant he was measuring a huge thigh bone against that gentleman's
               canvas trousers.</p>
            <p>"I thought so. A good four inches longer and you must be all of six feet high! Who
               says <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">these
                     islanders</orgName></rs> were not comparative giants?"</p>
            <p>He turned his flushed face from one to the other of us.</p>
            <p>"Bless me! what gigantic skulls!" cried <rs><persName key="#rbra">the
                     minister</persName></rs>, with increasing enthusiasm.</p>
            <p>"Just so. Look carefully at their conformation, my friend. I have exhumed skeletons
               on the other <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>, and
               also <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_ven">San Buenaventura</placeName>, but never found any of the
               size of these, nor did the facial angles of the skulls denote such high grade of
               intelligence. Without doubt these <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">San Nicolas Indians</orgName></rs> were physically
               and intellectually superior to <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the inhabitants of the neighboring
                     lands</orgName></rs>. This skull, for instance"&#8212;making a pivot of his
               left hand on which to airily poise the bony grin&#8212;"has all the attributes of the
               Caucasian type. A few geometrical squares properly outlined and labeled, and here's a
               phrenological bust for your study table!"</p>
            <p>Many of the skulls were apparently broken by a club or other blunt instrument, but
               the most diligent search in this aboriginal battlefield could not produce a single
               one showing the perforation of a bullet. On the south side of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">this modern Golgotha</placeName></rs> we noticed some
               of the skeletons with the knees drawn up to the breast, a method of burial common to
               the California races. The wind had long since cleared the porous earth from these
               mortal remains, and in this treeless cemetery each stark white heap served as a perch
               for funeral ravens and crows.</p>
            <p>There were divers[e] curious relics mingled with the crowding bones, among them stone
               knives fitted to wooden handles. These and other articles proved that as artificers
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     islanders</orgName></rs> greatly excelled <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">their redskin
                     contemporaries</orgName></rs>. With the female skeletons were found balls of
               red ochre carefully preserved in abalone shells. There were also bracelets, earrings
               and necklaces cunningly contrived out of polished bone and mother-of-pearl.</p>
            <p>By noon we were at the south shore, all but <persName key="#bor">Professor
                  Borland</persName>, who could not be induced to leave the ancient burial ground.
               Before us outspread <placeName type="region" key="#re_pacific">the great
                  Pacific</placeName>, its golden summer sheen lost in the azure line of the remote
               horizon. A few white-bosomed clouds floated overhead, and the light breeze was warm
               and caressing.</p>
            <p>We sat about on flat bowlders, eating out corned beef and crackers, and found
               infinite diversion in watching the porpoise, and the pelicans fish off the rocks.
               After a little <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and I wandered down the coast,
               which is incredibly desolate at this point. The beetling sea wall, hundreds of feet
               high, is washed into savage declivities and cuts, with uncouth effigies in rock
               bearing a surprising likeness to living creatures. One of these is almost the exact
               counterpart of the neck, breast and body of a bird with an alert, hooded head. This
               piece of Nature's sculpturing must be all of forty feet long, and at a distance looks
               quite as perfect as if fashioned by the hand of man.</p>
            <p>On the topmost ridges overlooking the lashing surf were unnumbered murres, and
               immediately we conceived the plan of fetching away some of their eggs. Eagerly
               climbing to the nearest rookery, we found ourselves in a whirlwind of flapping wings,
               while the frantic shrieks of the affrighted birds were deafening. It was gleesome
               sport, and what with the dire confusion made by the poor murres and our struggle to
               gain the almost inaccessible crags, we were quite breathless. However, we managed to
               cram a few dozen of the greenish, freckled eggs into the canvas bags strapped to our
               waists. There were thousands of these eggs lying loosely about on the warm rocks, for
               the "foolish guillemot" knows not to make a nest of any sort.</p>
            <p>Not all our eggs reached camp unbroken, but notwithstanding fishy odor the remainder
               made a toothsome addition to our bill of fare.</p>
            <p>After a week's sojourn on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName> we felt in a measure that we knew <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> by heart. The days were spent in long
               excursions over its length and breadth, and we slowly gained an intelligent
               conception of much that pertained to the nature and habits of <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the gentle
                     race</orgName></rs> that once had existence here. In spite of our numbers and
               the exceptional joyance and novelty of our life the all-pervading loneliness of this
               fragment sent a chill to the heart. The marvel grew upon us that <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a lone woman</persName></rs> should have
               endured years of enforced isolation here.</p>
            <p>Day by day we cast off the habits of civilization, and for the nonce became primeval
               in our luxurious disregard of appearances. I wore my torn blouse and trousers with
               the same unconcern that a savage wears his clout. All gifts of Nature&#8212;air,
               sunshine and the wild, untrammeled picturings of sea and shore&#8212;we appropriated
               as things specially provided for out physical enjoyment. The bountiful supply of
               ozone made our lungs sensitive to the slightest pressure, and we grew to question the
               ventilation of our sheeting tent, though the nights were hardly warm enough to do
               without this small protection.</p>
            <p>When <rs><date notAfter="1892-10-31">Sunday</date></rs> came round we followed the
               customary habit of sleeping later in the morning; only <rs><persName key="#bor">the
                     professor</persName></rs> disregardfully stole out at dawn with his hook and
               hammer. After our coffee and bacon, with one accord we sauntered shoreward, pausing
               to drink in the matchless ocean view off a peaky promontory. A thin vapor overspread
               the sun, and hung a shimmering net across the trembling plain of the sea. The
               atmosphere took on new warmth and softness as of invisible dews. We were all more or
               less moved by the Sabbath stillness of the scene and the entrancing play of lights on
               the water.</p>
            <p>The next hour held an experience we are none of us likely to forget. It did not
               strike me at the time as the least bit like a regular Sunday service, but somehow it
               was much more impressive. The reading was from Job, and the sublime imagery of the
               lines was singularly in keeping with our surroundings. With a grimacing skull wedged
               between the rocks facing us, and a stray sternum between the rocks facing up, and a
               stray sternum and unmated clavicles sticking out of the sand at our feet, there was
               something plaintively realistic in the words, "O that Thou wouldst hide me in the
               grave, and that Thou wouldst keep me secret!" And the awful question, "If a man die,
               shall he live again?" was never before so startlingly pertinent.</p>
            <p>When <rs><persName key="#ebru">[my] uncle</persName></rs> closed his well-worn pocket
               Bible <persName key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName> fell to thinking out loud, and we
               followed him with unabated interest. The audience was a mixed one, to be sure, but
               they were none the less observant, for all that. On a pinnacled crag close at hand a
               large bald eagle ruffed his clerkly neck feathers and pierced us with his
               carnage-brooding eyes. All the side pews were taken by shags and pelicans demurely
               winking at us [with] one eye while the other was wickedly intent on the frolicsome
               fish in the shoals. The nearest aisles were filled by dozens of solemn-visaged ravens
               looking eminently respectable in their black dress suits, but with their unregeneracy
               plainly manifest in their furtive glances at a carrion porpoise half buried in the
               sand. Just off the beach on a table rock a concourse of sea lions went through all
               manner of snail[-]like contortions, as if undergoing the pangs of an awakened
               conscience. The most innocent hearers of the dissertation were undoubtedly a ground
               owl mooning at us with his wide, expressionless eyes, and a covey of dainty plover
               making desultory pecks in the sand between somewhat frivolous flirts of their short
               tail feathers.</p>
            <p>When we took up "Greenland's Iey Mountains" the sea lions reared their black-maned
               heads and struck in a hoarse basso profundo whose sole note was the acme of
               miserableness. Instantaneously the entire shoal was alive with sleek, round heads all
               turning soulful eyes our way, until a line of paddling seals occupied what might be
               considered the "mourners' bench" in front.</p>
            <p>Never did the grand old hymn sound so wholly glorious! The thunderous surges put in
               the organ tones, trailing them out to uphold the strains, while the echoing rocks
               multiplied them into a thousand far-away melodies. With the wild creatures from "the
               springs of the sea" and the birds of the land hearkening, we again burst forth in
               Selkirk's majestic complaint:</p>
            <p><floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <lg>
                        <l>"I am monarch of all I survey,</l>
                        <l>My right there is none to dispute;</l>
                        <l>From the centre all round to the sea</l>
                        <l>I am lord of the fowl and the brute.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p> </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>"O Solitude, where are the charms</l>
                        <l>That sages have seen in thy face?</l>
                        <l>Better dwell in the midst of alarms</l>
                        <l>Than reign in this horrible place."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText></p>
            <p>By afternoon the wind veered to the south, and swept low and moaningly over the
               shivering dunes. For hours a continuous flock of sea fowl winged past the tent in the
               coppery illumination from the veiled sun. There were unnumbered thousands of these
               birds, and their cries sounded strange and solemnly prophetic. At sundown there was
               an ominous piling of swollen clouds in the west, above wide pools of throbbing light.
               One by one <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the neighboring
                     islands</placeName></rs> were muffled in gloom, until the black slip of land we
               inhabited seemed all that was left of the great spinning earth. Across the universe
               of boiling waters serpentine flashes of lightning ripped the intense blackness
               pressing down from the sky, and the sea took on a doleful plaint to the indistinct
               mutterings of thunder.</p>
            <p>At midnight the storm broke, and I never remember hearing such thunder. There came an
               appalling dash of rain and wind, mingled with the terrific bellowing of the surf on
               the rocks. So tremendous was the jar and the uproar that <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> appeared shaken to its foundation. It
               was only with the utmost exertion that we managed to keep the tent upright, but there
               was no more sleep for any of us. The sunrise, however, was well worth being up to
               see. It was altogether the most marvelous we had yet witnessed. Not a hint of the
               storm remained, aside from a rain-bathed freshness over all, even to the sea itself,
               which was all a-sparkle in the radiating light.</p>
            <p>After a lengthened barter with the "boss" Chinaman we secured a day's loan of
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_skiff1">the skiff</name></rs> for the sum of
               "fo'bittee," and stuffing stray morsels of food in our pockets, we made off for the
               day.</p>
            <p>Rounding the narrow peninsula that forms the south confine of <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_coralharbor">Coral Harbor</placeName>, we rowed as close to
               the shore as the breakers would permit. The unfrequented caverns, abounding in rare
               algæ and wriggling crustacean creatures, furnished us inexhaustible objects of
               interest. Our eyes were never weary searching the diaphanous water where countless
               scarlet, gold and argent fish flashed through the submarine groves. On a bed of
               exquisitely tinted shells and pebbles lay a pair of rusty iron rowlocks, seemingly
               within twenty feet of the surface, but upon sounding, the actual depth proved to be
               eighty fathoms.</p>
            <p>The ragged sea wall was all along scaly with shellfish, each with its valve opened to
               drink in the falling spray. Multitudes of gulls and shags were everywhere to be seen,
               but as we neared them they flew away with a wild clatter. Now and again from some
               castellated projection we were watched by a kingly eagle.</p>
            <p>The beaches we saw were too steep to make good landing ground, but we finally took
               advantage of an ingoing breaker, which set us pretty well up on the sand.</p>
            <p>Having fixed things to our satisfaction, we made our way cautiously along a backbone
               of sandstone running far out beyond the frothing breakers. Being now ravenously
               hungry, we chose the smoothest surface at hand and stretched ourselves to dry, and
               munch our apples and biscuit. The direct rays of the sun set us to steaming at a
               great rate, and provoked an imperative drowsiness. I fell asleep, and <persName
                  key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> must have done likewise, for I was vaguely conscious
               of his deep breathing beside me.</p>
            <p>An hour or so later my eyelids slowly unclosed in a delicious half-awakening, and the
               next instant I was straining my sight at what I took to be the tails of two enormous
               spotted snakes floating aimlessly out from a submerged bowlder. While absorbed in
               watching them a third undulatory shape was thrust like a tongue from the crevice, and
               was followed by a fourth and a fifth slimy, elongated tentacle, all of which
               broadened toward the same focus. When my curiosity was at its height a disgusting,
               jellylike mass detached itself from the rock and moved slowly forward by the aid of
               its eight feelers, three of which I had not perceived before.</p>
            <p>I now realized that the bundle of "snakes" was in reality the antennae of one round,
               glutinous creature possessed of two large, watery eyes which glared voraciously.
               Though I had never before seen this hideous and formidable monster, I was convinced
               it was the octopus, commonly called the "devilfish," and known to legendary lore as
               the "Kraken."</p>
            <p>Seeing the creature about to shamble off, I called sharply to <persName key="#lbor"
                  >Leroy</persName>. There was a loud splash and a choking cry in response. To my
               dismay I saw him struggling and sputtering in the water. In his violent awakening he
               had rolled off into the pool inhabited by the devilfish. I had read frightful
               accounts of its deadly embrace, and my presence of mind forsook me. I shrieked
               wildly:</p>
            <p>"Don't climb up here! Go farther down. For mercy's sake, hurry! He's right under
               you!"</p>
            <p>"I'm glad <emph>something</emph> is under me, for it seems a deucedly long way to the
               bottom! Lend a hand, can't you, and don't be so infernally scared!"</p>
            <p>He extended one hand, while the other clutched the notched wall, his toes barely
               touching the shell-like bowlder underneath. My eyes fell upon his shoes and socks
               drying beside me in the sun. Even now the blistering thongs of the octopus might be
               reaching for his bare flesh! Fortunately he was ignorant of its malevolent presence.
               I remembered also that he could not swim a stroke. We both strained every muscle; but
               not until he had felt his way some yards down the submarine ledge was it possible for
               our united efforts to get him up the slippery stones.</p>
            <p>When <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> scrambled to his feet I submitted to a
               briny but dramatic embrace. Then breaking away, I ran to look for the devilfish. He
               was nowhere in sight, but there was a slight movement of the water where the monster
               had buried itself in a cleft of the rock.</p>
            <p>When I explained to <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> he stopped wringing his
               clothes and stared open-mouthed, then laughed extravagantly.</p>
            <p>"<rs><persName key="#bor">The governor</persName></rs> will never forgive me for not
               allowing myself to be thoroughly wound up and sucked dry for the benefit of science.
               Think what a beautiful exemplification of the polyp's wonderful apparatus for
               exhausting air! Really, <persName key="#charles2">Charlie</persName>"&#8212;with
               whimsical gravity&#8212;"you did wrong to help me escape. The best we can do now is
               keep mum on the subject."</p>
            <p>And odd as it may appear, we carried out the suggestion, saying nothing about the
               adventure, even when the Chinamen a few days after hauled in their net only to find
               an octopus writhing among a score of other fish. Under the professor's tutelage we
               had a chance to come to a pretty good understanding of the creature's remarkable
               anatomy. Every snakelike feeler had on its under surface rows of suckers which act
               like cupping glasses to draw the blood of its victim. These tentacles are hollow, and
               supplied with sharp points on the ends. In fact, the whole shapeless, scabrous heap
               is quite revolting enough to give rise to the superstitious horror with which the
               "sea vampire" has ever been regarded.</p>
            <p>Much of the second week we spent investigating the eastern portion of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. Here a smooth tableland
               of thousands of acres is covered with nutritious grass and moss, where bands of sheep
               graze the year through. Unlike the dusky, burr-fringed flocks on <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, these animals were
               picturesquely white, and as nimble and wild as goats. No shepherd watches them day or
               night, and there is no dog to tease or wild beast to torture or kill them. Indeed,
               every one of these <placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Channel Islands</placeName>
               might truthfully be deemed a sheep's paradise. When the season comes round shearers
               are sent from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ven">Ventura</placeName> or <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and aside from this periodical
               attention the owners reck not of the welfare of these Crusoe-like island flocks.</p>
            <p>The sheep on <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName> are a queer
               lot. They are ignorant of the taste of water, there being none on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_an">the island</placeName></rs>. They get sufficient
               moisture from the dew and fog on the grass and succulent moss. When taken off
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName> these sheep have been
               known to perish with thirst beside running water.</p>
            <p>On the morning of <rs><date notAfter="1892-10-31">our second Saturday</date></rs> on
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>
               <persName key="#bor">Professor Borland</persName> seemed in an unusual hurry to be
               off on his customary tramp. The rest of us lingered behind, expecting every minute to
               catch a glimpse of the white sails of the <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie"
                     >Hattie</name></emph>. As the day waned our wonderment grew into a positive
               uneasiness.</p>
            <p>"It cannot be possible she is not coming!" <rs><persName key="#ebru">[my]
                     uncle</persName></rs> anxiously exclaimed, stopping in his impatient march to
               and fro on the beach, and directing a troubled glance at us. I knew he was picturing
               the disappointment of the dear home folks, who would be sure to look for us that
               night.</p>
            <p>The sun went down thirstily, leaving a fiery west that was like burnished brass.
               While we sat at supper <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs>
               returned. He greeted us with enforced cheerfulness, and I fancied his eyes evaded the
               grave regard of <rs><persName key="#ebru">my uncle</persName></rs> and <rs><persName
                     key="#rbra">the minister</persName></rs>.</p>
            <p>"The <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hattie">Hattie</name></emph> did not come!"
               [my] uncle abruptly began.</p>
            <p>"So I see, so I see! Well, we'll have to make the best of it till she does. I'm sure
               she couldn't leave us in a more charming spot. Why, that graveyard is a regular
               archæological mine! I could spend the rest of my days there."</p>
            <p>"So I supposed. Now, will you tell us just when we <emph>may</emph> expect <persName
                  key="#conl">Captain Conlan</persName>?"</p>
            <p>There was a cold insistence in Uncle Ned's voice that caused <rs><persName key="#bor"
                     >the perspiring professor</persName></rs> to wince and change color.</p>
            <p>"Certainly, <persName key="#ebru">Bruner</persName>. He'll be here without fail a
               week from to-day. The fact is, when I wrote to <rs><persName key="#mrsbor">my
                     wife</persName></rs> I told her to inform <rs><persName key="#mrsbru">Mrs.
                     Bruner</persName></rs> we had made up our minds to lengthen our stay to
                     <rs><date notAfter="1892-10-31">three weeks</date></rs> on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>. What more can you ask?"
                     <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> added, irritably.</p>
            <p>The <rs><persName type="group" key="#bor; #ebru">two friends</persName></rs> held
               hands a moment in silence, then <persName key="#ebru">Uncle Ned</persName>, quite
               pale and collected, replied, in a low voice:</p>
            <p>"I think you have behaved in a shamefully selfish and inconsiderate manner, and our
               business connection ends with to-day. The relics we find the coming week will be
               individual property."</p>
            <p>He glanced at <persName key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName> as if for confirmation. The
               latter quickly responded:</p>
            <p>"Quite right, my dear fellow. It is the least we can exact in common justice to
               ourselves."</p>
            <p>With this <rs><persName key="#ebru; #rbra">the two</persName></rs> walked apart,
               leaving <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> for the instant
               astonished and visibly perturbed.</p>
            <p>It puzzled me at the time, and it has since, to decide in my own mind whether
                  <persName key="#bor">Professor Borland</persName> had the vaguest realization of
               having done a dishonorable act in compelling us to remain another week on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>. After the conversation related
               he seemed to have totally forgotten the whole affair. He resumed his former
                  <emph>distrail</emph> or enthusiastic manner, according to his mood.</p>
            <p>This state of affairs might have proved dampening to our spirits under ordinary
               circumstances, but it must be confessed <persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and I
               felt but a momentary depression in consequence. The splendid freedom that was ours on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> had purged
               our nerves of every trace of supersensitiveness, and we continued to quaff royal
               bumpers of the true wine of life&#8212;the untainted air of the ocean.</p>
            <p>The ensuing Sabbath passed much as the previous one had done, but as the night
               deepened and <rs><persName key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> did not put in an
               appearance some fear was expressed lest he were lost or had met with an accident.
               After waiting another half-hour we agreed to go in search of him, each of us
               promising to fire a shot in case he should be found.</p>
            <p><persName key="#lbor">Leroy</persName> and I kept together, stumbling awkwardly in
               the dark over drifts of sand and ditches strewn with shell and rock. In the obscure
               light the most commonplace object presented a weird unreality which kept us all
               a-tingle with anticipation of something yet more awesome.</p>
            <p>Finally we half slid, half fell down a smooth embankment into a basinlike hollow,
               wherein we met a sight that was truly terrifying. The place was alive with spectral
               lights, revealing with frightful distinctness the fleshless grin of numberless
               skulls, and the ribby skeletons strewn about piece by piece, and all softly aflame.
               These lambent lights went out, were rekindled, shifted, danced and flickered, all in
               the same breath&#8212;a hideous play upon ghastly relics whose very nakedness was a
               dumb protest to the unholy illumination.</p>
            <p>Suddenly the full moon emerged from the fog, its familiar beams dispelling the
               strange phosphorescent display. Almost immediately the place regained much of its
               daytime appearance of unmitigated desolateness.</p>
            <p>"Hark! There's a gun. I hope father is all right. We'd better go straight back."</p>
            <p>I think neither of us was sorry to get away from that uncanny valley. We retraced our
               steps with all speed, and, shaping our course by the friendly beacon, we had no
               further difficulty in reaching camp.</p>
            <p>We were all glad enough to get back with our number unbroken, though <rs><persName
                     key="#bor">the professor</persName></rs> admitted that for a time he thought
               his case hopeless. He was completely lost in the fog, and had it not been for the
               stentorian shouts of <persName key="#rbra">Mr. Brand</persName> would probably have
               been forced to bivonae on the sand dunes the remainder of the night.</p>
            <p><rs><date notAfter="1892-10-31">The last three days</date></rs> of our outing were
               dismal enough, the rain falling in almost uninterrupted showers, making it impossible
               to kindle a camp fire. Fortunately we could share with the Chinamen the use of their
               tiny stove in the cabin, and were thus enabled to get something warm now and then.
               The worst of it was, our provisions ran short, so that between wet, cold and hunger
               there was genuine rejoicing when the <emph><name type="city" key="#sh_hattie"
                     >Hattie</name></emph> steamed into <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_coralharbor">Coral Harbor</placeName>. Only <rs><persName key="#bor">the
                     professor</persName></rs> lingered wistfully on shore until the last of his
               archæological treasures was snugly aboard, when we bade a long farewell to <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
