<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="journal"><orgName type="publication" key="#overlandmonthly">Overland
                     Monthly</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
               <date when="1875-10"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Schumacher1875">Some Remains of a Former
                     People</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="374" to="379"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#psc">Schumacher, Paul</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">SOME REMAINS OF <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">A FORMER
                        PEOPLE</orgName></rs>.</title></head>
            <p><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">THE group of islands</placeName></rs> off
                     <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">our southern
                     coast</placeName></rs>, of which <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San
                  Miguel</placeName> is the northernmost and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl"
                  >San Clemente</placeName> the farthest south, are reported by our oldest
               navigators as having been inhabited. In fact, <persName type="seaman" key="#jca"
                  >Cabrillo</persName>, who discovered <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName> and some of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs> in <date when="1542">1542</date>, makes the statement
               that he found them thickly populated by <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">an
                     ingenious people</orgName></rs>. Some collections of the remains of
                     <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">a former
                     race</orgName></rs> have been found on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">these islands</placeName></rs> at different times, and have
               reached the rooms of <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_smithsonian">the Smithsonian
                  Institution</orgName>. Another quite large collection, made by myself on
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the adjacent main-land</placeName>, was
               sent on; also, facts and conclusions reported, which induced <persName type="author"
                  key="#sba">Professor Spencer F. Baird</persName> to arrange an archæological
               exploring expedition to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these
                     islands</placeName></rs>, which commenced operations in <rs><date
                     when="1875-05">May of this year</date></rs> under my direction, and lasted
               nearly three months. On our way down, our party was accommodated by the revenue
               cutter <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_rush">Rush</name></emph>, <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#baker">Captain Baker</persName>, then on her southern cruise,
               which gave us easy access to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel
                  Island</placeName>.</p>
            <p><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">This island</placeName></rs> is a barren
               lump of sand, rising boldly from the sparkling ocean as we go south, and facing the
               sun in its descent from the meridian. There are some brown hills on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>&#8212;one forming the
               main ridge and the highest; but their dry and dusty appearance impresses the traveler
               with a dreariness not more comforting than the many light dunes and sandy slopes,
               over which the north-west winds whirl the sand in fog­like clouds that strike the
               practical eye with awe while roaming over these shifting hills. <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler Harbor</placeName>, which makes in on
               the eastern side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the
                  island</placeName></rs>, offers good shelter in north-west winds, and is well
               protected against a southwester by a reef stretching from the shore to <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sm">the islet</placeName></rs> which lies in the entrance
               of the small harbor, leaving <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">the
                     main channel</placeName></rs> on its northeastern side. High dunes rise from
               the bay at an angle of forty-five degrees, formed actually by the weight of the
               shifting sand, which rolls down the incline as if liquid. On landing, we found it
               necessary to wade through a mass of this steep loose sand to at least a height of
               eighty feet, where alone we could find a base on the top of a shell-heap to erect the
               tents for our small party.</p>
            <p>We found large shell deposits all over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, especially on the rocky northern end, about a mile
               from the harbor, near a spring. Another and larger spring is near the house. We found
               the kitchen refuse of a former population, covering a very large space. In traveling
               from here along the shore toward the north-western end, we passed many shell-mounds
               of greater or less extent, of which the surface findings are pretty well picked up by
               collectors and amateur <emph>curio</emph>-hunters, leaving only the heavy rude stone
               implements we occasionally met, as nobody cared particularly to be heavily loaded in
               traveling over these seemingly bottomless hills. We found on one of these shell
               deposits&#8212;thanks to their weight and insignificant appearance&#8212;very
               interesting and rare specimens of mortars, which showed the different stages of the
               manufacture of this utensil. At the north-west end, which is the farthest point of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs> from
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_cuylerharbor">Cuyler Harbor</placeName>, are
               undoubtedly found the largest shell-mounds on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>, but located on ever-shifting sand. We
               selected a wrong season, as the sand, driven by fierce north-west winds, had covered
               most of these deposits, and had made the two coves, which make in on both sides of
               the point, inaccessible for a boat-landing. Our findings, which we gathered in a
               week, were best procured, as we had learned during our previous explorations, in the
               graves. They corresponded in the main with the style of burial on <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_mld">the main-land</placeName>, where the grave­trench is
               partitioned into smaller rooms, although the materials used for this purpose are not
               slabs of sandstone as found in <placeName type="county" key="#co_slo">San Luis Obispo
                  County</placeName>, but mainly whalebones and split red wood; the skeletons lying
               closely packed from two to six feet underground, in an irregular state, with knees
               drawn up and arms stretched out on the sides of the body or resting over the chest.
               The implements we found buried in the common way about the skull.</p>
            <p>Sick and scaled by the exposure to the grinding sand, and under constant fear of
               losing our tents in the brisk blows that lasted day and night during our stay, we
               were glad to be able to charter a schooner which we found in port, owned by <orgName
                  type="company" key="#stockcompany">the Stock-raising Company</orgName> (who were
               engaged shearing their starving sheep), to take us to <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz Island</placeName>.</p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> is probably the
               prettiest island of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                  group</placeName></rs>; in picturesqueness it equals and in vegetation excels
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>. It is
               mountainous, with large stretches of <emph>mesa</emph>-land, especially at the
               eastern and western ends, where fine valleys and picturesque bluffs and ravines
               occur. Timber is found in many places on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz"
                     >the island</placeName></rs>, and quite extensive groves of conifers north of
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner's Harbor</placeName>,
               while stunted oak-trees grow on the high rocky hills and sides of the steep gulches,
               and low willows in the cañons. It is <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                     largest island</placeName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >the group</placeName></rs>, and has a fair shelter in <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_prisonersharbor">Prisoner's Harbor</placeName>, and in several places
               upon the west side, such as <placeName type="region" key="#re_smugglerscove"
                  >Smuggler's Cove</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_coche">Coche
                  Prietos</placeName>, and <placeName type="region" key="#re_forneyscove">Forney's
                  Cove</placeName>. There is good water in different springs and creeks found all
               over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs> the year
               round. It is owned by <orgName type="company" key="#scruzislandcompany">the Santa
                  Cruz Island Wool-growing Company</orgName>, which seems to be a profitable
               concern. Near a good wharf at <placeName type="region" key="#re_prisonersharbor"
                  >Prisoner's Harbor</placeName> stands a substantial adobe building, and back of it
               extends a beautiful valley which afforded us good camping-ground.</p>
            <p>Our party spent about a month on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">this
                     island</placeName></rs>, during which time we were active in making
               explorations all along its shores of fifty-eight miles in extent. Here we met the
               courteous officers of the steamer <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hassler"
                     >Hassler</name></emph> engaged in making soundings round <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs>. <rs><persName
                     type="seaman" key="#taylor">The captain</persName></rs> and all the officers
               offered their assistance in the most friendly manner to convey our party to such
               places as lay in their route of sailing and would not interfere with their own duty.
                     <rs><persName type="military" key="#cpat">The Superintendent of the United
                     States Coast Survey</persName></rs>, <persName type="military" key="#cpat"
                  >Captain C. P. Patterson</persName>, in view of the fact that the exploration was
               made at the expense of <rs><orgName type="governement" key="#gov_usa">the
                     Government</orgName></rs>, and for the national display at the coming <orgName
                  key="#centennial">Centennial Exposition</orgName>, having requested <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#taylor">Captain Taylor</persName>, the commander of the
                     <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_hassler">Hassler</name></emph>, to extend such
               help as he might deem proper, it gave us a great advantage in prosecuting our work,
               and saved much expense.</p>
            <p>Our main attention was again directed to finding and examining graves. The mode of
               burial is similar to that on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel
                  Island</placeName>, in the shell-mounds, and not separated from the kitchen refuse
               as described by <rs><persName type="author" key="#author3">a writer</persName></rs>
               in the <orgName type="publication" key="#overlandmonthly">OVERLAND</orgName> of <date
                  when="1874-10">October, 1874</date>, the adjacent ground being too rocky for the
               tools of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the former
                     population</orgName></rs>. Although each burying-ground we dug up yielded but
               poorly in comparison with such places on <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  neighboring main-land</placeName>, our findings on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scruz">this island</placeName></rs> were numerous, and many forms are
               new to science. We made here a collection of about thirty cases. The main articles we
               gathered were: Pots of magnesia-mica, worked in a wonderful manner out of solid
               pieces of this material, some specimens being thirty inches in diameter; mortars and
               pestles of sandstone; plates (<emph>tortillas</emph>) of magnesia-mica; bowls, cups,
               and spade­weights of serpentine; perforated sinkers; fish-hooks of shell and bone,
               very ingeniously made, especially those of bone; borers of all descriptions; a full
               set of tools for the manufacture of fish-hooks, together with the hooks in different
               stages of finish; a wooden sword, richly inlaid with shells; bone whistles and bone
               flutes; paints; shell-money, and money of pebble-stones; all kinds of shell-beads and
               ornamental carvings; brushes of soap-wood, used as combs; wooden utensils; a stone
               canoe, well modeled and finished; several canoes of wood; spoons; stone knives; flint
               lances, spear-heads, and arrow-points; specimens of iron knives and lances; part of a
               cradle, showing yet plainly the mode of making it; a large painted wooden carving;
               pipes; drinking-cups of stone; lamps; sling-balls; all kinds of bone carvings;
               remains of baskets, mats, and net-work; and many stone implements, the use of which
               is not yet ascertained.</p>
            <p>The burying-grounds at <placeName type="region" key="#re_smugglerscove">Smuggler's
                  Cove</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_coche">Coche
                  Prietos</placeName>, <placeName type="region" key="#re_almos">Almos</placeName>,
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_poso">Poso</placeName>, <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_forneyscove">Forney's Cove</placeName>, and <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_secretharbor">Secret Harbor</placeName> gave the best results. There is a
               report that a cave exists on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">the
                     island</placeName></rs>, showing remains of former habitation. We have been
               unable to ascertain anything proving the fact, and were assured by <persName
                  type="military" key="#sfo">Stehman Forney</persName>, of <orgName
                  key="#uscoastsurvey">the United States Coast Survey</orgName>, then doing the last
               of the topography of <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz
                  Island</placeName>, that no such cave exists. <rs><persName type="military"
                     key="#sfo">This gentleman</persName></rs>, and <persName type="military"
                  key="#green">Captain Greenwell</persName>, of the <orgName key="#uscoastsurvey"
                  >United States Coast Survey</orgName>, kindly rendered us their good services, and
               furnished information concerning <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the
                     islands</placeName></rs> and <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld"
                  >main-land</placeName> between <placeName type="region" key="#re_pointsal">Point
                  Sal</placeName> and <placeName type="region" key="#re_sanbuenaventuravalley">San
                  Buenaventura Valley</placeName>.</p>
            <p>While at <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">this island</placeName></rs> we
               enjoyed the visits of <persName type="author" key="#rothrock">Doctor
                  Rothrock</persName>, <persName type="author" key="#loew">Dr. Loew</persName>, and
               the zoölogist <persName type="author" key="#henshaw">Henshaw</persName>, all members
               of the scientific corps of <persName type="group" key="#wheelerexpedition">Lieutenant
                  Wheeler's Exploring Expedition</persName>. Being on their way to <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, the rendezvous for the members
               of that expedition, they made a close connection with <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_scruz">the island</placeName></rs> by the <emph><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_hassler">Hassler</name></emph>, and, having a few days' spare time,
               joined us in our rough camp at <placeName type="region" key="#re_forneyscove"
                  >Forney's Cove</placeName>, to observe our excavations, and also do some work
               themselves in their respective branches.</p>
            <p>At <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName> we chartered the
               schooner <emph><name type="ship" key="#sh_staroffreedom">Star of
                  Freedom</name></emph> to convey us to <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>. We reached <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">that
                     island</placeName></rs> on a dark night, with the wind blowing lively, which
               compelled <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#baker">the captain</persName></rs> to
               select the south end of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> as an anchorage. We fancied a campaign worse, if
               possible, than that at <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>,
               as <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> appeared to
               be a faint lump in a thick fog-like cloud of sand which was whirled densely over
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_staroffreedom">our neat craft</name></rs>,
               although we were a half-mile off shore. <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#baker">The
                     captain</persName></rs>, with a shrill-sounding voice, recited his usual spicy
               prayers with much vehemence; on the sand-spit, not far off, the breakers, which form
               a half-mile in length, rise to a great height, and cause a roaring like thunder; at
               intervals we heard the howling sea-lions in the kelpy water, if not at their rookery
               on the near shore; which, with the darkness, the annoying sand, and the furious wind
               rattling the anchor-chain in madness, gave the impression that we had left rather
               than landed. With good prospects to lose our anchor and find ourselves the next
               morning probably at <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>, we awaited the coming dawn, trusting ourselves to the
               captain's care. The next morning was beautifully clear and almost calm; the sea was
               still rough, and as the swells, caused by a strong current that passes the south end,
               swept the shore in an angle, care had to be taken to prevent <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_staroffreedom">the boat</name></rs> going broadside on, which is
               equivalent to capsizing.</p>
            <p><rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">The island</placeName></rs> is a lump of
               soft coarse yellowish-gray sandstone, about 500 feet in height. The broad backbone,
               which seems almost level on its top, falls off on both sides in steep gulches and
               ravines, where the eye is met by innumerable cave-like carvings done by the grinding
               sand. The eastern end is sandy; dunes stretching there across <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, beginning with the
               depression at the end of which the house is located. The vegetation of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> is like that of
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, ruined by
               overstocking it with sheep, which are here found in like starving condition. On the
               eastern end, near the house, we found some malva-bushes cleaned of their foliage to
               the reach of a sheep, which gave them the appearance of scrub oak-trees when seen
               from a distance. There are a few trees near the house, where a strong never-ceasing
               spring supplies the necessary water, which has a somewhat sweetish taste. The
               shifting sand has almost buried the adobe house, and its old inmate, the
               superintendent of <orgName type="company" key="#stockcompany">the Stock-raising
                  Company</orgName>. Farther on to the north-eastward, at the so-called <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_chineseharbor">Chinese Harbor</placeName>, is another
               spring with good water. It is at the eastern end, on the dunes, where we found the
               shell-mounds abundantly, although some are found at intervals all along the shore
               from the house toward the sand-spit on the south end, beyond which but few small ones
               exist; also a few on the western shores. The mode of burial on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">this island</placeName></rs> is different from that
               previously investigated. The bodies rest in distinct graves by themselves, lying on
               their backs, feet drawn up, and arms folded over the chest; the head either resting
               on the occiput, the side, or sunk to the breast. The skeletons, as a rule, were
               facing the east, although other directions were observed. Some show signs of having
               been buried in matting coated with asphaltum. Most of the skeletons and implements
               are laid bare by the winds. Our <emph>modus operandi</emph> was here changed; spade
               and pick were dispensed with, and in the first days our party went over the
               shell-mounds and piled the findings in heaps, which afterward were conveyed to the
               boat by horses procured of <rs><persName key="#sancatgov">the
                  "governor"</persName></rs> of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> (as <rs><persName key="#sancatgov">the old
                     man</persName></rs> styles himself), and thence taken by water to our
               camping-ground for a careful packing in boxes brought with us from <placeName
                  type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>. We obtained 127
               mortars&#8212;a heavy collection by itself&#8212;about 200 pestles, cups, trinkets, a
               small lot of quite unique sculptures, and some articles new to science.</p>
            <p>The money deposits on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this
                     island</placeName></rs> are remarkable. In some places on the shell-mounds we
               noticed, apart from the skeletons, and not buried with them, numerous small heaps of
               shells of the <emph>Olivella bipicata</emph>, and some of the land­shell <emph>Helix
                  strigosa</emph>; also, a uniform size of pebbles, seemingly blackened by fire,
               averaging in quantity from a half to one cubic foot, which were evidently stored
               there, and afterward exposed to the drifts of sand, forming conspicuous diminutive
               hillocks. We found as many as sixty of these deposits on one shell­mound. This, with
               the position of some of the implements we observed, seems to point to the fact that
               the last inhabitants were taken off suddenly. We found, for instance, instead of
               being buried with the dead, any mortars set in the ground to the rim, the pestle
               either resting in its opening or lying alongside, as if it had done its duty only
               some days before.</p>
            <p>The last island visited was <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa
                  Catalina</placeName>. It appears to be a long mountain removed from its base and
               planted in the wide ocean, whose waters are here wonderfully clear on account of the
               micaceous bottom. This mountain, seventeen miles in length, descends in innumerable
               steep gulches and ravines, and often abruptly ends in perpendicular bluffs, some of
               which are over a thousand feet high. About five miles from its western end
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs> is
               almost cut in two by a remarkable isthmus, forming on the northern side <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_isthmuscove">Isthmus Cove</placeName>, and on the other,
               the southern side, the fine but small port of <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_catalinaharbor">Catalina Harbor</placeName>. The eastern and western
               parts of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>
               are connected only by narrow strips of made land, not forty feet above water, and
               about 600 yards from ocean to ocean. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                     >The island</placeName></rs> is well known, and belongs to <persName
                  type="investor" key="#jli">James Lick</persName>, and is settled by squatters,
               mostly engaged in stock-raising, fishing, etc. Some mining has been done on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">the island</placeName></rs>,
               but to no advantage. It is well timbered, with plenty of water in wells and springs.
               The Government barracks are still in good condition, and offer shelter to picnic
               parties from <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the neighboring
                  main-land</placeName>, also to sheep-shearers in the time of wool-clip. In front
               of the porch we made our collection of rattle-snakes, that creep out from under the
               brick base of the building to indulge a healthy digestion in the warm sunlight.</p>
            <p>The archæology of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">this
                     island</placeName></rs> is said to have been ransacked by <rs><persName
                     key="#sancatgentle">a scientific gentleman of merit</persName></rs>, who
               lingered formerly around the picturesque isthmus. He told me himself, some time ago,
               that he had even spotted the "fat boy"&#8212;meaning the image of the temple to the
               sun, as reported by <persName type="missionfather" key="#asc">Padre de la
                  Ascension</persName>, of <persName type="seaman" key="#jca">Cabrillo</persName>
               fame, whose narratives he studied in the original. To my deep regret I found that
               there was but little left for our party to gather, and nothing new to science. Even
               the thick singularly-shaped cranium, much of a <emph>dolichocephalic</emph> pattern,
               has already been described by <persName type="author" key="#bharte">Bret Harte
               </persName>as the prehistoric skull of the <orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                  key="#natam_stanislaus">Stanislaus</orgName>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
