<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
    schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name type="person">Sara L. Schwebel</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Publisher</resp>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Research and Development</resp>
                    <name type="org">The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive Research and
                        Development Team</name>
                    <name type="org">University of South Carolina Center for Digital
                        Humanities</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public
                        domain. If re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this
                        digital archive, we request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last
                        Indians Digital Archive, Center for Digital Humanities, University of South
                        Carolina.</p>
                    <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected
                        by U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing
                        post-1923 material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and
                        identifying images, as well as the content of the articles, remain the
                        property of the periodicals and/or of the authors and artists themselves.
                        Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited;
                        permission must be obtained from the copyright holder. Archival material
                        published in this archive is used with permission of the institution or
                        library that holds it. Further reproduction, as well as quotation beyond
                        fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the copyright
                        holder.</p>
                    <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                        exclusively with the user.</p>
                </availability>
                <date/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#sfchronicle">San
                            Francisco Article</orgName></title>
                    <publisher/>
                    <editor/>
                    <biblScope unit="volume">89</biblScope>
                    <biblScope unit="issue">170</biblScope>
                    <date when="1906-12-30"/>
                    <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>,
                            <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
                    <bibl>
                        <title type="main" key="#Edwords1906">A Female Crusoe on the Island Of
                            Skulls.</title>
                        <biblScope unit="page" n="5"/>
                        <author><persName type="author" key="#edwords">Edwords, Clarence
                                E.</persName></author>
                    </bibl>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="main"><hi rend="bold"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                        key="#lw">A Female Crusoe</persName></rs> on <rs><placeName
                                        type="island" key="#i_scl">the Island Of
                                    Skulls</placeName></rs>.</hi></title></head>
                    <byline><hi rend="bold"> By <persName type="author" key="#edwords">CLARENCE E.
                                EDWORDS</persName>.</hi></byline>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="8"><persName type="seaman" key="#ase">ALEXANDER
                                SELKIRK</persName> had his <persName type="author" key="#dde">Daniel
                                Defoe</persName> to immortalize him and the <placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_jf">island of Juan Fernandez</placeName>, and in every man's
                            memory lingers the delights of hours spent with <name type="fictional"
                                key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name> wandering over his little empire
                            with <persName type="fictional" key="#friday">his man Friday</persName>
                            and his parrot and goats, but the chronicler of the weary months and
                            years of waiting spent by <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                    >a lone Indian woman</persName></rs> on <placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scl">San Clemente island</placeName>, off the <placeName
                                type="region" key="#re_socal">southern coast of
                                California</placeName>, is yet to come.</span></p>
                    <p>It has been many years since she was found and taken to a hospitable home in
                            <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>, and still
                        no one has taken her wonderful experience as the theme for a novel, nor has
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente island</placeName>
                        achieved notice because of her habitation thereon for <rs><date from="1835"
                                to="1853">eighteen years</date></rs> in solitude. Along <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_socal">the southern coast of the
                            State</placeName>
                        <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">this island</placeName></rs> is
                            <title type="article" key="#IllustratedAmerican1892">better known as the
                            Island of Skulls</title> than by its geographical name, and while the
                        peculiar features of the semi-desert bit of land have appealed to popular
                        fancy little attention has been given to either <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the marooned woman</persName></rs>
                        or the reason why she was there. In fact, her very presence and rescue are
                        almost looked upon as myths by the later residents who have gradually taken
                        the places of the first population of <placeName type="county"
                            key="#co_ventura">Ventura</placeName> and <placeName type="county"
                            key="#co_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> counties.</p>
                    <p>San C[l]emente's shores are bleak and drear, guarded by inhospitable coasts,
                        where rock and wave of restless ocean serve to keep off all except those who
                        are driven by necessity or curiousity to visit the land. High cliffs,
                        running up thousands of feet above the water, seem to guard the secrets of
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs>, and there is nothing inviting in the appearance
                        or the prospects of the land. <span type="trope" n="3">For this reason all
                            early navigators passed <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                    island</placeName></rs> by, and thus it came about that
                                    <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the lone Indian
                                    woman</persName></rs> finally ceased to hope for rescue, and,
                            with the stolidity of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                    key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">her race</orgName></rs>, abandoned
                            herself to her fate, thinking, if she ever thought at all, that she
                            would end her days near where <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lwchild">her baby</persName></rs> had perished at the time
                            she was left to live or die as fate willed.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="14">For <date from="1835" to="1853">eighteen long
                                years</date> she had lived alone, eking out an existence from the
                            shellfish which are so abundant on <rs><placeName type="island"
                                    key="#i_chi">these California islands</placeName></rs>, and so
                            far had her mind wandered from the normal that when <persName
                                type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName> happened
                            to notice from the deck of <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">his
                                    vessel</name></rs> that a human being was on <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs>, she fled
                            to the interior like some wild thing, afraid of her own kind. Nor was
                            her rescue accomplished without a long search, and then almost a battle
                            before she could be induced to accompany <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">her
                                    captors</persName></rs>.</span></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">Record of
                        Adventure.</hi></title></head>
                    <p>There is still record of the captain's
                        adventure<!--I cannot find any account of Nidever's that matches these quotes. If we do find it, it should be linked here. | RM-->,
                        told in his own language, and from it we may learn of the conditions on
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs>, <date when="1853">more than thirty years
                            ago</date>, when he found <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                >the solitary woman</persName></rs>. His is a plain, blunt tale,
                        divested of all attempt at sensationalism, simply reciting the incident as
                        if [it] were but one of many strange happenings which came to him in his
                        roving life on the high seas.</p>
                    <p>"Light winds and calms had marked the voyage up <rs><placeName type="region"
                                key="#re_socalcoast">the coast</placeName></rs>," writes <persName
                            type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName>, "and as we
                        came to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the outer
                                island</placeName></rs> we were carried close in shore by a current.
                        It was a clear day with but little wind and we could see everything on
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs> plainly. As I looked up to the top of the high
                        cliff which bordered the ocean I thought I saw a man, and on getting my
                        glass I plainly made him out. He was without any clothing, and seemed to try
                        to avoid being seen. I was sure it was some person who had been marooned and
                        I made landing after anchoring just off shore in a little bay. I took
                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">three
                                sailors</persName></rs> with me and searched <rs><placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> for a long
                        time without finding any one, but I saw that some one [sic] was there, for I
                        came upon piles of shells from clams and other shellfish. When we got over
                        toward t[h]e interior of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                island</placeName></rs> we came upon a great pile of bones, among
                        which were human skulls and leg and arm bones. It looked as if there had
                        been a battle and a great number of people killed. We found a trail leading
                        into the hills near a spring, and on following it we came upon <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_lwcave">a cave</placeName>. <span type="trope"
                            n="14">Here we found a <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                    >woman</persName></rs> so wild that she fought and scratched us
                            when we took hold of her. She had no weapons, but used her hands and
                            rocks. We finally overpowered her and took her to <rs><name type="ship"
                                    key="#sh_nidever">the vessel</name></rs>, where we gave her
                            clothing to cover herself, as she was naked. I tried to talk to her, but
                            she could not understand Spanish, English or any of the Indian languages
                            which I knew.</span> She seemed frightened at first and we could not get
                        anything out of her, but before we reached shore she tried to make signs
                        which we could not understand. [I] took her to my house, where she stayed
                        until she died, about a year later."</p>
                    <p><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The captain</persName></rs> did
                        not tell the entire story, for he was not a novelist and could not see the
                        wonderful part of the incident. To him it was but a human being rescued and
                        cared for, and [hi]s great heart did not stop with taking <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> from
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">her
                            prison</placeName></rs>, but her welfare was looked after by him until
                        she died.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">Remains a
                        Mystery.</hi></title></head>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="6">Who <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw"
                                    >this woman</persName></rs> was, what <rs><orgName
                                    type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">her
                                    tribe</orgName></rs>, and why she was left on <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> for <date
                                from="1835" to="1853">all those years</date>, are mysteries which
                            will never be solved, for all who by any possibility might know
                            something about it died long before she was taken to <placeName
                                type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName></span>. Two
                        stories have remained from the day when she was taken to the home of
                            <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Captain Nidever</persName>,
                        both, however, being surmises for she could never explain the cause of her
                        exile. The most prevalent story, and at the same time the most improbable,
                        is that when the Spanish owners of the land visited the island of <placeName
                            type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente</placeName> they found
                                <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">a tribe of Indians</orgName></rs> on
                        the verge of starvation, and decided to take them to <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, where they could
                        be cared for. All <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the
                            Indians</persName> were taken to <rs><name type="ship"
                                key="#sh_peoresnada">a vessel</name></rs>, and as they were
                        preparing to set sail <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this
                                woman</persName></rs> remembered that she had left <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her baby</persName></rs>
                        behind. She rushed back after <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                key="#lwchild">the little one</persName></rs> and before she
                        returned a storm arose which drove <rs><name type="ship"
                                key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> to sea, and it was
                        impossible to again make a landing. <rs><name type="ship"
                                key="#sh_peoresnada">The vessel</name></rs> sailed for <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, the authorities
                        intending to return for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                woman</persName></rs> when the weather became settled, but as time
                        passed she was forgotten and left to her fate. According to the story
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">the
                                baby</persName></rs> died from exposure and hunger, but
                                <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                            woman</persName></rs> lived on shell fish. The improbability of this
                        story lies in the fact that <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">the Spanish</persName></rs> who thought
                        enough of humanity to take a whole <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">tribe of Indians</orgName></rs> away
                        from starvation would scarcely leave <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                key="#lw">a woman</persName></rs> to starve alone with <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her baby</persName></rs>.</p>
                    <p>That no tribe of Indians was taken from <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> is further established by
                        the fact that when <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                                woman</persName></rs> was taken to <placeName type="city"
                            key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> the Indians of the country for
                        miles up and down <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">the
                                coast</placeName></rs> and in the interior were brought to see if
                        they could talk with her. She could understand none of the languages, nor
                        could any of the old Indians remember anything about the incident, nor could
                        they understand even one word used by <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>. Through the sign language she
                        made known a few of her wants, and by signs she told of the <date
                            from="1835" to="1853">eighteen years</date> that had passed since she
                        was left alone. It is extremely probable, however, that many more than
                        eighteen years had passed, for the passage of time would be uncounted after
                        a few years. This story is generally accepted because it is considered the
                        most plausible by the unthinking, but to my mind the other story, even
                        thought it be almost a legend, more readily accounts for the woman's
                        presence on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs>, as it also accounts for the numerous skeletons
                        which are found scattered over the place.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">The Pirate
                        Theory.</hi></title></head>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="11">According to this second story <placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente island</placeName> was at
                            one time densely populated by a strong and war-like tribe of
                                    <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                    key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">Indians</orgName></rs> which waged
                            war on the tribes of <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                                mainland</placeName> to such an extent that all communication
                            between them was severed. <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                    key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">The island Indians</orgName></rs>
                            were savage, and refused all connection with other tribes, and made a
                            practice of eating those of their enemies who fell into their hands. It
                            is supposed that <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_seri"
                                >the Seri Indians</orgName> who now inhabit the <placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_tib">Tiburón island</placeName> in the
                                <placeName type="region" key="#re_calgulf">gulf of
                                California</placeName> are a part of the same race, and are probably
                            the descendants of those who were formerly the inhabitants of
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the Island of
                                    Skulls</placeName></rs>.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="13">In the early days, so the story runs, <rs><persName
                                    type="group"
                                    key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                                    >Russian pirates</persName></rs> sailed down the shores of
                                <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName> and
                            devastated all the towns along <placeName type="region"
                                key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName>. <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                                    >These pirates</persName></rs> happened to be driven to
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                island</placeName></rs> where <rs><orgName
                                    type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">this
                                    tribe</orgName></rs> made its home, and a battle ensued, which
                            ended only with the extinction of <rs><orgName
                                    type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                                    savages</orgName></rs> with the exception of <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one woman</persName></rs>, who
                            hid in a <placeName type="region" key="#re_lwcave">cave</placeName>
                            until <rs><persName type="group"
                                    key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                                    >the invaders</persName></rs> had departed.</span> This story
                        accounts for the pile of bones which is still to be seen on <rs><placeName
                                type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs>, but it, too,
                        has the elements of the mythical, for it has been many years since
                                <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                                >Russian pirates</persName></rs> sailed the waters of the <placeName
                            type="region" key="#re_calcoast">California coast</placeName>, and as
                        there are no records of such devastation by <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                                >these corsairs</persName></rs> it must be taken as the invention of
                        some one [sic] who desired to account for the unaccountable. It is a fact
                        that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>
                        herself could not tell anything about either the reason for her isolation
                        nor for the presence of the numerous skulls of human beings which lie
                        scattered over a great space on one part of <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs>.</p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="3">When found <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                                    key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> was strong and healthy, but
                            good care and the confinement of civilized life did not agree with her,
                            and she had been in the care of <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni"
                                >Captain Nidever</persName> but a few months until she sickened. It
                            seemed as if the long life in the open air had brought about a bodily
                            condition which resented the indoor life of civilization, and a cold
                            soon changed into consumption, which carried her off despite all the
                            care that could be given her.</span> When she died she was just
                        beginning to talk a little English, but not enough to give any account of
                        her adventures or of the cause of the pile of skulls and bones which lies
                        scattered over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                island</placeName></rs>. This being the case, we can but speculate
                        on these causes, and one man's theory is as good as another's.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">Lived on Shell
                        Fish.</hi></title></head>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="14">According to the statements of <rs><persName
                                    type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col">those who found the
                                    woman</persName></rs>, she had lost the art of making a fire,
                            and lived entirely on raw shell fish and such berries and roots as she
                            found on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                    island</placeName></rs></span>. There had evidently been huts on
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs> when <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                                key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the tribe</orgName></rs> was living
                        there, but these had all been destroyed by the elements, and <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> made her
                        habitation in <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_lwcave">a
                                cave</placeName></rs>, or rather depression in the side of the
                        cliff, which formed a shelter from the wind and rain. Her domestic habit
                        remained with her, as is evidenced by an immense pile of abalone shells near
                        where she made her home. <span type="trope" n="14">A mass of seaweed and
                            brush formed her bed, and, as she had no method of replenishing her
                            clothing, she finally became naked, and it is probable that she went
                            this way for many years.</span></p>
                    <p>How she occupied her time, and why she did not cast herself into the sea
                        rather than undergo the loneliness and desolation of her surroundings can be
                        understood only by understanding the Indian mind. Her reversion to complete
                        savagery, leaving nothing but the animal in her to fight for life against
                        all the adverse circumstances surrounding her, was a natural sequence of the
                        accident which marooned her, and even to the day of her death she showed a
                        fear of other Indians, with the exception of <rs><persName
                                type="nativeamerican" key="#natamwoman1">one woman</persName></rs>
                        to whom she became deeply attached.</p>
                    <p>The approach to <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente
                            island</placeName> seems barred by the high cliffs which face the sea,
                        but as one gets closer he finds numerous little bays and inlets, and except
                        in stormy weather the landing is easy. The hills, which rise almost from the
                        water's edge, present a most picturesque appearance, with deep indentations
                        traversing them in every direction. Color and form blend admirably to make a
                        beautiful picture, and give an inviting prospect which belies the dreary
                        aspect presented after one lands on the island and goes into the interior.
                        All the hills seem to be covered with the softest verdure; but as one gets
                        closer it is noticed that the coloring comes from the earth and not from
                        growth. These cliffs rise fully a thousand feet from the sea, and are the
                        nesting place of myriads of sea birds of many kinds. <span type="trope"
                            n="8">Here the murre, the tern, the gull and various other feathered
                            inhabitants make their home, undisturbed by man or other enemy, and
                            undoubtedly <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the female
                                    Crusoe</persName></rs>, who remained so long as their neighbor,
                            must have utilized their eggs as a part of her food supply.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="5">Not the least strange feature of <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> is a
                            peculiar formation of rock which takes on queer and weird forms,
                            resembling to a marked degree petrifactions of trees. Those who have
                            been in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_mp">Monument Park</placeName>,
                            in <placeName type="state" key="#st_co">Colorado</placeName>, will
                            understand the idea, for it is very similar. Like so many small tree
                            trunks, bereft of branches, these rocks rise in every direction, ranging
                            in size from small saplings to trees a foot in diameter. Investigation
                            shows, however, that they are not petrifactions, but are sandstone
                            formations which have been cut by nature's sand blast into the shapes
                            they now present. Standing erect, as they do, in the midst of a waste of
                            sand, they present a most drear and desolate appearance. It looks as if
                            some mighty cataclysm had swept over the place, arresting all growth,
                            and preserving conditions of a dead and gone age.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="5">Were one to permit his imagination to run riot, as
                            the conditions would warrant, he might well believe that the ghosts of
                            those who had fought the battle which left the plain strewn with
                            skeletons, were still standing guard over the land for which they
                            struggled. Go there on some moonlight night and the feeling changes into
                            the uncanny, and chills chase each other up and down the spines of even
                            the bravest men. Some of these formations take on the appearance of
                            animals, and some of human beings, while it is easy to see gnomes
                            working their unholy spite against mortals who dare to invade their
                            realm.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="5">It can readily be seen why the Indians of the
                            mainland shun <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">this
                                    island</placeName></rs>, and why it is impossible to get any of
                            them to go ashore. They have the hereditary fear of <rs><orgName
                                    type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                                    cannibals who once inhabited the place</orgName></rs> handed
                            down through generations and changed with the changing times until now
                            they no longer understand either cannibal or enemy in their terror, but
                            fear the spirits of evil whom they believe haunt the place where so many
                            bones attest the death of an unknown people.</span></p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="5">So deep rooted is the fear of <rs><placeName
                                    type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> that few
                            of the mainland Indians will even talk about it or the sights that are
                            to be seen there. They have heard of the dead bodies and of the strange
                            formations and are content to let it rest with the hearing. They have
                            not been to <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                    island</placeName></rs> nor will they ever go unless they are
                            driven there through stress of weather when they happen to be fishing
                            off shore and are caught in a storm.</span></p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head><title type="section"><hi rend="bold">Skeletons of
                        Humans.</hi></title></head>
                    <p>Lying some eighty miles southwest of the city of <rs><placeName type="city"
                                key="#ci_ven">San Buena Ventura</placeName></rs> and away from
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the other islands of the
                                Santa Barbara chain</placeName></rs> which forms the outer circle of
                                <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_sbchannel">the
                                channel</placeName></rs> made famous because of its use by the
                        national war ships in their trials of speed, <placeName type="island"
                            key="#i_scl">San Clemente island</placeName> is little visited and
                        little known. There is nothing on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl"
                                >the island</placeName></rs> to invite those commercially
                        incl[i]ned, and its archaeological opportunities have attracted but few
                        scientists on account of the difficulty experienced in reaching
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs> and the obstacles in the way of enjoying a
                        sojourn there. For this reason, perhaps, <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> is little known. What is
                        known is of a nature to invite only the most ardent student, for outside of
                        the queer formations mentioned but two facts are of importance.</p>
                    <p>Along <placeName type="regione" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>, from
                            <placeName type="region" key="#re_baja">Lower California</placeName>
                        clear up to the <placeName type="region" key="#re_colriver">Columbia
                            river</placeName> are to be found mounds containing what is known as
                        kitchen-middens where vanished Indian tribes once had their homes. On
                            <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San Clemente island</placeName> is
                        a kitchen-midden of most peculiar nature, in that it is composed almost
                        entirely of red abalone shells. These shells lie scattered all over a tract
                        of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs>
                        where <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva"
                                >the tribe</orgName></rs> evidently had its permanent domicile, and
                        as the wind blows and the sands shift these shells, change their position,
                        become uncovered, and are again buried in the sand. Along the shore of
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs> these abalones are found in great quanitities,
                        and from the size of the pile of shells on the mound they evidently formed
                        an important part of the provisions of <rs><orgName
                                type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                                Indians</orgName></rs>.</p>
                    <p>But it is to the skeletons of human beings that <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> owes its greatest
                        prominence. On the side of a sand-covered slope, extending from the sea to
                        the interior hills of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                island</placeName></rs> are found hundreds of bones of men and
                        women, and even of little children. Skulls by the dozen are there, and while
                        nearly all of them have the characteristics of the savage races, some have
                        the appearance of the Caucasian, and this leads to the belief that the bones
                        are those of the men who fell in battle between <rs><orgName
                                type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                                Indians</orgName></rs> and <rs><persName type="group"
                                key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                                >Russian pirates</persName></rs>. The dry atmosphere of
                                <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                            island</placeName></rs> has preserved the bones to such an extent that
                        it is impossible to tell the age, or rather, the time that has elapsed since
                        the people were killed. One of the strange features of these bones is the
                        fact that none of them show indications of having been broken by weapons.
                        The skulls are intact and in several instances the bones lie just as they
                        would normally, there being no animals on <rs><placeName type="island"
                                key="#i_scl">the island</placeName></rs> to disturb them.</p>
                    <p>It is easy to see from an examination of these bones that two races are
                        represented, for some of them are very large, while the most of them are of
                        people under the average size. The bones of the women and children are all
                        of the Indian type, but among the men many are large framed and the larger
                        skulls show a higher type of intellect. This admixture of the skeletons of
                        two distinct people is of itself a refutation of the belief that these
                        skeletons are of a tribe that was swept away by an epidemic of by
                        starvation.</p>
                    <p>While many utensils used in grinding corn and in cooking are found scattered
                        among the bones, and also among the shells of the kitchen-midden, neither
                        spear nor arrow head is to be found. Possibly such as may have been there
                        among the bones on the field of battle were carried away by the earlier
                        discoverers of the place, who took the relics most easily cared for. It
                        would seem probable that with all these skeletons there would be a few
                        evidences of a fierce fight, but, as before mentioned, no bones show marks
                        of wounds and no remains of weapons of any character are to be found.</p>
                    <p>Several well-preserved Indian mortars used in grinding corn are scattered
                        over the ground among the bones, and also among the abalone shells, and in
                        several places are broken bits of pottery of the crudest kind. This pottery,
                        as well as the mortars, has evidently been brought to the island, for there
                        are no evidences of kilns for burning the pottery, and the mortars are made
                        of a stone foreign to the island.</p>
                    <p><span type="trope" n="11">Another legend which accounts for the presence of
                            these bones is that <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                    island</placeName></rs> was sacred to a certain tribe which used
                            it only on ceremonial occasions when they took their prisoners there and
                            held feasts on human flesh. According to this story no people inhabited
                                    <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                island</placeName></rs>, but on periodical occasions this
                            cannibalistic tribe went there, and after feasting, left the bones,
                            which gradually accumulated. According to this theory <rs><persName
                                    type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> who
                            was rescued was one of the prisoners who escaped by some means and
                            remained hidden away for many years, even after the coming of the whites
                            caused a cessation of the savage rites.</span> Many things connected
                        with the bones as well as with <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">the
                                island</placeName></rs>, bear out this theory, and also account for
                        the fact that no weapons have been found, and that the bones show no
                        evidences of injury by w[o]unds.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
