<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="magazine"><orgName type="publication" key="#latimesmag">Los Angeles
                     Times Magazine</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">55</biblScope>
               <date when="1936-08-09"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_la">Los Angeles</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Bennett1936">Mrs. Robinson Crusoe: She Lived Isolated,
                     for Eighteen Years on San Nicolas—Off our Southern California Shores. When They
                     Rescued Her She Withered and Died in the Discomfort of our Cramped
                     Civilization</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="3"/>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="14"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#wbe">Bennett, William
                     Crosby</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main"><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">MRS. ROBINSON
                        CRUSOE</persName></rs></title></head>
            <byline>&#8212; BY <persName type="author" key="#wbe">WILLIAM CROSBY
               BENNETT</persName></byline>
            <p><span type="trope" n="8">She lived, isolated, for <rs><date notBefore="1835"
                        notAfter="1853" cert="high">eighteen years</date></rs> on <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>&#8212;off our <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_socalcoast">Southern California
                  shores</placeName>.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="3">When they rescued her she withered and died in the
                  discomfort of our cramped civilization[.]</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="8">THE original of Daniel Defoe's <name type="fictional"
                     key="#rcr">Robinson Crusoe</name> was, as everyone knows, a sailor named
                     <persName type="seaman" key="#ase">Alexander Selkirk</persName>, who, from
                     <date when="1704">1704</date> to <date when="1709">1709</date>, was marooned on
                  the island of <placeName type="island" key="#i_jf">Juan Fernandez</placeName>, 300
                  miles west of <placeName type="country" key="#co_chile">Chile</placeName>, and
                  from this bare record <rs><persName type="author" key="#dde">the
                     author</persName></rs> made his masterpiece of ingenuity, reflection and
                  adventure&#8212;a shrine destined to live as long as youthfulness exists in the
                  world; but few are aware that a century and a half later, <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">another forlorn creature</persName></rs>
                  dwelt alone on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">an uninhabited
                        island</placeName></rs>, off our <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast"
                     >California coast</placeName>. And to make matters worse, this time it was
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a female
                     Crusoe</persName></rs>. Against Selkirk's five years' isolation, <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">this poor thing</persName></rs> lived in
                  solitude for <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high"
                        >eighteen</date></rs>, without even a man <name type="fictional"
                     key="#friday">Friday</name> for company, and she probably would have ended her
                  life on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this rugged crumb of land in the
                        Pacific Ocean</placeName></rs>, unknown and unsung, had it not been for a
                  chance discovery of her presence there.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">It was on a sunny day in <date when="1835-07">July,
                     1853</date>, that <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">a party of otter
                        men</persName></rs> from <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                     Barbara</placeName> anchored <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">their
                        schooner</name></rs> off the northeastern coast of the Island of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, some eighty or ninety miles
                  distant, and established a camp on shore. The party consisted of <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Capt. Nidiver</persName>, a man named
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs>,
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#col">an Irish cook</persName></rs>
                  and <rs><persName type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">a crew of
                        mission Indians</persName></rs>. The evening after their arrival
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">the captain</persName></rs> and
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> strolled
                  a mile or so down the beach, enjoying their pipes and making plans for their work.
                  It was a moonlight [moonlit] night, almost as bright as day, with the stars
                  shining large and clear from a low sky. As they were about to retrace their steps
                  toward the camp <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidiver</persName>
                  stopped suddenly, looked hurriedly around, and then knelt on his knee to examine
                  the ground. Plainly outlined on the shore was the print of a slender, naked
                  foot!</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">"My God!" <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">the
                        captain</persName></rs> exclaimed. "There is a woman on <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>!" At dawn the next day
                  he and <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> returned
                  to the spot and found a basket of rushes hanging from a tree. It contained bone
                  needles, thread made of sinews, shell fish-hooks, ornaments and a partly completed
                  robe of birds' plumage, the feathers pointing downward, and so skillfully matched
                  as to seem one continuous sheen of changeful luster. <persName type="frontiersman"
                     key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> proposed leaving the things untouched, but
                        <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> scattered
                  them about, saying that if they were picked up it would be proof <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the owner</persName></rs> was alive and had
                  visited the place. Extending their search inland, they discovered several
                  circular, roofless inclosures, made of woven brush. Near these shelters were
                  poles, with dried meat hanging from elevated cross-pieces. In the fissures of the
                  rocks, near a spring of fresh water, were wedged dried fish and seal blubber; but
                  there was no sign of the near presence of <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">the one to whom the provisions
               belonged</persName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">After several days' search <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs> abandoned the task and started hunting the otters. This
                  lasted for weeks and <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the well-loaded
                        schooner</name></rs> was preparing for the return trip to <placeName
                     type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> when <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Capt. Nidiver</persName> proposed further search
                  for <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                  woman</persName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4">"If she is alive we ought to find her," he said. "If dead,
                  we will look for her body even if we have to scrape <rs><placeName type="island"
                        key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> inch by inch."</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="4"><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">The
                        captain</persName></rs> ordered preparations made and <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                        entire crew</persName></rs> started on what <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#col">the Irish cook</persName></rs> called a
                  woman-ghost hunt. Near the head of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs> they came across a bone house, skillfully interlaced
                  with rushes. An olla and stove-in basket were near the door, but all around the
                  weeds were untrampled and the whole place had a deserted look. Still <persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> urged <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">his
                        companions</persName></rs> on. After several days' march, a dangerous climb
                  over slippery rocks brought them to a spot where there were fresh footprints made
                  by the same slender naked foot. These were followed up the cliffs until they were
                  lost in the thick moss that covered the ground. <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                        key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs>, walking on ahead, sighted a moving object
                  long way off on the hills. At first glance it appeared like a bird, but it moved
                  about in such a singular manner that he advanced stealthily to find out what it
                  really was. Drawing nearer, he was dumfounded [dumbfounded] to discover it was the
                  head of a woman, barely visible above the low woven-brush sides of her roofless
                  retreat in the bushes.</span></p>
            <p>As <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">the sailor</persName></rs> approached
               nearer, a pack of tamed wild dogs, crouching at the woman's feet, began to growl; but
               without looking around she uttered a peculiar cry which immediately silenced them,
               and they ran away to the hills. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >Brown</persName></rs> halted within a few yards of her and, himself unseen,
               watched every movement within the hut. Inside the inclosure was a mound of grass,
               woven baskets filled with various articles and a rude knife made of a piece of iron
               hoop, thrust into a wooden handle. A fire smoldered near and a pile of bones lay in
               the ashes.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="3">The complexion of <rs><persName type="nativeamerian"
                        key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs>, he noted, was much fairer than the
                  ordinary Indian, her personal appearance pleasing, features regular, her hair
                  thick and brown, falling about her shoulders in a tangled mat.</span> From the
               time he arrived within hearing, she kept up a continual talking to herself. She was
               leaning forward, shading her eyes with her hand, watching the men from the schooner
               crossing the flat land far below her dwelling. After looking at them for a while with
               marked anxiety on her face, she crouched in terror, but immediately started up as if
               to run. <rs><persName type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">The men on the
                     flat</persName></rs> had not seen her, and <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                     key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs>, putting his hat on the ramrod of his gun,
               lifted and lowered it to attract their attention, and when he had done so, intimated
               with signs that <rs><persName type="nativeamerian" key="#lw">the
                  woman</persName></rs> was found, and that they should spread out in order to catch
               her if she tried to escape.</p>
            <p>Before <rs><persName type="group" key="#cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs> reached the cliff, <rs><persName type="frontiersman"
                     key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> stepped around in sight and spoke. She gave a
               frightened look, ran a few steps, but instantly controlling herself, stood still and
               addressed him in an unknown tongue. She seemed to be between 40 and 50 years of age,
               in fine physical condition, erect, with well-formed neck and [ar]ms and unwrinkled
               face. She was dressed in a tunic-shaped garment, made of the satiny plumage of the
               green cormorant, low in the neck, sleeveless, and reaching to the ankle. The dress
               was similar to the one found in the tree. As <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the men</persName></rs> came up, she
               greeted them each in the way she had met <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >Brown</persName></rs>, and with a simple dignity, not without its effect on
               both Indians and white men, made them welcome and set about preparing [f]ood for them
               from her scanty store.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="1">There were several dialects spoken by <rs><persName
                        type="group" key="#msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the Indian crew</persName></rs>,
                  but none of them was able to converse with <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                        key="#lw">the strange woman</persName></rs>, or understand a word she
                  uttered, and they were obliged to let her know by signs that they were going to
                  take her with them. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >Brown</persName></rs> went through the motion of packing her things in
                  baskets, shouldering them and walking in the direction of the beach. She
                  understood instantly and made preparations to go with them. One of the heaviest
                  loaded baskets she swung without any unusual effort over her back, and, taking a
                  burning brand from the fire, followed after <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the men</persName></rs> who
                  were carrying her other possessions. Upon reaching <rs><name type="ship"
                        key="#sh_nidever">the boat</name></rs>, she entered without hesitation,
                  going forward to the bow, kneeling and holding to either side.</span> When
                     <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_nidever">the schooner</name></rs> was reached,
               she went aboard without any trouble and sat down near the stove in the cabin and
               quietly watched <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the men</persName></rs>
               at their work. To replace her feather dress, which was subsequently sent to
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_rom">Rome</placeName> and placed in the <orgName
                  type="museum" key="#mu_vaticanmuseum">Vatican Museum</orgName>, <rs><persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> made her a petticoat of
               ticking; and with a man's cotton shirt and gay handkerchief, her semi-civilized dress
               was completed. While <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                  >Brown</persName></rs> was sewing, she watched him closely and laughed at his
               manner of using a needle. She showed him that her way was to puncture the cloth with
               her bone needle and then put the thread through the holes. She signified that she
               wished to try a threaded needle and <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                     >Brown</persName></rs> gave her sewing materials, but she could not thread the
               needle. <span type="trope" n="10"><rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi"
                        >Brown</persName></rs> did it for her and gave her an old coat of Capt.
                  Nidiver's to mend, and while she took her first sewing lesson she told by signs
                  portions of her life on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                        island</placeName></rs>.</span></p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="10">From time to time she had seen ships pass, but none came to
                  take her off. She watched as long as she could see them, and, after they were out
                  of sight, she threw herself on the ground and cried, but after a time she walked
                  over <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> until
                  she forgot about it and could smile again. She had seen people on the beach
                  several times. But she was afraid and hid until they had gone and then wept
                  because she had not made herself known. She intimated that <rs><persName
                        type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> had taken her by
                  surprise and she would not run because she liked his face and felt he had been
                  sent to take her to <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">her people</persName>,
                  who had gone away on <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">a ship</name></rs>
                  with white men. <rs><persName type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">The
                     sailor</persName></rs> understood by her signs that at one time she had
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">a nursing
                     baby</persName></rs>, which she represented by sucking her finger and placing
                  her arm in the position of holding an infant at the breast. She waved her hand
                  over the sea to indicate <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                        ship</name></rs> sailed away, and then that she could not find <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her child</persName></rs> and wept
                  until she was very ill and lay prostrate for days in a bed of plants. She had
                  nothing to eat but leaves. When she somewhat revived, she crawled to a spring and
                  after a time, as her strength returned, she made a fire by rubbing a pointed stick
                  she showed him along the groove of a flat stick until a spark was
               struck.</span></p>
            <p>Who was this mysterious woman? This was the question that <rs><persName
                     type="frontiersman" key="#cdi">Brown</persName></rs> asked himself, and one
               that naturally arises in our mind. In order to answer it in part, at least, it will
               be necessary to begin quite far back in history. The <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_chi">Santa Barbara Islands</placeName>, on one of which this strangest of
               strange romances was enacted, lie to the southward of the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_sbchannel">Santa Barbara Channel</placeName>, <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_an">the nearest of the group</placeName></rs> being some
               twenty-five miles distant from <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the
                  mainland</placeName>. <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">The
                     islands</placeName></rs> are named <placeName type="island" key="#i_an"
                  >Anacapa</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>,
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                  Nicolas</placeName>. In the year <date when="1542">1542</date>, <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#jca">Juan Rodriguez Cabrillo</persName>, the credited
               discoverer of <placeName type="region" key="#re_spcal">California</placeName>, landed
               on what is now known as <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>
               and christened it Isla de Posesion. He died on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs>
               <rs><date when="1543">the following year</date></rs> and is buried in its sands,
               although his grave has never been located. But delving still further into our
               research we find that even berore Cabrillo's time <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> and <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">islands</placeName></rs> were inhabited by <rs><orgName
                     type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">a populous
                     people</orgName></rs>, the origin of whom, however, is unknown.</p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, on which the scenes of
               this wild romance are laid, was the outermost of <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">the group</placeName></rs>. It was at one time the abode of
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a
                     people</orgName></rs> differing in customs and modes of life from those on
                  <placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName> and neighboring
                  islands.<span type="trope" n="3"> A scientist, named <persName type="author"
                     key="#lce">De Cessac</persName>, engaged in collecting archeological specimens
                  for the <orgName type="government" key="#gov_french">French government</orgName>,
                  left a well authenticated record that the relics found on <placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> were more elaborate and showed a superior
                  workmanship to those he examined on the other islands and <placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_mld">the mainland</placeName>.</span> He also found on <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> articles of warfare and domestic
               use which evidently belonged to a northern tribe and were similar to those found by
               him on the coast of <placeName type="region" key="#st_ak">Alaska</placeName>. Hence
               he draws the inference that <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> was at one time the dwelling place of the north country
               tribes.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="11">It is also recorded that a ship from <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_bo">Boston</placeName>, commanded by a <persName type="seaman"
                     key="#whi">Capt. Whitmore</persName>, brought down from <placeName type="city"
                     key="#ci_si">Sitka, Alaska</placeName>, a company of <orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">Kodiaks</orgName> for the
                  purpose of otter hunting on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName>. These were left as permanent settlers upon <rs><placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> and years of feud
                  resulted in a massacre, in which every male islander was killed by the powerful
                  and well-armed <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak"
                     >Kodiaks</orgName>. The women were taken by <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_kodiak">the victors</orgName></rs>,
                  lived with them and bore children.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="6">As the years passed <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName> faded away strangely and rapidly, so that in <date
                     when="1830">1830</date> less than twoscore men, women and children
                  remained.</span></p>
            <p>It was not until <date when="1835">1835</date> that the schooner <name type="ship"
                  key="#sh_peoresnada">Peor es Nada</name>, commanded by <persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#iwi">Capt. Williams</persName>, collector of the port of
                  <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San Pedro</placeName>, was sent by the
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#aji; #ndur; #misfats">church
                     fathers</persName></rs> to fetch <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the
                  benighted people of San Nicolas</persName> and place them under their spiritual
               guidance. On the way over a severe storm suddenly overtook <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> and a landing on <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs> was made with extreme
               difficulty. To make matters worse the wind continued to increase in fury. No time was
               to be wasted. <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">The islanders</persName>, some
               twenty in number, were hurried in boats to <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada"
                     >the schooner</name></rs> and she immediately set sail. In the excitement and
               confusion it was not realized that <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild"
                     >an infant</persName></rs> had been left behind on <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_sn">the island</placeName></rs>, but not many moments passed before
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the frantic
                  mother</persName></rs> made that fact known to <persName type="frontiersman"
                  key="#chu; #iwi">the captain</persName> and with gestures implored him to return.
               But on account of the storm and the fear of wrecking his vessel he dared not comply
               with her request. <span type="trope" n="9">Finding it was useless and <rs><name
                        type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the ship</name></rs> was heading out to
                  sea, <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the mother</persName></rs>
                  became desperate and in spite of all attempt[s] to detain her, threw herself into
                  the water and started to swim toward the shore.</span> It was impossible to
               attempt to save her and, as she soon vanished from sight in the terrific surf, she
               was supposed to have perished.</p>
            <p>After a rough passage, <rs><name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">the
                  schooner</name></rs> finally reached <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sp">San
                  Pedro</placeName>, where <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the
                  islanders</persName> were sent to <placeName type="mission" key="#mi_sg">San
                  Gabriel Mission</placeName>, fifteen miles away. It was the intention of <persName
                  type="frontiersman" key="#iwi">Capt. Williams</persName> to return immediately to
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> as soon as the storm
               abated, to see if <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                  woman</persName></rs> or <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild"
                     >child</persName></rs> were living, but <rs><name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the schooner</name></rs> received orders from the owners
               to proceed at once to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>
               and thence to <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>. She
               never reached <rs><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">the latter
                  port</placeName></rs>, but was wrecked at the entrance to the <placeName
                  type="region" key="#re_thegoldengate">Golden Gate</placeName>.</p>
            <p><rs><date when="1850">Fifteen years</date></rs> passed and the uncertain fate of
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> and
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">child</persName></rs> was
               forgotten apparently by everyone but <rs><orgName type="missionfathers"
                     key="#misfats">the tender-hearted mission fathers</orgName></rs>. Vessels were
               scarce, but in <date when="1850">1850</date> they managed to persuade one <persName
                  type="seaman" key="#tje">Thomas Jeffries</persName>, who had come into the
               possession of a small schooner, to visit <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the
                     island</placeName></rs> and search for them. On his return he reported no sign
               of human life there. But evidently <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the
                     woman</persName></rs> did not perish, although <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lwchild">her infant</persName></rs> did, and on
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">this sea-girt isle</placeName></rs>
               she lived a solitary life for <rs><date notBefore="1835" notAfter="1853" cert="high"
                     >eighteen years</date></rs>.</p>
            <p>On arriving at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName>,
                  <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Capt. Nidiver</persName> placed
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> in the
               care of <rs><persName key="#sni">his wife</persName></rs>. The news of her arrival
               and her strange life spread rapidly, and the house was crowded with visitors. When
               the ship <name type="ship" key="#sh_fremont">Fremont</name> came into port soon
               after, <rs><persName type="seaman" key="#fremontcpt">the captain</persName></rs>
               offered <persName type="frontiersman" key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> half of all he
               would make if he would allow him to exhibit <rs><persName type="nativeamerican"
                     key="#lw">the woman</persName></rs> in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San
                  Francisco</placeName>. The offer was coldly refused. <persName type="frontiersman"
                  key="#gni">Nidiver</persName> said that neither he nor <rs><persName key="#sni"
                     >his wife</persName></rs> would for a moment consider that <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the friendless creature</persName></rs> should
               be made a show of for the curious.</p>
            <p><rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">The strange woman</persName></rs> was
               bitterly disappointed when none of <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">her
                  kin</persName> could be found. <span type="trope" n="3">She was patient and
                  cheerful, however, looking eagerly into every new face for recognition, and
                  sometimes singing softly to herself. Soon she began to droop under civilization,
                  probably missing the outdoor life of her island camp.</span> After a time she
               became too weak to walk and was carried to the porch, where she dozed for hours in
               the sunshine. Believing that a return to the old diet might help her, <persName
                  key="#sni">Mrs. Nidiver</persName> procured seal meat and roasted it in ashes, but
               when it was presented to her she could not eat the food. One day she fell from her
               chair and immediately lapsed into unconsciousness. It was soon evident that she was
               reaching the end of her life. <persName type="missionfather" key="#sanchez">Father
                  Sanchez</persName>, a Catholic priest, was summoned and, after christening
                     <rs><persName type="nativeamericant" key="#lw">the nameless
                  creature</persName></rs> "Juana Marie," he administered the last rites of <orgName
                  type="church" key="#ch_catholic">the church</orgName> to <rs><persName
                     type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the dying woman</persName></rs>. <span
                  type="trope" n="3">Within the walled cemetery at the old <placeName type="mission"
                     key="#mi_sb">Santa Barbara Mission</placeName>, under the shelter of its tower,
                        <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">the heroine of San
                        Nicolas</persName></rs> was interred and, to this day; should you ask, the
                  Franciscan brothers will point out her grave.</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
