<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="journal"><orgName type="publication" key="#overlandmonthly">Overland
                     Monthly</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
               <date when="1874-06-15"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#ci_sf">San Francisco</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Dall1874">The Lord of the Isles</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="522" to="526"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#whd">Dall, William
                     Healey</persName></author><date when="1874-06-15"/>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><title type="main">THE <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">LORDS OF
                        THE ISLES</orgName></rs>. </title></head>
            <p>AS we survey the <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">Californian
                     islands</placeName></rs>, the question rises to the lips: Was ever land so
               wasted and desolate enshrined in such a rich and sunny sea, or blessed with a climate
               more delightful? The delicate haze peculiar to <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_calcoast">the coast</placeName></rs> softens and enriches the dry
               brown color of the hills; and the harshness of the bluffs and ragged peaks is
               modified by the blue, calm water which ripples on the shore. At a slight distance
               from some of the larger islands, the tangled chaparral and weedy growth, which nestle
               in the deep ravines, lend a slight verdure to the landscape, and on the whole the
               prospect is not unpleasing.</p>
            <p>On landing, this deceitful glamour is soon dispelled. The vegetation resolves itself
               into stunted, thorny bushes, prickly cactus, and sparse and unattractive weeds. Water
               is almost absent, and when found, except in one place on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>, is mawkishly sweet with alkali, or bitter
               with other minerals.</p>
            <p><placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">Clemente</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, and, for the most part, <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, are barren wastes of sand.
               Except the last, and including <placeName type="island" key="#i_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> and <placeName type="island" key="#i_an">Anacapa</placeName>,
               water is totally absent, except during the winter rains. <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sr">Santa Rosa</placeName>, <placeName type="island" key="#i_scruz">Santa
                  Cruz</placeName>, and <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                  >Catalina</placeName> are more favored, but only relatively. The last mentioned
               five are high and rocky, and the others comparatively low.</p>
            <p>Here and there are tolerable anchorages, and there is one good, but very small,
               harbor on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName>. The only
               value of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> is
               for sheep ranges, though in those places where water exists, in favorable seasons,
               the cultivator may obtain tolerable crops, in patches of small extent. When the
               season is unfavorable, the sheep and cattle die by thousands, not from thirst, but
               from the entire desiccation and disappearance of the scanty herbage necessary to
               sustain them. Small land-birds are scarce, and the more plentiful quail are very shy.
               A diminutive fox obtains a living in some unexplained way, and occasionally a
               cotton-tail rabbit may be seen disappearing in a clump of cactus, with a reckless
               disregard of the omnipresent spines which is little short of miraculous. Beneath
               every stone nestle the greenish-yellow centipede, a small kind of scorpion, or the
               disgusting tarantula. In the summer, the common rattlesnake abounds in every bunch of
               shrubbery and crevice of the rocks. On the sandy surface of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_southernchi">the lower islands</placeName></rs> may be
               seen, everywhere, anchored by their fore-legs and head deeply buried in the sand, a
               variety of beetles of the most nauseous odor and unprepossessing appearance. The
               large, but harmless, yellow molecricket which abounds there is hardly less uninviting
               in its physiognomy.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="11">In <date when="1602">1602</date> the harbor of <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Catalina</placeName> was visited by <persName
                     type="seaman" key="#svi">Viscaino</persName>, who reported it to be thickly
                  inhabited by <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">a
                     people</orgName> very ingenious, particularly in pilfering and hiding their
                  thefts.</span>
               <rs><persName key="#priest2">A priest</persName></rs> who formed one of his party
               afterward described a kind of temple to the sun, with images and idols carved in
               soap-stone, which he asserted to exist in the vicinity of the harbor. <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">The islands</placeName></rs> were doubtless
               inhabited down to <rs><date notAfter="1853">the early portion of this
                  century</date></rs>. <span type="trope" n="6">Strange to say, those which are at
                  present the most barren and desolate had once the largest population in proportion
                  to their size.</span></p>
            <p><rs><date when="1818">In the early part of this century</date></rs>, <orgName
                  type="organization" key="#rfurcompany">the Russians, assisted by some American
                  traders</orgName>, extended their trading voyages to the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_calcoast">coast of California</placeName> and to <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs>. While definite
               information seems unattainable, the traditions of the locality are to the following
               effect: About <date when="1811">1811</date>, <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; 
               #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                     >a Russian sea-otter party</persName></rs> incurred hostilities from
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the natives of
                     the islands</orgName></rs>, which resulted in a visit from <rs><name
                     type="ship" key="#sh_ilmena">a Russian cruiser</name></rs>, which attacked
                     <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                     natives</orgName></rs>, killing <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                     key="#natam_chumash">a number of them</orgName></rs>, and producing such
               consternation that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                     survivors</orgName></rs> returned to the <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_mld">the main-land</placeName></rs>, and never returned. <rs><date
                     notBefore="1811" to="1851">For nearly forty years</date></rs>
               <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">the islands</placeName></rs> remained
               unvisited, when some persons who had conceived the idea of putting sheep upon them
               examined them with that project in view.</p>
            <p>On <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName>, so it is stated, they
               found <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one old native
                  woman</persName></rs>, who had dragged out a wretched existence in solitude since
               the affray with <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak">the
                     Russians</persName></rs>. <span type="trope" n="6">She was taken to the
                        <rs><placeName type="region" key="#re_mld">the main-land</placeName></rs>,
                  and died there about <date when="1864">1864</date>, the last of <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">her
                     race</orgName></rs></span>. After learning to communicate with the settlers,
               she informed them that she was quite a young girl when <rs><placeName type="island"
                     key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> were depopulated, and in the hasty
               departure of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_chumash">the
                     survivors</orgName></rs> she had been left behind, probably by accident. Here
               she had lived alone, for <rs><date notBefore="1811" to="1851">nearly forty
                     years</date></rs>.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="3"><span type="trope" n="6">There is nothing to confirm the
                     existence of temples or idols, such as were described by <persName
                        type="missionfather" key="#asc">Padre de la Ascencion</persName>; but of
                           <rs><orgName type="group"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">an
                           abundant population</orgName></rs>, of great inventive ingenuity, and of
                     different conditions of climate and soil from those which now obtain, there are
                     indisputable proofs.</span></span> Near every ravine (including many now
               entirely dry, yet where water must formerly have been obtainable) the evidences of
               occupation, in the shape of shell-heaps, are conspicuous. Their magnitude and extent
               bear a direct relation to the abundance of water and the presence of a suitable
               landing-place for the canoes. Often they are of surprising thickness, indicating a
               prolonged occupation by <rs><orgName type="group"
                     key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">the
                     aborigines</orgName></rs>. The largest on <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scatalina">Catalina Island</placeName> are near the well-known springs,
               about five miles from the harbor.</p>
            <p>Most of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> are
               abundantly supplied with these shell-heaps, but they are particularly large and
               prolific in articles of use or ornament, on the outer desert islands of <placeName
                  type="island" key="#i_scl">Clemente</placeName>, <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, and on <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm"
                  >San Miguel</placeName>. Those on <placeName type="island" key="#i_scatalina"
                  >Catalina</placeName> are comparatively destitute of implements or human remains,
               and no exploration of them has revealed any signs of stone images or idols.</p>
            <p>Various persons have visited these deposits, and returned more or less repaid with
               ethnological material&#8212;especially some of the officers of the <orgName
                  key="#uscoastsurvey">U. S. Coast Survey</orgName>, who so employed the leisure
               afforded by weather unfavorable for surveying work. Of these, by far the richest
               collection was made by <persName type="author" key="#wha">Mr. Harford</persName>. It
               is now in the <orgName type="museum" key="#mu_nationalmuseum">National Museum at
                  Washington</orgName>, and was obtained on the <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm"
                  >island of San Miguel</placeName>. On visiting the shell-heaps on the north end of
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">this island</placeName></rs>, the
               investigator is obliged to traverse about four miles of barren sandy wastes, which
               are intersected by sharp and broken ridges trending in an east and west direction.
               The shifting sands are raised in an unintermitting steady stream by the prevalent
               north-west trade-wind, and cut the face and blind the eyes like a shower of needles.
               Through the sand here and there may be seen scant spears of a slender, dry grass; and
               in occasional patches the dry and dead remains of some shrubby plant, which in more
               favored localities raises a disproportionately small amount of tops compared with its
               knobby and swollen roots. Near the shell-heaps is a small grove of malva-trees, whose
               green leaves and penciled blossoms refresh the eyes. There are no young trees,
               however, as the omnipresent sheep crop every green thing within their reach close to
               the ground.</p>
            <p>Arrived on the ground, we see, as we do everywhere else, that the surface of shifting
               sand is underlaid by a layer of vegetable mold, several feet in thickness, once soft
               and verdant, now baked and desiccated by the sun and wind. At one time this was
               evidently bare; since then, the wind has brought the sand in constantly increasing
               heaps, until the reaction began to set in, and the winds at present seem to tend
               slightly toward removing some of the sand. The north point is T-shaped, forming two
               small coves, in one or the other of which a boat can land in almost any weather. The
               point is bold and rather high, with small sandy beaches in the coves. On the edge of
               this bank or bluff 1ived our ancient people. Here we see, where the sea has worn it
               away, a shower of pearly shells from top to bottom of the bank; destitute, it is
               true, of the strength and cohesiveness which distinguishes them when fresh, but
               gaining rather than losing in their brilliant lustre by the very change which is
               destroying them. We find almost all the different kinds of abalone, limpets, and
               spiral pearly shells, which are still abundant in these waters. Though these cover
               the whole face of the bluff, yet they are derived from one stratum only. This varies
               from two or three to twenty feet in thickness, and is in great part identical with
               the stratum of soil which underlies the sand. The shell-layers extend for miles along
               the shore. When these banks were the home of a myriad of busy and ingenious workmen,
                     <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">the island</placeName></rs> would seem
               to have been covered with verdure, and, in accordance with the climatic law, "to him
               that hath shall be given," rain must have been more abundant, and many springs have
               existed which are now dry. That these people cultivated the soil, there would seem to
               be little doubt. One of the most abundant relics to be found is the mortar and
               pestle, almost identical with those still used by the natives of <placeName
                  type="state" key="#st_nm">New Mexico</placeName> and <placeName type="state"
                  key="#st_az">Arizona</placeName> for roughly grinding the seeds of grasses into a
               kind of flour.</p>
            <p>Their houses were probably slight structures, which have disappeared and left no
               trace. Of their clothing we can form no idea from the record of the shell-heaps, but
               it is not improbable that it consisted of skins and woven grasses or vegetable
               fibres. Their food consisted of some cultivated vegetables or seeds, native fruits,
               fish, the flesh of seals and sea-lions whose bones abound in the shell-heaps, the
               smaller species of <emph>cetacea</emph>, birds, and particularly of the indigenous
               shell-fish, whose remains are everywhere before our eyes. Their means of navigation
               were probably canoes, made of materials derived from <rs><placeName type="region"
                     key="#re_mld">the main-land</placeName></rs>; perhaps, as among the <orgName
                  type="nativeamericantribes" key="#asesq">Asiatic Esquimaux</orgName>, obtained by
               barter. The selection of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">the outermost
                     islands</placeName></rs>, by preference, as a place of residence, is accounted
               for by the greater abundance of shell-fish, otter, and marine animals, and by the
               greater protection afforded by their isolation from attacks from without. <span
                  type="trope" n="11">That these were a war-like people is evident, from the number
                  of spear and lance heads found in the shell-heaps and graves. A doubt may be
                  thrown on the courage of at least one of them, from the fact that among the
                  articles obtained by <persName type="author" key="#wha">Mr. Harford</persName> was
                  a pelvic bone, with a long stone lance-head driven half through from behind;
                  attesting at once the strength of arm of the pursuer, and the fact that the
                  defunct met his fate while running away. The majority of the weapons found are
                  unmistakably for use in war, or in the chase; but there are certain heavy stone
                  rings, or perforated balls, worked with a great deal of skill, and which have
                  puzzled all the archæologists. The most probable explanation of the use of these
                  gigantic beads, is that a knotted stick or thong was passed through the centre,
                  and that they were then used as "slung-shots," or as the Patagonians use the
                     <emph>bolas</emph>.</span></p>
            <p>The activity of their domestic life is attested by the presence of fish-hooks made of
               abalone shell, stone spindles for twisting thread, the great variety of stone mortars
               and pestles (often with traces of rude ornamentation), and various nondescript but
               very curious bone tools and implements, one whole tool-chest of which we were
               fortunate enough to unearth. That they were not without relaxation may be inferred
               from the occurrence of sundry pipes, more like a modern cigar-holder in shape than
               anything else; and that their æsthetic tendencies were not wholly repressed, is shown
               by the discovery of an actual flute&#8212;a "tibia," in a double sense&#8212;made
               from the bone of an albatross, and pierced with five holes. This probably had a
               wooden mouth-piece originally, which had perished. Personal ornaments were in use,
               though mostly of a rather rude description. Beads and rough <emph>wampum</emph>
               strung on twisted sinew, alternating with sections of bones cut into "bugles," or
               with <emph>hyqua</emph>-shells, are very common. <span type="trope" n="3">A touching
                  record of parental love was disclosed in the myriads of beads and rounded plates
                  of abalone pearl, which lay within a tiny baby's grave. The dead were laid in the
                  earth near their habitations, apparently on their sides, with the knees drawn up
                  toward the chin. With them are usually found implements and ornaments, once
                  possessed by the dead, or contributed by the survivors as an equipment for him in
                  the "happy hunting grounds."</span> One exception to this general rule may be
               noticed: On a sandy shelf of the bluff near the harbor a large number of interments
               have been made at a depth of a foot or two below the original surface. The drifting
               sands have increased this to about three feet. Here we unearthed some twenty
               skeletons, all of adults, and not a single implement or ornament, of native make, was
               found. One glass bead of red color, three-sided and of antique make, was found,
               showing that these natives had had, at least, a slight opportunity for intercourse
               with traders. It may be that these remains were the hastily interred bodies of those
               who fell in the last fight with <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#1814huntingparty; #rfurcompany; #iba; 
                  #natam_aleuts; #natam_kodiak"
                     >the Russians</persName></rs>, or were a body of the enemy cut off and
               destroyed in some internecine quarrel. It is but proper to say, however, that none of
               the bones showed evidences of bullet or lance wounds. In the other burial-grounds,
               remains are much more numerous. <persName type="author" key="#wha">Mr.
                  Harford</persName> in one place found seventy skulls within a short distance of
               each other. Many of them show the bone variously called the "interparietal,"
               "supra-occipital," and "wormian bone," in the vicinity of the larger fontanel. This
               indicates that its presence can not be taken, as it has been by some ethnologists, as
               a proof of high antiquity or very degraded type. The <emph>crania</emph> are of
               medium size and development&#8212;<emph>brachycephalic</emph>; the teeth frequently
               showing evidences of caries existing before death, and always the flat-worn crowns,
               which indicate a diet of slightly cooked or gritty food.</p>
            <p>These notes would be incomplete did they not include a mention of the peculiar effect
               of the drifting sands on exposed stones and bones. Nature's application of the
               sand-blast, recently patented for application in the mechanic arts, is very
               effectual. Bones are cut away, or reduced to mere shells, in a short time; ordinary
               pebbles are cut in the direction of the prevailing winds into such fantastic forms
               that it is hardly possible to recognize them as natural productions. These curiously
               worn pebbles are found in <placeName type="country" key="#co_nz">New
                  Zealand</placeName>, on the <placeName type="region" key="#re_orcoast">coast of
                  Oregon</placeName>, and near the mouth of <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_klriver">Klamath River</placeName>, <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName>, as well as on <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi"
                     >the islands</placeName></rs>; and specimens from all these places have been
               mistaken by sanguine collectors for articles of human handiwork. Apart from the dead
               shells exposed along the edges of the bluffs, the only means by which the collector
               may determine where to look for ethnological material, are the portions of mortars
               and other implements from which the wind has cleared away the sand. These exposed
               portions always show more or less evidence of the erosive action of sand carried by
               the wind, and sometimes are reduced to very small dimensions, in comparison with the
               parts which remain imbedded and thus protected.</p>
            <p><span type="trope" n="3">Whether actively engaged in fishing or hunting&#8212;driving
                  their light canoes with facile paddles; laboriously fashioning their weapons or
                  implements of stone, bone, and pearly shell; or reposing in the golden glow of the
                  western sun while they puffed the lazy wreaths of smoke from their stone pipes,
                  pausing to catch the plaintive notes of the rude flute to which their children may
                  have chanted, while the mother prepared the evening meal&#8212;the life of
                        <rs><orgName type="group"
                        key="#natam_NicolenoTongva; #natam_GabrilenoTongva; #natam_chumash">these
                        ancient Lords of the Isles</orgName></rs> presents a pleasing contrast to
                  that of the ordinary savage of to-day. Though they have passed away, "unwept,
                  unhonored, and unsung," yet the rude record of the shell­ heap shall keep their
                  memory green.</span></p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
