<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Editor</resp>
               <persName>Sara L. Schwebel</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Digital Collections Manager</resp>
               <persName>Rachel M. A. Manuszak</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Lead Programmer</resp>
               <persName>Tyler Encke</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Provost Humanities Grants</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>University of South Carolina Department of English</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Center for Digital Humanities at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Magellan Scholar Program at the University of South Carolina</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Channel Islands National Park</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Student Conservation Association/AmeriCorps internship program</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Carnegie-Whitney Grant from the American Library Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <persName>Richard H. Dittman</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Financial support</resp>
               <orgName>Children’s Literature Association</orgName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <pubPlace>University of South Carolina</pubPlace>
            <availability status="free">
               <p>Periodicals and books published before 1 January 1923 are in the public domain. If
                  re-publishing, quoting from, or reproducing images from this digital archive, we
                  request that you cite it as follows: Lone Woman and Last Indians Digital Archive,
                  Center for Digital Humanities, University of South Carolina.</p>
               <p>Periodicals and books published on or after 1 January 1923 may be protected by
                  U.S. Copyright Law. All attempts to secure permission for republishing post-1923
                  material in this archive have been made. The names, logos, and identifying images,
                  as well as the content of the articles, remain the property of the periodicals
                  and/or of the authors and artists themselves. Further reproduction, as well as
                  quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from the
                  copyright holder. Archival material published in this archive is used with
                  permission of the institution or library that holds it. Further reproduction, as
                  well as quotation beyond fair use, is prohibited; permission must be obtained from
                  the copyright holder.</p>
               <p>Responsibility for any use of the contents of this digital archive rests
                  exclusively with the user.</p>
            </availability>
            <date/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title type="newspaper"><orgName type="publication" key="#kansun"
                  >Sun</orgName></title>
               <publisher/>
               <editor/>
               <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="issue">219</biblScope>
               <date when="1901-11-21"/>
               <pubPlace><placeName type="city" key="#parsons">Parsons</placeName>, <placeName
                     type="state" key="#st_ks">Kansas</placeName></pubPlace>
               <bibl>
                  <title type="article" key="#Julian1901_TS">Stories Of Riches. They Came from All
                     Parts of Our Wonderful Country. New Deposits of Precious Metals and Minerals
                     Discovered in the Far West--The Wonders of San Nicolas</title>
                  <biblScope unit="page" n="4"/>
                  <author><persName type="author" key="#eju">Julian, Edward</persName></author>
               </bibl>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <head><hi rend="bold"><title type="main">STORIES OF RICHES.</title>
                  <title type="sub">They Came from All Parts of <placeName type="country"
                        key="#co_usa">Our Wonderful Country</placeName>.</title>
                  <title type="sub">New Deposits of Precious Metals and Minerals Discovered in the
                        <placeName type="region" key="#re_amwest">Far West</placeName>&#8212;The
                     Wonders of <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San
                     Nicolas</placeName>.</title></hi></head>
            <byline>[Special <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal">California</placeName>
               Letter.]</byline>
            <p>THIS is, undoubtedly, the golden age of the scientist and explorer. Modern discovery
               has made transportation and communication between distant points so inexpensive and
               easy of accomplishment, and new inventions rendered it possible for excavating and
               prospecting to be carried on so rapidly that work which formerly required years of
               labor can now be accomplished in a few months. Not many years have passed since the
               financial world was electrified by news of the discoveries of precious metals at
                  <placeName type="city" key="#cripcre">Cripple Creek</placeName>. That the
               wonderful fields in that vincinity are not likely to be soon exhausted is proven by
               the great gold strike just made here. It is believed that the miners have found the
               dome of a large crater from which immense wealth will be extracted. Sylvanite and
               rich quartz glitter in florine tale. The vein seems to rise from a chimney in which
               is a great lake of unknown depth. The decomposed matter is of a bluish color and
               sparkles with grains of precious metals. Thousands of tons are already in sight.</p>
            <p>Wonderful stories reach our ears of the great mineral wealth of the <placeName
                  type="country" key="#phil">Philippines</placeName>, and as soon as <orgName
                  type="government" key="#gov_phil">the government</orgName> paves a legal way, it
               will be eagerly trodden by hurrying feet from all parts of the world.</p>
            <p>A disvovery of great interest to geologists as well as to seekers for wealth has been
               announced from <placeName type="state" key="#st_az">Arizona</placeName>. What is said
               to be the finest marble in the world has just been found near <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_cbow">Camp Bowie</placeName> by <persName key="#lrleg">L. R.
                  Legier</persName>, of <placeName type="city" key="#ci_ph">Phoenix</placeName>, who
               brought to the knowledge of the world in <date when="1881">1881</date> the big marble
               deposit in <placeName type="city" key="#ci_gunn">Gunnison county,
                  Colorado</placeName>. <persName key="#lrleg">Mr. Legier</persName> has been
               searching <placeName type="state" key="#st_az">Arizona</placeName> for marble for
                     <rs><date>15 year[s</date></rs>.] He has found it in small quantities in almost
               inaccessible localities, on several occasions, but a few days since he came suddenly
               upon marble ledges of inestimatable value right where soliders of the regular army
               have camped for <rs><date>20 years</date></rs>, totally unconscious of the wealth
               that lay near them. In one place the largest marble ledge is said to be three miles
               long on the surface and nowhere has it yet been found to be less than 1,000 feet
               wide. In this vicinity is marble enough of various kinds to supply the world. A large
               portion is said to be of finer quality than the best Carrara marble. It is fine and
               close grained. In a deep gorge about a mile from <placeName type="city"
                  key="#ci_cbow">Camp Bowie</placeName> the marble is black and surpasses that of
                  <placeName type="country" key="#co_ire">Ireland</placeName>, <placeName
                  type="country" key="#co_bel">Belgium</placeName> or <placeName type="country"
                  key="#co_egy">Egypt</placeName>, formerly the only countries where the stone had
               been found. This ledge is 300 feet wide. For miles stretches a vein of marbles of all
               colors and a marble mountain rises here, a great mass.</p>
            <p>Soon after gold was discovered in <placeName type="state" key="#st_cal"
                  >California</placeName> the gorge was the scene of one of those terrible tragedies
               which people of the present day of luxurious travel find it hard to comprehend.
                  <persName key="#dea">David Easton</persName> started to accompany the family of
               his fiance, <persName key="#hhig">Helen Hight</persName>, a beautiful girl, 18 years
               old, in their long journey across country from <placeName type="state" key="#st_oh"
                  >Ohio</placeName> to <placeName type="region" key="#re_calcoast">the
                  coast</placeName>. While passing through the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_chira">Chirachuhua mountains</placeName>, <rs><persName type="group"
                     key="#hightparty">the party</persName></rs> traveling with them got far in
               advance of <rs><persName type="group" key="#hhig; #hights">th[e]
                  Hights</persName></rs>, who stopped to repair a broken wheel. <span type="trope"
                  n="11">Suddenly a band of <orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_apache"
                     >Apaches</orgName> attacked <rs><persName type="group" key="#hhig; #hights">the
                        little company</persName></rs> in the rear and all were at once killed or
                  mortally wounded, except <persName key="#hhig">Helen</persName> and <persName
                     key="#dea">Easton</persName>, who were subjected to the most cruel tortures
                  their tormentors could devise. <persName key="#dea">Easton</persName> was finally
                  fastened to a cactus bush in such a position that the sharp needles lacerated his
                  flesh to the bone and doomed to thus witness the end of <rs><persName key="#hhig"
                        >the girl whom he loved</persName></rs>. He finally tore himself loose and
                  rushed to the brink of the precipice, over which <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_apache">Indians</orgName></rs> were
                  holding <rs><persName key="#hhig">the girl</persName></rs>. As she fell to the
                  rocks, 1,000 feet below, he attacked <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                        key="#natam_apache">the murderers</orgName></rs> and sent <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_apache">four of them</orgName></rs>
                  to the same doom, then loosened a bowlder which rolled crashing among <rs><orgName
                        type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_apache">his pursuers</orgName></rs>
                  and escaped down a trail, where he was soon afterwards found, wounded and dying,
                  by some of <rs><persName type="group" key="#hightparty">the
                     emigrants</persName></rs> who had returned to ascertain the cause of their
                  companions' long delay.</span> The marble mountain forms a massive monument to the
               suferers in the tragedy.</p>
            <p>There is a mountain of marble near <placeName type="city" key="#ci_colton">Colton,
                  Cal.</placeName>, where stone for building is quarried. In an excavation at the
               top large quantities of concrete are manufactured. <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_chi">The Channel islands</placeName>, off the <placeName type="region"
                  key="#re_paccoast">Pacific coast</placeName>, nearly opposite this point, present
               scenes of great interest to the antropologist. <span type="trope" n="5"><span
                     type="trope" n="6">Of these the best known, of course, is <placeName
                        type="island" key="#i_scatalina">Santa Catalina</placeName>, a resort of
                     such prominence that everyone has more or less knowledge of its strange caves
                     and grottoes, where the remains of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">an extinct race</orgName></rs> may be
                     seen.</span></span> Heretofore the other islands of <rs><placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_chi">this group</placeName></rs> have been, as a rule,
               neglected by what is now known as the civilized world. Toward one of these,
                  <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>, public interest is
               now especially turned, because the <orgName type="institution" key="#in_ucb"
                  >University of California</orgName> is about to begin the most thorough
               exploration of it ever made. It lies 60 miles off the coast of <placeName
                  type="county" key="#co_sb">Santa Barbara</placeName> and <placeName type="county"
                  key="#co_ventura">Ventura</placeName> counties. <span type="trope" n="5">Strange
                  presences seem to pervade all of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">these
                        little islands</placeName></rs>, where peoples of other days and customs
                  lived, worked and loved. On <placeName type="island" key="#i_scl">San
                     Clemente</placeName> are enormous mortars and pestles and indications that
                        <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_GabrilenoTongva">the
                        ancient inhabitants</orgName></rs> were a giant race.</span>
               <placeName type="island" key="#i_sm">San Miguel</placeName> is chiefly interesting
               from its topography. Great pillars twist around winding caves and rugged canyons
               suggest attractions to the explorer. Scientists from the <orgName type="museum"
                  key="#mu_smithsonian">Smithsonian institution</orgName> have secured quantities of
               ornaments and utensils of bone, shell and stone from <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_scruz">Santa Cruz</placeName>. <span type="trope" n="5"><span type="trope"
                     n="6">On <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName> are most
                     abundant evidences of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes"
                           key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">a people</orgName></rs> of large stature.
                           <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_chi">The islands</placeName></rs>
                     are seldom visited and loom in lonely desolation on the blue ocean. Science has
                     thus far been able to tell us little of the origin and life of <rs><orgName
                           type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">these aboriginal
                           settlers</orgName></rs> and how and why they disappeared so completely.
                     As far in the past as history deals with <rs><placeName type="island"
                           key="#i_chi">the islands</placeName></rs> skeletons by hundreds have been
                     strewn over <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">San Nicolas</placeName>.
                     Peculiar stone utensils have been found among the skeletons, indicating a
                     civlization which so far has not been comprehended.</span></span></p>
            <p>In <date when="1835">1835</date>, <rs><persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">16
                     members of a strange Indian race</persName></rs> were known to live here, and
                     <rs><persName type="group" key="#jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats">Franciscan
                     padres from the Santa Barbara mission</persName></rs> made an attempt to rescue
               them. A sudden storm drove <name type="ship" key="#sh_peoresnada">their sloop</name>
               from the shore when all <persName type="group" key="#bhagroup">the Indians</persName>
               were on board but <rs><persName type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">one
                  woman</persName></rs>. <span type="trope" n="6"><rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#bhagroup; #jru; #aji; #sanchez; #misfats; #1835crew; #chu; #isp; #iwi; #jsjo; #jdy; #lbu; #natam_hawaiian; #nativeamericans"
                        >Its occupants</persName></rs> were all lost, as <name type="ship"
                     key="#sh_peoresnada">the sloop</name> was cast on the rocks of <placeName
                     type="region" key="#re_pc">Point Conception</placeName>.</span>
               <span type="trope" n="1">Traditions existed among the fishermen of <rs><persName
                        type="nativeamerican" key="#lw">a lone woman</persName></rs> at <placeName
                     type="island" key="#i_sn">the island</placeName>, and in the <rs><date
                        notBefore="1850" notAfter="1859">[eighteen-] fifties</date></rs>
                  <rs><persName type="group" key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva"
                        >a small expedition</persName></rs> landed and found her in a costume of
                  colored bird skins eating blubber from a seal, which she conveyed to her mouth
                  with a bone knife. On seeing <rs><persName type="group"
                        key="#gni; #cdi; #col; #cook; #msh; #poli; #nsk; #hva">the
                     men</persName></rs>, she smiled, and falling on her knees, prayed to the
                  sun.</span> On arriving at <placeName type="city" key="#ci_sb">Santa
                  Barbara</placeName> she prostrated herself in adoration before <rs><persName
                     key="#riderhorseman; #mrni; #jsh; #ssh">a man on horseback</persName></rs>. Two
               weeks later she died from the effects of food to which she was not accustomed. This
               was a great disappointment to scientists, who hoped to learn from her lips the
               traditions of <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva"
                     >her race</orgName></rs>. The <placeName type="island" key="#i_sn">Island of
                  San Nicolas</placeName> is ten miles long and four wide at its widest point. It
               consists of a nearly level plateau at an elevation of 800 to 1,000 feet. Two-thirds
               of the surface is covered with drifting sand, the remainder affords excellent
               pasturage for thousands of sheep. Sheep shearers and shell gatherers are chiefest
               [sic] among its infrequent visitors. <placeName type="region" key="#re_coralharbor"
                  >Coral Harbor</placeName> is the only safe landing place and its entrance is but
               six or seven yards across. White pelicans in large numbers promenade its strip of
               beach. Circular depressions are the only marks of ancient dwellings of which none of
               the materials used in construction remain. Immense shell mounds and bones of fish,
               seals, whales, sea otters, foxes and birds show that <rs><orgName
                     type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     inhabitants</orgName></rs> were fond of animal food. The quantity of these
               proves that <rs><orgName type="nativeamericantribes" key="#natam_NicolenoTongva">the
                     population</orgName></rs> possessed healthy appetites.</p>
            <p>Biologists say that the number of varieties of mollusks in <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_sn">San Nicholas</placeName> are not exceeded in any region of the same
               area. From one of the elevations, the peaks of all the <placeName type="island"
                  key="#i_chi">Channel islands</placeName>, some 40 miles distant, are visible
               through the clear atmosphere. On one side of <rs><placeName type="island" key="#i_sn"
                     >the island</placeName></rs> is a sparse, petrified stone forest.</p>
            <byline><persName type="author" key="#eju">EDWARD JULIAN</persName>.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
